
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:54+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression A note on the false discovery rate of novel peptides in proteogenomics</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kun</forename>
								<surname>Zhang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Computing Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Lab of Intelligent Information Processing of Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CAS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100190</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100049</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yan</forename>
								<surname>Fu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">National Center for Mathematics and Interdisciplinary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Academy of Mathematics and Systems Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Random Complex Structures and Data Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100190</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wen-Feng</forename>
								<surname>Zeng</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Computing Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Lab of Intelligent Information Processing of Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CAS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100190</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100049</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kun</forename>
								<surname>He</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Computing Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Lab of Intelligent Information Processing of Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CAS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100190</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100049</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hao</forename>
								<surname>Chi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Computing Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Lab of Intelligent Information Processing of Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CAS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100190</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chao</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Computing Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Lab of Intelligent Information Processing of Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CAS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100190</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yan-Chang</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Beijing Proteome Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">National Center for Protein Sciences Beijing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">State Key Laboratory of Proteomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Engineering Research Center for Protein Drugs</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Beijing Institute of Radiation Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>102206</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yuan</forename>
								<surname>Gao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Beijing Proteome Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">National Center for Protein Sciences Beijing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">State Key Laboratory of Proteomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Engineering Research Center for Protein Drugs</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Beijing Institute of Radiation Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>102206</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ping</forename>
								<surname>Xu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Beijing Proteome Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">National Center for Protein Sciences Beijing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">State Key Laboratory of Proteomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Engineering Research Center for Protein Drugs</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Beijing Institute of Radiation Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>102206</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Si-Min</forename>
								<surname>He</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Computing Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Lab of Intelligent Information Processing of Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CAS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100190</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression A note on the false discovery rate of novel peptides in proteogenomics</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv340</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 2, 2015; revised on May 13, 2015; accepted on May 27, 2015</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Burkhard Rost Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Proteogenomics has been well accepted as a tool to discover novel genes. In most conventional proteogenomic studies, a global false discovery rate is used to filter out false posi-tives for identifying credible novel peptides. However, it has been found that the actual level of false positives in novel peptides is often out of control and behaves differently for different genomes. Results: To quantitatively model this problem, we theoretically analyze the subgroup false discovery rates of annotated and novel peptides. Our analysis shows that the annotation completeness ratio of a genome is the dominant factor influencing the subgroup FDR of novel peptides. Experimental results on two real datasets of Escherichia coli and Mycobacterium tuberculosis support our conjecture.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Tandem mass spectrometry (MS/MS)-based proteogenomics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Jaffe et al., 2004</ref>) has been applied to refinement of annotated genes, discovery of novel genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kim et al., 2014</ref>), personal genomics and disease-related studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Zhang et al., 2014</ref>). Unlike traditional genomic annotation techniques, such as in silico (ab initio or comparative) or cDNA-seq-based methods, proteogenomics allows validating proteincoding genes directly at the protein level, which is more favorable (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Renuse et al., 2011</ref>). To identify novel genes, researchers usually search the experimental MS/MS spectra against a large protein database that is constructed from the genomic or transcriptomic sequences and filter the search results to control the false discovery rate (FDR). It has been observed previously that, under a fixed FDR, the inflated database generated by, e.g. six-open-reading-frame (6-ORF) translation of a whole genome significantly decreases the sensitivity of peptide identification (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Blakeley et al., 2012</ref>). However, few studies probe into the effect of the large database on the estimated FDR, especially for the novel peptides. Most proteogenomic studies estimate a global FDR for all peptide identifications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Borchert et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Chaerkady et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Merrihew et al., 2008</ref>). That is, the identifications of annotated peptides and novel peptides are subject to FDR estimation in combination. Some researchers noted the high actual FDR of novel peptides and therefore employed more stringent filtering strategies, e.g. post error probability (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Brosch et al., 2011</ref>) or separate FDRs for annotated and novel peptides (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Branca et al., 2014</ref><ref type="bibr">). Recently, Krug et al. (2013</ref>highlighted that for well-annotated genomes, such as the Escherichia coli genome, the post error probability distribution of</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3249</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com<ref type="bibr">Bioinformatics, 31(20)</ref>,novel peptide hits is almost identical to that of decoy hits, indicating that most novel peptides were false positives. Krug's work implied that the identification accuracy of novel peptides is greatly affected by the completeness of genome annotation. In fact, the relationship between annotated and novel peptides is quite similar to that between unmodified and modified peptides. Recently, Fu has formally studied the factors that influence the subgroup FDRs of differently modified peptides (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Fu, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Fu and Qian, 2014</ref>). Here, we follow the same framework as in Fu's work to quantitatively investigate the subgroup FDRs of annotated and novel peptides identified by 6-ORF translation search.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>Let subscript k 2 fann; newg denote the subgroup of annotated (ann) and novel (new) peptide identifications, respectively. Here, the novel peptides are those from the previously unannotated region on a genome, excluding the peptide variants resulting from DNA mutation or mRNA alternative splicing. Then following Fu's formalization, we define (i) T, a true peptide identification; (ii) F, a false peptide identification; (iii) I k , a peptide identification belonging to subgroup k; (iv) FDRðxÞ, the global FDR of peptide identifications that score better than x, where both annotated and novel peptides are included; (v) FDR k ðxÞ, the subgroup FDR, e.g. FDR ann ðxÞ for annotated peptides and FDR new ðxÞ for novel ones. Following the derivation by Fu and Qian (2014), FDR k ðxÞ can be written asPðI k jF;X&gt;xÞ 1 À FDRðxÞ ;</p><formula>(1)</formula><p>where PðI k jT; X &gt; xÞ is the probability that an identification belongs to subgroup k under the condition that this identification is true and scores better than x, and PðI k jF; X &gt; xÞ is the probability that an identification belongs to subgroup k under the condition that this identification is false and scores better than x. Equation (1) implies that FDR k ðxÞ is determined by three variables, i.e. FDRðxÞ, PðI k jT; X &gt; xÞ and PðI k jF; X &gt; xÞ. To make the relationship in Equation (1) computable, we need to evaluate PðI k jT; X &gt; xÞ and PðI k jF; X &gt; xÞ, for both annotated and novel peptides. Note that we assume FDRðxÞ can be readily estimated using some methods, e.g. the commonly used target-decoy search strategy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Elias and Gygi, 2007</ref>). For convenience of discussion, we introduce two quantities: (i) h, the annotation completeness ratio, defined as the length ratio of the currently annotated genes to all genes on the genome; (ii) l, the annotation length ratio, defined as the length ratio of currently annotated genes to the whole genome. Presuming that only one gene exists at any genomic locus, the value scope of l is ½0; 1. Actually, l varies across species even if their genomes are well annotated (for E.coli it is about 0.88 and for Homo sapiens, it is less than 0.02). However, for a poorly annotated genome, l is relatively small, and we have l ¼ 0 if no gene is annotated. Suppose that the annotated and novel peptides could be equally likely retrieved by the search engine and their scores are identically distributed, then apparently, we have PðI ann jT; X &gt; xÞ ¼ h and PðI new jT; X &gt; xÞ ¼ 1 À h. PðI k jF; X &gt; xÞ depends on the sizes of the annotated database and the translated database. Given the genome length L, the summed length of annotated genes is lL. If falsely identified peptides distribute uniformly on the genome, we have PðI ann jF; X &gt; xÞ ¼ lL=6L ¼ l=6 and PðI new jF; X &gt; xÞ ¼ ð6 À lÞ=6. So far, we have obtained the probabilities that an identified peptide is an annotated or novel peptide given that this identification is true or false and scores better than x, as summarized in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. Now we first come to the formulation of FDR ann ðxÞ: FDR ann ðxÞ ¼ FDRðxÞ FDRðxÞ þ 6h l 1 À FDRðxÞ :</p><formula>(2)</formula><p>The value of l=h represents the length proportion of all genes on the genome and is a constant for a certain species. Therefore, we can conclude that FDR ann ðxÞ depends only on FDRðxÞ. Similarly, we can write FDR new ðxÞ as FDR new ðxÞ ¼ FDRðxÞ FDRðxÞ þ 6ð1ÀhÞ 6Àl 1 À FDRðxÞ :</p><formula>(3)</formula><p>If a genome has never been annotated (h ¼ 0, m ¼ 0), then no identification could be an annotated peptide and FDR new ðxÞ ¼ FDRðxÞ, which is consistent with the assumption. If a genome is completely annotated (h ¼ 1), then FDR new ðxÞ ¼ 1, meaning that all novel peptide identifications are false, which is also consistent with the assumption; in this case, as FDRðxÞ and m are usually very small, FDR ann ðxÞ approximately equals l=6 of FDRðxÞ. If we take FDRðxÞ ¼ 1%, the FDR ann ðxÞ is only 1.5% for E.coli (m ¼ 0.88) and 0.03% for H.sapiens (m &lt; 0.02), much more conservative than FDRðxÞ. On the other hand, if we assume h ¼ 0:999, l ¼ 0:6 and FDRðxÞ ¼ 1%, then we have PðI new jT; X &gt; xÞ ¼ 1=1000 and PðI new jF; X &gt; xÞ ¼ 9/10. The calculated FDR new ðxÞ is 90.1%, as large as 90 times of FDRðxÞ. In contrast, the FDR ann ðxÞ is only 1%. We can see that for well annotated genomes, FDR ann ðxÞ is overestimated, while FDR new ðxÞ is underestimated, if a global FDR is controlled. Since 0 l 1, we have 5=6 PðI new jF; X &gt; xÞ 1. It is easy to deduce from Equation (3) that l, as a parameter quantitatively reflecting the length ratio of the annotated genes to the whole genome, has little influence on FDR new ðxÞ. Let us take FDRðxÞ ¼ 1%, then for different h, the upper and lower bounds (occurring when l ¼ 0 and l ¼ 1, respectively) of FDR new ðxÞ can be calculated and are depicted by the dashed blue and solid red lines, respectively, in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure  1</ref>. It is worth emphasizing that FDR new ðxÞ is less than 10% if h does not exceed 90%. However, as h increases over 90%, FDR new ðxÞ ramps up quickly to a much higher level. Thus, we conclude that h significantly affects FDR new ðxÞ. Nevertheless, given FDRðxÞ ¼ 1%, the maximum difference between the upper and lower bounds of FDR new ðxÞ is less than 4.6%, and thus l does not substantially change FDR new ðxÞ, just as we deduced above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>By removing some genes from a completely annotated database based on their summed length, we could perform numerical simulation of h. Then, experimental FDR ann ðxÞ, which is the ratio of the number of identified annotated decoys to the number of annotated targets, and FDR new ðxÞ, which is the ratio of the number of identified novel decoys to the number of novel targets, can be calculated and compared to the theoretical ones<ref type="bibr">[</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Krug et al. (2013)</ref>concluded that the E.coli genome might have achieved a complete annotation. We downloaded one of these E.coli's datasets from PeptideAtlas, which consisted of six raw files (trypsin digested, SAX_01$SAX_06), 300 032 MS/MS spectra in total. The latest genome sequence and annotation data (NC_000913.3) were downloaded from the NCBI website. First, a stop-to-stop 6-ORF translation was applied to the E.coli's genome, and a commonly used contaminant database containing porcine trypsin and human keratins was concatenated. The simply reversed form of each protein sequence in the combined database was added, resulting in a combined target-decoy database to facilitate FDR estimation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Elias and Gygi, 2007</ref>). Next, the MS/MS spectra were searched against the combined database using pFind studio (version 2.8). Peptides were digested in silico with up to two missed cleavages allowed, and carbamidomethylation on cysteine was set as the fix modification and oxidation on methionine as the variable modification. The precursor and fragment mass error tolerances were set to 6 20 ppm and 6 0.5 Da, respectively. A global peptide-level FDR of 1% was used for quality assessment, which allowed us to identify 12 835 peptides. Among these peptides, 113 were contaminant ones, 12 619 were annotated ones and 103 were novel ones. Since the E.coli's genome has been almost completely annotated, the 103 novel target identifications should be mostly false ones. Just as expected, among the 128 decoy identifications above the threshold of FDR &lt; 1%, 97 were novel decoys, very close to the number of novel targets, indicating that the subgroup FDR of novel peptides was close to 1 (97/103 ¼ 0.94). To simulate h, we randomly removed some genes from the annotated database to vary the ratio of their summed length to all genes. Using the same global FDR threshold of 1%, we obtained the numbers of targets and decoys separately on annotated and novel peptides, allowing us to calculate the experimental FDR ann ðxÞ and FDR new ðxÞ. Given h and l, the theoretical FDR ann ðxÞ and FDR new ðxÞ were also calculated through Equations (2) and (3). Our simulation showed that, the experimental FDR ann ðxÞ were close to the theoretical value of 1.5%, with a minimum of 2.1% and a maximum of 3.6%. Moreover, the experimental FDR new ðxÞ fits well with the theoretical counterpart, as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2A</ref>. On the other hand, we can deduce the value of h from the experimental FDR new ðxÞ based on Equation (3). As shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2</ref>, the pairs of sampled and deduced values of h distribute diagonally, indicating that the deduced h could be used as an estimate of the real annotation completeness ratio. We also found that if we remove the 'novel genes' from the annotated database and search the spectra of novel peptides (identified by 6-ORF translation search) against the partially annotated database, then these spectra will be assigned with false peptides and random scores (see Supplementary Materials S2 and S3 for more details).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Results on E.coli</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Results on M.tuberculosis</head><p>M.tuberculosis is another organism that has undergone several proteogenomic studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">de Souza et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kelkar et al., 2011</ref>). The annotation length ratio of M.tuberculosis is about 0.91, and its genome is featured by the high GC content. Therefore, we selected M.tuberculosis as the second organism to verify our model. A dataset of 503 933 MS/MS spectra was generatedpartial annotation, we randomly removed some annotated genes from the database. Gene sampling was performed on the basis of h, with a step of 0.1 from 0 to 1, and in addition, 0.95 and 0.99 were also appended. (A) The experimental FDRnewðx Þ obtained on the E.coli dataset as shown by red crosses fits well with the theoretical value (blue line). The deduced values for h were approximately identical to the sampled ones, as shown by magenta triangles on the diagonal line. (B) On the M.tuberculosis dataset, genes were sampled 10 times for each value of h. The experimental FDRnewðx Þ values as shown by red boxes fit well with the theoretical values (blue line) when h is less than 0.9. As truly novel peptides may exist, the experimental FDRnewðx Þ diverges from the theoretical counterpart. The experimental FDRnewðx Þ is 0.69 when sampled h ¼ 1, and the deduced h is 0.996 correspondingly. However, all deduced values for h still match the sampled ones (green box), since the annotation completeness ratio is very close to 1 FDR of novel peptides in proteogenomics(see Supplementary Method for details of the data) and were searched against the translated genome (NC_018143.2) under the same parameter setting as for E.coli. The search resulted in 28 545 target peptides identified, including 682 contaminant ones, 27 528 annotated ones and 335 novel ones. Meanwhile, a total of 230 novel decoys were obtained above the peptide-level FDR of 1%, leading to an experimental FDR new ðxÞ of 0.69 (¼230/335) and a deduced h of 0.996, which was calculated through Equation (3). The disparity between the numbers of novel targets and decoys implies that a set of truly novel peptides may exist in M.tuberculosis. We performed a blast search for the 105 (¼335 À 230) top-scoring novel peptides and found that 68 of them have been annotated in other mycobacterial species, meaning that they are conservative and reliable. The rest of them should be experimentally validated through further efforts. The same simulation experiment of h as done on E.coli was also tested on M.tuberculosis. The deduced values of h are in line with the theoretical ones on differently sampled h, as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2B</ref>. The experimental FDR new ðxÞ also fits well with the theoretical counterpart for smaller h. However, the experimental FDR new ðxÞ apparently deviates from its theoretical value when h ! 0.95, because of the existence of truly novel peptides. This result shows that M.tuberculosis is not so completely annotated as E.coli, and FDR new ðxÞ is sensitive to the incomplete annotation, even when h approaches 1. In some previous researches, a filter of protein length is applied to the translated database. To test the influence of this operation on our model, we used four length filters of 30, 50, 100 and 500 to modify the original translated database of M.tuberculosis. The search results upon these four modified databases show that, a small length filter ( 100) causes minor effect on the theoretical estimation of FDR new ðxÞ and the deduced h calculated by Equation (3). However, a large filter such as 500, which removes 80% of annotated genes in M.tuberculosis, greatly shrinks the sample space of novel peptides and biases the estimation. In this situation, Equation (3) should be modified to fit the experimental data consequently (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S2</ref>). Therefore, to appropriately use the estimation in Equation (3), a suitable length filter (e.g. 100) is necessary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Discussions</head><p>Above, we have assumed that the annotated and novel peptides distribute equally in the expressed and unexpressed proteins. Since not all proteins are expressed in a specific sample under a specific condition, estimation of PðI k jT; X &gt; xÞ becomes harder. In fact, novel peptides in nearly completely annotated organisms may have lower expression levels or worse scores, because more abundant and better scoring peptides are easier to annotate, and accordingly, PðI new jT; X &gt; xÞ is smaller. This can lead to a larger FDR new ðxÞ and hence less credible novel peptide identifications. The peptide variants resulted from DNA mutation or mRNA alternative splicing are sometimes also considered as novel peptides. However, these variants are much like protein modifications, the sample space of which is difficult to estimate explicitly. Definitely, great care should be taken when reporting these variants, because the search space of these peptides become even larger, and according to Fu's (2012) corollary, more false positives will appear if a global FDR is used. In this article, we have revealed that the genome annotation completeness ratio is the dominant factor influencing the identification accuracy of novel peptides identified by 6-ORF translation search when a global FDR is used for quality assessment. The subgroup FDR of novel peptides will be seriously under-estimated if the genome has been well annotated (e.g. when the annotation completeness ratio exceeds 90%). For such well-annotated genomes, separate FDR control is very necessary as recently suggested by Nesvizhskii (2014). However, with a stringent FDR control (e.g. 1%), many low scoring but true peptide identifications may be excluded along with false positives. To increase the sensitivity and specificity of novelgene discovery, one should reduce the size of searched database as much as possible (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Nesvizhskii, 2014</ref>). For example, when the transcriptome information (especially from the strand-specific cDNAseq data) is available, it is apparently more favorable to search against the transcriptome as well than to search against the genome alone. If the transcriptome information is unavailable, it would be also helpful to reduce the 6-OFR translation database by removing sequences that are predicted to be hardly possible to be real proteins. From the point of view of data analysis, we believe that intelligent post-processing of search results is a promising resolution to sensitive discovery of novel peptides and genes. For example, machine learning techniques (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kall et al., 2007</ref>) can be used to discriminate true and false identifications of novel peptides and to re-score and re-rank the peptides using specific information in proteogenomics. Alternatively, the search results from multiple search engines can be combined properly to generate a set of reliable identifications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kelkar et al., 2011</ref>).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>computed by Equations (2) and (3)]. On the basis of this idea, we experimentally validated our theoretical model on two species, i.e. E.coli and Mycobacterium tuberculosis.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The upper and lower bounds of FDRnewðx Þ when FDRðxÞ ¼ 1%</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Simulation results on the E.coli and M.tuberculosis datasets. To simulate partial annotation, we randomly removed some annotated genes from the database. Gene sampling was performed on the basis of h, with a step of 0.1 from 0 to 1, and in addition, 0.95 and 0.99 were also appended. (A) The experimental FDRnewðx Þ obtained on the E.coli dataset as shown by red crosses fits well with the theoretical value (blue line). The deduced values for h were approximately identical to the sampled ones, as shown by magenta triangles on the diagonal line. (B) On the M.tuberculosis dataset, genes were sampled 10 times for each value of h. The experimental FDRnewðx Þ values as shown by red boxes fit well with the theoretical values (blue line) when h is less than 0.9. As truly novel peptides may exist, the experimental FDRnewðx Þ diverges from the theoretical counterpart. The experimental FDRnewðx Þ is 0.69 when sampled h ¼ 1, and the deduced h is 0.996 correspondingly. However, all deduced values for h still match the sampled ones (green box), since the annotation completeness ratio is very close to 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>2015, 3249–3253 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv340 Advance Access Publication Date: 14 June 2015 Discovery Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1. The probabilities and their estimates used in this article</figDesc><table>Identification type 
True positive 
False positive 

Annotated identification 
PðI ann jT; X &gt; xÞ ¼ h 
PðI ann jF; X &gt; xÞ ¼ l=6 
Novel identification 
PðI new jT; X &gt; xÞ ¼ 1 À h 
PðI new jF; X &gt; xÞ ¼ ð6 À lÞ=6 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">K.Zhang et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Addressing statistical biases in nucleotide-derived protein databases for proteogenomic search strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Blakeley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5221" to="5234" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proteogenomics of Pristionchus pacificus reveals distinct proteome structure of nematode models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Borchert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="837" to="846" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HiRIEF LC-MS enables deep proteome coverage and unbiased proteogenomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Branca</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shotgun proteomics aids discovery of novel proteincoding genes, alternative splicing, and &quot; resurrected &quot; pseudogenes in the mouse genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Brosch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="756" to="767" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A proteogenomic analysis of anopheles gambiae using high-resolution fourier transform mass spectrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Chaerkady</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1872" to="1881" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High accuracy mass spectrometry analysis as a tool to verify and improve gene annotation using Mycobacterium tuberculosis as an example</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>De Souza</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">316</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Target-decoy search strategy for increased confidence in large-scale protein identifications by mass spectrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Elias</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Gygi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="214" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian false discovery rates for post-translational modification proteomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Fu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Interface</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transferred subgroup false discovery rate for rare post-translational modifications detected by mass spectrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Fu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Qian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1359" to="1368" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proteogenomic mapping as a complementary method to perform genome annotation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Jaffe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semi-supervised learning for peptide identification from shotgun proteomics datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Kall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="923" to="925" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proteogenomic analysis of Mycobacterium tuberculosis by high resolution mass spectrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Kelkar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="011627" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A draft map of the human proteome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">509</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="575" to="581" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deep coverage of the Escherichia coli proteome enables the assessment of false discovery rates in simple proteogenomic experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Krug</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3420" to="3430" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of shotgun proteomics for the identification, confirmation, and correction of C. elegans gene annotations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Merrihew</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1660" to="1669" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proteogenomics: concepts, applications and computational strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Nesvizhskii</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1114" to="1125" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Renuse</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteogenomics. Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="620" to="630" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proteogenomic characterization of human colon and rectal cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">513</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="382" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">FDR of novel peptides in proteogenomics</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>