
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:55+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis ABRA: improved coding indel detection via assembly-based realignment</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">19 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lisle</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Mose</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>lmose@unc.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matthew</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Wilkerson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">D</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Neil</forename>
								<surname>Hayes</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Medical Oncology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Internal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Multidisciplinary Thoracic Oncology Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<settlement>Chapel Hill</settlement>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Charles</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Perou</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joel</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Parker</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>parkerjs@email.unc.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis ABRA: improved coding indel detection via assembly-based realignment</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2813" to="2815"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">19 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu376</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on January 14, 2014; revised on May 27, 2014; accepted on June 1, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Michael Brudno Availability and implementation: ABRA is implemented in a combin-ation of Java and C/C++ and is freely available for download at https://github.com/mozack/abra. Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Variant detection from next-generation sequencing (NGS) data is an increasingly vital aspect of disease diagnosis, treatment and research. Commonly used NGS-variant analysis tools generally rely on accurately mapped short reads to identify somatic variants and germ-line genotypes. Existing NGS read mappers have difficulty accurately mapping short reads containing complex variation (i.e. more than a single base change), thus making identification of such variants difficult or impossible. Insertions and deletions (indels) in particular have been an area of great difficulty. Indels are frequent and can have substantial impact on function, which makes their detection all the more imperative. Results: We present ABRA, an assembly-based realigner, which uses an efficient and flexible localized de novo assembly followed by global realignment to more accurately remap reads. This results in enhanced performance for indel detection as well as improved accuracy in variant allele frequency estimation.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>A number of realignment or assembly methods have been proposed to overcome the alignment errors and reference bias that limit indel detection. Short read micro aligner locally realigns reads to regionally assembled variant graphs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Homer and Nelson, 2010</ref>). Pindel uses a pattern growth approach to detect indels (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ye et al., 2009</ref>). Dindel realigns reads to candidate haplotypes and uses a Bayesian method to call indels up to 50 bp in length (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Albers et al., 2011</ref>). The Genome Analysis Toolkit (GATK)'s IndelRealigner seeks to minimize the number of mismatching bases via local realignment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">DePristo et al., 2011</ref>). Whole-genome de novo assembly approaches include Fermi (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Li, 2012</ref>) and Cortex Var (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Iqbal et al., 2012</ref>). SOAPIndel performs localized assembly and calling on regions containing reads where only one half of a paired read is mapped (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Li et al., 2012</ref>). Clipping REveals STructure (CREST) uses soft clipped reads and localized assembly to identify somatic structural variants (<ref type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</ref>). Targeted Iterative Graph Routing Assembler (TIGRA) uses targeted assembly to produce contigs from putative breakpoints (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Chen et al., 2014</ref>). Additional proprietary localized assembly methods have been developed by Complete Genomics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Carnevali et al., 2012</ref>) and Foundation Medicine (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Frampton et al., 2013</ref>). Our newly developed tool called ABRA accepts a Sequence Alignment/Map (SAM/BAM) file as input and produces a realigned BAM file as output, allowing flexibility in selection of variant calling algorithms and other downstream analysis. Global realignment allows reads that are unaligned or improperly mapped to be moved to a correct location. ABRA detects variation that is not present in the original read alignments and improves allele-frequency estimates for variation that is present. ABRA can be used to enhance both germ-line and somatic variant detection and works with paired-end as well as single-end data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>The ABRA algorithm consists of localized region assembly, contig building, alignment of assembled contigs and read realignment. Localized assembly of reads is done on small genomic regions of size</p><p>Assembled contigs for all regions are aligned to the reference genome. We currently use BWA MEM () for contig alignment. Chimerically aligned contigs are combined when appropriate (in cases of longer indels). Redundant sequence as well as sequence not varying from the original reference is removed. The result is used as the basis for an alternate reference. The original reads are mapped to the alternate reference using a nongapped alignment. Reads that unambiguously align more closely to the alternate than the original reference are modified to reflect the updated alignment information in the context of the original reference. Typical ABRA runtime for a human whole exome of depth 150X on a machine with eight cores is roughly 2 h using 516 GB of RAM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">HapMap trio</head><p>ABRA was applied to exome target regions of a CEPH Hapmap trio of three individuals sequenced to 50x as part of the Illumina Platinum Genomes project and aligned using bwa mem. Variants were called with and without ABRA using Freebayes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Garrison and Marth, 2012</ref>) and UnifiedGenotyper (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">DePristo et al., 2011</ref>). The GATK's HaplotypeCaller was used to call variants without ABRA and the GATK's IndelRealigner was applied to UnifiedGenotyper input. Coding indels with variant-allele frequency of 20% are used in this germ-line evaluation. ABRA enables an increase in the number of Mendelian consistent loci (MCL) detected and a decrease in Mendelian conflict rate (MCR) with either Freebayes or UnifiedGenotyper (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). The Freebayes/ABRA combination yields a decrease in MCR compared with HaplotypeCaller and remains competitive in number of MCL detected. Pre-/post-ABRA concordance for Mendelian consistent SNP loci is499%. Although we anticipate that ABRA will also provide improved performance in noncoding regions, this has not yet been explored.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">TCGA tumor and normal data</head><p>We applied ABRA to 100 normal exomes from the Breast Invasive Carcinoma (BRCA) cohort of The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) project (The Cancer Genome Atlas Network, 2012) using BWA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Li and Durbin, 2009</ref>) for the initial alignments. Germ-line variants were called both with and without ABRA using FreeBayes. We also called germ-line variants using HaplotypeCaller and Pindel for comparison purposes. To evaluate these calls in the absence of ground truth, we assembled predicted calls for all methods using TIGRA and aligned the resulting contigs with the BLAST-like alignment tool (BLAT) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kent et al., 2002</ref>). ABRA increased concordance with the TIGRA/BLAT results and maintained a low discordance rate (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 2</ref>). Further, ABRA generated estimated allele frequencies closer to 50 and 100%, which is expected in a diploid individual (see Supplementary Material). We next compared pre-and postABRA somatic variant calls on 750 TCGA BRCA normal/ tumor exome pairs. Strelka (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Saunders et al., 2012</ref>) and UNCeqR (<ref type="bibr">Wilkerson et al., 2012</ref>) were used for somatic calling. Improved detection of somatic mutation was observed in the post-ABRA calls (see Supplementary Material).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>ABRA improves on next-generation sequencing read alignments, providing enhanced performance in detection of indels as well as greater accuracy in variant allele frequency estimation. ABRA accepts BAM files as input and outputs realigned BAM files,</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Concordance/discordance with TIGRA assembled contigs for predicted calls from FreeBayes (pre-and post-ABRA), Pindel and Haplotype Caller. Indels within the ranges enabled by ABRA are evaluated (deletions up to 2000 bp and insertions up to the read length). The numbers in the figure represent a cutoff point for variant quality scores as reported in the respective caller's VCF output. A small number of preABRA deletions 430 bp and 0 pre-ABRA insertions 430 bp are called. FreeBayes currently does not use reads partially overlapping an insert as supporting evidence, which may impact post-ABRA sensitivity for longer insertions</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Mendelian consistent loci and Mendelian conflict rates for Freebayes and UnifiedGenotyper both pre-and post-ABRA. UnifiedGenotyper results with GATK Local Realignment around Indels as well as HaplotypeCaller results are also shown for comparison. Shapes in this figure represent variant depth, whereas color/shading represent caller and realignment method</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> kb. For exome or targeted sequencing, these regions roughly correspond to capture targets. For each region, a De Bruijn graph of k-mers is assembled from the input reads (Pevzner et al., 2001). K-mers containing low quality or ambiguous bases are filtered and k-mers that do not appear in at least two distinct reads are pruned from the graph, reducing the impact of sequencing errors on the assembly process. After initial pruning of the assembled graph, the graph is traversed to build contigs longer than the original read length. There is no smoothing of the graph to remove low-frequency variation, as we are interested in detecting such variation. All non-cyclic paths through the graph are traversed. In cases where a cycle in the graph is observed for a given region, that region is iteratively reassembled using increasing k-mer sizes until the cycle no longer exists or a configurable maximum k-mer size is reached. As currently implemented, detection of local insertions is limited to less than maximum k-mer size. Larger insertions of sequence from another location in the genome are likely to be aligned elsewhere and not included in local assembly, thus limiting detection of insertions as the size approaches read length. *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dindel: accurate indel calls from short-read data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Albers</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="961" to="973" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TIGRA: a targeted iterative graph routing assembler for breakpoint assembly</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="310" to="317" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational techniques for human genome resequencing using mated gapped reads</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Carnevali</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="292" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framework for variation discovery and genotyping using next-generation DNA sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Depristo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="491" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development and validation of a clinical cancer genomic profiling test based on massively parallel DNA sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Frampton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1023" to="1031" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Haplotype-based variant detection from shortread sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Garrison</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Marth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Improved variant discovery through local realignment of short-read next-generation sequencing data using SRMA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Homer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Nelson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">99</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">De novo assembly and genotyping of variants using colored de bruijn graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Iqbal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="226" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BLAT–the BLAST-like alignment tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Kent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="656" to="664" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring single-sample SNP and INDEL calling with whole-genome de novo assembly</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1838" to="1844" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Aligning sequence reads, clone sequences and assembly contigs with BWA-MEM. arXiv, 1303</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="page">3997</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast and accurate short read alignment with burrowswheeler transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Durbin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1754" to="1760" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SOAPindel: efficient identification of indels from short paired reads</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Eulerian path approach to DNA fragment assembly</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Pevzner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9748" to="9753" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strelka: accurate somatic small-variant calling from sequenced tumor-normal sample pairs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Saunders</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1811" to="1817" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Cancer Genome Atlas Network Comprehensive molecular portraits of human breast tumours</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">490</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrated RNA and DNA sequencing improves mutation detection in low purity tumors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Wilkerson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pindel: a pattern growth approach to detect break points of large deletions and medium sized insertions from paired-end short reads</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Ye</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2865" to="2871" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>