
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:39+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">ACE: accurate correction of errors using K-mer tries</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Siavash</forename>
								<surname>Sheikhizadeh</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Bioinformatics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wageningen University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>6700 AP</postCode>
									<settlement>Wageningen</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dick</forename>
								<surname>De Ridder</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Bioinformatics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wageningen University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>6700 AP</postCode>
									<settlement>Wageningen</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">ACE: accurate correction of errors using K-mer tries</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv332</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on November 23, 2014; revised on May 2, 2015; accepted on May 22, 2015</note>
					<note>Sequence analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Inanc Birol Contact: siavash.sheikhizadehanari@wur.nl Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The quality of high-throughput next-generation sequencing data significantly influences the performance and memory consumption of assembly and mapping algorithms. The most ubiquitous platform, Illumina, mainly suffers from substitution errors. We have developed a tool, ACE, based on K-mer tries to correct such errors. On real MiSeq and HiSeq Illumina archives, ACE yields higher gains in terms of coverage depth, outperforming state-of-the-art competitors in the majority of cases. Availability and implementation: ACE is licensed under the GPL license and can be freely obtained at https://github.com/sheikhizadeh/ACE/. The program is implemented in Cþþ and runs on most Unix-derived operating systems.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Genome sequencing involves reading thousands or millions of genome fragments and reconstructing the original genome, either by assembling these reads in de novo assembly projects, or aligning them to a known reference genome in re-sequencing studies. Over the last decade, next-generation sequencing (NGS) technology dramatically increased the ease with which material can be sequenced, yielding millions of short reads in a short time. The lower quality of the data (compared to Sanger sequencing) however significantly influences performance and memory consumption of assemblers and alignment algorithms; as a result, there has been a growing interest in correcting errors in short-read archives. Sequencing errors can result in substitutions, insertions, deletions and unconfirmed nucleotides represented by 'N' symbols. The most ubiquitous platform, Illumina, mostly suffers from substitution errors while for others, like 454 and Ion Torrent, insertions and deletions are most abundant. As an error at a specific genomic position occurs infrequently and randomly, an erroneous base can be detected and corrected taking advantage of the high frequency of the reads that cover that position. This is the idea behind all count-based error correction methods which count K-mers using various data structures. For example, SHREC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Schroder et al., 2009</ref>) constructs a generalized suffix trie while HiTEC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Ilie et al., 2011</ref>) uses a suffix array. Built upon SHREC, Hybrid-SHREC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Salmela, 2010</ref>) captures InDel errors as well as substitutions. SGA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Simpson and Durbin, 2012</ref>) performs error-correction using the FM-index derived from the compressed Burrows-Wheeler transform. BLESS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Heo et al., 2014</ref>) employs a bloom-filter and RACER (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Ilie and Molnar, 2013</ref>) organizes 2-bit-encoded K-mers as 64-bit integers and stores them in a hash table. Fiona, based on partial suffix array, is also able to deal with InDel errors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Schulz et al., 2013</ref>). Alternatively, K-spectrum based error correction methods, like Quake (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kelley et al., 2010</ref>) and Musket (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Liu et al., 2013</ref>) collect all K-mers appearing in the set of reads, and align those with a small Hamming distance from each other to achieve the correct consensus. Finally, MSA-based methods, like Coral (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Salmela and Schroder, 2011</ref>), apply multiple sequence alignment between reads that share K-mers to detect errors. A recent survey provides a comprehensive review of error-correction methods, and establishes a common set of benchmark data and evaluation criteria (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Molnar and Ilie, 2014</ref>). Here we present ACE, a new K-mer count-based algorithm. We employ the K-mer trie, a data structure more time/space-efficient than the suffix trees employed in SHREC. K-mer tries have been effective in solving some bioinformatics problems (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Brudno et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Sheikhizadeh and Hosseini, 2014</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>ACE is the Cþþ implementation of our algorithm, equipped with Open-MP directives to scale with the number of available processors. It organizes the K-mers of short reads (and their reverse-complement) in a K-mer trie. A K-mer trie of a sequence s (or set of sequences) is a trie of depth K which contains all K-mers of the sequence. Each edge has a label from the alphabet R; the concatenation of edge labels along the path from root to a node is called the spelled string of that node. Each leaf corresponds to one or more K-mers of s, and each node can contain the number of times that its spelled string appears in the sequence. A K-mer trie gives constant-time access to all patterns of length at most K, useful for counting and storing K-mers, detecting zygosity, determining ploidy and genome assembly. To cope with large datasets, ACE constructs K-mer sub-tries one by one (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>) by applying a prefix-based classification on K-mers and shortening them to k-mers where k ¼ K À p and p is the prefix length, determined based on the amount of available memory and the size of the input data. As the K-mer trie is very dense in the top levels, ACE further reduces memory consumption (and the size of search space) by building a root array instead of constructing the top triangle of the trie. Moreover, to efficiently organize billions of K-mers in the trie ACE applies another prefix-based division to allow parallel construction of the branches of each subtrie. In<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>, a branch has been divided into four sub-branches to be constructed and scanned for errors by four independent parallel threads. Branches are divided into 16, 64 or more sub-branches if more cores are available. More details on the algorithm, including a pseudo-code description, can be found in the Supplementary Material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>We experimentally compared the performance of ACE in increasing the coverage depth/breadth of reads/K-mers to those of seven stateof-the-art tools, using the benchmark data and following the same evaluation procedure as presented in a recent survey (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Molnar and Ilie, 2014</ref>). To be consistent with the result of<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. The gain of ACE in increasing the depth/breadth of reads/K-mers, compared to that of the best tool in<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Molnar and Ilie (2014)</ref>DepthNote: Highlights indicate the level of improvement.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>compares the gain of ACE to that of its best competitor among seven state-of-the-art read cleaners: BLESS, Coral, HiTEC, Musket, RACER, SGA and SHREC; more detailed results can be found in Supplementary Tables S3–S11. In these evaluations, Depth of coverage indicates the average number of times each base is covered by reads/K-mers and Breadth of coverage indicates the proportion of the genome covered by reads/K-mers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Molnar and Ilie, 2014</ref>). The first criterion is useful for quantitative applications and overlap-layout-consensus assembly, while the second is more applicable for de Bruijn graph-based genome assembly. ACE outperforms most other tools in terms of coverage depth gain, improving on the best competitor on 18 resp. 22 out of 22 datasets for reads resp. K-mers. In particular for MiSeq data, which contains more errors, the improvements can be significant. For coverage breadth, the picture is less clear: ACE outperforms the best alternative tool on 13 datasets on read coverage breadth gain, whereas K-mer coverage breadth gain was generally worse. However, all tools actually yield low read coverage breadth on most MiSeq data (as low as 0.25%) and decrease K-mer coverage breadth compared to the raw data (see Supplementary Tables S5–S6, S9– S10).<ref type="figure">Table 2</ref>compares the time and memory consumption of ACE to those of the three competitors which were able to successfully correct all datasets. While for most datasets memory consumption is reasonable, ACE has higher computational cost than most other tools, trading speed for accuracy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACE</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusion</head><p>We developed ACE, a command-line tool to accurately correct substitution errors in Illumina short-read archives. ACE generally outperforms the best among seven state-of-the-art read cleaners in terms of coverage depth, at higher computational cost. This makes it a useful tool for small to medium-sized datasets or applications where accuracy requirements warrant the investment in computational resources. In future work, we aim to lower the runtime of ACE by updating the K-mer trie instead of rebuilding it for each round of execution. This future version should also be able to handle InDel errors to extend its application to all sequencing platforms.Note: Time is given in seconds and memory in megabytes, both per input mega base pair.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Molnar et al., we chose the same value of K ¼ 20 for evaluations. The specifications of the MiSeq (M1–M9) and the HiSeq datasets (H1-H13) are presented in Supplementary Table 1. All experiments were conducted on a Linux server (SUSE 3.8.6-2) with an Intel V R Xeon V R ES-2667 CPU, exploiting 16 logical cores running at 2.9 GHz and 256 GB RAM.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The AT subtrie of the K-mer trie</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. Time and memory requirements of tools able to successfully correct all datasets</figDesc><table>Time (s/Mb) 
Space (MB/Mb) 

Musket RACER SGA ACE Musket RACER SGA ACE 

M1 
0.05 
0.55 
2.07 10.22 3.64 
17.80 
10.02 30.92 
M2 
0.14 
0.18 
0.85 3.14 4.31 
10.00 
5.40 5.30 
M3 
0.07 
0.27 
1.12 3.76 3.47 
7.20 
4.52 6.21 
M4 
0.07 
0.35 
1.16 3.92 3.18 
8.15 
3.95 7.01 
M5 
0.07 
0.25 
0.56 3.48 2.95 
6.24 
4.02 5.52 
M6 
0.07 
0.34 
1.25 3.90 2.35 
6.78 
3.10 5.70 
M7 
0.06 
0.23 
1.05 3.29 1.53 
3.18 
2.03 2.73 
M8 
0.06 
0.43 
1.82 8.29 0.26 
2.24 
0.90 12.86 
M9 
0.06 
0.33 
1.83 5.64 0.24 
1.21 
0.75 4.94 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">S.Sheikhizadeh and D.de Ridder at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LAGAN and Multi-LAGAN: efficient tools for largescale multiple alignment of genomic DNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Brudno</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="721" to="731" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BLESS: bloom-filter-based error correction solution for high-throughput sequencing reads</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Heo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1354" to="1362" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HiTEC: accurate error correction in high-throughput sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Ilie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RACER: rapid and accurate correction of errors in reads</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Ilie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Molnar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2490" to="2493" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quake: quality-aware detection and correction of sequencing errors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Kelley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">116</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Musket: a multistage k-mer spectrum-based error corrector for Illumina sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="308" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correcting Illumina data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Molnar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Ilie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Briefings in Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>adv. . online publication</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correction of sequencing errors in a mixed set of reads</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Salmela</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinfomatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1284" to="1290" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correcting errors in short reads by multiple alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Salmela</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Schroder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1455" to="1461" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SHREC: a short-read error correction method</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Schroder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2157" to="2163" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fiona: a parallel and automatic strategy for read error correction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Schulz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="356" to="363" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SMOTER: a structured motif finder based on an exhaustive tree-based algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Sheikhizadeh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hosseini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient de novo assembly of large genomes using compressed data structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Simpson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Durbin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="549" to="556" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>