
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression An R package suite for microarray meta-analysis in quality control, differentially expressed gene analysis and pathway enrichment detection</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">19 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xingbin</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15261</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dongwan</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Kang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Genomics Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kui</forename>
								<surname>Shen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Magee-Womens Research Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chi</forename>
								<surname>Song</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5 PharmaNet-i3, 224 Schilling Circle, Suite 160, Hunt Valley</addrLine>
									<postCode>21031</postCode>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Shuya</forename>
								<surname>Lu</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lun-Ching</forename>
								<surname>Chang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5 PharmaNet-i3, 224 Schilling Circle, Suite 160, Hunt Valley</addrLine>
									<postCode>21031</postCode>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Serena</forename>
								<forename type="middle">G</forename>
								<surname>Liao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5 PharmaNet-i3, 224 Schilling Circle, Suite 160, Hunt Valley</addrLine>
									<postCode>21031</postCode>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zhiguang</forename>
								<surname>Huo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5 PharmaNet-i3, 224 Schilling Circle, Suite 160, Hunt Valley</addrLine>
									<postCode>21031</postCode>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Shaowu</forename>
								<surname>Tang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5 PharmaNet-i3, 224 Schilling Circle, Suite 160, Hunt Valley</addrLine>
									<postCode>21031</postCode>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ying</forename>
								<surname>Ding</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computational and Systems Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Naftali</forename>
								<surname>Kaminski</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Pulmonary, Allergy and Critical Care Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Etienne</forename>
								<surname>Sibille</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yan</forename>
								<surname>Lin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5 PharmaNet-i3, 224 Schilling Circle, Suite 160, Hunt Valley</addrLine>
									<postCode>21031</postCode>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jia</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="institution">Henry Ford Health System</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>48202</postCode>
									<settlement>Detroit</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">George</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Tseng</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15261</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5 PharmaNet-i3, 224 Schilling Circle, Suite 160, Hunt Valley</addrLine>
									<postCode>21031</postCode>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression An R package suite for microarray meta-analysis in quality control, differentially expressed gene analysis and pathway enrichment detection</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2534" to="2536"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">19 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts485</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received and revised on May 2, 2012; accepted on July 29, 2012</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Trey Ideker Availability: http://www.biostat.pitt.edu/bioinfo/software.htm Contact: ctseng@pitt.edu Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>With the rapid advances and prevalence of high-throughput genomic technologies, integrating information of multiple relevant genomic studies has brought new challenges. Microarray meta-analysis has become a frequently used tool in biomedical research. Little effort, however, has been made to develop a systematic pipeline and user-friendly software. In this article, we present MetaOmics, a suite of three R packages MetaQC, MetaDE and MetaPath, for quality control, differentially expressed gene identification and enriched pathway detection for microarray meta-analysis. MetaQC provides a quantitative and objective tool to assist study in-clusion/exclusion criteria for meta-analysis. MetaDE and MetaPath were developed for candidate marker and pathway detection, which provide choices of marker detection, meta-analysis and pathway analysis methods. The system allows flexible input of experimental data, clinical outcome (case–control, multi-class, continuous or survival) and pathway databases. It allows missing values in experimental data and utilizes multi-core parallel computing for fast implementation. It generates informative summary output and visualization plots, operates on different operation systems and can be expanded to include new algorithms or combine different types of genomic data. This software suite provides a comprehensive tool to conveniently implement and compare various genomic meta-analysis pipelines.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Many high-throughput genomic technologies have advanced dramatically in the past decade. Microarray experiment is one example that has evolved into maturity with generally consensus experimental protocols and data analysis strategies. Its extensive application in the biomedical field has led to an explosion of gene expression profiling studies publicly available. Meta-analysis methods for combining multiple microarray studies have been widely applied to increase statistical power and provide validated conclusions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Tseng et al., 2012</ref>). In this article, we present the 'MetaOmics' software suite that contains three unified R packages—MetaQC, MetaDE and MetaPath—for systematic microarray meta-analysis pipeline. The MetaQC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Kang et al., 2012</ref>) package provides a quantitative and objective tool for determining the inclusion/exclusion criteria for meta-analysis. MetaDE contains many state-of-the-art genomic meta-analysis methods to detect differentially expressed genes. Finally, the MetaPath package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Shen and Tseng, 2010</ref>) provides a unified meta-analysis framework and inference to detect enriched pathways associated with outcome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">THE THREE R PACKAGES</head><p>The three R packages in MetaOmics allow flexible input format of experimental data and four different types of outcome variables (case–control, multi-class, continuous and survival). They also allow missing values in the individual experimental study or missing values caused by mismatched genes across studies (i.e. genes covered in one study but not covered in another study). For some computationally intensive routines, the packages allow usage of multi-core parallel computing for timely implementation. Detailed help files, tutorial and a case study are available in an online supplementary document as well as in the R packages. Below, we briefly describe features and functionality of the three packages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">MetaQC</head><p>MetaQC calculates the following six quantitative quality control (QC) measures: internal homogeneity of co-expression structure *To whom correspondence should be addressed. The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first three authors should be regarded as joint First Authors among studies (IQC), external consistency of co-expression pattern with pathway database (EQC) and accuracy and consistency of differentially expressed gene detection (AQCg and CQCg) or enriched pathway identification (AQCp and CQCp). Each QC index is defined as the minus log-transformed P-values from formal hypothesis testing in each QC criterion. Principal component analysis (PCA) biplots and standardized mean ranks are finally generated to assist visualization and decision. The identified problematic studies are suggested for further inspection to detect potential technical or biological causes of their low quality and to determine their exclusion from meta-analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">MetaDE</head><p>MetaDE package implements 12 major meta-analysis methods for differential expression (DE) analysis: Fisher (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Rhodes et al., 2002</ref>), Stouffer, adaptively weighted statistic (AW) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Li and Tseng, 2011</ref>), minimum P-value (minP), maximum P-value (maxP), rth ordered P-value (rOP) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Song and Tseng, 2012</ref>), fixed effects model (FEM), random effects model (REM) (<ref type="bibr">Choi et al., 2003</ref>), rank product (rankProd), rank sum (rankSum) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Hong et al., 2006</ref>), naive sum of ranks and naive product of ranks. Detailed algorithms, pros and cons of different methods have been discussed in a recent review article (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Tseng et al., 2012</ref>). Two additional considerations are involved in the implementation: (i) different choices of test statistics are available for different outcome variables, for example t-statistics, F-statistics, minimum multi-class correlation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Lu et al., 2010</ref>), linear regression, correlation coefficient and log-rank test; (ii) one-sided test correction may be needed to exclude genes with discordant DE direction (e.g. up-regulation in one study but downregulation in another study). MetaDE also provides options for gene matching across studies and gene filtering before meta-analysis. Outputs of the meta-analysis results include DE gene lists with corresponding raw P-values, q-values and various visualization tools. Heatmaps can be plotted across studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">MetaPath</head><p>MetaPath implements three meta-analysis framework for pathway enrichment analysis: MAPE_G, MAPE_P and MAPE_I (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Shen and Tseng, 2010</ref>). Meta-analyses for pathway enrichment are integrated either at the gene level (MAPE_G) or at the pathway level (MAPE_P). For MAPE_G, information across studies is combined at the gene level and then pathway enrichment analysis is applied. Conversely, for MAPE_P, pathway analysis is first performed in each study independently. The information across studies is then combined at the pathway level. Since MAPE_G and MAPE_P have been found with complementary advantages under different data structure, a hybrid framework (MAPE_I) has been developed. Similar to MetaDE, MetaPath also provides multiple options of gene matching, gene filtering, meta-analysis methods and test statistics to associate with outcomes. Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S1</ref>shows a workflow diagram of meta-analysis pipeline using the three packages. After data are preprocessed, MetaQC is applied to determine inclusion/exclusion criteria. MetaDE and MetaPath are then used to detect candidate markers or pathways associated with disease outcome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">PROSTATE CANCER EXAMPLE</head><p>To demonstrate application of MetaQC, MetaDE and MetaPath, we collected nine prostate cancer studies (Welsh, Yu, Lapointe, Varambally, Singh, Wallace, Nanni, Tomlins and Dhanasekaran), which contained normal and primary cancer samples. After gene matching by official gene symbols, preprocessing and filtering, 4441 genes were used for meta-analysis.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1A</ref>shows result of the MetaQC PCA biplot. Three of the nine studies (Nanni, Tomlins and Dhanasekaran) were determined with lower quality and were removed from meta-analysis.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1B</ref>shows the number of detected DE genes under different FDR threshold in the remaining six single study analysis and meta-analyses by Fisher, maxP, rOP (r ¼ 4) and AW methods. It is clear that meta-analysis usually detects more candidate markers, except for maxP. Finally,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1C</ref>and D shows a heatmap of detected pathways (q-value50.2 in any method) and Venn diagram of pathways detected by MAPE_P, MAPE_G and MAPE_I using MetaPath. The majority of the detected pathways appeared to be cancer related. Single-study analyses showed very weak pathway enrichment; MAPE_P and MAPE_G appeared to have complementary detection power (identified 23 and 15 pathways with only 5 in common). MAPE_I detected the largest number of pathways (34 pathways).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: The National Institutes of Health (MH077159, MH094862, HL095397 and HL101715). Conflict of inerest: None declared. REFERENCES Choi,J.K. et al. (2003) Combining multiple microarray studies and modeling interstudy variation. Bioinformatics, 19, i84–i90. A B C D</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. (A) PCA bi-plot from MetaQC. (B) Number of detected DE genes under different q-value threshold. (C) Heatmap showing minus logged q-values of detected pathways. (D) Venn diagram of detected pathways by the three MAPE methods</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">R package suite at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">X.Wang et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RankProd: a bioconductor package for detecting differentially expressed genes in meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Hong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2825" to="2827" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MetaQC: objective quality control and inclusion/exclusion criteria for genomic meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Kang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An adaptively weighted statistic for detecting differential gene expression when combining multiple transcriptomic studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Tseng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Appl. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="994" to="1019" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biomarker detection in the integration of multiple multi-class genomic studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Lu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="340" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meta-analysis of microarrays: interstudy validation of gene expression profiles reveals pathway dysregulation in prostate cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Rhodes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4427" to="4433" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hypothesis setting and order statistic for robust genomic meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Song</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Tseng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Applied Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>In. press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meta-analysis for pathway enrichment analysis when combining multiple genomic studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Shen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Tseng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1316" to="1323" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive literature review and statistical considerations for microarray meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Tseng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3785" to="3799" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>