
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:34+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis Assessing association between protein truncating variants and quantitative traits</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">19 2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Manuel</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Rivas</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matti</forename>
								<surname>Pirinen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Molecular Medicine Finland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Helsinki</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>00290</postCode>
									<settlement>Helsinki, Finland</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matthew</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Neville</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Oxford Centre for Diabetes, Endocrinology and Metabolism</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Radcliffe Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>OX3 7LJ</postCode>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">OUH Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>OX3 7LE</postCode>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kyle</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Gaulton</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Loukas</forename>
								<surname>Moutsianas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Molecular Medicine Finland</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Helsinki</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>00290</postCode>
									<settlement>Helsinki, Finland</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Got2d</forename>
								<surname>Consortium</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Cecilia</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Lindgren</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Fredrik</forename>
								<surname>Karpe</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Oxford Centre for Diabetes, Endocrinology and Metabolism</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Radcliffe Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>OX3 7LJ</postCode>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">OUH Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>OX3 7LE</postCode>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mark</forename>
								<forename type="middle">I</forename>
								<surname>Mccarthy</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Oxford Centre for Diabetes, Endocrinology and Metabolism</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Radcliffe Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>OX3 7LJ</postCode>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Peter</forename>
								<surname>Donnelly</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>donnelly@well.ox.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>OX1 3TG</postCode>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename>
								<surname>Barrett</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Wellcome Trust Centre for Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>OX3 7BN</postCode>
									<settlement>Nuffield, Oxford</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis Assessing association between protein truncating variants and quantitative traits</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2419" to="2426"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">19 2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt409</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 29, 2013; revised on June 14, 2013; accepted on July 8, 2013</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: In sequencing studies of common diseases and quantitative traits, power to test rare and low frequency variants individually is weak. To improve power, a common approach is to combine statistical evidence from several genetic variants in a region. Major challenges are how to do the combining and which statistical framework to use. General approaches for testing association between rare variants and quantitative traits include aggregating genotypes and trait values, referred to as &apos;collapsing&apos;, or using a score-based variance component test. However, little attention has been paid to alternative models tailored for protein truncating variants. Recent studies have highlighted the important role that protein truncating variants, commonly referred to as &apos;loss of function&apos; variants, may have on disease susceptibility and quantitative levels of biomarkers. We propose a Bayesian modelling framework for the analysis of protein truncating variants and quantitative traits. Results: Our simulation results show that our models have an advantage over the commonly used methods. We apply our models to sequence and exome-array data and discover strong evidence of association between low plasma triglyceride levels and protein trun-cating variants at APOC3 (Apolipoprotein C3). Availability: Software is available from http://www.well.ox.ac.uk/ ~rivas/mamba Contact:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Advances in DNA sequencing and customized exome arrays are quickly transforming the landscape of genomic studies of diseases and related quantitative traits (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bonnefond et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Jonsson et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Momozawa et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Nejentsev et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rivas et al., 2011</ref>). In sequencing studies of common diseases and quantitative traits, power to individually test any rare or low frequency variant is typically weak in attainable sample sizes. Hence, to boost the ability to detect signal, evidence is combined across variants. When designing such an 'aggregation' test, there are three main questions to consider:</p><p>Across which biological units should variants be combined?</p><p>Which variants mapping within those units should be included?</p><p>Which statistical models should be used?</p><p>As for the first question, an obvious choice of biological unit across which to combine variants is the gene, and we focus on this throughout the article, considering all the coding sequence of the gene as the relevant unit. An alternative would be to combine variants across all genes within a pathway, but this adds several complications, not least because of the currently rather imprecise knowledge of biological pathways. Within a gene one could include all observed variants, but this would be likely to include many neutral variants and/or variants with opposite direction of effects, both of which can lead to loss of power under many statistical methods. The ideal approach would be to combine only those variants that affect the trait of interest. This is, however, difficult in practice because these will not be known in advance. One approximation would be to include only the variants with functional effects. Even this is challenging with current limited knowledge of the function of coding variants in the human genome: commonly used predictors of the function of non-synonymous variants (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Adzhubei et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kumar et al., 2009</ref>) can often be unreliable (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Flanagan et al., 2010</ref>). One class of variants where functional prediction is much more straightforward is that which truncates the resulting protein product (stop-gain, frameshift coding, splice disrupting). The functional prediction is made based on the translational consequence of a mutation against a reference transcript set, for example, Gencode. Protein truncating variants (PTVs) are typically subject to nonsense-mediated decay (NMD), a cellular mechanism that detects nonsense mutations and prevents the expression of truncated proteins, resulting in loss of function of that copy of the protein. To a first approximation, PTVs are thus likely to have the same functional consequence, namely, loss of function *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>y</head><p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><p>(though see below for a more nuanced treatment), so that variants in this class within a gene may naturally be combined in assessing their effect on a trait or phenotype of interest. A second reason for focussing on PTVs is that there is ample evidence from studies of Mendelian phenotypes, common diseases and quantitative traits (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chen et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Herman et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Jones et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Pollin et al., 2008</ref>) that PTVs play an important role in the genetic architecture of human traits. Recent studies have highlighted and characterized PTVs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Cohen et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Hofker, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Isidor et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">MacArthur et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Musunuru et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Nejentsev et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rivas et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Schonfeld, 2003</ref>), commonly referred to as 'loss of function' (LoF) variants (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">MacArthur et al., 2012</ref>). These studies describe the effect and frequency of PTVs: they can have strong effects on phenotype, and they are, in general, rare, as selection has played a role in preventing them from reaching a high frequency in the population (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">MacArthur et al., 2012</ref>). Here, we introduce a new statistical method for assessing association between PTVs and quantitative traits. We first consider the straightforward case in which all PTVs are assumed to have the same effect, which would be appropriate, for example, if all caused loss of function. We then extend this approach to allow for the possibility that some PTVs have one effect and some have another, for example, if most PTVs are subject to NMD, and hence are LoF, whereas some (e.g. in the final exon) escape NMD and can act as loss of function, gain of function (by deleting an inhibitory domain) or neutral variants. The approach could be extended to allow more than two groups of PTVs, with PTVs in each group having the same effect, but for definiteness we focus in this article on the case of either one or two groups. We study the properties of the new method and compare it with other approaches. A simple alternative to our similar effects model is to use the mean trait value of the PTV carriers as the test statistic [see e.g. the collapsing methods of<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Li and Leal (2008)]</ref>. Other methods in our comparisons include the sequence kernel association test (SKAT) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al., 2011</ref>), SKAT-O (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Lee et al., 2012</ref>) and multiple linear regression. SKAT is a variance component test that allows variants with different direction of effects and maintains power when variants in a unit are non-causal, but is less powerful than the collapsing methods for variants with similar effects; SKAT-O uses the data to optimally combine the collapsing test and the non-collapsing SKAT, but pays a penalty for combining multiple methods in a single test (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Lee et al., 2012</ref>). These methods have been described and compared in<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bacanu et al. (2012)</ref>and Basu and Pan (2011). The main difference between our methods and the previously existing ones is that our Bayesian model comparison framework automatically incorporates information about the factors affecting power of the study (such as the number of PTV carriers). We discuss how this affects the ranking of genes within a study. We apply our methods to unpublished sequence and exomesingle nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)-array data and find a strong signal at APOC3 where PTVs lead to decreased plasma triglyceride levels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>Assume that among N individuals studied, n individuals carry one of the k PTVs observed in a gene considered, typically n ( N. Because PTVs are typically rare, we will assume here that individuals carry at most one such variant. (Two PTVs on the same chromosome are likely to have the same effect as one PTV, and individuals with PTVs on both chromosomes could be treated either as a separate class or in the same class if a dominant model were thought appropriate.) The same PTV might be carried by several individuals. We denote by Y 1 ,. .. , Y N the standardized quantitative trait values of the individuals and assume that the trait values Y 1 ,. .. , Y n correspond to the carriers of PTVs and the values Y nþ1 ,. .. , Y N correspond to the noncarriers of PTVs. We further assume that standardized trait values across the whole sample follow a standard normal distribution. If necessary this can be achieved by applying quantile normalization. If the PTV has a big effect on the trait, individuals carrying PTVs might have extreme trait values, which would be moved closer to the other values under quantile normalization. In this setting, there is a potential loss of power through quantile normalization, but we see this as being outweighed by the additional robustness it provides. Outlying observations can occur for many reasons aside from genetics (typically measurement errors), and the individuals who have these outlying observations will have PTVs at some genes, so that in the context of a genome-wide analysis, failure to quantile normalize can lead to a strong (false-positive) signal at the genes where the individuals with the outlying observations have a PTV. Analogous issues arise in Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) for quantitative traits where individuals with extreme trait values can contribute to a strong signal at SNPs where they are called homozygous for a rare variant. Under the null model, the gene does not affect the trait, and hence the trait values among both the PTV carriers and the PTV non-carriers follow the standard normal distribution: NULL :Y i $ N ð0, 1 2 Þ, for i ¼1, 2,. .. , n Y j $ N 0, 1 2 À Á , for j ¼ n þ 1, n þ 2,. .. , N:</p><p>The statistical challenge is then in principle straightforward: one looks for (strong) evidence against the null hypothesis. In effect, this reduces to asking whether Y 1 ,. .. , Y n follow a standard normal distribution. (If PTVs at the gene under consideration do affect trait values, this will also cause a deviation from normality for Y nþ1 ,. .. , Y N , when the entire sample is quantile normalized together, but because n ( N, this effect will be small, and we only look for evidence of departure from the null at Y 1 ,. .. , Y n .) One could adopt either a frequentist or a Bayesian statistical approach to the problem. We consider both, but we see substantial advantages here in adopting a Bayesian framework, for reasons we return to below. The Bayesian approach requires specification of the alternative hypothesis. We first consider the setting, which we call the similar effects model (SEM), where all PTVs have the same effect on gene function, and hence on the distribution of trait values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Similar effects model</head><p>Under the SEM, we assume that the effect of a PTV is to shift the mean of the distribution of trait values, so that the trait values of the PTV carriers follow a normal distribution with mean and standard deviation s, whereas the trait values for the remaining individuals follow a standard normal distribution:</p><formula>SEM :Y i $ N ð, s 2 Þ, for i ¼ 1, 2,. .. , n Y j $ N ð0, 1 2 Þ, for j ¼ n þ 1, n þ 2,. .. , N:</formula><p>In this work, we fix the value of s ¼ 1, but more general approaches could also allow a change under the alternative hypothesis in the variance of trait values, or potentially in their distribution. A change in variance could be handled easily if a conjugate prior were used; because the number of individuals with PTVs will typically be small, power to detect a change in the distribution of trait values will be limited.</p><p>To complete the specification of the alternative model, we must specify the distribution of the trait mean under the alternative hypothesis. Because it will not usually be known in advance whether PTVs will increase or decrease trait values, we use a 50:50 mixture of two normal distributions as a prior for :</p><formula>$ 1 2 N ðÀa, t 2 Þ þ 1 2 N ða, t 2 Þ,</formula><p>We fix the hyperparameters to a ¼ 1:5 and t 2 ¼ 0:5. With these values, 95% of the prior mass for lies in the set ðÀ2:89, À 0:12Þ [ ð0:12, 2:89Þ. In a Bayesian framework, the appropriate way to compare the null and alternative models is via the Bayes factor (BF) defined as the ratio of the probability densities of the observed data under the two models. In our setting, the BF reduces to a ratio of densities involving only trait values of the carriers of PTVs (Y PTV ¼ fY 1 ,. .. , Y n g) because under both models the data on the non-carriers of PTVs have the same distribution.</p><formula>BF SEM ¼ PrðYjSEMÞ PrðYjNULLÞ ¼ PrðY PTV jSEMÞ PrðY PTV jNULLÞ ¼ R Q i fðY i j</formula><p>, s 2 Þð0:5f ðj À a, t 2 Þ þ 0:5f ðja, t 2 ÞÞd Q i fðY i j0, 1 2 Þ ¼ 0:5 BFða, t, s, f1,. .. , ngÞ þ 0:5 BFðÀa, t, s, f1,. .. , ngÞ, where f ðÁjd, vÞ is the density function of the normal distribution with mean d and variance v and BFða, t, s, IÞ ¼ s ÀjIj t À1 jIj</p><formula>s 2 þ 1 t 2 À0:5</formula><p>Â exp À0:5a 2 t À2 À 0:5 s À2 À 1</p><formula>À Á X i Y 2 i ! Â exp P i Yi s 2 þ a t 2 2 2 jIj s 2 þ 1 t 2 À Á 0 B B B @ 1 C C C A ,</formula><p>where the index i runs through the index set I whose size is jIj.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Grouped effects model</head><p>In some biological contexts, different PTVs may have different effects on the trait. For example, different PTVs can affect different transcript isoforms, either trigger or escape NMD, or act as dominant gain of function variants, all of which have been observed in genes predisposing to cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Futreal et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Isidor et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Ruark et al., 2013</ref>). To cater for this setting, we extend our alternative model by allowing different groups of PTVs to have different impacts on the trait. Analysis of RNA sequencing data confirms that transcripts with premature termination codons 50 bp upstream of the final exon–exon junction escape NMD (Geuvadis RNA-Sequencing Project, unpublished data). The mutant mRNA products may well lead to resulting truncated proteins that act in a loss of function, or gain of function manner as observed in NOTCH2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Isidor et al., 2011</ref>) or have no impact on a trait. A prudent thing to do is to have an alternative model where PTVs450 bp upstream of the final exon–exon boundary could be placed in one of the groups with all other PTVs in the other group. However, the limitation in this setting is that it may well be the case that variants that escape NMD have a similar effect on trait values as variants that trigger NMD, or have no effect. We extend our alternative model and use biologically informed weights to reflect this: Let G be the set of all 2 k possible assignments of the k PTVs into two groups labelled þ and À. For any grouping g 2 G, let I þ ðgÞ and I À ðgÞ be the sets of indexes of the individuals who carry PTVs that g assigns to groups þ and À, respectively. We define the model</p><formula>GEMðgÞ :Y i $ N ð þ , s 2 Þ, for i 2 I þ ðgÞ Y i $ N ð À , s 2 Þ, for i 2 I À ðgÞ Y j $ N ð0, 1 2 Þ, for j4n:</formula><p>Our priors are þ $ N ða, t 2 Þ and À $ N ðÀa, t 2 Þ, with a ¼ 1:5 and t 2 ¼ 0:5, and again we keep s ¼ 1 fixed. In other words, we assume that the phenotype of an individual with a truncating variant in a relevant gene will be towards the tails of the distribution. The BF between GEMðgÞ and the null model is</p><formula>BF GEM ðgÞ ¼ PrðYjGEMðgÞÞ PrðYjNULLÞ ¼ PrðY PTV jGEMðgÞÞ PrðY PTV jNULLÞ ¼ R Q i2IþðgÞ f ðY i j þ , s 2 Þf ð þ ja, t 2 Þd þ Q i2IþðgÞ fðY i j0, 1 2 Þ Â R Q i2IÀðgÞ f ðY i j À , s 2 Þf ð À j À a, t 2 Þd À Q i2IÀðgÞ fðY i j0, 1 2 Þ ¼ BFða, t, s, I þ ðgÞÞ Â BFðÀa, t, s, I À ðgÞÞ</formula><p>We define the final GEM as a linear combination of submodels GEMðgÞ by choosing a weight w g ! 0 for each grouping g 2 G with the constraint P g w g ¼ 1: The corresponding BF is</p><formula>BF GEM ¼ X g2G w g BF GEM ðgÞ:</formula><p>Note that by giving a weight of 0.5 to each of the two groupings in which all variants belong to the same group, and a weight of 0 to all other groupings, we are back to the SEM. We refer to the approach that uses biologically informed weights based on NMD predictions as grouped effects model (GEM)-NMD. Let I 1 ðI 0 Þ be the indexes of individuals carrying variants that are predicted to trigger (escape) NMD. We define model GEM-NMD by using w g / 1 for such groupings g 2 G in which individuals in I 1 and individuals in I 0 belong to different groups and by using w g / 2 À minfjIþðgÞj, jIÀðgÞg for other groupings. In sequencing datasets even for current large experiments, the numbers of PTVs in any gene will tend to be small, meaning that there are only few data for distinguishing the null and alternative models. Use of the GEM requires averaging over submodels corresponding to different assignments of PTVs to groups. In the absence of good biological information (such as escape or not from NMD as just described) to assign PTVs to groups, or equivalently to heavily constrain the prior on submodels, the averaging across submodels is likely to come at a considerable cost in power in these settings. In our simulation study and application below, we thus focus only on GEM-NMD, rather than the more general versions of the GEM model. Finally, we note that under GEM-NMD the averaging over submodels described above maintains the symmetry in SEM: under the prior, the probability that a particular group of PTVs increases trait values while the other group decreases them is the same as the probability that the first group decreases trait values and the second increases them. This is appropriate biologically because it will typically not be possible to predict in advance, for example, whether loss of function mutations will cause an increase or decrease in trait values.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>provides an illustration of the prior and sampling distribution for SEM and GEM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Other approaches</head><p>When expecting similar effects across the variants, a simple alternative to our SEM is to use 1 n ð P n i¼1 Y i Þ 2 as a test statistic (with 2 1 distribution under the null). We call this approach Collapse because it is similar in spirit to the collapsing methods of<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Li and Leal (2008)</ref>. Other methods that we use in comparisons are the SKAT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al., 2011</ref>), with the default weight parameters of<ref type="bibr">Beta(1,25)</ref>for the linear weighted kernel and Davies' method to compute the P-value, SKAT-O (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Lee et al., 2012</ref>) using method ¼ 'optimal' and multiple linear regression (lm) as</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2421</head><p>Association between protein truncating variants and quantitative traits implemented in R. Our method and Collapse use the normalized trait values only from the PTV carriers; other methods use trait values on all individuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Simulation study</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1">Comparison of SEM and Collapse</head><p>For a fixed value of n, both P-value from Collapse and BF SEM (with s 2 ¼ 1) depend on the data only through P n i¼1 Y i , and both show monotonically increasing deviation from the null model with increasing P n i¼1 Y i . It follows that SEM (with s 2 ¼ 1) shares the frequentist properties of Collapse, i.e. has the same power and produces the same P-values under the null if used as a test statistic. However, a main difference between the methods is that this similarity does not hold across genes with different numbers of PTVs. Rankings across all genes in a study by BF and by P-value will in general be different, and for the reasons given in the Discussion, ranking by BF is preferable.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 2</ref>provides an illustration of this effect. In it, the Pvalue is fixed at 0.001, and the figure plots, for different values of n, both the mean value of the trait among PTV carriers and the BF. Because the P-value is fixed, any gene with this combination of n and mean trait value would have the same P-value and hence the same rank in the P-value-based ranking. The ranking by BF is lower for small n and for larger n, compared with intermediate values of n. When n is small (say 1 or 2), there are few observations of traits for PTV carriers, so limited power to assess the null and alternative hypotheses. To achieve a small P-value, these observations need to be relatively large in absolute value, but the Bayesian approach will downweight them because of the limited amount of data, and the prior assumption that changes of that magnitude in trait values for PTV carriers are unlikely. The relative downweighting in the Bayesian approach of datasets with large n is for a different reason and is related to Lindley's paradox in statistics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Lindley, 1957</ref>). For example, with n ¼ 50, the data correspond to a rather small change in mean trait values. The Bayesian approach compares the probability of this under the null (closely related to the P-value) with the probability under the alternative, and it turns out that this small change is also relatively unlikely under the alternative (because the alternative assigns most of its mass to larger changes in trait value), reducing the BF.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">Critical values when</head><p>the BF is used as a test statistic For ease of use, we provide a table of critical values of the BF when it is used as a frequentist test statistic. As mentioned previously, we are able to evaluate the null distribution of BF SEM (with s 2 ¼ 1) analytically, and hence to calculate critical values analytically. For GEM-NMD, the same can be done by simulations.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>gives the critical value for the BF corresponding to the type I error rates () of (i) 0.01, (ii) 0.001 and (iii) 0.0001, evaluated at different numbers of observed PTVs (n ¼ 3, 4, 5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.3">Power comparisons</head><p>We performed power comparisons among the various frequentist approaches, including the use of the BFs described above as frequentist test statistics. First consider the scenario when all PTVs at a gene have the same effect on the trait, as would be expected for typical 'loss of function' variants. To assess this, we simulated 3–5 PTVs each seen in a single individual. Trait values for PTV carriers were drawn from an N 2, 1 ð Þ distribution, and the remaining trait values for a total of 2000 trait observations were drawn from an N 0, 1 ð Þ. For this scenario (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>), the most powerful methods are our SEM and Collapse, which, as explained above, have exactly the same power. SKAT-O (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Lee et al., 2012</ref>) comes next, and the power is the lowest for SKAT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al., 2011</ref>) and linear regression. In the second scenario, we assumed that PTVs in a gene contribute to trait variance and can have an effect in opposite directions, with the direction of effect specified by the impact of</p><formula>(a) ( b) i. ii. iii. i. ii. iii. 1 1 0 0 s s s 2 2 2 µ µ µ</formula><p>Prior on µ and µ Prior on µ a-a-a a</p><formula>, Y i $ N , s 2 À Á ; and</formula><p>(iii) 50:50 mixture of two normal distributions as prior for</p><formula>$ 1 2 N Àa, t 2 À Á þ 1 2 N a, t 2 À Á .</formula><formula>þ $ N a, t 2 À Á and À $ N Àa, t 2 À Á M.A.Rivas et al.</formula><p>NMD (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). In our simulation of this scenario, trait values were drawn from an N À2, 1 ð Þdistribution for individuals with a copy of a variant predicted to trigger NMD, and N 2, 1 ð Þ for individuals with a copy of a variant predicted to escape NMD and N 0, 1 ð Þ otherwise (one variant was selected to escape NMD). Not surprisingly, GEM-NMD, which uses information on NMD, is clearly the most powerful model. Next comes SKAT and linear regression, then SKAT-O and last SEM and Collapse, which have almost no power in this scenario. In addition, we included a weighted version of SKAT (SKATw) in the power comparisons. For the variants predicted to trigger NMD, we assigned a weight of ffiffi ffi 2 p , and for the variants predicted to escape NMD, we assigned a weight of 1. This approach ranks below SKAT-O but above Collapse and SEM. There may be scenarios in which a putative variant is erroneously labelled as a PTV, for example, because of a sequencing artifact or an incorrect annotation. In these settings, our approach will lose power. To illustrate this, we focus on the SEM and simulations applied in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. We assume that one of the n ¼ 3, 4, 5 PTVs is actually a sequencing artifact and that the trait value of the corresponding individual is drawn from a standard normal distribution. In this case, power to detect the association decreases to 13,35 and 55% for n ¼ 3, 4, 5, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Application of the method to plasma triglyceride levels and truncating variant data from the Genetics of Type 2 Diabetes study and Oxford Biobank study</head><p>We applied the proposed approach to exome-sequencing data from the Genetics of Type 2 Diabetes (GoT2D) study and plasma triglyceride levels. The dataset consisted of 2760 T2D cases and control individuals of Northern European descent. Exome target capture was performed with the Agilent SureSelect Human All Exon hybrid selection kit and sequence obtained on HiSeq. Subsequent alignment and allele calling used Burrows-Wheeler Aligner (BWA) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Li and Durbin, 2010</ref>) and Genome Analysis Toolkit (GATK) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">DePristo et al., 2011</ref>) generating 688 731 variants that passed quality control and were included in the analysis. To illustrate the performance of our models, we focus here on data for APOC3 for which a null mutation p.R19X has previously been implicated to be associated to plasma lipid profile and apparent cardioprotection (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Hofker, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Pollin et al., 2008</ref>). Variant annotation in using the pyplinkseq library (part of PLINK/SEQ toolset [http://atgu.mgh.harvard.edu/plinkseq/] and MAMBA dependency), identifies two candidate PTVs predicted to trigger NMD: the previously mentioned stop-gain mutation, p.R19X (MAF ¼ 0.00025, allele count ¼ 1), and a donor essential splice variant c.IVS2 þ 1G 4A (MAF¼ 0.002, allele count ¼ 8). After application of the SEM to the data, the posterior distribution indicates that plasma triglyceride levels of individuals with PTVs at APOC3 are 1.2 standard deviations (SD) lower than the population mean, indicating a strong effect (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 3</ref>). The effects of the splice and the stop-gain variants are at 1.19 and 1.44 SD below the population mean, respectively (BF for SEM ¼ 63.44). The splice variant explains 0.29% of the trait variance in our data, whereas the null mutation explains 0.04% of the trait variance. To compare with other methods, we applied (i) Collapse, (ii) SKAT, (iii) SKAT-O and (iv) multiple linear regression to the data (<ref type="figure">Table 3</ref>). We find that our models, Collapse and SKAT-O give similar results (as measured by P-value), whereas SKAT and lm give clearly larger P-values, probably because they are not assuming similar effect sizes across the two variants. When we compare the ranks of genes in an exome-wide analysis, the SEM and SKAT rank APOC3 as #3 and #5, respectively. We were able to confirm these effects using Illumina exome array genotyping in the Oxford Biobank cohort (n ¼ 4443 samples,<ref type="bibr">[</ref>Note: a A total of 10 000 000 replicates were generated to evaluate critical values at the corresponding Type I error rate together with its 95% confidence intervals (L95, U95). The critical values for SEM were calculated analytically.Note: For GEM-NMD, thresholds for the given type I error rate are given in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Association between protein truncating variants and quantitative traits</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Application of the method</head><p>Larger BFs correspond to stronger evidence in favour of the alternative hypothesis over the null. The BF calculated in our approach has a direct interpretation as the way in which the data changes the weight, which should be given to the null and alternative hypotheses. Formally, the posterior odds (i.e. in the light of the data) on the alternative hypothesis can be calculated by multiplying the prior odds (i.e. before the data) by the BF. We envisage that a primary application of this and similar methods will be in the analysis of quantitative traits measured in individuals for whom whole-genome or whole-exome sequence data are available, or perhaps for whom genetic data are obtained from an exome-SNP-array. For a single dataset one could use the size of the BF to indicate the strength of the evidence in favour of the alternative hypothesis. It can also be helpful to plot the posterior distribution on the mean trait value for individuals carrying PTVs. Many studies will consist of two phases, discovery and replication. In this setting, analyses of the discovery data would aim to rank genes for follow-up according to the evidence for departures from the null hypothesis at that gene. In such a ranking exercise, the use of BFs has considerable advantages over the use of P-values. The interpretation of a P-value obtained in a particular experiment depends on both the alternative hypothesis and the power of the statistical method used. In the current context, power will change with n, the number of PTVs observed at the gene: there will be more power to reject the null hypothesis (for a specific alternative hypothesis) at genes that happen to have more PTVs in the sample, and as a consequence, informally, a low P-value will be more informative for a gene with more PTVs than the same P-value would be for a gene with fewer PTVs. For this reason, simple ranking of genes by P-value is unlikely to be optimal. In contrast, BFs quantify the evidence for the alternative hypothesis as compared with the null (P-values only measure tail probabilities under the null), so can be compared naturally even for genes with different numbers of PTVs. Although we see advantages in adopting a Bayesian perspective, our approach could be used in a frequentist context by calculating the BF and using this as a frequentist test statistic. Conditional on the number of PTV carriers at the gene, n, a Pvalue can then be obtained by asking for the probability, under the null hypothesis, of obtaining the same or a larger BF than the one actually calculated from the data. Under the SEM, the null distribution of the BF can be calculated explicitly, allowing a simple analytic computation of P-values. For more complicated alternative hypotheses, P-values can be obtained easily by simulation under the null. In the SEM setting, the statistical problem is a simple one, namely, of detecting a mean shift in a (typically small) number of observations. Our method is the obvious Bayesian approach to the problem, and when the resulting BF is used as a test statistic it is effectively equivalent to the obvious frequentist approach. We have, necessarily, used particular prior distributions for the change in mean trait value caused by the PTVs. In our method these are relatively broad, but they could be adjusted as our biological knowledge grows, as could the priors in the GEMthe second is that a more precise specification of the prior will gain power if it reflects reality but could substantially lose power otherwise. What are the sample sizes required to obtain exome-wide significant results? Under the assumption that effect sizes are 2, 1.5 and 1 SDs from the mean, to get a P-value of 2:5 Â 10 À6 (where 2:5 Â 10 À6 is obtained by Bonferroni correction ¼ 0.05/ number of genes), using the SEM would require 8, 14 and 31 PTV carriers, respectively, to achieve 80% power to detect the association. PTV frequencies are likely to vary orders of magnitude between genes, and our current understanding is that only a limited number of genes have a low frequency (40.1%) PTV, whereas in most genes any single PTV will be private or extremely rare. If a fraction 10 Àk of the population (k ¼ 2, 3, 4,. . .) carries a PTV at a particular gene, then we need to sample $1:0 Â 10 1þk , 1:7 Â 10 1þk or 3:6 Â 10 1þk individuals to achieve 80% probability of finding at least 8, 14 or 31 PTV carriers at that gene, respectively. As we generate more cellular genomics data, we will improve our understanding of the impact of PTVs on gene function. For example, combining DNA and RNA sequence data will enable better predictions of mechanisms underlying NMD, which will, in turn, give more accurate predictions of the biological consequences that the analyzed variants may have. Current annotation of loss of function variants is based on some reference transcript set, for example, GENCODE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Harrow et al., 2012</ref>), and selection of variants mapping within the units to include is chosen from the most deleterious annotation across all transcripts. Transcript quantifications for the relevant tissue or cell types will enable better annotation and selection of rare variants for combining in statistical analyses. Thus, now is a good time to think about how this knowledge can be used in future data analyses. Our Bayesian framework provides one way to do this, and we hope that it will stimulate research on both the methodological aspects of these models and on the enhanced prior specification based on biological knowledge.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">CONCLUSION</head><p>We have developed and studied a novel statistical method for assessing the association between PTVs and a quantitative trait. The approach is formulated in a Bayesian statistical framework, and can be used in a Bayesian framework or in providing a test statistic for frequentist application. Bayesian application is recommended in ranking genes for follow-up in a discovery dataset. The frequentist application allows calculation of P-values for association, which can be helpful in settings where these are required. We have presented two versions of the method. In the first, SEM, all PTVs are assumed to have effects in the same direction. This would be appropriate, for example, if all PTVs were thought to result in loss of function of that copy of the gene. We also described a more general version of the approach allowing different classes of PTV in terms of their effect on trait values. We see the major application of this more general method in taking a more nuanced view of the consequences of PTVs, and distinguishing between those likely to be subjected to NMD and those that escape NMD (e.g. many or all PTVs in the last exon of the gene) and may result in gain of function. As our biological understanding of the NMD mechanism increases, we expect that it will add power to allow potentially different effects for PTVs escaping NMD, for example, by applying GEM-NMD (in which they may have similar effects or different effects) and SEM (in which their effect on the trait would be the same, even though the molecular consequences of the mutation would be different). Finally, we have established and replicated an association between PTVs in APOC3 and lowering of plasma triglyceride levels.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Plots of mean trait value for PTV carriers (X-axis) and BF from SEM (a ¼ 1:5, t 2 ¼ 0:5, s 2 ¼ 1) (Y-axis), for different values of n (written next to each point) the number of PTV carriers, for a fixed P-value of 0.001. The dashed line shows the density of the prior (restricted to positive values) on mean effect size under SEM (not on scale)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. (a) Prior and sampling distribution for the SEM: (i) distribution of the trait values under the null model, Y i $ N 0, 1 ð Þ; (ii) distribution of the trait values under the alternative model, Y i $ N , s 2 À Á ; and (iii) 50:50 mixture of two normal distributions as prior for $ 1 2 N Àa, t 2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>(b) Prior and sampling distribution for the GEM: (i) distribution of the trait values under the null model; (ii) under the alternative model, trait values are grouped around þ and À ; and (iii) priors for</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><figDesc>http://www.oxfordbiobank.org.uk]). Quantification of plasma triglyceride concentrations in the Oxford Biobank was made after an overnight fast. Combined analysis of plasma triglyceride levels and variant genotype data for c.IVS2 þ 1G 4A (allele count ¼ 3) and p.R19X (allele count ¼ 31) from the Oxford Biobank cohort and the GoT2D samples demonstrates strong supporting evidence for protein truncating variant association to low plasma triglyceride levels (BF for SEM ¼ 8 Â 10 8 ). The combined posterior effect size for c.IVS2 þ 1G 4A and p.R19X is 1.23 and 1.66 SD below the mean, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. (a) Protein and transcript locations of APOC3 mutations, including predicted impact of splice variant on transcript splicing. Transcript diagram demonstrates that variant c.IVS2 þ 1G 4A will disrupt proper splicing of the second exon and create a new spliced mRNA with exon 1 and exon 3 joining because of proper recognition of splice sequence in the donor site of exon 1 and acceptor site of exon 3. Genomic codon position is shown for the stop-gain mutation, i.e. g.55C 4T. (b) Prior, likelihood and posterior of mean trait value after combining data from the Oxford Biobank study and GoT2D study. The shaded histogram in each panel represents the distribution of trait values for the relevant PTV carriers</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Critical values for BFs from SEM and GEM-NMD corresponding to different Type I error rates () with 3, 4 and 5 PTVs</figDesc><table>NPTV 
SEM 
GEM-NMD a 

0.01 
3 
8.765 
9.34 (9.30,9.39) 
4 
7.77 
8.93 (8.88,8.98) 
5 
6.81 
8.36 (8.32,8.41) 
0.001 
3 
64.56 
59.94 (59.01,60.84) 
4 
63.98 
63.99 (62.76,65.01) 
5 
60.07 
63.81 (62.63,64.94) 
0.0001 
3 
438.45 
362.10 (349.11,380.70) 
4 
489.86 
438.52 (412.02,460.90) 
5 
496.85 
459.96.72 (434.96,484.73) 
0.00001 
3 
2814.95 
2035.51 (1790.69,2277.75) 
4 
3564.12 
2703.12 (2336.41,3197.85) 
5 
3924.31 
3199.53 (2778.93,3765.76) 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2.</figDesc><table>Power, expressed as a percentage, at ¼ 0:001, to detect asso-
ciation for two scenarios: (i) variants impact trait values in same direction 
with similar effects, and (ii) variants impact trait values in different dir-
ections with direction of effect determined by NMD 

¼ 0:001 
Similar 
Grouped 

N P T V 
3 
4 
5 
3 
4 
5 
SKAT 
42 
49 
69 
44 
55 
66 
SKAT-O 
53 
65 
86 
37 
45 
60 
Collapse 
55 
81 
86 
2 
0 
1 
SEM 
55 
81 
86 
2 
0 
1 
GEM-N MD 
— 
— 
— 
51 
65 
79 
SKATw 
— 
— 
— 
28 
46 
56 
Multiple linear regression 
42 
49 
69 
44 
55 
66 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 3.</figDesc><table>Comparison of association P-values and BFs for APOC3 
truncating variants and plasma triglyceride levels in the GoT2D exome-
sequencing study 

Measure Collapse SKAT SKAT-O lm 
SEM 
GEM-NMD 

P-value 
0.00065 0.0016 0.00063 0.003 0.00065 0.00066 
BF 
— 
— 
— 
— 
63.4 
42.3 

Note: P-value for GEM-NMD is based on 1 000 000 simulations and its 95% 
empirical confidence interval is (0.000607–0.000707). </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.A.Rivas et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank all members of the GoT2D Consortium for useful feedback, conversations and advice on the manuscript. We thank the sequencing platforms at the Broad Institute and the Wellcome Trust Centre for Human Genetics Research for generating the data.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Funding: This work was supported by the Wellcome Trust Centre for Human Genetics core grants</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">the National Institute of Health/National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases [RC2 DK088389]; the Medical Research Council [G0601261]; Framework VII: European Network of Genomic and Genetic Epidemiology (ENGAGE) [HEALTH-F4</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Wellcome</forename>
				<surname>Trust</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="005688" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">]; the Clarendon Scholarship, NDM Studentship and Green Templeton College Award from University of Oxford (to M</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Wellcome</forename>
				<surname>Trust</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Research</forename>
				<surname>Career Development</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Fellow</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">); the Academy of Finland [257654 to M.P.]; and the Royal Society Wolfson Merit Award and Wellcome Trust Senior Investigator Award [095552</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>in. part to P.D.]</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Conflict of Interest: none declared</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">REFERENCES</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A method and server for predicting damaging missense mutations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Adzhubei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of statistical tests for association between rare variants and binary traits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Bacanu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42530</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of statistical tests for disease association with rare variants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Basu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Pan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="606" to="619" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rare MTNR1B variants impairing melatonin receptor 1B function contribute to type 2 diabetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Bonnefond</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exome sequencing identifies truncating mutations in PRRT2 that cause paroxysmal kinesigenic dyskinesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1252" to="1255" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low LDL cholesterol in individuals of african descent resulting from frequent nonsense mutations in PCSK9</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Cohen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="165" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framework for variation discovery and genotyping using next-generation DNA sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Depristo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="491" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using sift and polyphen to predict loss-of-function and gain-of-function mutations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Flanagan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Test Mol. Biomarkers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="533" to="537" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A census of human cancer genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Futreal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="183" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Association between protein truncating variants and quantitative traits 2425 at :: on</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-08-30" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gencode: the reference human genome annotation for the encode project</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Harrow</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1760" to="1774" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Truncations of titin causing dilated cardiomyopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Herman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N. Engl. J.Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">366</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="619" to="628" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">APOC3 null mutation affects lipoprotein profile APOC3 deficiency: from mice to man</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Hofker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Truncating mutations in the last exon of NOTCH2 cause a rare skeletal disorder with osteoporosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Isidor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="306" to="308" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exomic sequencing identifies PALB2 as a pancreatic cancer susceptibility gene</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">324</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="217" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A mutation in APP protects against alzheimer&apos;s disease and age-related cognitive decline</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Jonsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">488</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting the effects of coding non-synonymous variants on protein function using the SIFT algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Kumar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1073" to="1081" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal tests for rare variant effects in sequencing association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="762" to="775" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Methods for detecting associations with rare variants for common diseases: application to analysis of sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Leal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="321" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast and accurate long-read alignment with burrowswheeler transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Durbin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="589" to="595" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A statistical paradox</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Lindley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="192" />
			<date type="published" when="1957" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic survey of loss-of-function variants in human protein-coding genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Macarthur</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">335</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="823" to="828" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Resequencing of positional candidates identifies low frequency IL23R coding variants protecting against inflammatory bowel disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Momozawa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exome sequencing, ANGPTL3 mutations, and familial combined hypolipidemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Musunuru</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N. Engl. J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">363</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2220" to="2227" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rare variants of IFIH1, a gene implicated in antiviral responses, protect against type 1 diabetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Nejentsev</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">324</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="387" to="389" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A null mutation in human APOC3 confers a favorable plasma lipid profile and apparent cardioprotection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Pollin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1702" to="1705" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deep resequencing of GWAS loci identifies independent rare variants associated with inflammatory bowel disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Rivas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1066" to="1073" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mosaic PPM1D mutations are associated with predisposition to breast and ovarian cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Ruark</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">493</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="406" to="410" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Familial hypobetalipoproteinemia a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Schonfeld</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Lipid Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="878" to="883" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rare-variant association testing for sequencing data with the sequence kernel association test</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Rivas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>