
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:46+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis BadiRate: estimating family turnover rates by likelihood-based methods</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">P</forename>
								<surname>Librado</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departament de Genètica and Institut de Recerca de la Biodiversitat (IRBio)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitat de Barcelona</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>645, 08028</postCode>
									<settlement>Diagonal, Barcelona</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">F</forename>
								<forename type="middle">G</forename>
								<surname>Vieira</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departament de Genètica and Institut de Recerca de la Biodiversitat (IRBio)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitat de Barcelona</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>645, 08028</postCode>
									<settlement>Diagonal, Barcelona</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">J</forename>
								<surname>Rozas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departament de Genètica and Institut de Recerca de la Biodiversitat (IRBio)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitat de Barcelona</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>645, 08028</postCode>
									<settlement>Diagonal, Barcelona</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis BadiRate: estimating family turnover rates by likelihood-based methods</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="281"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr623</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 24, 2011; revised on November 4, 2011; accepted on November 7, 2011</note>
					<note>[17:42 20/12/2011 Bioinformatics-btr623.tex] Page: 279 279–281 Associate Editor: David Posada Contact: jrozas@ub.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The comparative analysis of gene gain and loss rates is critical for understanding the role of natural selection and adaptation in shaping gene family sizes. Studying complete genome data from closely related species allows accurate estimation of gene family turnover rates. Current methods and software tools, however, are not well designed for dealing with certain kinds of functional elements, such as microRNAs or transcription factor binding sites. Results: Here, we describe BadiRate, a new software tool to estimate family turnover rates, as well as the number of elements in internal phylogenetic nodes, by likelihood-based methods and parsimony. It implements two stochastic population models, which provide the appropriate statistical framework for testing hypothesis, such as lineage-specific gene family expansions or contractions. We have assessed the accuracy of BadiRate by computer simulations, and have also illustrated its functionality by analyzing a representative empirical dataset. Availability: BadiRate software and documentation is available from</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>It is generally accepted that gene and genome duplications are a major evolutionary mechanism for generating functional innovation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Ohno, 1970</ref>). The increasing availability of closely related genome sequences allows an accurate analysis of gene family evolution (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hahn et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Sanchez-Gracia et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Vieira and Rozas, 2010</ref>). Such studies have shown that most families are highly dynamic and evolve under a birth-and-death (BD) process (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Nei and Rooney, 2005</ref>). Indeed, the comprehensive analysis of gene gains and losses can provide helpful insight into the role of natural selection and adaptation in shaping gene family size variation. The stochastic BD model (BDM) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hahn et al., 2005</ref>) implemented in the programs CAFE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">De Bie et al., 2006</ref>) and BEGFE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Liu et al., 2011</ref>) allows estimating the family turnover rate (λ) by maximum likelihood (ML) and by Bayesian methods, respectively. This model, nevertheless, has some drawbacks. First, it assumes equal BD rates, an assumption that may not hold. Secondly, because duplicationsmodel (LI). This model is nearly equivalent to that implemented in CAFE (except for the innovation parameter), which allows the comparison between the two programs. We have implemented three statistical frameworks to estimate family turnover rates and the number of members in internal nodes: maximum a posteriori (MAP), ML and parsimony (see Supplementary Material). Likelihood-based methods have the advantage of contrasting biological relevant scenarios, such as the identification of gene families or specific-lineages with extreme turnover rates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Johnson and Omland, 2004</ref>). Moreover, the MAP approach allows the incorporation of prior biological information without a large computational cost. BadiRate requires as input the established species phylogenetic tree and a tab-delimited file with the family size of each species represented in the phylogeny (see BadiRate's documentation).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Relative performance of the different methods. Computer simulations based on gene families of five members (S = 5) at the most internal node, and a null innovation rate (I= 0). (A) The box plot represents the error values (see Supplementary Material) distribution across tested methods. (B and C) Surface plots showing the error values of the ML estimates in scenarios simulated under a combination biologically realistic BD rates. Analysis under the BDI, LI and P models are conducted with BadiRate and are depicted in blue, green and cyan, respectively. The model implemented in CAFE is depicted in red. BD rates are measured in number of events per gene per million years (See Supplementary Material for details).</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. from zero ancestral genes are not possible (zero is an absorbing state in the probabilistic BDM), it cannot handle gene families without elements in the phylogenetic root. These assumptions can therefore bias the estimates of both the number of members in internal nodes, as well as the BD rate. Two recently developed computer programs, GLOOME (Cohen et al., 2010) and Count (Csuros, 2010), overcome these difficulties. Nevertheless, GLOOME can only model presence/absence of phyletic patterns instead of size changes, whereas Count assumes independent turnover rates for all lineages, which precludes testing biological relevant hypothesis such as linage-specific accelerations. Here, we describe BadiRate, a new software tool to estimate family turnover rates through the Gain-and-Death (GD) and the Birth-Death-and-Innovation (BDI, also known as Birth-Deathand-Immigration) stochastic models. The current implementation allows modeling families of diverse functional elements, such as microRNAs, cis-regulatory elements or coding-protein genes. Additionally, these models provide a statistical framework for hypothesis testing, such as family expansions/contractions in specific lineages. 2 DESCRIPTION BadiRate implements methods to estimate the family turnover rates such as, gain (γ), birth (β), death (δ) and innovation (ι) rates. These rates can be classified as density-dependent (BD) and densityindependent (gain and innovation). Indeed, the probability of having a death (e.g. a gene loss via deletion or pseudogenization) or a birth (e.g. a gene gain by unequal crossing-over) event is proportional to the actual family size. Conversely, the probability of having a gain or innovation [e.g. horizontal gene transfer (HGT) or by de novo origin of short cis-regulatory elements] event does not depend on the actual gene number. We have implemented two stochastic population models in BadiRate, the BDI and the GD models (Csuros and Miklos, 2009; Hahn et al., 2005) (for details see Supplementary Material), to analyze the evolution of such diverse functional elements. The GD model is especially suitable for analyzing families where members might have a de novo origin, such as transcription factor binding sites (TFBSs) and small non-coding RNAs (miRNAs, piRNAs, etc) or even families exhibiting high HGT. In contrast, the BDI model is appropriated to study gene families whose major mechanism for the acquisition of genes is density-dependent (although it can also model scenarios with a reduced number of HGT or de novo origin events). BadiRate also implements a particular case of the BDI model in which BD rates are assumed to be equal, the Lambda-Innovation © The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> SIMULATION RESULTS We assessed the accuracy of the turnover rates estimates by computer simulations on the well-characterized 12 Drosophila species phylogeny (Supplementary Material; Supplementary Figures S1, S2, S3, S4 and S5). Particularly, we benchmarked the BadiRate ML (under the BDI, LI and GD models) and parsimony estimates, as well as the CAFE (v2.2) ML estimates (under the implemented BDM model). Our results show that, in general (and as expected), the parsimony algorithm performs worse than ML methods (Fig. 1A). Among the ML models, the BDI method outperforms all others (LI and CAFE), especially in cases where small-size families have asymmetric birth/death rates, i.e. β&gt;δ or vice versa (Fig. 1B; Supplementary Figure S2). Apart from the higher accuracy of the BDI model, which mainly results from the separate estimation of BD rates, the LI model also outperforms CAFE even in scenarios with a null innovation rate (Fig. 1A and C; Supplementary Figure S3). Unlike LI and CAFE, which are particular cases of the BDI model, the performance of the GD model is not directly comparable to BDI. Still, our simulations show good performance of the GD model in the analyzed scenarios (Supplementary Figure S4). 4 EMPIRICAL RESULTS We also illustrate the BadiRate application by analyzing the suggested miRNA expansion in the D.willistoni lineage (Nozawa et al., 2010). Since the identification of the miRNA copies in the 11 Drosophila species was conducted by similarity based on the available D.melanogaster miRNA data, the identification of the family members is less accurate for longer divergence times. To control for this effect, we contrasted two scenarios, one assuming independent turnover rates in two classes of branches (in the internal lineages leading to D.melanogaster and in the rest of branches) and the other incorporating a third class of turnover rates (for the D.willistoni lineage). The lower Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) value of the second scenario (AIC = 1509.8128) compared with the first one (AIC = 1518.3918) suggests that the D.willistoni lineage indeed has distinct miRNA turnover rates. We also inferred the most likely number of miRNA elements in the internal nodes of the Drosophila phylogeny; these figures are very similar to that estimated in (Nozawa et al., 2010) (Supplementary Figure S6).</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank F.C. Almeida, M.C. Frias-Lopez, S. Guirao-Rico, A. Sanchez-Gracia and V. Soria-Carrasco, and three anonymous reviewers for their comments and suggestions on the manuscript and on the software.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GLOOME: gain loss mapping engine</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Cohen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2914" to="2915" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Count: evolutionary analysis of phylogenetic profiles with parsimony and likelihood</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Csuros</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1910" to="1912" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Streamlining and large ancestral genomes in Archaea inferred with a phylogenetic birth-and-death model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Csuros</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Miklos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2087" to="2095" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bioinformatics-btr623.tex] Page</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="279" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BadiRate</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CAFE: a computational tool for the study of gene family evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>De Bie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1269" to="1271" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the tempo and mode of gene family evolution from comparative genomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Hahn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1153" to="1160" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene family evolution across 12 Drosophila genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Hahn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">197</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model selection in ecology and evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Johnson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Omland</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Bayesian model for gene family evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">426</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concerted and birth-and-death evolution of multigene families</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Rooney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="152" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Origins and evolution of microRNA genes in Drosophila species</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nozawa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="180" to="189" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Evolution by Gene Duplication</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Ohno</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular evolution of the major chemosensory gene families in insects</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Sanchez-Gracia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Heredity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="208" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative genomics of the odorant-binding and chemosensory protein gene families across the Arthropoda: origin and evolutionary history of the chemosensory system</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Vieira</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Rozas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="476" to="490" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>