
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:42+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Basic4Cseq: an R/Bioconductor package for analyzing 4C-seq data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">. 22 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Carolin</forename>
								<surname>Walter</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Medical Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of M € unster</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>48149 M € unster</addrLine>
									<settlement>Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Daniel</forename>
								<surname>Schuetzmann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Molecular Tumorbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of M € unster</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>48149</postCode>
									<settlement>M € unster</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Frank</forename>
								<surname>Rosenbauer</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Molecular Tumorbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of M € unster</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>48149</postCode>
									<settlement>M € unster</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Martin</forename>
								<surname>Dugas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Medical Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of M € unster</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>48149 M € unster</addrLine>
									<settlement>Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Basic4Cseq: an R/Bioconductor package for analyzing 4C-seq data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="3268" to="3269"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">. 22 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu497</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 24, 2014; revised on June 6, 2014; accepted on July 17, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Gunnar Ratsch Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Basic4Cseq is an R/Bioconductor package for basic filtering , analysis and subsequent near-cis visualization of 4C-seq data. The package processes aligned 4C-seq raw data stored in binary alignment/map (BAM) format and maps the short reads to a corresponding virtual fragment library. Functions are included to create virtual fragment libraries providing chromosome position and further information on 4C-seq fragments (length and uniqueness of the fragment ends, and blindness of a fragment) for any BSGenome package. An optional filter is included for BAM files to remove invalid 4C-seq reads, and further filter functions are offered for 4C-seq fragments. Additionally, basic quality controls based on the read distribution are included. Fragment data in the vicinity of the experiment&apos;s viewpoint are visualized as coverage plot based on a running median approach and a multi-scale contact profile. Wig files or csv files of the fragment data can be exported for further analyses and visualizations of interactions with other programs. Availability and implementation: Basic4Cseq is implemented in R and available at http://www.bioconductor.org/. A vignette with detailed descriptions of the functions is included in the package. Contact: Carolin.Walter@uni-muenster.de</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Circular chromosome conformation capture combined with high-throughput sequencing (4C-seq) is a method that allows the identification of chromosomal interactions between one potential interaction partner, called viewpoint, and virtually any other part of the genome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Gheldof et al., 2012</ref>). Two rounds of digestion and ligation with two distinct restriction enzymes are performed to create a 4C-seq library. Unlike regular next-generation sequencing data, valid 4C-seq reads can only originate from precisely defined points in the genome. Any 4C-seq read will map to the end of a so-called 4C-seq fragment, i.e. a genomic region flanked by two primary restriction sites. When a secondary restriction site is not present, a fragment is called blind; a fragment end is defined as the region between a primary restriction site and the nearest secondary restriction site (van de<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Werken et al., 2012a</ref>). Blind fragments are expected to yield less reads than non-blind fragments; the length of a fragment end in general can cause variations in the read count. Any repetitive fragment end is to be interpreted with caution (van de<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Werken et al., 2012a</ref>). Consequently, these properties have to be considered during the analysis of 4C-seq data to prevent biases or misinterpretation. van de Werken et al.'s 4Cseqpipe is a pipeline to analyze 4C-seq data, which respects these issues (van de<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Werken et al., 2012a</ref>). However, it is not embedded into the R/Bioconductor environment, has little transparency regarding internal data structures, limited output options and less flexibility for smaller interactions with a length of up to 10 kb. The package r3Cseq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Thongjuea et al., 2013</ref>) works on regular binary alignment/map (BAM) files and can detect and visualize interactions, but does not differentiate between fragment types, which is a source of bias. The recently published fourSig method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Williams et al., 2014</ref>) includes fragment filtering options and detects different types of interactions, but does not provide more complex visualization routines for the data profile in the viewpoint region. In contrast, Basic4Cseq offers routines for the analysis of 4C-seq fragment data that are easy to customize. Provided functionality includes fragment filtering, quality control, explorative near-cis visualization and data export/import functions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">AVAILABLE FUNCTIONALITY</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Preprocessing and virtual fragment library creation</head><p>Basic4Cseq expects 4C-seq data stored in BAM format. SAMtools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Li et al., 2009</ref>) and BEDtools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Quinlan and Hall, 2010</ref>) can be used to remove reads on very short or blind fragments directly from the BAM file. Basic4Cseq uses BSgenome packages to split a given genome at primary restriction sites. The resulting fragments are scanned for the presence of a secondary restriction site, and the ends of each fragment are checked for uniqueness. Fragment data are stored as a virtual fragment library file, which can be applied for 4C-seq experiments with the same underlying genome, restriction enzyme combination, and read length.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Filtering of 4C-seq data</head><p>Owing to sequencing errors or SNPs, the alignment of raw 4Cseq data needs to allow a certain number of mismatches. However, mismatches in the first restriction enzyme sequence can lead to mapped reads outside the predefined 4C-seq fragment ends. Overlaps of these reads with valid fragment ends may *To whom correspondence should be addressed. distort the true 4C-seq signal. Basic4Cseq can optionally discard any read with mismatches in the restriction enzyme sequence, if this sequence is present. Additional filtering options are available for the virtual fragment library. Very short or long fragments as well as blind fragments can be discarded; all repetitive fragment ends are removed per default to prevent ambiguous data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Visualization</head><p>After preprocessing, the aligned short reads are mapped to the virtual fragment library. Basic4Cseq analyzes per default data from non-blind, unique fragment ends to prevent bias. It provides a visualization of the viewpoint region similar to the pipeline from van de<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Werken et al. (2012a)</ref>: Fragment-based data are reads per million (RPM)-normalized and smoothed to counter the effects of single, overrepresented fragment ends. Smoothing options include a running median and a running mean approach; quantiles are further smoothed and interpolated with R's loess function. Fragments adjacent to the viewpoint of the 4C-seq experiment are removed to prevent bias through overrepresented sequences caused by self-ligation. Basic4Cseq visualizes both raw fragment data and running medians, plus quantile data in a single plot. Additionally, multi-scale contact profiles of the chosen fragment data are created for running median or running mean windows with varying window sizes. Read counts per fragment are normalized to<ref type="bibr">[0,</ref><ref type="bibr">1]</ref>, and the resulting intensity values are expressed on a log 2 scale to allow for better visibility of distant interactions. Basic4Cseq can annotate custom regions of interest for easier interpretation and comparison of experiments. Import and near-cis visualization of fragment-based data (e.g. fourSig fragment data, which are easily convertible) is possible as well.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>shows a near-cis interaction profile with the typical high coverage at the experiment's viewpoint. Further peaks suggest high contact intensities between the underlying genomic regions and the viewpoint. Comparisons between filter options and alternative tools are added as supplement. For regions located either more remote from the viewpoint or on other chromosomes, it is advisable to use a statistical enrichment approach for the analysis of the 4C-seq fragment data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Splinter et al., 2012</ref>). Basic4Cseq can export filtered 4C-seq data as csv or wig files for use with other programs, e.g. Splinter et al.'s domainogram and spider-plot functions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Splinter et al., 2012</ref>). Additionally, a visualization routine based on RCircos (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Zhang et al., 2013</ref>) is included for imported trans interaction data intervals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Read distribution and quality control</head><p>The distribution of reads throughout 4C-seq fragment ends can provide information on the quality of the experiment data (van de<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Werken et al., 2012b</ref>). Basic4Cseq provides the following quality control statistics: number of total reads, cis/overall ratio of reads and the percentage of covered fragment ends within a certain distance around the experiment's viewpoint. Reference values for high-quality experiments are 41 million reads total, a cis/overall ratio of 440% and a large fraction of covered fragment ends in the viewpoint's vicinity (van de Werken et al., 2012b).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Coverage plot based on a running median approach of RPMnormalized fetal liver sample data around the experiment's viewpoint (annotated as 'VP') at the Myb promoter, with an additional multiscale contact intensity profile. Fragment end-based resolution increases the visibility of small interactions. The corresponding raw data were taken from Stadhouders et al. (2012)</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> CONCLUSION Basic4Cseq enables users to analyze 4C-seq experimental data in the R/Bioconductor environment. Quality control statistics can be calculated, and virtual fragment libraries with relevant fragment data generated. Functions for near-cis visualizations are included; both coverage profiles and heatmap-like multiscale contact intensity visualizations allow the exploration of contact profiles around the viewpoint. The package allows users to import fragment data for visualization, and to export filtered 4C-seq reads as csv or wig files for visualization or further analysis of significant interactions. Conflicts of Interest: none declared.</note>

			<note place="foot">Basic4Cseq at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting long-range chromatin interactions using the chromosome conformation capture sequencing (4c-seq) method</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Gheldof</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">786</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="212" to="225" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Sequence alignment/map (SAM) format and SAMtools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2078" to="2079" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Quinlan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Hall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="841" to="842" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determining long-range chromatin interactions for selected genomic sites using 4C-seq technology: from fixation to computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Splinter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="230" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic long-range chromatin interactions control Myb proto-oncogene transcription during erythroid development</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Stadhouders</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="986" to="999" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">r3Cseq: an R/Bioconductor package for the discovery of long-range genomic interactions from chromosome conformation capture and next-generation sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Thongjuea</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">132</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust 4C-seq data analysis to screen for regulatory DNA interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Van De Werken</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="969" to="971" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">4C technology: protocols and data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Van De Werken</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Enzymol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">513</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">fourSig: a method for determining chromosomal interactions in 4C-Seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Williams</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">68</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RCircos: an R package for Circos 2D track plots</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">244</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>