
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">BioNetFit: a fitting tool compatible with BioNetGen, NFsim and distributed computing environments</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Brandon</forename>
								<forename type="middle">R</forename>
								<surname>Thomas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Northern Arizona University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Flagstaff</settlement>
									<region>AZ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lily</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Chylek</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Northern Arizona University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Flagstaff</settlement>
									<region>AZ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Cornell University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ithaca</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joshua</forename>
								<surname>Colvin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Northern Arizona University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Flagstaff</settlement>
									<region>AZ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Suman</forename>
								<surname>Sirimulla</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Basic Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saint Louis College of Pharmacy</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Saint Louis</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andrew</forename>
								<forename type="middle">H A</forename>
								<surname>Clayton</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Center for Microphotonics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Science, Engineering and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Cell Biophysics Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Swinburne University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hawthorn</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">William</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Hlavacek</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Theoretical Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Los Alamos National Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Los Alamos</settlement>
									<region>NM</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Richard</forename>
								<forename type="middle">G</forename>
								<surname>Posner</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Northern Arizona University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Flagstaff</settlement>
									<region>AZ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">BioNetFit: a fitting tool compatible with BioNetGen, NFsim and distributed computing environments</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv655</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 24, 2015; revised on October 20, 2015; accepted on November 3, 2015</note>
					<note>Systems biology *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online. Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Rule-based models are analyzed with specialized simulators, such as those provided by the BioNetGen and NFsim open-source software packages. Here, we present BioNetFit, a general-purpose fitting tool that is compatible with BioNetGen and NFsim. BioNetFit is designed to take advantage of distributed computing resources. This feature facilitates fitting (i.e. optimization of parameter values for consistency with data) when simulations are computationally expensive. Availability and implementation: BioNetFit can be used on stand-alone Mac, Windows/Cygwin, and Linux platforms and on Linux-based clusters running SLURM, Torque/PBS, or SGE. The BioNetFit source code (Perl) is freely available (http://bionetfit.nau.edu).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Biomolecular interactions can be represented by formalized rules (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Chylek et al., 2014a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Stefan et al., 2014</ref>). Collections of rules form rule-based models, which provide concise representations of biomolecular interaction networks and can be analyzed to obtain insights into how system-level behavior emerges from biomolecular interactions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Chylek et al., 2014a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Stefan et al., 2014</ref>). Rule-based models must be analyzed with specialized algorithms and software tools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Chylek et al., 2014a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Stefan et al., 2014</ref>), such as BioNetGen (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Harris et al., 2015</ref>), which interprets models encoded in the BioNetGen language (BNGL) and provides deterministic, stochastic and hybrid forward simulation capabilities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Harris et al., 2015</ref>). To date, other critical methods of analysis, such as fitting (parameter estimation), have typically been applied ad hoc (e.g. by writing problem-specific programs), as in the study of<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kozer et al. (2013)</ref>or<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Chylek et al. (2014b)</ref>, which leads to duplication of effort and hinders the ability to reproduce results. Although many algorithms and software implementations are available for analysis of models specified in traditional forms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Press et al., 2007</ref>), such as that of ordinary differential equations (ODEs), standard techniques are not easily applied to rule-based models except for those rule-based models that can be recast into a traditional model form. Translating a set of rules into a reaction network (i.e. a list of reactions) or the corresponding ODEs for the mass-action kinetics of the network, a capability provided by BioNetGen, is expensive and sometimes impracticable. In such cases, direct simulation methods<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Sneddon et al., 2011</ref>), which is compatible with BNGL-specified models, expand the range of biomolecular interaction networks that can be studied, because the cost of network-free simulation scales with the number of rules in a model, not the number of reactions implied by the rules (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Danos et al., 2007</ref>). Software that provides a general-purpose fitting capability and that interfaces with a network-free simulator has not hitherto been available. Here, we present BioNetFit, a general-purpose fitting program for rule-based models that is compatible with BioNetGen and NFsim. Because of the potentially high cost of network-free simulation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Chylek et al., 2014a</ref>), BioNetFit has been designed to be used on clusters. It can also be used on stand-alone computers. BioNetFit implements a genetic algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Whitley, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Smith and Eiben, 2008</ref>). Below, we provide an overview of BioNetFit and a demonstration of its capabilities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>Source code and a user manual, which includes installation instructions, are available at the BioNetFit Web site (http://bionetfit.nau.edu). Dependencies are described in the user manual and in Supplementary Methods. Collections of files needed to run example fitting jobs are included in the BioNetFit distribution in the 'examples' directory and six subdirectories named 'example1' through 'example6.' Step-by-step instructions for running these fitting jobs are included in the user manual. The fitting procedure implemented in BioNetFit is described in Supplementary Methods. Running BioNetFit requires several problem-specific plain-text files: a BNGL model-specification (.bngl) file (i.e. a BioNetGen/ NFsim input file); one or more data (.exp) files, each with two or more white space-separated columns; and a BioNetFit configuration (.conf) file (see the 'examples' directory in the BioNetFit distribution). If NFsim is being used, a .rnf file may also be required. To run BioNetFit, a user must identify the parameters that are free to vary in fitting in the .conf file and include a simulation command in the .bngl file for each .exp file. Each simulation command should generate outputs corresponding to the data in the associated .exp file. See the BioNetFit user guide and Supplementary Methods for additional information. Demonstration results were obtained by running BioNetFit on the Monsoon cluster at Northern Arizona University (http://nau.edu/hpc/). The .bngl, .exp and .conf files required to repeat the demonstration results presented in the Results section are provided as Supplementary Files S1–S6. These files are also provided in the 'example1' and 'example2' subdirectories of the 'examples' directory within the BioNetFit distribution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>To provide a demonstration of capabilities, we used BioNetFit together with BioNetGen, NFsim and experimental data of<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kozer et al. (2013)</ref>to estimate parameter values for a published (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kozer et al., 2013</ref>) and an extended version of a model for activation of the epidermal growth factor (EGF) receptor (EGFR). Each version of the model accounts for EGF-induced oligomerization of EGFR. The published model is defined in Supplementary File S1, which is a .bngl file that directs BioNetGen's ODE solver to produce simulation results. The file is derived from the .bngl file used by<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kozer et al. (2013)</ref>. This version of the model limits EGFR oligomers to a maximum size of four receptors per oligomer. This limitation was introduced by<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kozer et al. (2013)</ref>to avoid the need to use computationally expensive network-free simulation in fitting, which was performed using problem-specific code. The extended model is defined in Supplementary File S2, which is a .bngl file that directs NFsim to produce simulation results. The file is derived from the .bngl file used by<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kozer et al. (2014)</ref>. This version of the model imposes no constraints on the size of linear oligomers. It is otherwise identical to the published model of<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kozer et al. (2013)</ref>. The steady-state dose-response and time-series data used in each of the two fitting runs are provided in Supplementary Files S3 and S4, which are .exp files. Supplementary Files S5 and S6 are the BioNetFit configuration (.conf) files for the two fitting runs. These files complement Supplementary Files S1 and S2, respectively. In the fitting procedure, BioNetFit evaluated the consistency of simulation results with all available data (i.e. BioNetFit found a global fit). The chi-square metric was used to determine goodness of fit. Parameter estimates are summarized in Supplementary Table S1. The number of free parameters was nine, which included five physical parameters (e.g. rate constants) and four scaling factors (parameters of a measurement model), which define linear relationships between measured quantities and model-predicted quantities. The quality of the fit for the original and extended models is illustrated in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. For best-fit parameter values, the extended model predicts that EGFR oligomers larger than tetramers do not form appreciably (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). This finding justifies the omission of these oligomers in the analysis of<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kozer et al. (2013)</ref>. BioNetFit's ability to take advantage of simulation runs performed in parallel on a cluster enabled consideration of the extended model, which had to be simulated by calling NFsim. The KMC (stochastic simulation) method implemented in NFsim tends to be computationally expensive, because in such methods, system state is advanced one reaction event at a time (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Chylek et al., 2014a</ref>). Use of NFsim was required because the extended model places no constraint on the size of (linear) EGFR oligomers, which form via polymerization-like reactions. Network-free simulation is typically required to cope with polymerization-reactions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Chylek et al., 2014a</ref>). As expected, we found that simulations performed by NFsim (for the extended model) were significantly more expensive than simulations performed by BioNetGen's ODE solver (for the original model). The cost difference depends on various factors, including hardware, model parameter values and algorithmic parameter settings. For a representative CPU in the cluster we used and the parameter settings of Supplementary Files S1 and S2, an NFsim simulation is 5-fold more expensive than an ODE-based simulation. It should be noted that the cost difference depends sensitively on the value of one particular algorithmic parameter called f in Supplementary File S2, which scales system size. In general, the cost of a discrete-event stochastic simulation, the type of simulation performed by NFsim, depends on the number of reaction events per unit time, which in turn depends on system size (measured by the number of reactive molecules in the system). In Supplementary File S2, we set f ¼ 0.01, which corresponds to a system size of 1% of a cell. This setting reduces the cost of individual simulation runs (and memory requirements) at the expense of introducing noise (i.e. fluctuations arising from probabilistic reaction events). The noisiness of simulation results complicates the comparison of predicted and measured (population averaged) quantities. Because of this issue, in fitting, multiple NFsim simulations were performed for each BioNetFitgoodness-of-fit evaluation. BioNetFit allows a user to cope with the noisiness of stochastic simulation results in a brute-force manner by repeating simulation runs a user-specified number of times and then averaging the results. This procedure serves to smooth stochastic simulation results. Results from two additional non-trivial fitting demonstrations are summarized in Supplementary Tables S2 and S3, which provide bestfit parameter estimates, and Supplementary Figures S2 and S3, which illustrate the quality of fits obtained. The files needed to reproduce these results are provided in the 'example3' and 'example4' subdirectories of the 'examples' directory in the BioNetFit distribution. The demonstrations each require NFsim. The 'example3' demonstration concerns a rule-based model for interaction of a trivalent ligand with a bivalent cell-surface receptor and parameter estimation on the basis of equilibrium data collected via flow cytometry (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Monine et al., 2010</ref>). The 'example4' demonstration concerns a rule-based model for early events in T-cell receptor signaling and parameter estimation on the basis of temporal phosphoproteomic data collected via mass spectrometry-based proteomics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Chylek et al., 2014b</ref>). Notably, because changes in phosphorylation levels were measured relative to basal phosphorylation levels, this fitting problem required normalization of model outputs at the basal steady state, which is explained in the BioNetFit user manual.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusions</head><p>Parameter estimation is a critical step in model building and modelguided analysis of data. BioNetFit provides a fitting capability that is suitable for a broad range of rule-based modeling applications because of its compatibility with BioNetGen and NFsim. Moreover, BioNetFit can potentially be used with traditionally formulated models (e.g. ODE models), because BioNetGen has the capability to translate models encoded in the SBML format (<ref type="bibr">Hucka et al., 2003</ref>) into BNGL format (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Harris et al., 2015</ref>). Importantly, BioNetFit is designed to take advantage of distributed computing resources, which can make fitting feasible even when simulation runs are computationally expensive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by NIH/NIGMS grant R01GM111510. The Moonson cluster at Northern Arizona University is supported by Arizona's Technology and Research Initiative Fund.<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>. The stochastic simulation results shown here represent averages from multiple simulation runs. In fitting, each stochastic simulation run was repeated and the results averaged to obtain smoothed time courses. The CPU time typically required for a single stochastic simulation was 3 min. The fitting procedure for the extended model involved a total of 10 000 (stochastic) simulations. Because of parallel processing, the procedure took only 40 h. The number of EGFR clusters (the sum of EGFR monomers, dimers, etc.) per lm 2 is indicated on the vertical axis of panel (a) and</p><p>(c). The relative level of EGFR phosphorylation (arbitrary units) is indicated on the vertical axis of panel (b) and (d)</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Plots illustrating the quality of fits found by BioNetFit. Together with Supplementary Files S1 and S3–S5 and BioNetGen's ODE solver, BioNetFit was used to estimate values for the free parameters of the model of Kozer et al. (2013) for EGFR activation. Together with Supplementary Files S2–S4 and S6 and NFsim, BioNetFit was also used to estimate values for the corresponding parameters of an extended model, which can only be analyzed using network-free simulation. In each case, parameter estimates are based on the data of Kozer et al. (2013), which are represented by points with error bars. The left panels, (a) and (b), show fits to the steady-state dose-response data. The right panels, (c) and (d), show fits to the time-series data. Solid curves show deterministic simulation results produced by BioNetGen's ODE solver. Dotted curves show stochastic simulation results produced by NFsim. Curves are based on the best-fit parameter values, which are summarized in Supplementary Table S1. The stochastic simulation results shown here represent averages from multiple simulation runs. In fitting, each stochastic simulation run was repeated and the results averaged to obtain smoothed time courses. The CPU time typically required for a single stochastic simulation was 3 min. The fitting procedure for the extended model involved a total of 10 000 (stochastic) simulations. Because of parallel processing, the procedure took only 40 h. The number of EGFR clusters (the sum of EGFR monomers, dimers, etc.) per lm 2 is indicated on the vertical axis of panel (a) and (c). The relative level of EGFR phosphorylation (arbitrary units) is indicated on the vertical axis of panel (b) and (d)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 798 Bioinformatics, 32(5), 2016, 798–800 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv655</figDesc><table>Advance Access Publication Date: 9 November 2015 
Applications Note must be used (Chylek et al., 2014a). These methods have been called 
network-free methods, because they do not involve processing a set of 
rules to obtain a list of reactions. Rather, rules are used as reaction-
event generators within a particle-based kinetic Monte Carlo (KMC) 
simulation. Network-free simulators, such as NFsim (</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">B.R.Thomas et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank the High Performance Computing support staff at Northern Arizona University for assistance in using the Monsoon cluster. We thank the New Mexico Consortium for providing temporary office space to LAC. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rule-based modeling: a computational approach for studying biomolecular site dynamics in cell signaling systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Chylek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Wiley Interdiscip. Rev. Syst. Biol. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phosphorylation site dynamics of early T-cell receptor signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Chylek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plos One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104240</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scalable simulation of cellular signaling networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Danos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lect. Notes Comput. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4807</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioNetGen 2.2: advances in rule-based modeling The systems biology markup language (SBML): a medium for representation and exchange of biochemical network models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Harris</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="524" to="531" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>arxiv.org/pdf/1507.03572.pdf Hucka,</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring higher-order oligomerisation and phosphorylation—a combined experimental and theoretical approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Kozer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. BioSyst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1849" to="1863" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recruitment of the adaptor protein Grb2 to EGFR tetramers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Kozer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2594" to="2604" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling multivalent ligand-receptor interactions with steric constraints on configurations of cell-surface receptor aggregates</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Monine</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Numerical Recipes: The Art of Scientific Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Press</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, UK</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd. Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to Evolutionary Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Eiben</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient modeling, simulation and coarse-grain ing of biological complexity with NFsim</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Sneddon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="183" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-state modeling of biomolecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Stefan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003844</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A genetic algorithm tutorial</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Whitley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>