
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:32+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Breakpointer: using local mapping artifacts to support sequence breakpoint discovery from single-end reads</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">7 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ruping</forename>
								<surname>Sun</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Computational Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max-Planck-Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63–73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">I</forename>
								<surname>Love</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Computational Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max-Planck-Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63–73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Tomasz</forename>
								<surname>Zemojtel</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Computational Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max-Planck-Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63–73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anne-Katrin</forename>
								<surname>Emde</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Computational Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max-Planck-Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63–73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ho-Ryun</forename>
								<surname>Chung</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Computational Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max-Planck-Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63–73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Martin</forename>
								<surname>Vingron</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Computational Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max-Planck-Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63–73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Stefan</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Haas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Computational Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max-Planck-Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63–73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Breakpointer: using local mapping artifacts to support sequence breakpoint discovery from single-end reads</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1024" to="1025"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">7 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts064</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on November 3, 2011; revised on January 23, 2012; accepted on January 27, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: GS MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [12:44 12/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts064.tex] Page: 1024 1024–1025 Associate Editor: Michael Brudno Supplementary information: Supplementary material is available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We developed Breakpointer, a fast algorithm to locate breakpoints of structural variants (SVs) from single-end reads produced by next-generation sequencing. By taking advantage of local non-uniform read distribution and misalignments created by SVs, Breakpointer scans the alignment of single-end reads to identify regions containing potential breakpoints. The detection of such breakpoints can indicate insertions longer than the read length and SVs located in repetitve regions which might be missd by other methods. Thus, Breakpointer complements existing methods to locate SVs from single-end reads. Availability: https://github.com/ruping/Breakpointer</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Identifying structural variants (SVs) from short sequencing reads remains challenging. Existing next-generation sequencing (NGS)based methods for SV detection are primarily based on the analysis of paired-end reads (PE) assuming that deviations from the expected mapping distance are caused by SVs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alkan et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Medvedev et al., 2009</ref>). Alternatively, to characterize SVs from single-end reads (SE), split-read methods can be adopted to generate pseudo PE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Smith, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ye et al., 2009</ref>). However, the short length of the artificial PE limits the mappability and the size of detectable insertions (up to medium size). Alternative SE-based methods are needed to facilitate the discovery of breakpoints of longer insertions and SVs located in repetitive regions. SVs usually cause specific mapping artifacts in the vicinity of the SV boundaries. Reads slightly crossing the breakpoint of an SV can be mapped only if they contain a few bases of the variant (depending on the allowed edit distance). This case usually leads to consistent misalignments next to the breakpoint. Such misalignments have already been used to clean SNP calls (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Li, 2011</ref>) or to determine the regions for local realignment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">DePristo et al., 2011</ref>). In contrast, reads spanning the breakpoint will be unmappable. Consequently, on the left or right side of the SV boundary, fewer read alignments will start or end, respectively (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1A</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S1</ref>). Our tool Breakpointer locates SV breakpoints by analyzing both * To whom correspondence should be addressed. misalignment artifacts and local non-uniform read distribution created by SVs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>Given a small genomic region R of size w, the depth of coverage D is defined as the number of reads (of length l) overlapping R. In addition, we introduce 'end-depth' D e as the number of only those reads starting/ending (summarized as 'ends') within R. Assuming uniform coverage, under a given D, D e will follow a binomial distribution as: D e ∼ B(n = D,p = 2w w+l ). Regions containing the breakpoint of an SV will have higher D e than expected, because a lack of mappable breakpoint-spanning reads leads to a depth skew toward ending reads. Some aligned reads slightly overlapping with the SV will generate consistent mismatches around the breakpoint (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1A</ref>). Such mismatches will only occur in the ends of the mappable reads but not in the reads spanning R, e.g. reads from a wildtype allele. We summarize these local mapping features around SV boundaries as 'breakpoint signature'. To capture this signature, Breakpointer proceeds in three stages (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1B</ref>): First, using a sliding window of size w ( l), Breakpointer scans the read alignment along a reference genome, calculates the pileup-corrected sequencing depth D and end-depth D e for each window. The skewness of depth in each window is represented by the score S B , which is equal to the negative logarithm (of base 10) of the P-value computed from a binomial test. Windows with S B &gt; 1 are selected and then merged into non-overlapping regions. For variable read length, Breakpointer groups reads based on their length and generates S B based on weighted P-values (Supplementary Note). Second, mismatch screening is performed on each merged region, with the aim to enrich for those regions likely to encompass SV breakpoints. We only consider mismatches located 10 bp from the read ends (referred as 'ME'). A score S M is assigned to a region with c positions showing MEs:</p><formula>S M = c t=1 (−log 10 (P t )) and P t = n k k i=1 i. n j=k+1 (1− j ),</formula><p>where P t is the probability of seeing k MEs out of n reads at a position t in a merged region, assuming that MEs are sequencing errors. i is the maximum of the Phred base-error rate at position t in read i or a local error rate computed from the number of MEs in this region. We use local error rate because in real data there are regions containing many mismatches despite high-quality scores. Small gaps are treated as mismatches (taking of surrounding bases for deletions). Regions with no MEs are removed since their depth skewness are likely caused by technological artifacts or mappability. Given a true SV event, unmappable breakpoint-spanning reads will match the SV boundary including MEs. Thus, in the last step, each candidate region is validated by detecting breakpoint-supporting reads in the unmapped pool. The regions with no supporting unmappable reads are filtered out. Breakpointer sorts the selected regions according to S B , S M and generates two rank scores accordingly. A confidence score RC is assigned to each region by combining the two ranks. Breakpointer requires sorted BAM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Li et al., 2009</ref>) files as an input and outputs validated regions in GFF format.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS AND DISCUSSIONS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Simulation</head><p>We characterize the power of Breakpointer to locate the breakpoints of known human indels (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Mills et al., 2006</ref>) implanted into chromosome X (Supplementary Note). The results, summarized in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1C</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>, highlight the ability of Breakpointer to uncover the breakpoints of known indels with various sizes at high sequencing coverages (recall &gt;0.8 and FPR: false positive rate &lt;0.02 at &gt;30× coverage). Breakpointer can discover the breakpoints of insertions longer than the read length, which is beyond the ability of split-read methods (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Real data</head><p>Breakpointer is also tested on Illumina whole-genome sequencing data from an Yoruban genome (NA18507,<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bentley et al., 2008</ref>). Predictions by Breakpointer are intersected with external variant sets detected by alternative approaches from the same individual (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Kidd et al., 2008</ref>) and sets from population studies (<ref type="bibr">Mills et al., 2011a, b</ref>). The fraction of Breakpointer predictions overlapping with DIP (deletion/insertion polymorphisms detected by capillary sequencing a part of NA18507 genome) increases with combined rank score RC (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1D</ref>), suggesting that the breakpoint signature represents true SV breakpoints. Predictions overlapping known SVs were comparable between Breakpointer and other methods using PE (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table  S2</ref>), indicating that Breakpointer achieves equivalent accuracy to PE-based methods by just using SE. The comparison between the known SVs overlapped by Breakpointer and Pindel (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ye et al., 2009</ref>, an anchored split read mapping method) reveals that Breakpointer locates the breakpoints of (i) insertions longer than the read length and (ii) many indels in repetitive regions which are missed by Pindel (Supplementary Table S3,<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>). Breakpointer analyzes the initial small-gapped alignment of the entire read, showing complementarity to Pindel which splits the initial unmapped reads. Besides the breakpoints of indels, Breakpointer also uncovers the breakpoints of some large SVs, e.g. mobile insertions and nonhomologous recombinations, by using 36 bp SE (Supplementary Note), although the power to detect repeat-mediated SVs is limited due to mapping difficulties in highly repetitive regions and sequence homology around breakpoints.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>By evaluating mapping features at the boundaries of SVs, our method locates the breakpoints of a wide range of SVs. Breakpointer does not investigate the SV content; it is designed as a supportive breakpoint discovery tool that ideally should be used in combination with other methods for genotyping SVs. Breakpointer requires a high coverage (&gt;20×) to reach an optimal performance. The predictions can be used not only to provide additional support for alternative methods, but also to find breakpoints of SVs that otherwise might be missed by other tools. Thus, by requiring only single-end reads, it complements the current set of SV detection methods.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. (A) Depth skewness toward ending reads (small bar) and misalignments close to the breakpoints (black vertical line) of SVs (black bar). (B) Summary of Breakpointer algorithm. (C) Indel recall rate and false positive rate (FPR) at different coverage levels in the simulation. Recall: the breakpoint of an indel is encompassed by a prediction; FP: a prediction is not overlapping with any implanted indels; ins: insertions. (D) The fraction of predicted breakpoints by Breakpointer in the genome of NA18507 overlapping with DIP database. The predictions are grouped according to RC and S B score, respectively. Also shown is the fraction of random regions overlapping with DIP.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: Max Planck Society. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome structural variation discovery and genotyping</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Alkan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="376" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate whole human genome sequencing using reversible terminator chemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Bentley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">456</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framework for variation discovery and genotyping using next-generation DNA sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Depristo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="491" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping and sequencing of structural variation from eight human genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Kidd</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">453</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2078" to="2079" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving SNP discovery by base alignment quality</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1157" to="1158" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational methods for discovering structural variation with next-generation sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Medvedev</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An initial map of insertion and deletion (INDEL) variation in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Mills</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1182" to="1190" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping copy number variation by population-scale genome sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Mills</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">470</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Natural genetic variation caused by small insertions and deletions in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Mills</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="830" to="839" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying insertion mutations by whole-genome sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BioTechniques</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pindel: a pattern growth approach to detect break points of large deletions and medium sized insertions from paired-end short reads</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Ye</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2865" to="2871" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>