
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:34+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis BSeQC: quality control of bisulfite sequencing experiments</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xueqiu</forename>
								<surname>Lin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Life sciences and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tongji University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20092</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Deqiang</forename>
								<surname>Sun</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dan L. Duncan Cancer Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>77030</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Benjamin</forename>
								<surname>Rodriguez</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dan L. Duncan Cancer Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>77030</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Qian</forename>
								<surname>Zhao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Life sciences and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tongji University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20092</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hanfei</forename>
								<surname>Sun</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Life sciences and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tongji University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20092</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yong</forename>
								<surname>Zhang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Life sciences and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tongji University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20092</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wei</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Life sciences and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tongji University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20092</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dan L. Duncan Cancer Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>77030</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis BSeQC: quality control of bisulfite sequencing experiments</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">24</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="3227" to="3229"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt548</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 23, 2013; revised on September 2, 2013; accepted on September 18, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Martin Bishop/p/bseqc/. Contact: wl1@bcm.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Bisulfite sequencing (BS-seq) has emerged as the gold standard to study genome-wide DNA methylation at single-nucleotide resolution. Quality control (QC) is a critical step in the analysis pipeline to ensure that BS-seq data are of high quality and suitable for subsequent analysis. Although several QC tools are available for next-generation sequencing data, most of them were not designed to handle QC issues specific to BS-seq protocols. Therefore, there is a strong need for a dedicated QC tool to evaluate and remove potential technical biases in BS-seq experiments. Results: We developed a package named BSeQC to comprehensively evaluate the quality of BS-seq experiments and automatically trim nucleotides with potential technical biases that may result in inaccurate methylation estimation. BSeQC takes standard SAM/ BAM files as input and generates bias-free SAM/BAM files for downstream analysis. Evaluation based on real BS-seq data indicates that the use of the bias-free SAM/BAM file substantially improves the quantification of methylation level. Availability and implementation: BSeQC is freely available at: http:// code.google.com</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>DNA methylation, an epigenetic modification affecting the organization and function of the genome, plays an important role in several key biological processes, including transcriptional regulation, X-chromosome inactivation, genomic imprinting, silencing of repetitive elements and chromatin structure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Robertson, 2005</ref>). Bisulfite conversion followed by next-generation sequencing (BS-seq) has emerged as a powerful technique for detecting genome-wide DNA methylation at single-nucleotide resolution (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Laird, 2010</ref>). Ideally, BS-seq experiment should be able to directly and exactly quantify the methylation level of every cytosine in the genome. However, current BS-seq protocols possess several intrinsic technical biases, which may impact methylation level estimation. These biases include overhang end-repair, 5 0 bisulfite conversion failure, sequencing into the adaptor and 3 0 low sequencing quality (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bock, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Liu et al., 2012</ref>). Although the last two biases are also present in other next-generation sequencing data, the first two biases, i.e. end-repair and 5 0 bisulfite conversion failure, are highly specific to BS-seq protocols. BS-seq reads with the first two biases can be perfectly mapped to the reference genome; however, they will result in biased methylation estimation. First, after sonication, the overhangs of DNA fragments are normally end-repaired with unmethylated cytosines to restore the double stranded DNA (Illumina WGBS for Methylation Analysis Guide). This may introduce artificially low methylation rates at both ends of the DNA fragments. Second, bisulfite conversion failure is known to be enriched at the 5 0 end of reads, most likely caused by the re-annealing of sequences adjacent to the methylated adapters in bisulfite conversion (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Berman et al., 2012</ref>). This may bring in artificially high methylation rates at the 5 0 end of reads. Most quality control (QC) tools, such as htSeqTools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Planet et al., 2012</ref>) and FastQC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Andrews, 2010</ref>), only focus on the general sequence quality and adaptor trimming, or other next-generation sequencing applications such as RNA-seq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Wang et al., 2012</ref>). To the best of our knowledge, BSmooth and Bis-SNP are the only two tools that support QC specific to BS-seq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Hansen et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Liu et al., 2012</ref>). However, their QC functions are highly limited. The QC model in BSmooth was designed to work with its own alignment and analysis pipeline, and thus cannot take standard BAM/SAM files as input. Furthermore, BSmooth can detect but not correct the biases. Bis-SNP only supports the correction of 5 0 bisulfite conversion failure. Because BS-seq experiments are widely used and the resulting data will continue to grow exponentially in the near future, there is a strong need for a dedicated QC tool to assess and improve the quality of BS-seq experiments. BSeQC, the tool we developed, is focused on the technical biases specific to BS-seq experiments. BSeQC can automatically evaluate and remove the biases based on a user defined statistical cutoff. Evaluation based on real BS-seq data indicates that, after bias removal, the quantification of methylation level is significantly improved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>BSeQC uses M-bias plot, i.e. average DNA methylation level for each read position, to assess and visualize bisulfite-specific biases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Hansen et al., 2011</ref>). For each CpG in uniquely aligned read, BSeQC records its relative position in the read and methylation state (methylated: C or unmethylated: T).As the methylation levels are expected to be independent of the read positions, the M-bias plot ought to exhibit a horizontal line. If there are biases, the M-bias plot will show position-specific deviation from the horizontal line, which are often observed at both ends of reads. Because different DNA strands and read lengths can have distinct biases, BSeQC generates separate M-bias plots for different strand and read length configurations. BSeQC also produces non-CpG cytosine M-bias plots to detect bisulfite conversion failure because non-CpG cytosines should be almost completely converted. To remove biases detected in the M-bias plot, BSeQC uses a statistical cutoff to make trimming decision automatically. Given the observation that read center positions (30–70% of read length) usually have high quality, whereas both read ends are susceptible to technical biases, the average methylation levels in read center positions can be used to fit a normal NULL distribution $N , 2 À Á . The methylation level of each read end position is then evaluated by a P-value, indicating the statistical significance of the deviation from the NULL. The positions of all the reads will be trimmed if they exhibit significant biases, i.e. P 0.01. BSeQC automatically uses the most stringent trimming decision made by either CpG or non-CpG cytosines M-bias plots. After bias removal, BSeQC generates a corresponding bias-free SAM/BAM files for the downstream analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>We demonstrated the capabilities of BSeQC using two publicly available datasets: (i) paired-end WGBS from mouse ES-derived neuronal progenitor cells (mNPC) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Stadler et al., 2011</ref>), and (ii) single-end WGBS from H1 human ES cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Lister et al., 2009</ref>). After reads mapping using BSMAP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Xi and Li, 2009</ref>), we observed the end-repair bias in the 5 0 of 'AE' strand (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>) and the 5 0 bisulfite conversion failure in the 'þþ' strand in the M-bias plots of paired-end mNPC data (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1A</ref>). This observation indicates that different DNA strands may exhibit different technical biases in BS-seq experiments (Supplementary Note S1). As expected, the 5 0 bisulfite conversion failure is more obvious in non-CpG cytosine M-bias plots (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>). In the single-end H1 data, we used BSMAP to remove adaptor and low-quality nucleotides during mapping. However, there are still biases in the 3 0 of 'þþ' strands of both replicates, probably indicating residual adapters and low-quality nucleotides that cannot be fully removed by conventional QC approaches (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2A</ref>). In addition, we observed different biases in different read length in H1 data (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>). Because there is no ground truth for methylation estimation, we decided to use the concordance between two replicates to evaluate the performance of BSeQC bias trimming. As expected, the agreement of methylation level distributions between two read mates derived from the same paired-end mNPC data is significantly increased after BSeQC trimming, especially in high methylation levels (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1B</ref>). The Kullback–Leibler distance, a measurement of difference between two probability distributions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kullback and Leibler, 1951</ref>), decreases from 0.207 to 0.129 after BSeQC trimming. Similar improvement can also be observed in single-end H1 data (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2B</ref>), RRBS data (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S4</ref>) and mouse NPC data (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S5</ref>). Together, we conclude that the usage of BSeQC can significantly improve the methylation estimation.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>For a given input SAM/BAM file, BSeQC piles up all the records and plots the mean methylation level at each read position. *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> CONCLUSION BSeQC serves as a critical step between reads mapping and methylation estimation. BSeQC comprehensively evaluates the technical biases related to BS-seq protocols and automatically makes trimming decision using a statistical cutoff. This is a vast improvement to arbitrarily read trimming (e.g. the first three and last three nucleotides). In addition to M-bias plot guided bias trimming, BSeQC can also automatically remove clonal reads from over-amplification and avoid double counting of overlapped segments in paired-end reads (Supplementary Fig. S6). With its standard SAM/BAM input/output interface, BSeQC can be easily incorporated into any existing BS-seq data analysis pipeline. In summary, we believe BSeQC will greatly facilitate the analysis and understanding of DNA methylation bisulfite sequencing data. Funding: 973 Program of China [2010CB944900], CPRIT RP110471-C3 and NIH [R01HG007538]. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</note>

			<note place="foot">X.Lin et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">BSeQC at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">FastQC. A quality control tool for high throughput sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Andrews</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-10-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regions of focal DNA hypermethylation and long-range hypomethylation in colorectal cancer coincide with nuclear lamina-associated domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Berman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysing and interpreting DNA methylation data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Bock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="705" to="719" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BSmooth: from whole genome bisulfite sequencing reads to differentially methylated regions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hansen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">83</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased methylation variation in epigenetic domains across cancer types</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hansen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="768" to="775" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On information and sufficiency, information and sufficiency</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kullback</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Leibler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Math. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="1951" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Principles and challenges of genome-wide DNA methylation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Laird</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human DNA methylomes at base resolution show widespread epigenomic differences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Lister</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">462</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">BSeQC analyses of paired-end mNPC data. (A) M-bias plots for two complementary strands of chr1. Horizontal line: M-bias plot; dash vertical line: trimming positions. (B) Distributions of methylation levels. Blue line: mate1 (þþ and Àþ strands); red line</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Fig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>þÀ. and ÀÀ strands</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bis-SNP: combined DNA methylation and SNP calling for Bisulfite-seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">htSeqTools: high-throughput sequencing quality control, processing and visualization in R</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Planet</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="589" to="590" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA methylation and human disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Robertson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="597" to="610" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA-binding factors shape the mouse methylome at distal regulatory regions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Stadler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">480</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="490" to="495" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RSeQC: quality control of RNA-seq experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2184" to="2185" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BSMAP: whole genome bisulfite sequence MAPping program</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Xi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">232</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>