
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-11T00:00+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">BS-SNPer: SNP calling in bisulfite-seq data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Shengjie</forename>
								<surname>Gao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biomedicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Aarhus</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">BGI Co. Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518083</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">BioInformatics Research Center (BIRC)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>8000</postCode>
									<settlement>Aarhus</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dan</forename>
								<surname>Zou</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">BGI Co. Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518083</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National University of Defense Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>410073</postCode>
									<settlement>Changsha</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Likai</forename>
								<surname>Mao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">BGI Co. Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518083</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Genomic Biology Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">QIMR Berghofer Medical Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Brisbane</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Huayu</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Departments of Biostatistics and Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Colorado-Anschutz Medical Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>80204</postCode>
									<settlement>Denver</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pengfei</forename>
								<surname>Song</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution">The Fourth People&apos;s Hospital of Shenzhen (Futian hos-pital)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518033</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Youguo</forename>
								<surname>Chen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Obsterics and Gynecology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">the First Hospital Affiliated to Suzhou University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Jiangsu Suzhou 215006</addrLine>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Shancen</forename>
								<surname>Zhao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">BGI Co. Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518083</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Changduo</forename>
								<surname>Gao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">College of Information Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Qingdao University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>266071</postCode>
									<settlement>Qingdao</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xiangchun</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">BGI Co. Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518083</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zhibo</forename>
								<surname>Gao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">BGI Co. Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518083</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xiaodong</forename>
								<surname>Fang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">BGI Co. Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518083</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Huanming</forename>
								<surname>Yang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">BGI Co. Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518083</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Torben</forename>
								<forename type="middle">F</forename>
								<surname>Ørntoft</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>8000</postCode>
									<settlement>Aarhus</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Karina</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Sørensen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>8000</postCode>
									<settlement>Aarhus</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lars</forename>
								<surname>Bolund</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>bolund@biomed.au.dk, kdso@clin.au.dk or orntoft@ki.au.dk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biomedicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Aarhus</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">BGI Co. Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518083</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">BioInformatics Research Center (BIRC)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>8000</postCode>
									<settlement>Aarhus</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">BS-SNPer: SNP calling in bisulfite-seq data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv507</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 21, 2015; revised on August 3, 2015; accepted on August 21, 2015</note>
					<note>Sequence analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first four authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Associate Editor: Inanc Birol Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Sodium bisulfite conversion followed by sequencing (BS-Seq, such as whole genome bisulfite sequencing or reduced representation bisulfite sequencing) has become popular for studying human epigenetic profiles. Identifying single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) is important for quantification of methylation levels and for study of allele-specific epigenetic events such as imprinting. However, SNP calling in such data is complex and time consuming. Here, we present an ultrafast and memory-efficient package named BS-SNPer for the exploration of SNP sites from BS-Seq data. Compared with Bis-SNP, a popular BS-Seq specific SNP caller, BS-SNPer is over 100 times faster and uses less memory. BS-SNPer also offers higher sensitivity and specificity compared with existing methods. Availability and implementation: BS-SNPer is written in Cþþ and Perl, and is freely available at https://github.com/hellbelly/BS-Snper.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Sodium bisulfite conversion followed by sequencing (BS-Seq) has become popular for studying human epigenetic profiles (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Laird, 2010</ref>). Whole genome bisulfite sequencing detects 90% of methylation events and SNPs in the nuclear DNA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Lister et al., 2009</ref>). However, its cost remains too high for most laboratories. Reduced representation bisulfite sequencing (RRBS) is a more efficient and economical way to monitor genome-wide promoter and CpG island methylation status (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Laird, 2010</ref>) and it has become a popular method to investigate epigenetic changes in clinical tissue samples (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Berman et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hansen et al., 2011</ref>). SNP identification is important for identification of allelespecific epigenetic events such as, gamete specific and genetic imprinting (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Reik and Walter, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Wilkins, 2005</ref>). However, SNP calling from BS-Seq data has been shown to be complicated. One problem is that reads from two genomic strands are not complementary at methylated loci. Two methods were widely used to solve this problem. One is to align the reads in a three-letter space; the other is</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4006</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.<ref type="bibr">, 2012</ref>) to align the reads in a three-letter space. BSMAP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Xi and Li, 2009</ref>) uses a wildcard algorithm. Another problem is that true C/T SNPs in samples cannot be distinguished from C/T substitutions caused by bisulfite conversion and, thus, could be misidentified as unmethylated Cs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Liu et al., 2012</ref>). Given that over two-thirds of all SNPs occur in CpG context (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Tomso and Bell, 2003</ref>), sequence variations need to be addressed as an important error source. After alignment, real methylation status could be recovered, because a C/T SNP in Watson strand and G/A SNP in Crick strand should be interpreted as unmethylated cytosine variation (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>). Thus, Watson and Crick strands should be independently treated to reduce such errors. To our knowledge, Bis-SNP is a popular BS-Seq data based SNP calling tool. Another BS-Seq specific SNP caller, MethylExtract, is slightly faster than Bis-SNP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Barturen et al., 2013</ref>). However, BisSNP performs better in sensitive and accuracy. Here, we present BSSNPer, a program for BS-Seq variation detection from alignments in standard BAM/SAM format (). We implemented a novel algorithm (called 'dynamic matrix algorithm', see text below) and approximate Bayesian modeling to improve the performance. Using published RRBS data, BS-SNPer showed higher specificity and sensitivity with lower memory requirement and was over 100 times faster than Bis-SNP.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bioinformatics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>Two steps are implemented to obtain the final SNP set. In the first step, a candidate SNP set is obtained from alignments, usually in the BAM/SAM format, using a novel method 'dynamic matrix algorithm'. In the second step, the candidate set was converted to the final SNP set using Bayes model, considering alignment quality and read support.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Step 1. Dynamic matrix algorithm</head><p>Alignments are filtered based on sequencing quality, mapping quality and mismatch rates. Mutations are removed if their frequencies are lower than a certain threshold (default 0.1). The formulae to calculate the frequencies are listed in Supplementary Table S1. For the remaining candidate SNP set, positions, reference bases, the numbers of supporting reads and average sequencing quality for all four bases in both Watson and Crick strands are recorded. In order to improve memory and computation efficiency, these data are dynamically allocated and freed for each chromosome. For each position in a chromosome, the data are stored in the form of a vector; thus the data of a chromosome are stored in a matrix. The content and size of the matrix change with the chromosomes. The method is thus called 'dynamic matrix algorithm'.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Step 2. Approximate Bayesian modeling</head><p>In brief, the Bayesian inference of each genotype is based on its posterior distributions, P(GjD), using Bayes' formula. The posterior distribution is built upon two components: the prior distribution of each genotype P(G), and the likelihood P(DjG), which is the probability of observing reads D given genotype G. For the prior P(G), we referred to the model of SOAPsnp (). We observed that, when sequencing depth was higher than 10, the choice of the prior had no large effects. The likelihood, which represents the error rates caused by multiple sources, is calculated by the formula P(Djg ¼ G) ¼ Y n i¼1</p><p>PðDijg ¼ GÞ for multiple independent samples D i , where i ¼ 1, 2,. .. , n, and n is the number of reads. We used average error rate instead of full evaluation in error rate, which increases the modeling speed. The genotype with largest probability is recognized as the final SNP. See Supplementary Text for more details.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved.</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>, 31(24), 2015, 4006–4008 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv507 Advance Access Publication Date: 28 August 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table>a wildcard algorithm which accounts for the C/T conversions. 
Many software packages have been developed based on these 
two methods. Bismark (Krueger and Andrews, 2011), 
MethylCoder (Pedersen et al., 2011), BRAT-BW (Harris et al., 
2012) and BS Seeker (Chen et al., 2010) are based on the Burrows– 
Wheeler transform. Bismark and BS Seeker use Bowtie (Langmead 
and Salzberg</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> Results Our previous RRBS data (Huang et al., 2014) were used to test the performance of BS-SNPer and to compare it with Bis-SNP. The data comprise one para-normal sample (below called &apos;Normal&apos;; normal tissue adjacent to cancer tissue at a distance of at least 5 cm) and three cancer samples, i.e. primary renal cell carcinomas (pRCC), local invasion of the vena cava (IVC) and distant metastasis to the brain (MB) tissues from a patient with metastatic clear cell renal cell carcinoma. Whole exome sequencing data in the same work (Huang et al., 2014) were employed to assess the performance of SNP calling. All reads of four samples were aligned to the GRCh37 assembly (hg19) of the human genome using the program BSMAP with options &apos;-z 64-p 12-s 16-v 10-q 2&apos;. The alignments were then fed into both BS-SNPer, MethylExtract and Bis-SNP under same conditions. We evaluated the algorithms on a system equipped with a six-core Intel Xeon E5650 2.66 GHz processor and 32 GB memory. The system runs on 64-bit Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4.1. The minimal running time of four samples of MethylExtract and Bis-SNP was 6 and 20 h, respectively, whereas BS-SNPer only used around 10 min for each</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Compared with Bis-SNP, the increase in speed was more than 100 times in all four cases, including normal tissue (Normal), pRCC, local IVC, distant MB</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>of. our published data (Huang et al.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The increase in speed was not at the cost of memory or accuracy. The maximal memory usage of BS-SNPer was 8 GB, whereas MethylExtract and Bis-SNP used 10 GB for all cases, respectively. BSSNPer also showed higher sensitivity and specificity for all four samples (Supplementary Table S2) For example</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Normal tissue</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">2730</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">SNPs were detected by BS-SNPer, among which 2335 were validated by exome data [false positive rate (FPR) 14.47%]. Bis-SNP detected 3483 SNPs</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>while. 2011 of them were validated (FPR 42.26%</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">As exome sequencing detected 2873 SNPs for this sample, false negative rate of BS-SNPer was 18.73%, whereas that of Bis-SNP and MethylExtract was 30% and 57.01%, respectively (Supplementary Table S2) In conclusion, based on a dynamic matrix algorithm and Bayesian statistical framework, we present BS-SNPer, a SNP calling tool for BS-Seq data. BS-SNPer provides high performance in terms of speed, memory usage, accuracy and sensitivity</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">MethylExtract 39.93%)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">MethylExtract: high-quality methylation maps and SNV calling from whole genome bisulfite sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">References</forename>
				<surname>Barturen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regions of focal DNA hypermethylation and longrange hypomethylation in colorectal cancer coincide with nuclear laminaassociated domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Berman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BS Seeker: precise mapping for bisulfite sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Bs-Snper</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">203</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased methylation variation in epigenetic domains across cancer types</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hansen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="768" to="775" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BRAT-BW: efficient and accurate mapping of bisulfite-treated reads</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Harris</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1795" to="1796" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multilayered molecular profiling supported the monoclonal origin of metastatic renal cell carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bismark: a flexible aligner and methylation caller for bisulfite-seq applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Krueger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Andrews</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1571" to="1572" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Principles and challenges of genomewide DNA methylation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Laird</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Langmead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Salzberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="359" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2078" to="2079" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SNP detection for massively parallel whole-genome resequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1124" to="1132" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human DNA methylomes at base resolution show widespread epigenomic differences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Lister</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">462</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bis-SNP: Combined DNA methylation and SNP calling for Bisulfite-seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MethylCoder: software pipeline for bisulfite-treated sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Pedersen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2435" to="2436" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic imprinting: parental influence on the genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Reik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Walter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequence context at human single nucleotide polymorphisms: overrepresentation of CpG dinucleotide at polymorphic sites and suppression of variation in CpG islands</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Tomso</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Bell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">327</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="308" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic imprinting and methylation: epigenetic canalization and conflict</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Wilkins</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="356" to="365" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BSMAP: whole genome bisulfite sequence MAPping program</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Xi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">232</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>