
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:55+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression CAGExploreR: an R package for the analysis and visualization of promoter dynamics across multiple experiments</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Emmanuel</forename>
								<surname>Dimont</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>655 Huntington Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Oliver</forename>
								<surname>Hofmann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>655 Huntington Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Shannan</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Ho Sui</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>655 Huntington Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alistair</forename>
								<forename type="middle">R R</forename>
								<surname>Forrest</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">RIKEN Omics Science Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>230-0045</postCode>
									<settlement>Yokohama, Japan</settlement>
									<region>Kanagawa</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Genomic Technologies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">RIKEN Center for Life Science Technologies</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>230-0045</postCode>
									<settlement>Yokohama</settlement>
									<region>Kanagawa</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hideya</forename>
								<surname>Kawaji</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">RIKEN Omics Science Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>230-0045</postCode>
									<settlement>Yokohama, Japan</settlement>
									<region>Kanagawa</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Genomic Technologies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">RIKEN Center for Life Science Technologies</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>230-0045</postCode>
									<settlement>Yokohama</settlement>
									<region>Kanagawa</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">RIKEN Preventive Medicine and Diagnosis Innovation Program</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>351-0198</postCode>
									<settlement>Wako</settlement>
									<region>Saitama</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Fantom</forename>
								<surname>Consortium</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Winston</forename>
								<surname>Hide</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>655 Huntington Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression CAGExploreR: an R package for the analysis and visualization of promoter dynamics across multiple experiments</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1183" to="1184"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 25, 2013; revised on February 5, 2014; accepted on February 27, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Ziv Bar-Joseph Contact: edimont@mail.harvard.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Alternate promoter usage is an important molecular mechanism for generating RNA and protein diversity. Cap Analysis Gene Expression (CAGE) is a powerful approach for revealing the multiplicity of transcription start site (TSS) events across experiments and conditions. An understanding of the dynamics of TSS choice across these conditions requires both sensitive quantification and comparative visu-alization. We have developed CAGExploreR, an R package to detect and visualize changes in the use of specific TSS in wider promoter regions in the context of changes in overall gene expression when comparing different CAGE samples. These changes provide insight into the modification of transcript isoform generation and regulatory network alterations associated with cell types and conditions. CAGExploreR is based on the FANTOM5 and MPromDb promoter set definitions but can also work with user-supplied regions. The package compares multiple CAGE libraries simultaneously. Supplementary Materials describe methods in detail, and a vignette demonstrates a workflow with a real data example. Availability and implementation: The package is freely available under the MIT license from CRAN (http://cran.r-project.org/web/ packages/CAGExploreR).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>It has been predicted that the majority of human genes have multiple promoters. The differential use of transcription start sites (TSSs) in alternative promoters is a complementary mechanism to alternate splicing for the generation of RNA diversity that is now becoming better understood (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Pal et al., 2011</ref>). Tissuespecific TSS usage has been identified in mammalian genomes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Carninci et al., 2006</ref>), and alternate TSS usage has been identified in cancers when compared with normal cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Thorsen et al., 2011</ref>), implying that promoter-specific transcription coupled with gene expression exists as hallmarks of cell state. The profound impact of switches in transcript isoform production is well recognized for its role in regulation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Trapnell et al., 2010</ref>). Cap Analysis Gene Expression (CAGE) captures, sequences and maps capped 5 0 RNA tags. In addition to being a platform for measuring gene expression, it has more importantly provided molecular biologists with enhanced resolution of gene regulation by revealing the precise locations of transcription initiation events (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Plessy et al., 2010</ref>). CAGE data have recently become more plentiful, thanks to the recent ENCODE (2012) and FANTOM5 (Forrest A.R.R<ref type="bibr">. et al., 2014</ref>) publications. Analysis of TSS choice provides insight into the variation of transcription factor binding, epigenetic modifications and regulatory network activation between different cell types. Although CAGE allows for the identification of individual TSS, it is more convenient to group clusters of TSSs detected in close vicinity into 'promoter' regions. This makes CAGE an attractive platform for de novo promoter identification. The relative transcription occurring at TSSs among alternative promoters of a gene is termed promoter composition (PC). We describe CAGExploreR, an R package that conveniently summarizes, visualizes and ranks changes in PC (also called promoter 'switching') genome-wide across different samples. The dynamics of differential PC is especially intriguing when this phenomenon leads to changes in the abundance of different transcript isoforms or protein products within the cell population under study.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>highlights the conceptual difference between PC and differential gene expression. Four samples, A–D, are evaluated at four color-coded promoter regions located near or within a gene. Total gene expression measured as mapped tags per million sequenced following optional library normalization with edgeR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Robinson et al., 2010</ref>) is obtained by summing the number of tags that map to the union of the gene region, all four promoters including the regions between them and dividing by effective library size. PC is measured as a proportion vector. A and B have no change in PC, but the gene is differentially expressed. A and C have no differential gene expression but there is differential PC. Finally, A and D demonstrate both differential gene expression and differential PC. Existing bioinformatics tools that analyze count data from sequencing technologies treat genes as elementary indivisible units and usually measure differences in expression via a contrast between two groups of samples. Examples include edgeR *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Robinson et al., 2010</ref>) and Cuffdiff (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Trapnell et al., 2010</ref>) for differential gene expression and transcription analysis, respectively. Unlike these tools, CAGExploreR treats genes as multiunit blocks composed of promoter subunits and compares their relative expression within the gene across samples. It is not restricted to the analysis of contrasts between pairs of experiments but rather is designed to scale to any number of experiments for simultaneous comparison.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MODEL AND METHODS</head><p>Typical CAGE output consists of a BAM library file that maps sequenced tags to the genome, which CAGExploreR converts to a table of tag counts that correspond to promoter regions using either the built-in FANTOM5, MPromDb (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Gupta et al., 2011</ref>) or a set of user-specified promoter definitions such as de novo identified regions. Internally, a table of counts is generated for each mapped gene, with rows corresponding to the different samples or libraries and columns corresponding to promoters, and displayed accordingly as in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. The promoter counts are normalized to proportions within each gene and sample. The simplest case would be a 2 Â 2 table when comparing the PC across two samples for a gene with two promoters. Genes are assigned a proportional entropy reduction score (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Theil, 1970</ref>), which ranges from 0, when PC stays constant across every sample, to 1, when every sample transcribes exclusively from a unique promoter, for overall promoter switching. For each gene, the test of the null hypothesis of no differential PC corresponds to the test that the entropy reduction score is 0. P-values for this test are obtained using a Monte Carlo approach (Supplementary Methods). The switching effect size for promoter pairs is reported using the odds ratios for every nested 2 Â 2 table within a gene. In addition, entropy-based measures are used to quantify the level of heterogeneity in gene expression across samples. All P-values are adjusted for multiple comparisons using the Benjamini– Hochberg method to control the false discovery rate or some other appropriate user-specified method. CAGExploreR generates text-based and visual HTML reports and figures similar to<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>for further analysis. When several conditions are being compared, they can be grouped together via hierarchical clustering on a gene-by-gene basis, demonstrating which conditions have similar PC profiles. This profiling helps demonstrate whether the PC across replicates clusters together within experimental conditions. Consequently, the user can assess replicate agreement at the gene level and so can gain a sense of biological variability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DISCUSSION</head><p>We present CAGExploreR, the R package that addresses the important task of detecting changes in PC in CAGE experiments. The method is scalable to any number of conditions and/or promoter regions for simultaneous comparison. The method is flexible and can be applied to any experiment that produces tag counts grouped by classification factors in which the detection of switching or changes in composition is of interest, e.g. gene expression switching within gene sets, pathway activity switching within regulatory and molecular networks, isoform and exon switching using RNA-Seq. To use this software for any of the aforementioned applications, the user need only to change the genomic region definitions from promoter regions to other regions of interest. This work is part of the FANTOM5 project. Data download, genomic tools and copublished manuscripts have been summarized at http://fantom.gsc. riken.jp/5/top/.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Differential PC and differential gene expression. A, B, C and D are four arbitrary samples being compared. Gene displayed has four promoters</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">E.Dimont et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide analysis of mammalian promoter architecture and evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Carninci</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="626" to="635" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated encyclopedia of DNA elements in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Encode</forename>
				<surname>Consortium</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">489</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A promoter level mammalian expression atlas</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R R</forename>
				<surname>Forrest</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MPromDb update 2010: an integrated resource for annotation and visualization of mammalian gene promoters and ChIP-seq experimental data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Gupta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative transcription exceeds alternative splicing in generating the transcriptome diversity of cerebellar development</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Pal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1260" to="1272" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linking promoters to functional transcripts in small samples with nanoCAGE and CAGEscan</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Plessy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="528" to="534" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the estimation of relationships involving qualitative variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Theil</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Sociol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tumor-specific usage of alternative transcription start sites in colorectal cancer identified by genome-wide exon array analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Thorsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">505</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Trapnell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="515" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>