
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:50+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis CBrowse: a SAM/BAM-based contig browser for transcriptome assembly visualization and analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">18 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pei</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xiamen University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>361005</postCode>
									<settlement>Xiamen</settlement>
									<region>Fujian</region>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Botany</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Guoli</forename>
								<surname>Ji</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>glji@xmu. edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xiamen University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>361005</postCode>
									<settlement>Xiamen</settlement>
									<region>Fujian</region>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Min</forename>
								<surname>Dong</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xiamen University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>361005</postCode>
									<settlement>Xiamen</settlement>
									<region>Fujian</region>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Botany</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Emily</forename>
								<surname>Schmidt</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Botany</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Software Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Miami University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>45056</postCode>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<region>OH</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Douglas</forename>
								<surname>Lenox</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Botany</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Software Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Miami University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>45056</postCode>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<region>OH</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Liangliang</forename>
								<surname>Chen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xiamen University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>361005</postCode>
									<settlement>Xiamen</settlement>
									<region>Fujian</region>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Qi</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xiamen University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>361005</postCode>
									<settlement>Xiamen</settlement>
									<region>Fujian</region>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lin</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Botany</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jie</forename>
								<surname>Zhang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Plant Protection</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory for Biology of Plant Diseases and Insect Pests</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Agricultural Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100193</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chun</forename>
								<surname>Liang</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>liangc@muohio.edu or liangc.mu@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Botany</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Software Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Miami University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>45056</postCode>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<region>OH</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Plant Protection</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory for Biology of Plant Diseases and Insect Pests</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Agricultural Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100193</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alex</forename>
								<surname>Bateman</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis CBrowse: a SAM/BAM-based contig browser for transcriptome assembly visualization and analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2382" to="2384"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">18 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts443</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 30, 2012; revised on July 5, 2012; accepted on July 9, 2012</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Availability: CBrowse is distributed under the GNU General Public License, available at http://bioinfolab.muohio.edu/CBrowse/ Contact: Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>To address the impending need for exploring rapidly increased transcriptomics data generated for non-model organisms, we developed CBrowse, an AJAX-based web browser for visualizing and analyzing transcriptome assemblies and contigs. Designed in a standard three-tier architecture with a data pre-processing pipeline, CBrowse is essentially a Rich Internet Application that offers many seamlessly integrated web interfaces and allows users to navigate, sort, filter, search and visualize data smoothly. The pre-processing pipeline takes the contig sequence file in FASTA format and its relevant SAM/BAM file as the input; detects putative polymorphisms, simple sequence repeats and sequencing errors in contigs and generates image, JSON and database-compatible CSV text files that are directly utilized by different web interfaces. CBowse is a generic visu-alization and analysis tool that facilitates close examination of assembly quality, genetic polymorphisms, sequence repeats and/or sequencing errors in transcriptome sequencing projects.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Web-based genome browsers, such as GBrowse (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Stein et al., 2002</ref>) and UCSC Genome Browser (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kent et al., 2002</ref>), are widely utilized for visualizing genomes and their sequence features to facilitate various data analyses that address interesting biological questions. For non-model organisms without sequenced genomes, transcriptome sequencing is definitely the most efficient way to explore the transcribed portions of genomes and determine their dynamics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Braütigam et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Feldmeyer et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Parchman et al., 2010</ref>). Many bioinformatics programs have been developed/improved to address the challenges in transcriptome assembly, especially de novo assembly without a reference genome, using complementary DNA (cDNA)/messenger RNA (mRNA) data from next-generation sequencing and Sanger sequencing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Braütigam et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Feldmeyer et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Martin and Wang, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Zheng et al., 2011</ref>). So far, there is no open-source, web-based contig browser yet that allows users to navigate transcript assembly, visualize contigs and examine genetic polymorphisms, simple sequence repeats and sequencing errors embedded in the assembly. To address the impending need for exploring rapidly increased transcriptomics data for non-model organisms, we developed CBrowse (contig browser), an AJAX-based web browser to visualize and analyze transcriptome assemblies and their individual contigs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2383</head><p>Transcriptome assembly visualization and analysis errors and generate image, JSON and database-compatible CSV text files that are utilized by different web viewers of CBrowse (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig 1)</ref>. Our Cþþ program relies on the application programming interface (API) of BamTools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Barnett et al., 2011</ref>) to access BAM files, uses tinyXML library (http://www.grinninglizard. com/tinyxml/) to generate and parse configuration files and map index files in XML format and utilizes GD library (http:// www.libgd.org) to draw alignment graphics in PNG format. The pipeline not only extracts overall information for a transcriptome assembly (e.g. total number of contigs and associated reads, average reads per contig and contig length distribution) and calculates its N50 length but also retrieves summary information for each contig and computes its sequence coverage. For simple sequence repeats, our pipeline invokes Phobos (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Mayer et al., 2010</ref>) to identify perfect/imperfect repeats and generates results in GFF format. The repeat unit size and the minimum repeat number are customizable using the configuration XML file. By default, the repeat unit size is between 1 and 12 nt, while the minimum repeat number is set to be 8 for mono-nucleotides, 5 for dimers, 4 for triplets and 3 for repeats with a unit size of 4–12 nt. For putative polymorphisms and sequencing errors, our Cþþ program examines base by base for any discrepancy between each contig and its component sequence reads. Along a given contig, the Cþþ program identifies all putative polymorphic positions, which must be covered by 10 individual sequence reads and the accumulated occurrence of any polymorphic type is 5. The valid polymorphism types include single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs, single-base mismatch), single base indel and multiple-base mismatch and indels. The frequency of any valid polymorphism type needs to be at least 2 for any putative polymorphic position along a contig. Our pipeline also invokes SAMTools and BCFTools to call SNPs and short indels and generate results in VCF format, which can be explored through our Polymorphism Viewer (see below). Implemented in PHP and JavaScript (i.e. Dojo and MapEasy libraries), CBrowse web interfaces are AJAX-based and compatible with Mozilla Firefox (8.0 or above), Google Chrome and Internet Explorer (9.0 or above). As shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, there are five major viewers in CBrowse: (i) Contig Viewer presents summary information about the assembly as well as individual contigs; (ii) Sequence Viewer allows users to manipulate, examine and scan individual nucleotides of each contig; (iii) Polymorphism Viewer provides the polymorphism types (SNPs, single indels and other multiple-base mismatches/ indels), positions and frequencies for each contig; (iv) SSR Viewer displays the detected simple sequence repeats in each contig and (v) Alignment Viewer offers both bird's eye and nucleotide resolution of sequence alignments in Google-map style, with color-coded nucleotide differences between contigs and their component sequence reads. In particular, all these interfaces allow users to search and navigate data easily.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSION</head><p>Similar to GBrowse 2.0 (http://gmod.org/wiki/GBrowse), X-MAP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Yates et al., 2008</ref>), Genome Projector (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arakawa et al., 2009</ref>) and JBrowse (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Skinner et al., 2009</ref>), CBrowse essentially is an AJAX-based Rich Internet Application that decouples interactions with users from interactions with the server. Such decoupling empowers web applications with rich graphic user interface (GUI) characteristics such as desktop application, enables a asynchronous client–server communication and offers faster and smoother user experience by partial updates in web pages. Different from these genome browsers, CBrowse is designed for analyzing and visualizing transcriptome assembly and contigs, with unique functionality such as seamlessly integrated data grid viewer, alignment viewer and sequence viewer that allow users to navigate, sort, filter, search and visualize transcriptome data efficiently. As an open source project, our web-based CBrowse can be utilized by the research community to disseminate and release transcriptome data over the Internet.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The snapshots of CBrowse web interfaces Panel A: the major web portal shows contig length distribution for an assembly. Panel B: The data grid view shows contig summary information. Panel C: the sequence viewer shows its functionality with one contig. Panel D: the alignment view in bird's-eye resolution. Panel E: the alignment view in nucleotide resolution that displays and highlights the differences between contig sequence and individual sequence reads</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: This project was funded partially by the NIH-AREA (1R15GM94732-1 A1 to C.L.), the Key Project of Chinese National Programs for Fundamental Research and Development (973 Program: No. 2009CB118902), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 61174161 to J.G.), the Specialized Research Fund for the Doctoral Program of Higher Education of China (No. 20090121110022 to J.G.), and the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities in China (Xiamen University: No. 2011121047, No. 201112G018 and No. CXB2011035 to J.G.). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> IMPLEMENTATION As shown in Supplementary Figure S1, CBrowse is designed to follow a standard three-tier software architecture composed of Data Layer, Business Logic Layer and Presentation layer, with a data pre-processing pipeline. The data pre-processing pipeline detects simple sequence repeats for contigs, makes inferences from read alignments about putative polymorphisms and sequencing errors and stores resultant data in a hard-drive file system (HDFS), which can be optionally imported into a SQL-based database (e.g. MySQL or PostgreSQL). Data layer enables data accessing through HDFS or a database, Business Logic Layer processes users&apos; requests submitted from Presentation Layer and Presentation Layer displays the desired data in different web interfaces. Since Sequence Alignment/Map (SAM) format and its sister format Binary Sequence Alignment/Map (BAM) are widely adopted in presenting sequence alignment information for both genome and transcriptome assembly (Barnett et al., 2011; Li et al., 2009), the input files for the pre-processing pipeline are as follows: (i) a SAM/BAM file that contains alignment information for all individual cDNA/mRNA reads mapped to the contigs, (ii) a sequence file in FASTA format that contains all contigs within a transcriptome assembly and (iii) a Extensible Markup Language (XML) configure file that provides necessary information (e.g. species name, assembly name and data location) for data processing (Supplementary Fig. S1). Implemented in Cþþ with Perl wraps, the pipeline can process input data; detect polymorphisms, simple sequence repeats and sequencing *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</note>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">P.Li et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome Projector: zoomable genome map with multiple views</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Arakawa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BamTools: a Cþþ API and toolkit for analyzing and managing BAM files</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Barnett</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1691" to="1692" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Critical assessment of assembly strategies for non-model species mRNA-Seq data and application of next-generation sequencing to the comparison of C(3) and C(4) species</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Braütigam</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Bot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3093" to="3102" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Short read Illumina data for the de novo assembly of a non-model snail species transcriptome (Radix balthica, Basommatophora, Pulmonata), and a comparison of assembler performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Feldmeyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">317</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human genome browser at UCSC</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Kent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="996" to="1006" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Sequence alignment/map (SAM) format and SAMtools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2078" to="2079" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Next-generation transcriptome assembly</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Martin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="682" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide analysis of tandem repeats in Daphnia pulex–a comparative approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Mayer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">277</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptome sequencing in an ecologically important tree species: assembly, annotation, and marker discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Parchman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">180</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">JBrowse: a next-generation genome browser</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Skinner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1630" to="1638" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The generic genome browser: a building block for a model organism system database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Stein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1599" to="1610" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">X-Map: annotation and visualization of genome structure for Affymetrix exon array analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Yates</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="780" to="786" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">iAssembler: a package for de novo assembly of Roche-454/ Sanger transcriptome sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Zheng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">453</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>