
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:59+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining CDRUG: a web server for predicting anticancer activity of chemical compounds</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">. 24 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gong-Hua</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory of Genetic Resources and Evolution</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Kunming Institute of Zoology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jing-Fei</forename>
								<surname>Huang</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>huangjf@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory of Genetic Resources and Evolution</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Kunming Institute of Zoology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Kunming Institute of Zoology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chinese University of Hongkong Joint Research Center for Bio-resources and Human Disease Mechanisms</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>650223</postCode>
									<settlement>Kunming</settlement>
									<region>Yunnan</region>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining CDRUG: a web server for predicting anticancer activity of chemical compounds</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="3334" to="3335"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">. 24 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts625</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 16, 2012; revised on September 26, 2012; accepted on October 14, 2012</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Cancer is the leading cause of death worldwide. Screening anticancer candidates from tens of millions of chemical compounds is expensive and time-consuming. A rapid and user-friendly web server, known as CDRUG, is described here to predict the anticancer activity of chemical compounds. In CDRUG, a hybrid score was developed to measure the similarity of different compounds. The performance analysis shows that CDRUG has the area under curve of 0.878, indicating that CDRUG is effective to distinguish active and inactive compounds. Availability: The CDRUG web server and the standard-alone version are freely available at http://bsb.kiz.ac.cn/CDRUG/.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Cancer causes millions of deaths per year. Screening candidates from natural or synthetic compounds is an efficient way for cancer drug discovery (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Shoemaker, 2006</ref>). In the past decades, tens of millions of chemical compounds have been deposited in the public database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Wang et al., 2012</ref>). Discovering anticancer compounds from this huge database through experimental methods is expensive and time-consuming (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Chabner and Roberts, 2005</ref>). Although the National Cancer Institute (NCI) has been screening the anticancer compounds for tens of years, only 1% ($70 000) compounds were tested for screening anticancer compounds (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Shoemaker, 2006</ref>). Therefore, a rapid and effectively computational method is required for prediction of anticancer activity of chemical compounds. Here, we constructed a web server, termed Cancer Drug (CDRUG), to predict the anticancer activity of given compound(s). CDRUG uses a novel molecular description method (relative frequency-weighted fingerprint) to implement the compound 'fingerprints'. Then, a hybrid score was calculated to measure the similarity between the query and the active compounds. Finally, a confidence level (P-value) is calculated to predict whether the query compound(s) have, or do not have, the activity of anticancer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>To predict the anticancer activity of chemical compounds, we first constructed a benchmark dataset, which contains two subsets, active and inactive dataset. The active dataset consists of 8565 anticancer compounds, whereas the inactive dataset includes 9804 compounds. All of the datasets are from NCI-60 Developmental Therapeutics Program (DTP) project (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Shoemaker, 2006</ref>). The detailed method of constructing benchmark dataset can be found in Part I of Supplementary Material. Second, we used a novel molecular description method, termed as relative frequency-weighted fingerprint (RFW_FP), to calculate the compound 'fingerprints'. RFW_FP was calculated as follows:</p><p>RFW FPðiÞ ¼ BitðiÞ Â F active ðiÞ F inactive ðiÞ ð1Þ where i represents ith Daylight pattern or fingerprint. In Daylight theory, each compound contains more than one and less than 1024 patterns or fingerprints. RFW_FP(i) is ith relative frequency-weighted fingerprint. Bit(i) is calculated by Pybel (O'<ref type="bibr">Boyle et al., 2008</ref>), a python wrapper of Openbabel (O'<ref type="bibr">Boyle et al., 2011</ref>); if the compound has ith fingerprint, Bit(i) ¼ 1, else Bit(i) ¼ 0. F active (i) and F inactive (i) are the frequency of ith fingerprint in the active and inactive compounds, respectively. is the amplifying factor. In this study, was optimized as 4.0 (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>). Third, the relative frequency-weighted Tanimoto coefficient (RFW_TC) between two compounds was calculated as follows:</p><formula>RFW TCðm, nÞ ¼ S mn S m þ S n þ S mn ð2Þ</formula><p>where RFW_TC(m,n) is the relative frequency-weighted Tanimoto coefficient between two compounds (m and n). S m and S n are the sum of relative frequency-weighted fingerprints in compound m and n, respectively. S mn is the sum of the common relative frequency-weighted fingerprints between two compounds. Fourth, a hybrid score (HSCORE), based on both the RFW_TC and the MinMax Kernel (KMM) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Swamidass et al., 2005</ref>), was calculated to measure the similarity between two chemical compounds. HSCORE was calculated as follows:</p><p>HSCOREðm, nÞ ¼ RFW TCðm, nÞ Â KMMðm, nÞ ð 3Þ where HSCORE(m,n) is the hybrid score between two compounds (m and n). KMM(m,n) is the MinMax kernel (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Swamidass et al., 2005</ref>) between two compounds and is calculated by jCompoundMapper (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Hinselmann et al., 2011</ref>), a Java API for molecular kernel theory (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Swamidass et al., 2005</ref>). Finally, for each query chemical compounds, the maximum HSCORE between the query and the active dataset (8565 compounds) was calculated. Then the P-value, based on the maximum HSCORE, was calculated. Because the maximum HSCORE is not 41.0, and because the *To whom correspondence should be addressed. maximum HSCORE of the inactive compounds have a generalized extreme value distribution (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>), we can calculate the P-value as follows:</p><p>pðxÞ ¼ Fð1:0; , , Þ À Fðx; , , Þ ð 4Þ where p(x) is the P-value at the maximum HSCORE of x; F(x;m,,) is the cumulative function of generalized extreme value distribution. Using the maximum likelihood method ('fgev' function in R 'evd' package), we estimated the location parameter m of 0.094, the scale parameter of 0.063 and the shape parameter of 0.302. To implement the performance of CDRUG, 20 runs of 5-fold cross-validation method (Part II in Supplementary Material) were used to calculate the area under the curve (AUC). Four non-hybrid methods (including Daylight Tanimoto coefficient, RFW_TC, Tanimoto Kernel and MinMax kernel) and six hybrid methods were used to test the performance of the CDRUG (Part V of Supplementary Material).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DESCRIPTION OF CDRUG</head><p>CDRUG uses a novel weighted method (RFW_FP) to implement the molecular fingerprints, and it then uses a hybrid score to measure the compound similarity. The result shows that CDRUG outperforms other methods (P510 À13 , t-test) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1A</ref>and Supplementary Figs S4 and S5). When non-hybrid methods were used, MinMax kernel obtained the best performance with the AUC of 0.865. But when the hybrid methods were used, the AUC of CDRUG increased to 0.878. CDRUG can hit $65% positive results at the false-positive rate of 0.05 (Supplementary Figs S4 and S5). These results indicated that the CDRUG is effective to predict anticancer activity of the chemical compounds. CDRUG is rapid. It accepts one or more compounds to implement a prediction. A query with 1–20 compounds requires $35 s, whereas a query with 1000 compounds only requires $4 min. Therefore, CDRUG can be applied to both case-study and large-scale prediction. CDRUG is user-friendly. The only requirement of CDRUG is the SMILE(s) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Weininger, 1988</ref>) of the query compound(s). The result contains the query compound(s), the matched compound(s), average GI50 value of the matched compound(s), the maximum HSCORE and the P-value. CDRUG also predicts whether the query compound(s) have or do not have the activity of anticancer. The results are categorized as highly possible, possible and less possible depending on the P-value, and they are coloured by green, black and grey, respectively (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1B</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>CDRUG web server provides an effective, rapid and user-friendly interface to predict anticancer activity of chemical compounds.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: National Basic Research Program of China (2009CB941300); the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31123005); Chinese Academy of Sciences (2007211311091 to J.F.H.). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Overview of CDRUG. (A) Comparison of different methods. Non-hybrid methods are coloured by blue. CDRUG (hybrid method of RFW_TC Â KMM) is coloured by red. KMM ¼ MinMax kernel; KTC ¼ Tanimoto kernel; DTC ¼ Daylight Tanimoto coefficient; RFW_TC ¼ relative frequency-weighted Tanimoto coefficient. (B) The output page of CDRUG. Highly possible, possible and less possible results are coloured by green, black and grey, respectively</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Timeline—chemotherapy and the war on cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Chabner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Roberts</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">jCompoundMapper: an open source Java library and command-line tool for chemical fingerprints</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Hinselmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cheminform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open Babel: an open chemical toolbox</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Boyle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cheminform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">33</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pybel: a Python wrapper for the OpenBabel cheminformatics toolkit</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Boyle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem Cent. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The NCI60 human tumour cell line anticancer drug screen</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Shoemaker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="813" to="823" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kernels for small molecules and the prediction of mutagenicity, toxicity and anti-cancer activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Swamidass</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="368" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PubChem&apos;s BioAssay Database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="400" to="412" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smiles, a chemical language and information-system. 1. Introduction to methodology and encoding rules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Weininger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Comput. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>