
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:54+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">ChIPseeker: an R/Bioconductor package for ChIP peak annotation, comparison and visualization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Guangchuang</forename>
								<surname>Yu</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>guangchuangyu@gmail.com or tqyhe@jnu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Life Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Functional Protein Research of Guangdong Higher Education Institutes</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jinan University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510632</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory of Emerging Infectious Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">School of Public Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">The University of Hong Kong</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Hong Kong SAR</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Li-Gen</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Guangdong Information Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510031</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Qing-Yu</forename>
								<surname>He</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Life Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Functional Protein Research of Guangdong Higher Education Institutes</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jinan University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510632</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">ChIPseeker: an R/Bioconductor package for ChIP peak annotation, comparison and visualization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv145</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 2, 2015; revised on March 4, 2015; accepted on March 6, 2015</note>
					<note>Genome analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: John Hancock Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>ChIPseeker is an R package for annotating ChIP-seq data analysis. It supports annotating ChIP peaks and provides functions to visualize ChIP peaks coverage over chromosomes and profiles of peaks binding to TSS regions. Comparison of ChIP peak profiles and annotation are also supported. Moreover, it supports evaluating significant overlap among ChIP-seq datasets. Currently, ChIPseeker contains 15 000 bed file information from GEO database. These datasets can be downloaded and compare with user&apos;s own data to explore significant overlap datasets for inferring co-regulation or transcription factor complex for further investigation. Availability and implementation: ChIPseeker is released under Artistic-2.0 License. The source code and documents are freely available through Bioconductor</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Chromatin immunoprecipitation coupled with high-throughput sequencing (ChIP-seq) has become standard technology to investigate genome wide binding sites of transcription factors (TFs). To analyze these DNA binding sites to determine their potential regulatory functions, proximal genes/transcripts and regulatory elements are considered to annotate these loci. Several applications were developed for annotating ChIP-seq data. ChIPpeakAnno (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Zhu et al., 2010</ref>) is an R package that designed for ChIP-seq and ChIPchip data annotation. Because ChIPpeakAnno does not consider strand information, it misclassifies peaks with wrong orientation (see Supplemental File). Other tools including PAVIS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Huang et al., 2013</ref>) and PeakAnalyzer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Salmon-Divon et al., 2010</ref>), they all have similar functions of annotating peaks by nearest genes and proximal genomic features. Existing tools are all designed for single dataset. ChIP-seq is rapidly becoming a common technique and there are a large number of datasets available in the public domain. Results from individual experiments provide a limited understanding of chromatin interactions, as there is many factors cooperate to regulate transcription. Existing software lack of functionalities for comparing profiles of ChIP-seq datasets in different levels, including profiles of peaks binding to TSS regions, annotation and enriched functional profiles. There are increasing evidences shown that combinations of TFs are important for regulating gene expression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Perez-Pinera et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Zhu et al., 2008</ref>). However, systematically identification of TF interactions by ChIP-seq is still not available. Even if a specific TF binding is essential for a particular regulation was known, we do not have prior knowledge of all its co-factors. There are no systematic strategies available to identified un-known co-factors by ChIPseq. To fill this gap, we present an R/Bioconductor package, ChIPseeker, for ChIP peak annotation, comparison and visualization. It incorporates statistical testing of co-occurrence of difference ChIP-seq datasets and can be used to identify co-factors by exploring publicly available ChIP-seq datasets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Functions</head><p>ChIPseeker implements annotatePeak function for annotating peaks with nearest gene and genomic region where the peak is located. Almost all annotation software calculates the distance of a peak to the nearest TSS and annotates the peak to that gene. This can be misleading as binding sites might be located between two start sites of different genes or hit different genes, which have the same TSS location in the genome. The anntatePeak function provides parameters to annotate genes with a max distance cutoff and all genes within this distance will be reported for each peak. For annotating genomic region, annotatePeak function reports detail information when genomic region is Exon or Intron. For instance, 'Exon (uc002sbe.3/9736, exon 69 of 80)', means that the peak is overlaps with the 69th exon of the 80 exons that transcript uc002sbe.3 possess and the corresponding Entrez gene ID is 9736. ChIPseeker provides plotAnnoBar, plotAnnoPie, vennpie and plotDistToTSS functions to visualize ChIP peak annotation. plotAnnoBar and plotDistToTSS functions support comparing among different ChIPseq data. ChIPseeker supports annotating ChIP-seq data of a wide variety of species if they have transcript annotation TxDb object available. Users can generate a TxDb object from UCSC Genome Browser, BioMart database or GFF/GTF3 file by makeTranscript DbFromUCSC, makeTranscriptDbFromBiomart and makeTran scriptDbFromGFF functions respectively. These functions are available via the GenomicFeatures package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Lawrence et al., 2013</ref>). For functional enrichment analysis, ChIPseeker works fine with in house developed Bioconductor package, clusterProfiler (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Yu et al., 2012</ref>), DOSE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Yu et al., 2015</ref>) and ReactomePA. Once the peaks are annotated, users can use these packages to identify predominant biological themes through Gene Ontology, Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes, Disease Ontology and Reactome Pathway. Functional profile comparison is also supported by clusterProfiler. ChIPseeker provides covplot to visualize the peak locations and intensities over the whole genome. The plotAvgProf2 function visualizes the average profile of ChIP peaks binding to TSS region, while peakHeatmap function generate a heatmap of ChIP peaks binding to TSS regions. These two functions can accept a list of bed files and plot profiles and heatmaps among several ChIP experiments, making it easy to compare among different ChIP experiments based on the profiles of peaks binding to TSS regions. For comparing overlap of peaks and annotated genes, ChIPseeker provides vennplot to calculate the overlap and visualize the result. This method is widely used to compare different ChIP experiments and to infer cooperative in regulation. However simple overlap calculation is insufficient. In ChIPseeker, we provide enrichPeakOverlap function to perform statistically rigorous comparisons of ChIP-seq datasets. ChIPseeker provides shuffle function to randomly permute the genomic locations of ChIP peaks. The enrichment analysis of peak overlap is based on permutation test. A thousand (nShuffle ¼ 1000, by default) of random ChIP data were generated to estimate the background null distribution of the overlap. The P-value is then calculated by the probability of observing more extreme overlap. Multiple comparison corrections including Bonferroni, Benjamini and False Discovery Rate (FDR) are also incorporated. With the enrichPeakOverlap function, we can estimate how well two replicated experiments are and also compare overlap of two ChIP datasets from experiments of two binding proteins. If the overlap is significant, then these two proteins may cooperate in regulations. To make this co-factor inference available to the community, we incorporated the ChIP seq data deposited in GEO database. With these datasets, we can compare our own dataset to those deposited in GEO to identified co-occurrence binding proteins that maybe cooperated with the one we are interested in. Hypothesis can be generated by this inference and serve as a starting point for further investigations. Within the ChIPseeker package, we have collected information of about 15 000 bed files deposited in GEO database, which covers 68 species. User can access detail information by getGEOInfo function for specify genome version. ChIPseeker provides downloadGEObedFiles function to download all the bed files of a particular genome. Users can also use downloadGSMbedFiles to download all bed files with a specific GSM accession number list. After downloading the bed files, users can pass the folder to enrichPeakOverlap function, which will parse the folder and compare all the bed files. It is also possible to test the overlap significance among bed files that are mapping to different genome versions and even bed files from different species if chain file is passed to enrichPeakOverlap.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>ChIPseeker is developed as an R package within the Bioconductor (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Gentleman et al., 2004</ref>) project and is released under Artistic-2.0 License. ChIPseeker integrates ChIP annotation, comparison and visualization and serves as a toolbox for analysis of ChIP-seq data. It can visualize genomic coverage of ChIP-seq data, annotate genomic features of ChIP peaks and their nearest genes. ChIPseeker supports visualize intensities of ChIP peaks binding to TSS sites and comparison based on these profiles. It supports statistical test for overlap among ChIP-seq datasets. More importantly, it removes a major obstacle for scientists to query and utilize ChIP-seq data in public domains.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (21271086 to Q.Y.H) and Guangdong Natural Science Research Grant (32209003 to Q.Y.H.). The fundings are all received from China. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com Bioinformatics, 31(14), 2015, 2382–2383 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv145 Advance Access Publication Date: 11 March 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bioconductor: open software development for computational biology and bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Gentleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">80</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PAVIS: a tool for peak annotation and visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3097" to="3099" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Software for computing and annotating genomic ranges</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Lawrence</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synergistic and tunable human gene activation by combinations of synthetic transcription factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Perez-Pinera</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="239" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PeakAnalyzer: genome-wide annotation of chromatin binding and modification loci</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Salmon-Divon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">415</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">clusterProfiler: an R Package for comparing biological themes among gene clusters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Yu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">OMICS J. Integr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="284" to="287" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DOSE: an R/Bioconductor package for disease ontology semantic and enrichment analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Yu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="608" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating large-scale functional genomic data to dissect the complexity of yeast regulatory networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Zhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="854" to="861" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ChIPpeakAnno: a Bioconductor package to annotate ChIP-seq and ChIP-chip data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Zhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">237</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ChIPseeker</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>