
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:49+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies ChromoHub: a data hub for navigators of chromatin-mediated signalling</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lihua</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Structural Genomics Consortium</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>M5G1L7</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xi</forename>
								<surname>Ting Zhen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Structural Genomics Consortium</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>M5G1L7</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Emily</forename>
								<surname>Denton</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Structural Genomics Consortium</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>M5G1L7</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Brian</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Marsden</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Clinical Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Structural Genomics Consortium</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nuffield</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Oxford University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>OX3 7DQ</postCode>
									<settlement>Headington</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matthieu</forename>
								<surname>Schapira</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Structural Genomics Consortium</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>M5G1L7</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>M5S 1A8</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies ChromoHub: a data hub for navigators of chromatin-mediated signalling</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2205" to="2206"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts340</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 2, 2012; revised on June 6, 2012; accepted on June 7, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [19:06 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts340.tex] Page: 2205 2205–2206 Associate Editor: Martin Bishop Contact: matthieu.schapira@utoronto.ca Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The rapidly increasing research activity focused on chromatin-mediated regulation of epigenetic mechanisms is generating waves of data on writers, readers and erasers of the histone code, such as protein methyltransferases, bromodomains or histone deacetylases. To make these data easily accessible to communities of research scientists coming from diverse horizons, we have created ChromoHub, an online resource where users can map on phylogenetic trees disease associations, protein structures, chemical inhibitors, histone substrates, chromosomal aberrations and other types of data extracted from public repositories and the published literature. The interface can be used to define the structural or chemical coverage of a protein family, highlight domain architectures, interrogate disease relevance or zoom in on specific genes for more detailed information. This open-access resource should serve as a hub for cell biologists, medicinal chemists, structural biologists and other navigators that explore the biology of chromatin signalling. Availability: http://www.thesgc.org/chromohub/.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Chromatin-mediated control of gene expression and cell fate is regulated in part by distinct combinations of post-translational modifications on histone proteins, predominantly methylation or acetylation of lysine or arginine side chains at the N-terminal tails of histones (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Fierz and Muir, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kouzarides, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Strahl and Allis, 2000</ref>). Alteration of this histone code can lead to diseases states, and chemical inhibition of proteins that write, read or erase histone marks represents a promising avenue to restore to normal level diseaseassociated gene expression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arrowsmith et al., 2012</ref>). Following the clinical validation of this strategy with histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Prince et al., 2009</ref>), writers, readers and erasers of histone marks constitute emerging therapeutic target classes for a variety of * To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. disease conditions. Consequently, a dramatic increase in research activity has been observed in the field. The rapidly growing body of heterogeneous data generated by diverse communities of scientists is in part accessible through public repositories or the published literature. But retrieving the data is time-consuming at best for the non-specialist: will a cell biologist know where to find what small molecule inhibitors are available for his protein of interest, and what their IC 50 's are? Will a medicinal chemist easily retrieve all compounds co-crystallized with her protein target? Will a biochemist know which somatic aberration, buried in vast cancer genomics databases, is linked to the protein he is characterizing? We have built a database that integrates such heterogeneous data types extracted from multiple repositories and the published literature. A simple yet powerful web interface allows research scientists coming from diverse horizons who are interested in writers, readers and erasers of the histone code to interrogate this database through phylogenetic representations of each protein family. The interface is freely available and should promote crosspollination between diverse communities of scientists interested in epigenetic signalling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Assembling protein families</head><p>Human protein families were defined by the presence of specific domains involved in writing, reading and erasing histone marks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arrowsmith et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kouzarides, 2007</ref>): protein methyltransferase (PMT) and histone acetyltransferase (HAT) domains for writers, lysine demethylase (KDM) and HDAC domains for erasers and bromodomains (BRD) for readers of acetylated lysines. Different domains are known to bind methyl-lysines (Tudor, MBT, Chromo, PWWP, PHD and BAH), and each defined a subfamily of its own (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kuo et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Taverna et al., 2007</ref>). The human protein reference database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Keshava Prasad et al., 2009</ref>), the PFAM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Punta et al., 2012</ref>) and SMART databases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Schultz et al., 2000</ref>) were queried to retrieve all human genes containing at least one of these domains. Duplicates were removed and missing genes clearly documented in the published literature were added manually.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Generating phylogenetic trees</head><p>For each protein family, two phylogenetic trees were produced. The first was based on a ClustalW (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Larkin et al., 2007</ref>) multiple sequence alignment of the default UniProt protein variant of each human gene. The second was based on a multiple sequence alignment of the domain after which the family was named (a domain-based tree was not generated for HATs as the catalytic domain is not always clearly defined for this family). In this case, a seed</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chromohub: a chromatin signalling database</head><p>sequence alignment was derived from available protein structures by aligning residues that were superimposed in the three-dimensional space in ICM (Molsoft, San Diego). Additional sequences were appended by aligning them to the closest seed sequence in ICM. A PHP script plotted a phylogenetic tree from the Newick string of the multiple sequence alignment and automatically defined X,Y coordinates next to each leaf of the tree for metadata mapping (Supplementary Methods). We verified that this methodology produced a phylogeny in agreement with trees previously published in the literature (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Filippakopoulos et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Richon et al., 2011</ref>). A larger version of the PMT family was reported that includes numerous putative arginine methyltransferases; these were not included as the authors of that work stated that they did not want to imply that these proteins are protein arginine methyltransferases per se (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Richon et al., 2011</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Metadata source</head><p>Data related to the biology, structural and chemical coverage of each gene were extracted from diverse repositories and stored in MySQL. Function summary, sub-cellular location and polymorphisms were retrieved from UniProt records. Tissue expression data were collected from the GNF's BioGPS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Wu et al., 2009</ref>). Cancer-associated chromosomal aberrations were extracted from the Mitelman database (http://cgap.nci.nih. gov/Chromosomes/Mitelman) and the Sanger Institute's cancer gene census (http://www.sanger.ac.uk/genetics/CGP/Census/). Protein interactions were from the String database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Szklarczyk et al., 2011</ref>). Structural coverage was produced by querying the Protein Databank (http://www.rcsb.org/pdb) with Blast. Protein domain architecture was defined by querying the PFAM database with HMMER (e-value cutoff of 0.01) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Sonnhammer et al., 1998</ref>). NIH funding was extracted from NIH's RePORT (http://projectreporter.nih. gov/reporter.cfm) and published literature from Pubmed. NCBI's built-in links between Pubmed records and genes were used to retrieve articles associated to human, mouse or rat orthologues of the gene of interest, and keywords embedded in Pubmed's MeSH terms served to associate Pubmed records with diseases. Histone substrates and chemical inhibitors were manually extracted from the literature and all records were linked to their respective Pubmed or patent reference. All chemical inhibitors from BindingDb can also be mapped on the trees (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Liu et al., 2007</ref>). Pubmed records, disease association, funding and structure coverage are updated automatically on a weekly basis. Other data are updated manually.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>The online user interface is based on phylogenetic representations of protein families involved in writing, reading and erasing histone post-translational modifications. Users can choose between phylogenetic classification derived from multiple alignments of fulllength sequences or sequences of the domain after which the family was named. Thumbnails of phylogenetic trees for each protein family can be clicked to display larger images. Once a tree is selected, the sequence alignment used to generate the tree can be downloaded. Checkboxes can be selected to map a diverse array of data on the tree of interest. Information on the data source is provided in a window that pops-up when hovering over a<ref type="bibr">[i]</ref>icon next to the checkbox. Once a checkbox is selected, associated symbols are shown next to each protein for which data is available. More information is then accessible by hovering over or clicking on the symbol of interest. Users can easily navigate the functional, structural and chemical landscape of each protein family. They can display functional summaries for each gene on the trees, list structures in the Protein Databank covering each gene and map them on linear representations of the protein where PFAM domains are highlighted, display small molecule co-crystallized with any protein or retrieve chemical inhibitors reported in the published or patent literature; they can see the number of entries in Pubmed for each gene and inspect disease associations automatically inferred from Pubmed records; users can easily access chromosomal aberrations linked to cancer, tissue expression data, sub-cellular location or histone substrates. Images can be saved on the desktop and embedded in presentations. Newcomers in the field can search for potential collaborators by looking for research laboratories with active funding on their gene of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>The explosion of research activity on epigenetic signalling and recent technological breakthroughs in genome-scale biology are providing a wealth of data related to writers, readers and erasers of histone marks. The open-access resource that we have developed should help research scientists involved in chromatin biology rapidly find data that inform their research.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [19:06 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts340.tex] Page: 2206 2205–2206</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: The Structural Genomics Consortium is a registered charity (1097737) that receives funds from Canadian Institutes of Health Research, Eli Lilly Canada, Genome Canada, GlaxoSmithKline, the Ontario Ministry of Economic Development and Innovation and the Novartis Research Foundation, Pfizer, Abbott, Takeda and the Wellcome Trust. Conflict of Interest: None declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author(s) 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by/3.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2206"> at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epigenetic protein families: a new frontier for drug discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Arrowsmith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Drug Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="384" to="400" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chromatin as an expansive canvas for chemical biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Fierz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Muir</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="427" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Histone recognition and large-scale structural analysis of the human bromodomain family</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Filippakopoulos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">149</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="214" to="231" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human Protein Reference Database—2009 update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Keshava</forename>
				<surname>Prasad</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="767" to="772" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chromatin modifications and their function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Kouzarides</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="693" to="705" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The BAH domain of ORC1 links H4K20me2 to DNA replication licensing and Meier–Gorlin syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Kuo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">484</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Larkin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2947" to="2948" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BindingDB: a web-accessible database of experimentally determined protein–ligand binding affinities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="198" to="201" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical studies of histone deacetylase inhibitors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Prince</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3958" to="3969" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Pfam protein families database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Punta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemogenetic analysis of human protein methyltransferases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Richon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Biol. Drug Des</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SMART: a web-based tool for the study of genetically mobile domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Schultz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="234" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PFAM: multiple sequence alignments and HMM-profiles of protein domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Sonnhammer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucl. Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="320" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The language of covalent histone modifications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Strahl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Allis</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">403</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The STRING database in 2011: functional interaction networks of proteins, globally integrated and scored</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Szklarczyk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="561" to="568" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How chromatin-binding modules interpret histone modifications: lessons from professional pocket pickers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Taverna</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1025" to="1040" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioGPS: an extensible and customizable portal for querying and organizing gene annotation resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">130</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>