
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Circleator: flexible circular visualization of genome-associated data with BioPerl and SVG</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">. 21 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jonathan</forename>
								<surname>Crabtree</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Genome Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21201</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sonia</forename>
								<surname>Agrawal</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Genome Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21201</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anup</forename>
								<surname>Mahurkar</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Genome Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21201</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Garry</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Myers</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Genome Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21201</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Microbiology and Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21201</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">i3 Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>PO Box 123</postBox>
									<postCode>2007</postCode>
									<settlement>Sydney, Broadway</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Microbial Pathogenesis</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland Dental School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21201</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Rasko</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Genome Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21201</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Microbiology and Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21201</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Microbial Pathogenesis</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland Dental School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21201</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Owen</forename>
								<surname>White</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Genome Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21201</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Health-Related Informatics and Bioimaging</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20740</postCode>
									<settlement>College Park</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Epidemiology and Public Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21201</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Circleator: flexible circular visualization of genome-associated data with BioPerl and SVG</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="3125" to="3127"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">. 21 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu505</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received and revised on May 28, 2014; accepted on July 18, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Circleator is a Perl application that generates circular figures of genome-associated data. It leverages BioPerl to support standard annotation and sequence file formats and produces publication quality SVG output. It is designed to be both flexible and easy to use. It includes a library of circular track types and predefined configuration files for common use-cases, including. (i) visualizing gene annotation and DNA sequence data from a GenBank flat file, (ii) displaying patterns of gene conservation in related microbial strains, (iii) showing Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms (SNPs) and indels relative to a reference genome and gene set and (iv) viewing RNA-Seq plots. Availability and implementation: Circleator is freely available under the Artistic License 2.0 from http://jonathancrabtree.github.io/ Circleator/ and is integrated with the CloVR cloud-based sequence analysis Virtual Machine (VM), which can be downloaded from</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>There are numerous circular genome visualization tools, with varying degrees of interactivity, usability and utility. They differ in the data types and formats they accept, the types of output they produce and the ease of customizing the mapping from input data to graphical display. Flexibility and ease-of-use are frequently at odds, with the most flexible tools often being the hardest to customize, particularly for non-programmers. To address this issue, Circleator provides multiple configuration options, allowing each user to choose the one that best suits his/her needs. Similar tools include GenomePlot (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gibson and Smith, 2003</ref>), a Perl/Tk application and DNAPlotter (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Carver et al., 2008</ref>), a Java application, both of which have graphical user interfaces and also support linear displays. GenoMap (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Sato and Ehira, 2003</ref>) is a Tcl/Tk microarray data viewer, and the GeneWiz browser (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hallin et al., 2009</ref>) is an interactive Java applet. Some combine analysis and visualization: BRIG (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alikhan et al., 2011</ref>) incorporates a BLAST-based prokaryotic genome comparison algorithm, and CGView Server (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Grant and Stothard, 2008</ref>) is a CGView-based (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Stothard and Wishart, 2005</ref>) web service that runs on-the-fly BLAST comparisons. At the other extreme, some tools display only predefined datasets: The Microbial Genome Viewer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kerkhoven et al., 2004</ref>) and Genome Projector (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Arakawa et al., 2009</ref>) are web-based tools in this category. GenomeDiagram (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Pritchard et al., 2006</ref>) supports linear and circular displays, but requires Python programming expertise. Circos (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Krzywinski et al., 2009</ref>) is a popular and powerful stand-alone tool but its use of complex hierarchical configuration files may put it out of reach of some users. The D3.js toolkit (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bostock et al., 2011</ref>) has a Circos-like 'chord diagram', but does not, to our knowledge, accept standard bioinformatic file formats. Circster (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Goecks et al., 2013</ref>), which uses D3.js, adds circular drawing capabilities to Galaxy. Circleator follows the computer design principle of making the common case fast: if a researcher has data in a standard format and needs a routine visualization then he/she should not have to reformat the data or experiment with parameter values. Conversely, with sufficient time, it should be possible to create novel and intricately detailed figures. Circleator users who wish to accomplish the former can choose a predefined configuration file, whereas those seeking more flexibility can write their own. Circleator's configuration file format supports several novel high-level abstractions (e.g. loops, symbolic track references, feature-based coordinate scaling) and reuses existing standards e.g. SVG, CSS (Cascading Style Sheets), where possible.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>Circleator is a stand-alone Perl application that has also been incorporated into CloVR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Angiuoli et al., 2011</ref>). It uses BioPerl (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Stajich et al., 2002</ref>) for internal data representation and produces SVG (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Dahlstr€ om et al., 2011</ref>) output, from which PDF, PNG and JPEG may be generated. *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Input data</head><p>Circleator accepts reference sequence(s) and annotation in any BioPerlsupported format, including GenBank format; Sequence Alignment/Map and BGZF-compressed SAM (SAM/BAM) alignment files; output from Cufflinks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Trapnell et al., 2010</ref>), Tandem Repeats Finder (TRF) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Benson, 1999</ref>) and the BLAST Score Ratio (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Rasko et al., 2005</ref>) utility; SNPs in Variant Call Format (VCF) and tab-delimited quantitative data, such as gene expression data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Features</head><p>Circleator outputs SVG natively, rather than using a graphics library that supports only a subset of SVG. It can draw text along circular paths and display semitransparent and overlapping tracks. The scale may vary around the circle, as in Circos, but also along the radius of the circle (i.e. a single figure may combine both global context and local detail, as in<ref type="figure">Fig. 1B</ref>). Regions to scale may be selected with a user-defined filter, e.g. to magnify by 100Â all SNP loci at which more than half of the genomes differ from the reference without having to explicitly list the relevant coordinate spans.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Configuration</head><p>Each line in the manually editable Circleator configuration file corresponds to a circular track. The configuration file supports loops, which allow the same set of tracks to be displayed for 80 genomes in a SNP comparison without repeating everything 80 times; pseudo-tracks, which do not appear in the figure but can load data or perform data transformations (e.g. the compute-deserts track, which identifies all regions of a specified length that do not contain any features of a specified type); track references, which allow tracks to reference each other by name, e.g. highlight each of the SNP deserts identified in track SD1 in red; and various feature filters, e.g. to draw only forwardstrand genes whose gene product field contains the keyword 'kinase'. Circleator supports the following configuration options, listed in order of increasing flexibility and decreasing ease-of-use: (i) reuse a predefined configuration file as is; (ii) customize a predefined configuration file; (iii) write a new configuration file using the predefined track types and (iv) define new track types, glyphs and/or filters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Documentation and test suite</head><p>The predefined configuration files and track types are well documented, and the HTML track documentation is automatically generated from the same Circleator configuration file that defines them. Circleator also has a set of regression tests that help to verify the correctness of the images it produces.<ref type="figure">Fig. 1. (A)</ref>The genome of Gardnerella vaginalis HMP9231 annotated with percent GC content (red), genes, GC-skew (green) and read coverage (blue) from five human metagenomic samples. (B) SNPs from an 80-genome Yersinia pestis SNP panel with the scale in the outer rings expanded to show the affected bases. The reference base and position is shown on the outside and SNPS are color-coded according to their predicted type. Additional details for these figures and others may be found in the supplementary information</p></div>
			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> CONCLUSIONS Circleator is a visualization tool that leverages BioPerl and SVG to produce publication-ready circular figures of genomeassociated data. It is highly configurable but includes predefined configuration files and a library of well-documented circular track types that allows users to create complex figures without programming expertise.</note>

			<note place="foot">J.Crabtree et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3127"> Circleator at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BLAST Ring Image Generator (BRIG): simple prokaryote genome comparisons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Alikhan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">402</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CloVR: a virtual machine for automated and portable sequence analysis from the desktop using cloud computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Angiuoli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">356</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Genome Projector: zoomable genome map with multiple views</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Arakawa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tandem repeats finder: a program to analyze DNA sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Benson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="573" to="580" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">D3: Data-driven documents</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Bostock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. Comput. Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2301" to="2309" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNAPlotter: circular and linear interactive genome visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Carver</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) 1.1. 2nd edn</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">€</forename>
				<surname>Dahlstr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Om</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-07-30" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>date. last accessed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome visualization made fast and simple</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Gibson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1449" to="1450" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Web-based visual analysis for high-throughput genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Goecks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">397</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The CGView server: a comparative genomics tool for circular genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Grant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Stothard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="184" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeneWiz browser: an interactive tool for visualizing sequenced chromosomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Hallin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stand. Genomic Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="204" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization for genomics: the microbial genome viewer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Kerkhoven</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1812" to="1814" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circos: an information aesthetic for comparative genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Krzywinski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1639" to="1645" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GenomeDiagram: a python package for the visualization of large-scale genomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Pritchard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="616" to="617" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of comparative genomic analyses by BLAST score ratio</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Rasko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GenoMap, a circular genome data viewer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Sato</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Ehira</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1583" to="1584" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Bioperl toolkit: Perl modules for the life sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Stajich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1611" to="1618" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circular genome visualization and exploration using CGView</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Stothard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Wishart</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="537" to="539" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Trapnell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="515" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>