
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:45+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining Comment on &apos;Discovering hospital admission patterns using models learnt from electronic hospital records&apos;. The importance of using the right codes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Guillermo</forename>
								<forename type="middle">H</forename>
								<surname>Lopez-Campos</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>guillermo.lopez@unimelb.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Health and Biomedical Informatics Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Melbourne</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Parkville</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Fernando</forename>
								<surname>Martin-Sanchez</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Healthcare Policy and Research. Division of Health Informatics. Weill Cornell Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kathleen</forename>
								<surname>Gray</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Health and Biomedical Informatics Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Melbourne</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Parkville</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining Comment on &apos;Discovering hospital admission patterns using models learnt from electronic hospital records&apos;. The importance of using the right codes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
				<date type="submission" when="2015-11-2" />
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Bioinformatics, 32(13), 2016, 2079–2080 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw078 Advance Access Publication Date: 15 February 2016 Letter to the Editor accd.net.au/Downloads.aspx Accessed October 26 2015</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">the use of alphanumeric characters suggest the use of ICD-10 (http:// www.who.int/classifications/icd/en, Accessed October 26 2015), but the number of chapters, 12, does not match the 22 chapters included in ICD-10. Of further concern is the article&apos;s selection of the code E62, which it describes as &apos;respiratory infections/inflammations&apos;. The author places this code, according to its starting letter &apos;E&apos;, under chapter four (IV) of ICD-10 (&apos;Endocrine, nutritional and metabolic diseases&apos;). The conceptual mismatch alone should raise doubts even among readers unfamiliar with ICD-10, and indeed further inspection would reveal that E62 does not exist as an ICD-10 code (http://apps.who.int/classifications/icd10/browse/2016/en, Accessed October 26 2015). Because of the lack of details about the dataset used and given the aforementioned example, we proceeded to analyze in further detail the rest of the codes provided in this article, comparing them with the ICD-10 codes, to check whether this was an unfortunate error limited to the introduction or a misconception propagated in further sections of the article. Our analysis of the codes in Table 1 of the article, which are said to account for 75% of the analyzed admissions, showed that they are either incorrect—meaning that they do not match the description provided (24 out of 30, 80%)—or non-existent (the remaining 6 out of 30, 20%). After this initial analysis, we attempted to identify a plausible origin for the codes used in this article, comparing them with other medical informatics codes. The results of our analysis point toward the use of the Australian Refined Diagnosis Related Groups (ARDRGs). Determining the exact version used is impossible due the removal of the additional letter that builds the code) (https://www. V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Markov model developed by the same author (similar to those presented in his reference 3, Arandjelovic, 2015a, b). For us to do a more detailed analysis in the interests of replicating this study would have required access to the original dataset. Despite the journal policy encouraging dataset publication, we understand if the dataset cannot be made available due to ethical and confidentiality issues associated with the secondary use of data extracted from clinical records. For this very reason, it is concerning to note that this article lacks any mention of ethical approval or procedures used for data anonymization, nor even acknowledgement of the original data source. This article&apos;s disregard for the meaning of clinical codes, its loose use of key healthcare terminology (the term &apos;admission&apos; is indistinctly used referring to codes, admission causes, diagnosis and apparently even for actual hospital admission events) and its critical omission of key information about the health data source all emphasize the need for greater collaboration between the bioinformatics and medical informatics communities to advance research of this kind. This is essential to ensure that there is fundamental understanding of the context where data are derived and where new methods and systems will be applied. Conflict of interest: none declared.</note>

			<note place="foot">G.H.Lopez-Campos et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovering hospital admission patterns using models learnt from electronic hospital records</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Arandjelovic</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3970" to="3976" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of health outcomes using big (health) data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Arandjelovic</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Int. Conf</title>
		<meeting>. Int. Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2543" to="2546" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time prediction of mortality, readmission, and length of stay using electronic health record data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Cai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Med. Inf. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sentiment Measurement in hospital Discharge Notes is Associated with readmission and mortality risk: an electronic health record study</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Mccoy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLos One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="0136341" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>