
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:44+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Comparing clustering and pre-processing in taxonomy analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">. 22 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Marc</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Bonder</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>bonder.m.j@gmail.com or b.brandt@acta.nl</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Preventive Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Academic Centre for Dentistry Amsterdam (ACTA)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Amsterdam</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">VU University Amsterdam</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for Integrative Bioinformatics (IBIVU)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">VU University Amsterdam</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">The Netherlands Associate Editor: Inanc Birol</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sanne</forename>
								<surname>Abeln</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for Integrative Bioinformatics (IBIVU)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">VU University Amsterdam</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">The Netherlands Associate Editor: Inanc Birol</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Egija</forename>
								<surname>Zaura</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Preventive Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Academic Centre for Dentistry Amsterdam (ACTA)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Amsterdam</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">VU University Amsterdam</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bernd</forename>
								<forename type="middle">W</forename>
								<surname>Brandt</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Preventive Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Academic Centre for Dentistry Amsterdam (ACTA)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Amsterdam</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">VU University Amsterdam</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Comparing clustering and pre-processing in taxonomy analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2891" to="2897"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">. 22 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts552</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 6, 2012; revised on August 27, 2012; accepted on September 1, 2012</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online. Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Massively parallel sequencing allows for rapid sequencing of large numbers of sequences in just a single run. Thus, 16S ribo-somal RNA (rRNA) amplicon sequencing of complex microbial communities has become possible. The sequenced 16S rRNA fragments (reads) are clustered into operational taxonomic units and taxo-nomic categories are assigned. Recent reports suggest that data pre-processing should be performed before clustering. We assessed combinations of data pre-processing steps and clustering algorithms on cluster accuracy for oral microbial sequence data. Results: The number of clusters varied up to two orders of magnitude depending on pre-processing. Pre-processing using both denoising and chimera checking resulted in a number of clusters that was closest to the number of species in the mock dataset (25 versus 15). Based on run time, purity and normalized mutual information, we could not identify a single best clustering algorithm. The differences in clustering accuracy among the algorithms after the same pre-processing were minor compared with the differences in accuracy among different pre-processing steps.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Recent developments in massively parallel sequencing allow for rapid characterization of a large number of sequences in a single run. 16S ribosomal RNA (rRNA) amplicon sequencing can reveal the composition of complex microbial communities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Schuster, 2008</ref>). The unprecedented sequencing depth means that even less abundant species can be detected via their sequences. The taxonomic composition of such samples may be characterized by grouping the sequence fragments (reads) into clusters of operational taxonomic units (OTUs). For many, often uncultivable, microbes, the 16S rRNA sequences are unknown. To avoid the dependency on incomplete databases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Cole et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sun et al., 2012</ref>), microbial community composition is typically determined by using a taxonomyindependent analysis (TIA). In this approach, the 16S rRNA sequences are compared against each other without directly assigning a taxonomy to the sequence; the number and size of the clusters</p><p>(OTUs) indicate the diversity of the sample. Recent benchmark studies have revealed several clustering programs that adequately cluster into OTUs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Huse et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schloss and Westcott, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sun et al., 2012</ref>). For this study, we selected all commonly used clustering approaches implemented in Quantitative Insights Into Microbial Ecology (QIIME) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Caporaso et al., 2010</ref>), and we also included ESPRIT-Tree as it performed well in a recent comparison of clustering methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sun et al., 2012</ref>) and as well as methods that include rRNA secondary structure information (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Wang et al., 2012</ref>). Recent reports suggest that before the clustering step several data cleaning, or pre-processing, steps should be performed to correct errors introduced during (pyro)sequencing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Edgar et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Haas et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kunin et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Quince et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Reeder and Knight, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schloss et al., 2011</ref>). The two most important pre-processing steps are denoising, which corrects errors within the reads based on raw sequencing output (flowgrams), and chimera checking, which removes chimeric sequences. The aim of this study is to identify suitable combinations of pre-processing steps and clustering methods for oral microbial sequence data. We used two sets of pyrosequenced reads of 16S rRNA to evaluate cluster accuracies. The first set, a mock dataset, had a known species composition (15 species; Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). The second set, a clinical dataset, has reads from samples of human saliva collected in a study on the influence of Candida on the composition of the oral microbiome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kraneveld et al., 2012</ref>). Assessing the performance of the pre-processing and clustering combinations is non-trivial, since no gold standard is available for the taxonomic composition of the samples. In this work, we use two strategies to assess this performance. First, we take a simple approach and check whether the number of clusters agrees with the expected number of species in the mock sample. The taxonomic composition of the clinical sample may be approximated by assigning a taxonomic label from a reference rRNA database to each read. Second, we assess the clusters based on labelling of sequences. Therefore, we calculate the purity and normalized mutual information (NMI) scores (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Press et al., 2007</ref>). Purity scores reflect the homogeneity of a cluster. If the majority of the labels in each cluster are the same, the purity score is high. However, the purity score does not penalize for the creation of multiple clusters that contain the same label(s). The NMI score, in addition, reflects the mutual information between the clusters and the taxonomic labels; a high NMI score is achieved when high purity is reached with a minimum number of clusters. *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.1">Datasets</head><p>We used a mock and clinical dataset. Both sets were pyrosequenced (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Margulies et al., 2005</ref>). Amplification was performed using 16S rRNA PCR primers targeting the V5–V7 hypervariable region: forward primer 785F (GGATTAGATACCCBRGTAGTC) and reverse primer 1175R (ACGTCRTCCCCDCCTTCCTC). The primers included the 454 Life Sciences (Branford, CT, USA) Adapter A (for forward primers) and B (for reverse primers) fused to the 5 0 end of the 16S rDNA bacterial primer sequence and a unique 10 nucleotide molecular identification code. From the clinical dataset, all samples with at least 1250 reads and at most 20 000 reads were selected. These thresholds were chosen to exclude samples with possible errors in sample preparation and over-or under amplification before sequencing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2">Reference database A 16S</head><p>rRNA reference is necessary for chimera checking (UCHIME), clustering (QIIME BLAST, UCLUST reference) and for evaluating clustering results. This reference database was produced by an in silico amplification of the SILVA SSU 16S rRNA reference database, version 108 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Pruesse et al., 2007</ref>). A single nucleotide mismatch was allowed for each primer and the longest amplicon was taken in case multiple amplicons were formed from one sequence. The resulting amplicon sequences were made non-redundant. If identical sequences had different taxonomic lineages, the longest shared lineage was used. A suffix was added if multiple different sequences had exactly the same lineage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Read preparation and pre-processing</head><p>QIIME (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Caporaso et al., 2010</ref>) was used to pre-process the reads. Default settings were used, except for the following: minimum sequence length: 150; sliding window size: 50; reverse primer removal: truncate_only. The reverse primer was removed when it was found. Reads with one or more mismatch to the forward primer were discarded. Next, the two sets were pre-processed in four different ways: (i) no cleaning (NC), (ii) chimera checked (CC), (iii) denoised (D) and</p><p>(iv) denoised and chimera checked (DCC). This resulted in eight different test sets for further analysis. The reads were denoised with denoiser with default settings for denoising 454 GS FLX Titanium (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Reeder and Knight, 2010</ref>), which is now part of QIIME (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Caporaso et al., 2010</ref>). For chimera checking, we used UCHIME (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Edgar et al., 2011</ref>) in both the reference and the de novo mode. If a read was marked as chimeric in either of the two methods, the read was filtered out. We used our non-redundant SILVA database (see above) as the reference for UCHIME.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Clustering algorithms</head><p>The datasets, pre-processed in the four different ways, were all clustered into OTUs with five different clustering approaches: UCLUST version 4.2.40 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Edgar, 2010</ref>), mothur clustering version 1.6.0 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Schloss et al., 2009</ref>), ESPRIT-Tree beta release September 2011 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cai and Sun, 2011</ref>), CD-HIT version 3.1.1 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Li and Godzik, 2006</ref>) and QIIME BLAST clustering (QIIME 1.3.0 and BLAST 2.2.22) (<ref type="bibr">Altschul et al., 1990</ref>). The QIIME BLAST clustering approach matches the reads to the closest sequence in the database and groups the reads based on the BLAST label. For UCLUST, we used both the de novo mode and the reference mode. For the 'denoised and chimera checked' set, the UCLUST reference optimal mode was also tested. This method often gives the same output as UCLUST reference but has a much longer run time (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Edgar, 2010</ref>). For mothur, both average and complete linkages were tested. Furthest linkage is the default, but in a recent study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Huse et al., 2010</ref>), it was concluded that average linkage outperforms furthest linkage. For both BLAST and UCLUST in reference mode, we used our primer-specific non-redundant SILVA rRNA database as reference. Except for the distance, which we set to 97% sequence identity, we used default settings for the clustering algorithms as these were found to be optimal by the authors of the different (respective) clustering methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Clustering accuracy</head><p>To determine the accuracy of clustering, we labelled the reads with a taxonomic lineage by BLASTing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Altschul et al., 1997</ref>) (BLAST 2.2.25þ) all reads to our (trimmed) SILVA reference database (95% identity threshold). It is not trivial to assign a unique taxonomic label to a read, since a single read sometimes can be mapped to two labels with equal BLAST scores (this can also occur at 100% identity and 100% coverage). To solve this problem, we use either a consensus or a unique labelling approach. In the consensus approach, the labels were merged to the highest shared taxonomic category when a query had two or more hits with equal score. The suffix, added during reference databasecreation, was removed. For instance, when a read is labelled with: 'Bacteria;Firmicutes;Bacilli;Lactobacillales;Lactobacillaceae_21' and 'Bacteria;Firmicutes;Bacilli;Lactobacillales;Lactobacillaceae;Lactobacillus_2', then the label of the sequence in the consensus treatment becomes: 'Bacteria;Firmicutes;Bacilli;Lactobacillales;Lactobacillaceae'. In the unique approach, all the labels remain unique: if a query had two or more hits with equal score, they were combined into one header by adding a separation mark. The headers were always written in alphabetical order. The appended number, which made the header unique, was not removed in the unique treatment. For instance, if a read is assigned the same labels as the previous example, the unique treatment would result in this label: 'Bacteria;Firmicutes;Bacilli;Lactobacillales;Lactobacillaceae;Lactobacillus_2_/_Bacteria;Firmicutes;Bacilli;Lactobacillales; Lactobacillaceae_21'. Clustering accuracy was evaluated with cluster purity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Press et al., 2007</ref>) and the NMI (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Press et al., 2007</ref>). For both scoring functions, we discarded the reads that did not have a label assigned after BLASTing as there is no obvious way to evaluate clusters, including reads with 'unknown' labels. Cluster purity is calculated as:</p><formula>purity , C ð Þ¼ 1 N X k max j j! k \ c j j ð 1Þ</formula><p>where ¼ {w 1 , w 2 ,. .. , w k } is the set of clusters, C ¼ {c 1 , c 2 ,. .. , c j } is the set of classes as defined by the taxonomic labels and N is the total number of sequences. As a second scoring function, the NMI was used. The NMI is calculated as:</p><formula>NMI , C ð Þ¼ I , C ð Þ ½H ð Þ þ H C ð Þ=2 ð2Þ</formula><p>where I( ,C) is the mutual information gain, H(X) is the entropy. The NMI and purity were calculated using the lineage returned by BLAST for both unique and consensus treatments. Depending on the BLAST results, the lineages can be up to any taxonomic level.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>The accuracy of several clustering algorithms was assessed using two test sets of sequence reads: a mock dataset and a clinical dataset. The datasets were pre-processed in four ways: (i) no cleaning (NC),The clustering results were evaluated in two ways: a consensus and a unique method (see Methods section). The consensus method merges the assigned lineages to a highest shared taxonomic level, while the unique method only merges the labels. Here, the number of unique labels in the unique set is larger than in the consensus set (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). The clustering accuracy was measured with the purity and the NMI. Below, the results of the clustering evaluation on the mock and clinical datasets are presented.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Mock dataset</head><p>The mock community test set contained 15 oral microbial species (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). All pre-processing steps affected the number of reads and unique reads (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). First, we compared the total run time of the pre-processing and clustering algorithms combined (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). The QIIME BLAST clustering method required the most time. The fastest QIIME BLAST clustering, on 'denoised and chimera checked' data, was around 118 h slower than the other clustering methods on the same dataset. Next, the number of clusters formed was compared (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>). Ideally, in a TIA, the number of species is identical to the number of clusters. However, this was not the case. Even the lowest number of clusters (25) was 66% higher than expected (15), based on the number of species in the mock. Furthermore, the effect of denoising is much larger than chimera checking on both the number of clusters and the number of unique reads (Tables 1 and 3). Since the composition of the mock set is known, we also tested whether all taxa present in the mock could be identified (using the consensus taxonomic labels). It was not always possible to unambiguously assign a taxonomic lineage, including the species level, by BLASTing the reads against our reference database. However, this was mainly caused by the extensive reference database and not by the reads themselves. For most species, even in silico produced amplicons match more than two species in our reference database (with the same score and at 100% identity). For example, the Streptococcus mutans amplicon is 100% identical to Streptococcus uncultured Streptococcus sp. and Streptococcus uncultured bacterium, allowing only the assignment of the genus name. Most importantly, all 10 genera present in the mock could be found after any pre-processing of the data. Next, we will evaluate the different clustering methods and pre-processing steps based on consensus and unique labelling of the reads.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1">Consensus labelling of reads</head><p>The cluster purities depend on the specific clustering algorithm and on the pre-processing approach (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1A</ref>). The clusters based on 'denoised and chimera checked' data had the highest purity. The clustering methods QIIME BLAST, 'UCLUST reference' and 'UCLUST reference optimal' resulted in a cluster purity of one while the others were very close to one. The purity showed a larger variation for the other pre-processing steps, especially when the data was not denoised (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1A</ref>). It should be noted that high purity is easier to acquire when the number of clusters is high. Indeed, a positive correlation between the number of clusters and the purity was observed. However, for mothur clustering with average linkage, this was not the case. The NMI shows a similar trend (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1B</ref>): the 'denoised and chimera checked' data again showed superior scores. CD-HIT, ESPRIT-Tree and UCLUST were the best performing clustering algorithms on this dataset with a scoreAmong the different pre-processing steps, the'denoised and chimera checked' pre-processing showed the best results. Based on purity, NMI scores and run time, CD-HIT, ESPRIT-Tree and UCLUST performed equally well after this pre-processing (NMI of 0.94, purity of almost 1 and 25 clusters).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">Unique labelling of reads As</head><p>in the consensus read labelling, the average purity and NMI was highest for the 'denoised and chimera checked' pre-processing (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). UCLUST in reference modes and mothur resulted in the best purity scores (about one). However, both the NMI scores and the number of clusters showed that mothur formed too many clusters. Out of the non-reference based cluster methods, CD-HIT, ESPRIT-Tree and UCLUST perform similarly well based on purity, NMI and number of clusters. The average cluster purity was generally lower in the unique than in the consensus read labelling. The average NMI scores, for all pre-processing steps, were higher in the unique than in the consensus read labelling. Both are consequences of the higher number of unique labels in the unique set, which is due to merging the labels differently. The complete results of the unique read labelling are shown in Supplementary Table 3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Clinical dataset</head><p>The same evaluations of clustering as above were performed on the clinical dataset. For the two most time-consuming methods, namely mothur and QIIME BLAST, we made the reads non-redundant before clustering; after clustering, the reads were reinflated to the input sample size. The time it took to make the reads unique and to inflate was included in the total run time of mothur and QIIME BLAST OTU picking methods. In addition, a distance cutoff (5% for furthest linkage and 15% for average linkage) was used during the distance matrix calculation in mothur, such that this matrix still fits in memory. In both cases, clustering was performed at 97% sequence identity. For mothur average, the matrix was still too large for the NC and CC set. The four different pre-processing steps resulted in different numbers of (unique) reads (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>). Denoising was the most time-consuming step (552 CPU hours). The QIIME BLAST clustering method required the most time while only clustering the unique reads. The run times of the pre-processing procedures and clustering methods are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_5">Table 5</ref>. Since the species composition of clinical data is unknown, the correct number of clusters is unknown. However, there was a large difference in the number of clusters formed, especially among the pre-processing methods (<ref type="figure">Table 6</ref>). The number of unique reads decreased enormously after denoising or chimera checking, but especially after doing both. When one compares the decrease in number of unique reads per clusters between the mock and the clinical set after each cleaning step, a similar trend can be observed. Roughly the same decrease in number of clusters per unique read is observed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Consensus labelling of reads</head><p>The cluster purity for all the clustering algorithms and the different pre-processing approaches are shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 2A</ref>and B. The 'denoised and chimera checked' data had overall the highest purity and NMI scores, as was the case for the mock set. The clustering methods 'UCLUST reference' and 'UCLUST reference optimal' had the highest purity (about one). Out of the non-reference based cluster methods, ESPRIT-Tree and UCLUST perform similarly well when combining purity, NMI scores and number of clusters. The complete consensus results are in Supplementary Table 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Unique labelling of reads As</head><p>with the consensus treatment, generally, the purity and NMI scores were highest for the 'denoised and chimera checked' pre-processing<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. The purity and NMI scores for the consensus and unique treatments on the mock dataset. (A) Consensus purity, (B) consensus NMI, (C) unique purity and (D) unique NMI (<ref type="figure">Figure 2C</ref>and D). Interestingly, for CD-HIT, the NMI was (marginally) higher for the 'denoised' data than for the 'denoised and chimera checked' data. 'UCLUST reference optimal' and 'UCLUST reference' performed the best with the purity very close to one. Based on the NMI, the highest scoring algorithms were 'UCLUST reference optimal' and 'UCLUST reference' (NMI very close to one). The complete results of the unique read labelling are shown in Supplementary Table 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>We compared different pre-processing and clustering methods with respect to the clustering of sequences into OTUs. The different pre-processing methods showed clear differences in the number of clusters that were formed. The 'denoised and chimera checked' data formed the number of clusters that was closest to the number of species in the mock.</p><p>The cluster algorithms formed minimally 25 clusters (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>), whereas 15 species were present in the mock community. In the clinical dataset, we observed around 300–450 clusters after denoising and chimera checking. When using only one of the two pre-processing methods, 1000–3000 clusters were formed. Without any pre-processing, the number of clusters reached beyond 7000. As with the mock community data, in the clinical dataset clustering the 'denoised and chimera checked' data performed best if the NMI and purity scores were used as the quality criterion. The actual number of valid clusters in the clinical dataset is unknown. Based on cloning and traditional Sanger sequencing, currently, there are 600–1200 species reported that are associated with the human oral microbiome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dewhirst et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Paster et al., 2001</ref>). However, the oral microbiome diversity is estimated to be at least an order of magnitude higher based on data from high-throughput sequencing approaches (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Keijser et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Yang et al., 2012</ref>). Considering the decreasing number of clusters in the mock set in relation to increasingread pre-processing and a similar trend in the reduction of number of clusters in the clinical set, it is likely that the previous estimates are at the higher end of the actual diversity. We observe the same overestimation in microbial diversity as the authors of pre-clustering (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Huse et al., 2010</ref>) and denoising algorithms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Quince et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Reeder and Knight, 2010</ref>). The differences in the NMI and purity scores for the clustering methods are minor when compared with the differences for the pre-processing methods. The UCLUST reference-based methods generally outperform the other methods based on the NMI score, while the purity scores were also high. Both suggest that the UCLUST reference methods are the methods of choice. However, it is important to note that these methods form a larger number of clusters than expected and larger than the minimal number of clusters found and use the same reference database on which the taxonomic labels are based, making such a statement too bold. In general, UCLUST and ESPRIT-Tree came out top among the non-reference based methods. They showed a similar performance based on purity and NMI scores, while giving the lowest number of clusters. A reference database is required for chimera checking in reference mode and for UCLUST in the reference modes. Here, we used a trimmed and non-redundant reference, which greatly reduces run times (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Brandt et al., 2012</ref>). In this study, we did not use the trimmed set for training a classifier, but it has been found that this improves taxonomic classification (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Werner et al., 2012</ref>). The majority of the mock reads (99.8%) has been labelled with expected lineages. Although the mock contains 15 species, we do not expect 15 clusters. The V5–V7 regions of Streptococcus mitis and Streptococcus oralis are almost identical (99-100%). Thus, the expected number of clusters is (at least) 14. The different clustering algorithms returned 25 clusters at best. However, 11 of these 25 clusters have very few members (four are even singletons). If we use a relaxed threshold on cluster size of only 418 members, indeed, the 14 expected clusters remain. Given the relatively large number of very small clusters, we do not expect this to generalize to a clinical sample. While a threshold on cluster size is more difficult to determine for a clinical sample, very small clusters (e.g. with less than five members) could also be disregarded here (O ¨ zok et al., 2012), though at the risk of underestimating diversity. The determination of the microbiome, based on a few hypervariable regions of the 16S rRNA gene, makes it difficult to differentiate between several taxa on species level or even genus level. Furthermore, the sequencer creates errors (noise), which makes it even more difficult or impossible to differentiate between related species, such as Streptococcus species. In such cases, denoising, to filter out errors created by the sequencer, may regard the small differences between sequences as noise. Thus, pyrosequencing (a region of) 16S rRNA can distinguish between different genera or species, possibly in combination with denoising, only when sequences of the related taxa differ enough. It is important to note that denoising, chimera checking and clustering methods are context dependent: the result for a single read depends on the entire input set. This is specifically relevant for denoising of data from large studies, since it is typically done on several input files, like in this study. For example, similar sequences in one file can be denoised to Sequence A, while in another be denoised to Sequence B, simply because Sequence A is more dominant in the one file and Sequence B in the other. There was a remarkable difference in the number of reads discarded by chimera checking before and after denoising. On average, there was a 27% decrease in the number of non-unique reads when denoising was performed first. Moreover, denoising, which can also be seen as a pre-clustering step, has a huge influence on the number of clusters generated. However, denoising differs from the (other) clustering methods as it takes flowgram data into account. This potentially allows denoising to differentiate between true sequence differences and sequencing noise. The results of this study and other studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kunin et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schloss et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schloss and Westcott, 2011</ref>) suggest that it remains important to further investigate combinations of pre-processing steps. We find that the number of OTUs varies between one and two orders of magnitude depending pre-processing methods and clustering algorithms. Using a single-species reference (Escherichia coli), it was found that stringent filtering and low clustering thresholds should be applied to prevent overestimation of diversity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kunin et al., 2010</ref>): unfiltered reads overestimated the number of OTUs by two orders of magnitude (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kunin et al., 2010</ref>). With respect to technical variation, pre-processing and reduction of error rate, the thorough work of Schloss et al.</p><p>(2011) on mock communities is interesting. They also report that filtering (sliding window quality filter or denoising combined with chimera removal) is required to reduce the number of OTUs closer to the number of expected OTUs. Even after a 30-fold reduction in sequencing error rate, the number of expected OTUs and genera was not obtained (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schloss et al., 2011</ref>). More recently, it was also recommended to remove pyrosequencing errors and chimeras before clustering (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Jiang et al., 2012</ref>). While we could not identify a single best clustering algorithm, CD-HIT, ESPRIT-Tree and UCLUST perform well. In another study, UCLUST also performs well and comparable to CD-HIT but is outperformed by an average neighbour algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schloss and Westcott, 2011</ref>). ESPRIT-Tree, an average linkage-based<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. The purity and NMI scores for the consensus and unique treatments on the clinical dataset. Mothur average could not be used for the NC and CC set. (A) Consensus purity, (B) consensus NMI, (C) unique purity and (D) unique NMI hierarchical clustering algorithm, was found to outperform CD-HIT, UCLUST and mothur (average linkage) in another benchmark study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sun et al., 2012</ref>). In summary, we tested four pre-processing methods and multiple clustering algorithms to cluster sequences into OTUs. By combining these steps, we assessed the influence of read filtering on clustering. We showed that cleaning influences the number of OTUs much more when compared with the different clustering methods. The pre-processing method that resulted in the highest NMI, the highest purity and the number of clusters closest to the expected number of clusters was the combination of denoising with chimera checking. Our results give strong evidence that without pre-processing steps the data contains too many errors in order for any clustering algorithm to perform well. This warrants further investigation in pre-processing techniques that allow for the correction of such errors, as more accurate pre-processing will have a larger effect than improving current clustering techniques. Alternatively, integrated approaches may be investigated.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>(ii) chimera checked (CC), (iii) denoised (D) and (iv) denoised and chimera checked (DCC), for further details see Methods section. The resulting sets were all clustered using five different clustering algorithms: UCLUST, mothur clustering, ESPRIT-Tree, CD-HIT and QIIME BLAST.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2. Comparison of the total run time of the clustering algorithms and pre-processing methods on the mock dataset</figDesc><table>Pre-processing 
</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1.</figDesc><table>Comparison of the number of total reads, non-redundant (unique) reads, removed reads, number of reads without a label and number of labels 
for each pre-processing method on the mock set 

Pre-processing 
No. of reads 
No. of unique reads 
No. of removed 
reads 

No. of reads 
labelled as unknown 

No. of 
unique labels 

No. of 
consensus labels 

NC 
38612 
11618 
0 
371 
637 
106 
CC 
33375 
8431 
5237 
15 
390 
61 
D 
38612 
190 
0 
192 
85 
42 
DCC 
34885 
45 
3727 
18 
29 
23 

NC stands for no cleaning, CC stands for chimera checked, D stands for denoised and DCC stands for denoised and chimera checked. </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 3. Comparison of the number of clusters formed for each clustering algorithm and pre-processing method</figDesc><table>Pre-processing 
</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 6. Comparison of the number of clusters formed for each clustering algorithm and pre-processing method</figDesc><table>Pre-processing 
</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 5.</figDesc><table>Comparison of the total run time of the clustering algorithms and pre-processing methods on the clinical dataset 

Pre-procesing 
Clustering algorithms 

QIIME BLAST 
CD-HIT 
ESPRIT-Tree 
Mothur 
furthest 

Mothur 
average 

UCLUST 
UCLUST ref 
UCLUST ref 
optimal 

NC 
426:49:07 
13:41:22 
4:51:37 
19:01:07 
* 
2:51:17 
2:46:40 
CC 
407:55:49 
179:14:54 
176:09:02 
181:12:24 
* 
175:23:37 
175:25:18 
D 
566:02:45 
555:59:20 
555:06:41 
555:05:36 
555:05:34 
555:05:15 
555:06:39 
DCC 
560:17:08 
558:37:20 
558:18:45 
558:18:08 
558:18:04 
558:18:04 
558:18:35 
560:22:45 

Run time is given in hours:minutes:seconds. *Mothur average could not be used for the NC and CC set. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 4. Comparison of the number of total reads, non-redundant (unique) reads, removed reads, number of reads without a label and number of labels for each pre-processing method on the clinical set</figDesc><table>Pre-processing 
No. of reads 
No. of unique 
reads 

No. of removed 
reads 

No. of reads labelled 
as unknown 

No. of 
unique labels 

No. of 
consensus labels 

NC 
496 149 
110 508 
0 
11 449 
2754 
854 
CC 
391 136 
61 571 
105 013 
731 
1850 
62 
D 
496 148 
2933 
1 
7702 
1109 
33 
DCC 
418 469 
591 
77 680 
517 
356 
200 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.J.Bonder et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Clustering and pre-processing in taxonomy analysis at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank Eefje Kraneveld, Mark Buijs and Jessica Koopman for providing the sequence datasets.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3389" to="3402" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TaxMan: a server to trim rRNA reference databases and inspect taxonomic coverage</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Brandt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ESPRIT-Tree: hierarchical clustering analysis of millions of 16S rRNA pyrosequences in quasilinear computational time</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Cai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Sun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">QIIME allows analysis of high-throughput community sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Caporaso</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="336" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Ribosomal Database Project (RDP-II): sequences and tools for high-throughput rRNA analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Cole</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="294" to="296" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human oral microbiome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Dewhirst</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bacteriol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">192</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5002" to="5017" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Search and clustering orders of magnitude faster than BLAST</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Edgar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2460" to="2461" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UCHIME improves sensitivity and speed of chimera detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Edgar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2194" to="2200" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chimeric 16S rRNA sequence formation and detection in Sanger and 454-pyrosequenced PCR amplicons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Haas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="494" to="504" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ironing out the wrinkles in the rare biosphere through improved OTU clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Huse</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1889" to="1898" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two-stage clustering (TSC): a pipeline for selecting operational taxonomic units for the high-throughput sequencing of PCR amplicons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Jiang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">30230</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pyrosequencing analysis of the oral microflora of healthy adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J F</forename>
				<surname>Keijser</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Dent. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1016" to="1020" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relation between oral Candida load and bacterial microbiome profiles in Dutch older adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Kraneveld</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wrinkles in the rare biosphere: pyrosequencing errors can lead to artificial inflation of diversity estimates</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Kunin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="118" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cd-hit: a fast program for clustering and comparing large sets of protein or nucleotide sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Godzik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1658" to="1659" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome sequencing in microfabricated high-density picolitre reactors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Margulies</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">437</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="376" to="380" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ecology of the microbiome of the infected root canal system: a comparison between apical and coronal root segments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>¨ Zok</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. Endod. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="530" to="541" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bacterial diversity in human subgingival plaque</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Paster</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bacteriol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">183</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3770" to="3783" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Numerical Recipes: The Art of Scientific Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Press</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>NY, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SILVA: a comprehensive online resource for quality checked and aligned ribosomal RNA sequence data compatible with ARB</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Pruesse</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7188" to="7196" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Removing noise from pyrosequenced amplicons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Quince</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">38</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapidly denoising pyrosequencing amplicon reads by exploiting rank-abundance distributions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Reeder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Knight</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="668" to="669" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reducing the effects of PCR amplification and sequencing artifacts on 16S rRNA-based studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Schloss</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing and improving methods used in operational taxonomic unit-based approaches for 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Schloss</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Westcott</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3219" to="3226" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introducing mothur: open-source, platform-independent, community-supported software for describing and comparing microbial communities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Schloss</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7537" to="7541" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Next-generation sequencing transforms today&apos;s biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Schuster</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A large-scale benchmark study of existing algorithms for taxonomy-independent microbial community analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Sun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Secondary structure information does not improve OTU assignment for partial 16s rRNA sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ISME J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1277" to="1280" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of training sets on classification of high-throughput bacterial 16s rRNA gene surveys</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Werner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ISME J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="94" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Saliva microbiomes distinguish caries-active from healthy human populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ISME J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>