
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:49+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Covariate-modulated local false discovery rate for genome-wide association studies</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rong</forename>
								<forename type="middle">W</forename>
								<surname>Zablocki</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Computational Science Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">San Diego State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>92182</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andrew</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Schork</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Cognitive Sciences Graduate Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at San Diego</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Richard</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Levine</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics and Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">San Diego State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>92182</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ole</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Andreassen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Clinical Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oslo</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>0424</postCode>
									<settlement>Oslo, Norway</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anders</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Dale</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Cognitive Sciences Graduate Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at San Diego</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Multimodal Imaging Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at San Diego</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wesley</forename>
								<forename type="middle">K</forename>
								<surname>Thompson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at San Diego</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<surname>Hancock</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Covariate-modulated local false discovery rate for genome-wide association studies</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2098" to="2104"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu145</idno>
					<note type="submission">Advance Access publication April 7, 2014 Received on May 8, 2013; revised on March 3, 2014; accepted on March 5, 2014</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have largely failed to identify most of the genetic basis of highly heritable diseases and complex traits. Recent work has suggested this could be because many genetic variants, each with individually small effects, compose their genetic architecture, limiting the power of GWAS, given currently obtainable sample sizes. In this scenario, Bonferroni-derived thresholds are severely underpowered to detect the vast majority of associations. Local false discovery rate (fdr) methods provide more power to detect non-null associations, but implicit assumptions about the ex-changeability of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) limit their ability to discover non-null loci. Methods: We propose a novel covariate-modulated local false discovery rate (cmfdr) that incorporates prior information about gene element–based functional annotations of SNPs, so that SNPs from categories enriched for non-null associations have a lower fdr for a given value of a test statistic than SNPs in unenriched categories. This readjustment of fdr based on functional annotations is achieved empirically by fitting a covariate-modulated parametric two-group mixture model. The proposed cmfdr methodology is applied to a large Crohn&apos;s disease GWAS. Results: Use of cmfdr dramatically improves power, e.g. increasing the number of loci declared significant at the 0.05 fdr level by a factor of 5.4. We also demonstrate that SNPs were declared significant using cmfdr compared with usual fdr replicate in much higher numbers, while maintaining similar replication rates for a given fdr cutoff in de novo samples, using the eight Crohn&apos;s disease substudies as independent training and test datasets. Availability an implementation: https://sites.google.com/site/covmo dfdr/</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Large-scale hypothesis testing has emerged as a critical component of genetic analysis with the advent of high-throughput microarrays (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Efron and Tibshirani, 2002</ref>). For example, it is now possible to survey a large number of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) across the entire genome in an attempt to locate genetic variations associated with trait variability or disease risk. An advantage of large-scale genome-wide association studies (GWAS) is the ability to discover the potential effect of any number of variants across the genome, without making strong a priori hypotheses about the subset of the genome to consider (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Risch and Merikangas, 1996</ref>). A disadvantage is that a large number of false positives may occur when many hypothesis tests are conducted simultaneously (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Devlin and Roeder, 1999</ref>). Consequently, modern GWAS have adopted a stringent Bonferroni-derived multiple testing threshold of P 5 Â 10 À8 for declaring individual SNP associations significant. Unfortunately, these GWAS have largely failed to identify substantial portions of the genetic basis of highly heritable diseases and complex traits (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Collins, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Manolio et al., 2009</ref>). Recent work has strongly suggested this could be because many genetic variants, each with individually small effects, compose their genetic architecture, limiting the power of GWAS to detect true associations, given currently obtainable sample sizes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Yang et al., 2010</ref>). This scenario is especially damaging to power if all SNPs are treated as a priori exchangeable and hence equally likely to be related to the phenotype of interest, an implicit assumption of Bonferroni thresholds and false discovery rate (FDR) control (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995</ref>). Other work has placed an emphasis on characterizing the biological function of genetic variants across the genome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Torkamani et al., 2011</ref>). Typically, this work has focused on understanding how differences in the protein-coding region of genes may damage or alter the corresponding protein structure. However, recent efforts have attempted to characterize the potential effect of variants within non-coding elements, which may alter the timing, amount or location of gene expression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">ENCODE Consortium, 2012</ref>). Emerging from this research is a picture of widespread heterogeneity in the potential biological functionality of variants across the genome. A number of researchers have suggested that this heterogeneity of function *To whom correspondence should be addressed translates to association studies, with certain genetic elements or categories of variants containing more or less trait-associated variants (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Hindorff et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Schork et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Smith et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Yang et al., 2011</ref>). Given this, it is potentially of use to leverage functional annotations or other locus-specific covariates to improve gene discovery and replication of associations in de novo samples. Classical multiple-comparison procedures, such as the Bonferroni correction, control the family-wise error rate (FWER) or the probability of committing one or more Type I errors in a family of hypothesis tests. These procedures tend to be underpowered in large-scale testing paradigms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Efron, 2007</ref>). In other words, FWER procedures can be excessively conservative when thousands or millions of cases are tested. Benjamini and<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Hochberg (1995)</ref>proposed an alternative approach to Type I error control termed the FDR, defined as the expected proportion of errors among the rejected hypotheses. Variants of their algorithm are applied to P-values of test statistics (null hypothesis tail probabilities) from many tests to control FDR to a specified level under various conditions. Efron and<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Tibshirani (2002)</ref>developed an extension of FDR called the local false discovery rate (fdr) from an empirical Bayes point of view, defining fdr as the posterior probability that the null hypothesis is true, given the observed test statistic. The empirical Bayes approach to fdr is closely related to the<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Benjamini and Hochberg (1995)</ref>algorithm for FDR control (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Efron and Tibshirani, 2002</ref>). These groundbreaking methodologies for controlling multiplicity under large-scale hypothesis testing have received widespread attention and development (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Brown et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Efron, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ferkingstad et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Genovese et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Lawyer et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Lewinger et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Miller et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Ploner et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Sun et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Tusher et al., 2001</ref>).<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Lewinger et al. (2007)</ref>proposed a mixture model of non-central 2 test statistics, where the probability of being associated with a phenotype (having a non-centrality parameter different from zero) depends on multiple covariates.<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ferkingstad et al. (2008)</ref>proposed an estimator that allows for modulating the fdr of each null hypothesis based on external covariates. If fdr depends on levels of a measured covariate, then the exchangeability assumption implicit in the definition of fdr is not optimal, and sizeable gains in power can be realized by accounting for this dependence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Efron, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Sun et al., 2006</ref>). The key technique to account for the dependence of fdr on the covariate x in the approach of<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ferkingstad et al. (2008)</ref>was to bin the data into B sets according to ordered values of x. The assumption was that the influence of x on the posterior probability is nearly constant in each bin if bins are small enough (in practice, B ¼ 10 to 20). The fdr is then estimated in each bin, possibly with smoothing across the bins. This approach works best for one covariate and becomes impractical as the number of covariates increases. It has been applied to large-scale testing of neuroimaging data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Lawyer et al., 2009</ref>). In prior work, we have developed a scheme to assign gene element–based functional annotations for SNPs genome-wide, which takes into account the locus–locus correlations [linkage disequilibrium (LD)] that GWAS depend on for whole genome coverage (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Schork et al., 2013</ref>). This LD-weighted annotation scheme provides multiple scores for each SNP in several genic categories, including exon, intron, 5 0 untranslated regions (5 0 UTR) and 3 0 untranslated region (3 0 UTR). Scores incorporate not only the category of a given variant but also the categories of all variants for which it is in LD (correlated with). Intergenic SNPs are defined as having zero scores in all functional categories and being 4100 kb away from a protein-coding gene, providing a hypothesized 'null' collection. Using these functional annotations and summary statistics from 14 large GWAS, we showed that test statistics resulting from SNPs that are in LD with the 5 0 UTR of genes show the largest abundance of associations, while SNPs in LD with exons and the 3 0 UTR are also enriched. SNPs in LD with introns are modestly enriched and intergenic SNPs show a depletion of associations, relative to the average SNP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Schork et al., 2013</ref>). A more detailed description of how the LD-weighted genic annotations were produced is given in the Supplementary Materials. This situation is illustrated in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>, which displays Q–Q plots of À log 10 transformed P-values from a GWAS of Crohn's Disease (CD) of 51 109 subjects, obtained through a publicly accessible database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Franke et al., 2010</ref>). Enrichment for true associations is expressed as a leftward deflection of the Q–Q plots stratified by genic category, representing an overabundance of low P-values compared with that expected under the global null hypothesis of no associations. Leftward deflections are directly related to decreased fdr for a given P-value threshold. The 5 0 UTR SNPs are most enriched, followed by exons, 3 0 UTR and introns. Intergenic SNPs are impoverished for true effects. These results were consistent across all assessed phenotypes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Schork et al., 2013</ref>) and strongly suggest that all SNPs should not be treated as a priori exchangeable for purposes of hypothesis testing but that certain categories are much more likely to show an association. The current article leverages the information available in genic annotation categories for large-scale GWAS hypothesis testingby presenting a novel, fully Bayesian approach for generalized covariate-modulated local false discovery rate (cmfdr) estimation, implemented using a Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) sampling algorithm. Through this approach, we are able to model the influence of a vector of covariates on the distribution of the test statistics and hence on the fdr. Section 2 gives a brief review of fdr (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Efron and Tibshirani, 2002</ref>) and introduces cmfdr, constructed from a Bayesian two-group mixture model that incorporates covariates. Section 3 presents the MCMC algorithm for fitting the model and drawing inferences and applies cmfdr to examples involving both simulated and real data. The last section is devoted to a discussion of results and future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Review of fdr</head><p>Efron and Tibshirani (2002) made the assumption that the test statistic z i , 1 i n, has a different distribution based on whether the null hypothesis H 0, i is true or false, where n is the total number of tests (SNPs). The non-null distribution will tend to have more extreme values of the test statistic. Hence, z i follows a two-group mixture model</p><formula>fðz i Þ ¼ 0 f 0 ðz i Þ þ 1 f 1 ðz i Þ, ð1Þ</formula><p>where 0 is the proportion of true null hypotheses, 1 ¼ 1 À 0 is the proportion of true non-null hypotheses, f 0 is the probability density function if H 0 is true and f 1 is the probability density function if H 0 is false. Local false discovery rate (fdr) is the posterior probability that the i th test is null given z i , which by Bayes rule is given by</p><formula>fdrðz i Þ ¼ 0 f 0 ðz i Þ fðz i Þ ¼ 0 f 0 ðz i Þ 0 f 0 ðz i Þ þ 1 f 1 ðz i Þ : ð2Þ</formula><p>The null density was assumed to be standard normal (theoretical null) or normal with mean and variance estimated from the data (empirical null). The mixture density 0 f 0 ðzÞ þ 1 f 1 ðzÞ was estimated by fitting a high-degree polynomial to histogram counts (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Efron, 2010</ref>). If a set of SNPs are selected with an estimated fdr for some 2 ð0, 1Þ, then we expect that on average ð1 À Þ Â 100% of these will be true non-null SNPs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Covariate-modulated fdr</head><p>A set of external covariates observed for each hypothesis test may influence the distribution of the test statistic (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Efron, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Sun et al., 2006</ref>). Under this scenario, incorporating the covariate effects into fdr estimation can dramatically increase power for gene discovery. For example, the distribution of GWAS z-scores may depend on SNP-level functional annotations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Schork et al., 2013</ref>), pleiotropic relationships with related phenotypes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Andreassen et al., 2013a</ref>, b), gene expression levels in certain tissues, evolutionary conservation scores and so forth. These external covariates can be used to break the exchangeability assumption implicit in Equation (1) and potentially increase the power for gene discovery over using standard fdr given in Equation (2). Let x i ¼ ð1, x 1i , x 2i , :::, x mi Þ T , where x i denotes an ðm þ 1Þ-dimensional vector of covariates (including intercept) for the i th SNP. The cmfdr is defined as</p><formula>cmfdrðz i Þ ¼ 0ðxiÞf0ðziÞ fðzijxiÞ ¼ 0ðxiÞf0ðziÞ 0ðxiÞf0ðziÞþ1ðxiÞf1ðzijxiÞ ð3Þ</formula><p>where 1 ðx i Þ ¼ 1 À 0 ðx i Þ is the prior probability that the i th test is nonnull given x i and f 1 ðz i jx i Þ is the non-null density of z i given x i. By Bayes' rule, cmfdr is the posterior probability that the i th test is null given both z i and x i. We assume that the density under the null hypothesis does not depend on covariates. Both the probability of null status and the non-null density are allowed to depend on covariates, as described below. Central to the estimation of the null proportion is the assumption that 0 is large (say40.90) and that the vast majority of SNPs with test statistics close to 0 are in fact null. These assumptions are reasonable for GWA data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Hon-Cheong et al., 2010</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A Bayesian Two-group model</head><p>Summary statistics from GWAS are often made publicly available only as 2-tailed P-values, and hence, the magnitude of the z score is recoverable but not the sign. Moreover, the sign of the z score is a result of arbitrary allele coding. Hence, we formulate the mixture model for the absolute z-scores. The extension of our method to signed z-scores is straightforward.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Folded normal-gamma mixture model The distribution of z under</head><p>H 0 is assumed to have the folded normal distribution, with null density f 0 ðzÞ ¼ 2 0 ðzÞI z!0 , where ðzÞ is the normal density with mean 0 and standard deviation 0 , and I z!0 is an indicator function that takes the value 1 when z ! 0 and 0 otherwise. The density of z under the alternative hypothesis H 1 is assumed to have a gamma distribution with shape parameter aðxÞ and rate parameter .<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>gives a graphic presentation of these distributions. We chose a parametric non-null density for computational efficiency in modeling the effects of covariates. Parametric estimates of the non-null density also potentially provide more power than non-parametric estimates. We chose the gamma density because of its flexible shape and ability to model right-skewed heavy-tailed distributions. Covariates x are allowed to modulate the shape parameter of the gamma distribution aðxÞ ¼ expfx T g where ¼ { 0 , 1 , 2 , :::, m } T is an unknown parameter vector. The rate parameter is an unknown scalar not depending on x. While it is possible to model the rate parameter as a function of x, we have found that this leads to poor model convergence in the sampling algorithm, perhaps because of the lack of identifiability with other model parameters.Additionally, we specify a location parameter 40 to bind the nonnull gamma densities away from zero. The 'zero assumption' of<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Efron (2007)</ref>states that the central peak of the z-scores consists primarily of null cases. Such an assumption is necessary to make the non-null distribution identifiable and for the MCMC sampling algorithm to converge. The assumption that the vast majority of SNPs with z-scores close to 0 are null is already commonly made in GWAS. Hence, we set the location parameter ¼ 0:68 in the gamma distribution, corresponding to the median of the null density f 0. All SNPs with absolute z-scores 50.68 are thus a priori considered null. We complete the mixture model formulation by positing a latent indicator vector ¼ ð 1 ,. .. , n Þ, where i ¼ 1 if the i th SNP is non-null and 0 otherwise. Then 1 ðx i Þ is the prior probability that i ¼ 1 given covariates x i. The dependence of 1 on x is modeled via a logistic regression</p><formula>1 ðx i Þ ¼ Prð i ¼ 1jx i Þ ¼ expðx T i Þ 1 þ expðx T i Þ , where ¼ f 0 , 1 , 2</formula><p>, :::, m g T is a vector of unknown parameters. The augmented likelihood function is then given by</p><formula>Lð, , , 2 0 j, z, XÞ ¼ Y n i¼1 f 0 ðz i j 2 0 Þ 0 ðx i j&#x0D;Þ Â Ã 1Ài Â f 1 ðz i j, Þ 1 ðx i j&#x0D;Þ ½  i Á , ð4Þ</formula><p>where z ¼ ðz 1 ,. .. , z n Þ T is the vector of test statistics and X is the n Â ðm þ 1Þ design matrix. Integrating out the latent indicators gives the mixture model corresponding to Equation (3).</p><p>Prior distributions We apply weakly informative priors to unknown</p><formula>parameters f, , , 2 0 g: $ Nð0, AE Þ, $ Nð0, AE Þ,</formula><formula>$ Gammaða 0 , b 0 Þ, 2 0 $ InverseGammaða 0 , b 0 Þ, ð5Þ</formula><p>where AE and AE have large values on the diagonal, a 0 and b 0 are shape and rate parameters of gamma distribution and a 0 and b 0 are shape and scale parameters of inverse gamma distribution, respectively. Hyperparameters are fixed by the user. In the applications below, we set the dispersion matrices AE and AE to be diagonal with variance 10 000; ða 0 , b 0 Þ and ða 0 , b 0 Þ were both set to (0.001,0.001). Sampling scheme We sample the parameters , , and 2 0 in turn from their full conditional distributions via a Gibbs sampler using Metroplis–Hastings (M-H) steps. Combining (4) and (5), the full conditional distributions are given as follows:where I ð¼0Þ is an indicator function, and fðÁj. . .Þ denotes the probability density of a parameter conditional on all other parameters and the data. The full conditional posteriors for and in (6) do not take standard forms and are sampled using a multiple-try M-H sampler (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Givens and Hoeting, 2005</ref>) with a multivariate t-distribution candidate. The full conditional for has a gamma distribution and for 2 0 an inverse gamma distribution, so that both can be sampled directly. Each iteration of the Gibbs sampler also includes generation of , with a Bernoulli full conditional distribution. For k 2 f0, 1g pð i ¼ kj. . .Þ / f 0 ðz i j 2 0 Þ 1Àk f 1 ðz i jaðx i Þ, Þ k expðx T i Þ k 1 þ expðx T i Þ :</p><formula>fðj. . .Þ / Y i:i¼1 jz i À j aðxiÞ À aðx i Þ ð Þ aðxiÞ " # expfÀ T AE À1 2 g fð&#x0D;j. . .Þ / Y n i¼1 expfx T g i 1 þ expfx T g " # exp À T AE À1 2 ( ) ð6Þ fðj. . .Þ / a0À1þ P i: i ¼1 aðxiÞ Â exp À b 0 þ X i:i¼1 jz i À j ! ( ) : fð 2 0 j. . .Þ / ð 2 0 Þ À P n i¼1 I ð i ¼0Þ 2 þa 0 þ1 0 @ 1 A 2</formula><p>We can obtain an a posteriori estimate of cmfdr(z i ) for each z i as follows. Assume we have L draws fð ðlÞ , ðlÞ , ðlÞ , 2ðlÞ 0 Þ : 1 l Lg from the posterior distribution of the parameters. For each draw l, cmfdr ðlÞ ðz i Þ ¼ 0 ðx i j ðlÞ Þf 0 ðz i j 2ðlÞ 0 Þ 0 ðx i j ðlÞ Þf 0 ðz i j 2ðlÞ 0 Þ þ 1 ðx i j ðlÞ Þf 1 ðz i j ðlÞ , aðx i j ðlÞ ÞÞ :</p><p>Then, for example, the posterior median of cmfdr(z i ) can be estimated by taking the median of cmfdr ðlÞ ðz i Þ across all L posterior draws. The algorithm has been implemented in the R statistical package and is available at https://sites.google.com/site/covmodfdr/.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simulation</head><p>We simulated phenotypes under different settings of generative parameters from real genotype data available for n ¼ 3719 healthy individuals. For each permutation of simulation settings, we generated 100 unique phenotypes. We restricted our simulations to chromosome 1 (N ¼ 191 128 SNPs) for computational efficiency, assuming it was representative of the whole genome. These simulations allow us to evaluate the performance of our method in scenarios that approximate realistic GWAS conditions, including correlated SNPs according to true LD patterns. A detailed description of the simulations and an expanded table including comparisons with the methods of Efron (2007) and<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Lewinger et al. (2007)</ref>are given in the Supplementary Materials.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>displays the median number of SNPs rejected and the false discovery proportion (FDP), or the proportion of rejected SNPs not in LD with a causal SNP. The cmfdr performs reasonably well across enrichment settings for more highly polygenic phenotypes, rejected SNPs conservatively for 1 ¼ 0:05, but becoming progressively worse at controlling the FDP for phenotypes with low 1. The fdr of Efron (2007) controls the FDP at similar levels but also has less power than cmfdr (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S5</ref>). The 2 mixture model of<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Lewinger et al. (2007)</ref>rejects more SNPs than either fdr or cmfdr, but also exhibits considerably higher FDP across the range of polygenicity levels. In particular, their model is unstable for null GWAS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Real data application</head><p>The data consist of n ¼ 942 772 SNP summary test statistics (SNP z-scores) from a GWAS meta-analysis of eight substudies of CD on n ¼ 21 389 subjects (6333 cases), obtained through a publicly accessible database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Franke et al., 2010</ref>). CD is a type of inflammatory bowel disease that is caused by multiple factors in genetically susceptible individuals. For this example, we selected the five SNP annotations from<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Schork et al. (2013)</ref>displayed in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>to serve as covariates: intron, exon, 3 0 UTR, 5 0 UTR and intergenic; all annotation scores with the exception of Intergenic were first log transformed. These were entered together into the covariate-modulated mixture model, with the empirical null setting. The MCMC algorithm was run for 25 000 iterations with 20 000 retained draws. Plots of posterior draws showed convergence to stable posterior distributions for all parameters.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>shows the histogram of z-scores (all cases), the null subdensity 0 f 0 and the posterior median fit of the mixture density. The estimated overall non-null proportion 1 is 0.014. The fdr for each z-score is given by the height of the null subdensity at that score divided by the height of the mixture density. The parameter estimates are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. The 3 0 UTR and 5 0 UTR categories are associated with higher values of the shape parameter (and hence higher variance). Intron, exon, 3 0 UTR and 5 0 UTR are all associated with higher probability of non-null status. In contrast, intergenic SNPs are associated with higher values of the shape parameter and much lower probability of non-null status (0.001 non-null proportion for intergenic SNPs compared with the overall 1 ¼ 0:014). The positive ^ coefficient for intergenic SNPs is a reflection of this sparsity because intergenic SNPs require more extreme z-scores than genic SNPs to obtain a high-posterior probability of being non-null.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>compares the number of non-null SNPs rejected using usual fdr (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Efron, 2007</ref>), and cmfdr with the five annotation categories. cmfdr rejected far more SNPs than fdr (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Efron, 2007</ref>). For example, for a 0.05 cutoff, cmfdr rejects 3194 SNPs, whereas fdr rejects only 592, a factor of 5.4 times as many rejected SNPs. These 3194 SNPS consisted of 108 independent loci (leading SNP cmfdr 0:05 and 41 Mb apart from each other). Of these 108 independent loci, 66 had been previously described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Franke et al. (2010</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">). Franke et al. (2010</ref>described an additional five loci that were not discovered using a 0.05 cutoff; however, in our analysis, each of these loci had a cmfdr 50:06. We found 42 novel loci where the leading SNP had a cmfdr 0:05. Reporting these findings as discoveries in accordance with the best practices in GWAS would require replication in an independent sample and a detailed characterization of their biological significance,Rate parameter ( ^ ) 1.50<ref type="bibr">[1.48,1.53]</ref>Note: All estimates are presented in the form of median<ref type="bibr">[</ref>both of which are beyond the scope of this article. However, to demonstrate that our proposed method identifies plausible candidate SNPs that might warrant this further investigation, we undertook a pleiotropy analysis. Given that CD is known to share etiology, including pleiotropic genetic factors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Cho and Brant, 2011</ref>) with ulcerative colitis, it is likely that causal SNPs would show joint associations. We found significant enrichment for nominal associations (p50:05) with ulcerative colitis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Anderson et al., 2011</ref>) for both the 71 previously discovered loci (Bonferroni adjusted hypergeometric PÀvalue ¼ 1:33 Â 10 À36 ) and the 42 novel loci (Bonferroni adjusted hypergeometric PÀvalue ¼ 6:24 Â 10 À5 ). A complete list of previously discovered and novel gene names is given in the Supplementary Materials. We performed further analyses on CD substudies to determine whether this observed increase in the number of loci declared significant translates to increased number of replicating SNPs in de novo samples. The CD meta-analysis was composed of summary statistics from eight substudies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Franke et al., 2010</ref>). We computed z-scores from each of the 70 possible combinations of four substudies, leaving the z-scores computed from the remaining four independent substudies as test samples. We then estimated fdr and cmfdr for each training sample. For a given fdr cutoff, we determined the number of SNPs that replicated in the test sample. Replication was defined as one-sided P 0:05 and with the same sign as the corresponding z score in the training sample. Number of replicated SNPs was much higher using cmfdr compared with fdr. For example, for usual fdr there was an average of 365 replicated SNPs (94.6% of SNPs declared significant) with an fdr cutoff of 0.05 in the training sample. In contrast, with the same cutoff using cmfdr, there was an average of 2956 SNPs (92.5% of declared significant SNPs) that replicated according to this definition, or almost 8.1 times as many<ref type="bibr">SNPs.</ref>Similar increases in the number of replicated SNPs was observed for other cutoffs in the range. The larger number of SNPs declared significant for cmfdr compared with usual fdr largely remained when matched with empirical replication rates rather than nominal fdr threshold. For example, there was an average of 339 SNPs declared significant using usual fdr with an empirical replication rate of 0.95, compared with 2769 using cmfdr, or 8.2 times as many SNPs. In general, and in contrast to some of the simulation settings, replication rates were close to nominal for both usual fdr and cmfdr, across a range of cutoffs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>Methods for large-scale hypothesis testing that control Type I error rates without being overly conservative are crucial in GWAS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Efron, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Franke et al., 2010</ref>). It has become increasingly evident that many complex phenotypes and diseases have many genetic determinants, each with small effect (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Yang et al., 2010</ref>). Hence, traditional FWER correction is too conservative and severely underpowered. FDR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995</ref>) and fdr (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Efron and Tibshirani, 2002</ref>) have come to be accepted broadly as routine techniques to control for the rate of false positive in large-scale hypothesis testing settings in a number of fields. However, even these methods do not account for the vast majority of phenotypic variance explained by common variants (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Andreassen et al., 2013b</ref>). A problem with these and other multiple testing methods is that all SNPs are treated as exchangeable. In particular, each SNP is given the same a priori probability of being non-null. On the contrary, we (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Schork et al., 2013</ref>) and others (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Hindorff et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Smith et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Yang et al., 2011</ref>) have shown that the functional role of SNPs has a strong impact on the probability of association across a broad array of complex phenotypes and diseases. This work proposes a novel Bayesian approach (cmfdr) to incorporate a set of important covariates into the fdr under a heteroscedastic model, where the probability of non-null status and the distribution of the test statistic under the non-null hypothesis are both modulated by covariates. The primary advantage of our methodology over traditional fdr methods is that two SNPs with the same z score can have different values of cmfdr if one is in a more enriched category than the other. Hence, by using SNP annotations to modulate fdr, more SNPs can be discovered for a given level of fdr control. In other words, methods such as cmfdr that break the exchangeability assumption are potentially more powerful than traditional fdr methods that assume exchangeability. In the CD example, we discovered 5.4 times as many SNPs (unpruned) using cmfdr compared with usual fdr for an identical 0.05 cutoff. The increase in number of replicated SNPs in de novo subsamples from fdr to cmfdr was even more dramatic. Parameter estimates of covariates can also be biologically informative about the relative functionality of different biological classifications of variants. It is crucial to note that our LD-weighted SNP annotations were computed independently of the phenotypes investigated. Thus, modifying the fdr based on information from genic categories does not bias results toward rejecting more null hypotheses. Moreover, the cmfdr methodology is capable of handling any relevant source of information, including, for example,The proposed methodology has some drawbacks. First, as currently formulated, it assumes all hypothesis tests are independent. This is not true for SNPs in LD, and our 95% credible intervals are probably too small. Moreover, it remains unclear what impact LD has on FDP control because it may be the case that all or almost all 'tag SNPs' are in partial LD with causal SNPs but are not themselves causal. Correlation across SNPs can be handled, for example, by repeatedly and randomly pruning SNPs for independence before running the MCMC algorithm, by using a discrete Markov random field formulation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Li et al., 2010</ref>) or by modeling SNPs simultaneously using, for example, a multivariate mixed-effects model framework (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Carbonetto and Stephens, 2013</ref>). We have implemented a random pruning option available with the R code distribution. Second, it may be the case for some applications that the gamma distribution does not fit the tail probabilities of the non-null distribution well. We have used other distributions (e.g. the skewed generalized normal) and are currently developing a non-parametric alternative that produces flexible fits to tail probabilities. Although non-parametric estimates of the non-null density avoid bias from lack of model fit, parametric alternatives can be more powerful if the fit is adequate. Finally, it appears from simulations that the cmfdr methodology can be overly liberal in scenarios where 1 is close to 0. Care must therefore be taken when applying cmfdr in these circumstances.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Q–Q plot of enrichment by functional annotation category for CD. The x-axis displays Àlog 10 transformed empirical P-values, and the y-axis the-log 10 transformed nominal P-values</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Null and non-null distibutions. Mixture model Equation (1) consists of weighted mixture of folded normal (dotted line) and gamma densities (solid line)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Histogram of CD absolute z-scores. Solid line gives estimated null subdensity 0 ðxÞf 0 ðzÞ, where x was set to the sample mean. Dashed line gives estimated overall mixture model fðzÞ ¼ 0 ðxÞf 0 ðzÞ þ 1 ðxÞf 1 ðzjðxÞÞ. The fdr for each z score is given by the height of the null subdensity at that score, divided by the height of the mixture density. Local FDR 0:05 for z-scores 44.05 (vertical bar)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><figDesc>95% credible interval].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Power of fdr versus cmfdr. The x-axis is the cutoff to declare SNPs significant; the y-axis is number of rejected SNPs times 1-nominal fdr. The solid line indicates the number of SNPs rejected for usual fdr (Efron, 2007) using empirical null. The dashed line indicates the number of SNPs rejected using cmfdr with empirical null. SNPs not pruned for LD</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2.</figDesc><table>Parameter estimates with 95% posterior credible intervals from 
CD GWAS 

Parameters 
^ 

^ 


Intercept 
0.33 [0.45,0.57] 
À4.58 [À4.81,À4.35] 
Intron 
À0.04 [À0.01,0.01] 
0.22 [0.17,0.27] 
Exon 
À0.13 [À0.16,À0.10] 
0.82 [0.76,0.89] 
3 0 UTR 
0.05 [0.02,0.08] 
0.27 [0.21,0.34] 
5 0 UTR 
0.23 [0.17,0.28] 
0.40 [0.31,0.50] 
Intergenic 
0.77 [0.56,0.98] 
À2.4 [À2.83,À1.97] 
</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">cmfdr at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">R.W.Zablocki et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">R.W.Zablocki et al.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank Dr Verena Zuber for her comments. The authors would also like to thank the anonymous reviewers for their valuable suggestions.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meta-analysis identifies 29 additional ulcerative colitis risk loci, increasing the number of confirmed associations to 47</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Anderson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="246" to="252" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved detection of common variants associated with schizophrenia by leveraging pleiotropy with cardiovascular disease risk factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Andreassen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved detection of common variants associated with schizophrenia and bipolar disorder using pleiotropy-informed conditional False Discovery Rate method</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Andreassen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003455</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Benjamini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Hochberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical analysis of a telephone call center: a queueingscience perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Brown</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrated enrichment analysis of variants and pathways in genome-wide association studies indicates central role for IL-2 signaling genes in type 1 diabetes, and cytokine signaling genes in Crohn&apos;s Disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Carbonetto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Stephens</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent insights into the genetics of inflammatory bowel disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Cho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Brant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastroenterology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1704" to="1712" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Has the revolution arrived?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Collins</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">464</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="674" to="675" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic control for association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Devlin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Roeder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="997" to="1004" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Size, power and false discovery rates</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Efron</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1351" to="1377" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Large-Scale Inference: Empirical Bayes Methods for Estimation, Testing, and Prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Efron</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empirical bayes methods and false discovery rates for microarrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Efron</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Tibshirani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated encyclopedia of DNA elements in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Encode</forename>
				<surname>The</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Consortium</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">489</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unsupervised empirical bayesian multiple testing with external covariates</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Ferkingstad</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Appl. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="714" to="735" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide meta-analysis increases to 71 the number of confirmed Crohn&apos;s disease susceptibility loci</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Franke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1118" to="1125" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thresholding of statistical maps in functional neuroimaging using the false discovery rate</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Genovese</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="870" to="878" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Givens</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Hoeting</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computational Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>WileyInterscience Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">483</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>WileyInterscience Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Potential etiologic and functional implications of genome-wide association loci for human diseases and traits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Hindorff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9362" to="9367" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the total number of susceptibility variants underlying complex diseases from genome-wide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Hon-Cheong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13898</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Local and covariate-modulated false discovery rates applied in neuroimaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Lawyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hierarchical Bayes prioritization of marker associations from a genome-wide association scan for further investigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Lewinger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="871" to="883" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A hidden Markov random field model for genome-wide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding the missing heritability of complex diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Manolio</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">461</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="747" to="753" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controlling the false discovery rate in astrophysical data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Miller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3492" to="3505" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multidimensional local false discovery rate for microarray studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ploner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="556" to="565" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The future of genetic studies of complex human diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Risch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Merikangas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">255</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1516" to="1517" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic architecture of the missing heritability for complex human traits and diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Schork</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003449</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide association of bipolar disorder suggests an enrichment of replicable associations in regions near genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002134</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stratified false discovery control for large-scale hypothesis testing with application to genome-wide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Sun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="519" to="530" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Annotating individual human genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Torkamani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="241" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Significance analyses of microarrays applied to the ionizing radiation response</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Tusher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5116" to="5121" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Common SNPs explain a large proportion of the heritability for human height</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="565" to="569" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome partitioning of genetic variation for complex traits using common SNPs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="519" to="525" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>