
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:47+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">CRISPR-ERA: a comprehensive design tool for CRISPR-mediated gene editing, repression and activation</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Honglei</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Bioinformatics Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Synthetic and Systems Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">TNLIST/Department of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tsinghua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100084</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Stanford Chemistry, Engineering &amp; Medicine for Human Health (ChEM-H)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zheng</forename>
								<surname>Wei</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Bioinformatics Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Synthetic and Systems Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">TNLIST/Department of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tsinghua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100084</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Antonia</forename>
								<surname>Dominguez</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioengineering</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yanda</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Bioinformatics Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Synthetic and Systems Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">TNLIST/Department of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tsinghua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100084</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xiaowo</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Bioinformatics Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Synthetic and Systems Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">TNLIST/Department of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tsinghua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100084</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lei</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Qi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Stanford Chemistry, Engineering &amp; Medicine for Human Health (ChEM-H)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioengineering</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemical and Systems Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>443 Via Ortega, Shriram Center 376</addrLine>
									<postCode>94305-4125</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">CRISPR-ERA: a comprehensive design tool for CRISPR-mediated gene editing, repression and activation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv423</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 13, 2015; revised on July 3, 2015; accepted on July 16, 2015</note>
					<note>Genome analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: John Hancock Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The CRISPR/Cas9 system was recently developed as a powerful and flexible technology for targeted genome engineering, including genome editing (altering the genetic sequence) and gene regulation (without altering the genetic sequence). These applications require the design of single guide RNAs (sgRNAs) that are efficient and specific. However, this remains challenging, as it requires the consideration of many criteria. Several sgRNA design tools have been developed for gene editing, but currently there is no tool for the design of sgRNAs for gene regulation. With accumulating experimental data on the use of CRISPR/Cas9 for gene editing and regulation, we implement a comprehensive computational tool based on a set of sgRNA design rules summarized from these published reports. We report a genome-wide sgRNA design tool and provide an online web-site for predicting sgRNAs that are efficient and specific. We name the tool CRISPR-ERA, for clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeat-mediated editing, repression, and activation (ERA). Availability and implementation: http://CRISPR-ERA</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The bacterial adaptive immune system, CRISPR (clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats), was recently developed as a powerful and multi-purpose technology for genome engineering, including editing (modifying the genomic sequence) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cong et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Mali et al., 2013</ref>), and regulation (repressing or activating expression of genes) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Gilbert et al., 2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Gilbert et al., , 2014</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Qi et al., 2013</ref>). The system is highly programmable, utilizing a single protein, the nuclease Cas9 for editing or the nuclease-deficient dCas9 for regulation. A single guide RNA (sgRNA) is required for precise and programmable DNA targeting (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Doudna and Charpentier, 2014</ref>). Effective and specific genome engineering requires careful design of sgRNAs, which remains a major challenge. Computational tools have been used to facilitate the design of sgRNAs for CRISPR editing but not for other applications such as transcriptional regulation. These computational tools should enable automated sgRNA design and offtarget site validation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bae et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Doench et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Heigwer et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">O'Brien and Bailey, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Xiao et al., 2014</ref>). A major goal of our designer tool is to address the discrepancy for designing sgRNAs that allow efficient and highly specific repression or activation of genes and for generating genome-wide sgRNA libraries for genetic screening in different organisms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3676</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.comHere, we describe CRISPR-ERA webserver, an automated and comprehensive sgRNA design tool for CRISPR-mediated editing, repression, and activation (ERA) (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). CRISPR-ERA utilizes a fast algorithm to search for genome-wide sgRNA binding sites and evaluates their efficiency and specificity using a set of rules summarized from published data for CRISPR editing, repression and activation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cong et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Doudna and Charpentier, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Gilbert et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Qi et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ran et al., 2013</ref>). The design features are annotated and the target sites can be visualized in a genome browser. We also provide a local version for the generation of whole-genome sgRNA libraries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>For each target gene or genomic site, CRISPR-ERA first searches all targetable sites in that particular organism for patterns of N 20 NGG (N ¼ any nucleotide). Each target sequence is then calculated for two scores (Supplementary Methods): (i) an efficacy score (E-score) based on the sequence features such as GC content (%GC), presence of poly-thymidine (which is a terminator for effective transcription of sgRNAs), and location information such as the distance from target gene transcriptional start sites (TSS); and (ii) a specificity score (S-score) based on the genome-wide off-target binding sites. For each sgRNA design, we compute the genomewide sequences that contain an adjacent NRG (R ¼ A or G) protospacer adjacent motif (PAM) site and zero, one, two, or three mismatches complementary to the sgRNA using Bowtie (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Langmead et al., 2009</ref>), which are regarded as off-target binding sites. The penalty score for NAG off-target is smaller than NGG off-target. The sgRNAs are finally ranked by the sum of E-score and S-score (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>; Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>). We implement a user-friendly web server (http://CRISPR-ERA. stanford.edu) that hosts the web application for the sgRNA designer tool. The webserver will host a broad category of sequenced organisms. Currently, it provides sgRNA design service for nine most commonly used prokaryotic and eukaryotic organisms including Escherichia coli, Bacillus subtilis, Saccharomyces cerevisiae, Drosophila melanogaster, Caenorhabditis elegans, Danio rerio, Rattus norvegicus, Mus musculus, and Homo sapiens, etc. (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>.). The web application enables rapid searching in the pre-assembled sgRNA database using an indexing searching approach (Supplementary Methods). The program outputs the sequence, target location, off-target details of the possible sgRNAs, their E-and S-scores etc. Results can be visualized using the UCSC genome browser to highlight the custom tracks (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2 and S3</ref>).<ref type="figure">1</ref>. CRISPR-ERA workflow and example. The CRISPR-ERA algorithm takes input information, including types of genome manipulation, organism, and gene name or genome location, and then computes and evaluates sgRNAs within the targeted genome region. By default, for editing, the algorithm chooses sgRNA sequences within coding region; for repression, the algorithm computes sgRNA binding sites within a 3 kb region centered at TSS (or the sense strand of the 5 0 end of the gene for bacteria only); for activation, the algorithm computes sgRNA binding sites up to 1.5 kb upstream of TSS. In this figure, mouse gene Sox2 is shown as an example. E, efficacy score; S, specificity penalty score (Supplementary Methods)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Conclusions</head><p>CRISPR-ERA enables easy, fast, and predictive design of sgRNAs for broad applications of CRISPR in genome editing, gene repression and activation. The tool can be applied to other types of CRISPR applications such as genome imaging (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Chen et al., 2013</ref>) and CRISPR synthetic circuit design (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Kiani et al., 2014</ref>), and expanded to other organisms. We also provide the source code for the generation of whole-genome sgRNA libraries, useful for genomewide screening based on CRISPR, CRISPRi or CRISPRa (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Gilbert et al., 2014</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">, Shalem et al., 2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Wang et al., 2013</ref>).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Bioinformatics, 31(22), 2015, 3676–3678doi:10.</head><figDesc>1093/bioinformatics/btv423 Advance Access Publication Date: 23 July 2015 Applications Note</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. CRISPR-ERA workflow and example. The CRISPR-ERA algorithm takes input information, including types of genome manipulation, organism, and gene name or genome location, and then computes and evaluates sgRNAs within the targeted genome region. By default, for editing, the algorithm chooses sgRNA sequences within coding region; for repression, the algorithm computes sgRNA binding sites within a 3 kb region centered at TSS (or the sense strand of the 5 0 end of the gene for bacteria only); for activation, the algorithm computes sgRNA binding sites up to 1.5 kb upstream of TSS. In this figure, mouse gene Sox2 is shown as an example. E, efficacy score; S, specificity penalty score (Supplementary Methods)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Funding</head><figDesc>L.S.Q. acknowledges support from NIH Office of The Director (OD), and National Institute of Dental &amp; Craniofacial Research (NIDCR). H.L., Z.W., Y.L. and X.W. are supported by the 973 program (2012CB316503), NSFC (grant number 61322310, 31371341) and FANEDD (grant number 201158). This work was also supported by NIH Director's Early Independence Award (grant number OD017887, L.S.Q.) and NIH R01 (grant number DA036858, L.S.Q.). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cas-OFFinder: a fast and versatile algorithm that searches for potential off-target sites of Cas9 RNA-guided endonucleases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Bae</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1473" to="1475" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic imaging of genomic loci in living human cells by an optimized CRISPR/Cas system</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1479" to="1491" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiplex genome engineering using CRISPR/Cas systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Cong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">339</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="819" to="823" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rational design of highly active sgRNAs for CRISPR-Cas9–mediated gene inactivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Doench</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1262" to="1267" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The new frontier of genome engineering with CRISPR-Cas9</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Doudna</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Charpentier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">346</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1258096" to="1258096" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CRISPR-mediated modular RNA-guided regulation of transcription in eukaryotes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Gilbert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="442" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-scale CRISPR-mediated control of gene repression and activation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Gilbert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="647" to="661" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">E-CRISP: fast CRISPR target site identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Heigwer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CRISPR transcriptional repression devices and layered circuits in mammalian cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kiani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="723" to="726" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Langmead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA-guided human genome Engineering via Cas9</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Mali</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">339</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="823" to="826" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GT-Scan: identifying unique genomic targets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>&apos;brien</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Bailey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2673" to="2675" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Repurposing CRISPR as an RNA-guided platform for sequence-specific control of gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Qi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1173" to="1183" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Double nicking by RNA-guided CRISPR Cas9 for enhanced genome editing specificity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Ran</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="479" to="480" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-scale CRISPR-Cas9 knockout screening in human cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Shalem</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">343</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic screens in human cells using the CRISPR-Cas9 system</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">343</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CasOT: a genome-wide Cas9/gRNA off-target searching tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Xiao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1180" to="1182" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>