
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:49+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis CytoCom: a Cytoscape app to visualize, query and analyse disease comorbidity networks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mohammad</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Ali</forename>
								<surname>Moni</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Computer Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cambridge</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of CSE</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Pabna University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Pabna</settlement>
									<country key="BD">Bangladesh</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Haoming</forename>
								<surname>Xu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Computer Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cambridge</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pietro</forename>
								<surname>Liò</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Computer Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cambridge</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis CytoCom: a Cytoscape app to visualize, query and analyse disease comorbidity networks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu731</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 7, 2014; revised on October 6, 2014; accepted on October 28, 2014</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>CytoCom is an interactive plugin for Cytoscape that can be used to search, explore, ana</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The term 'comorbidity' refers to the coexistence or presence of multiple diseases or disorders in relation to a primary disease or disorder in a patient (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Moni and Liò , 2014</ref>). A comorbidity relationship between two diseases exists whenever they appear simultaneously in a patient more than chance alone (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Hidalgo et al., 2009</ref>). It represents the co-occurrence of diseases or presence of different medical conditions one after another in the same patient (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Moni and Liò , 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Hidalgo et al., 2009</ref>). Two diseases are connected if they are coexpressed in a significant number of patients in a population (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Hidalgo et al., 2009</ref>). If two diseases have associated comorbidity, the occurrence of one of them in a patient may increase the likelihood of developing another disease.</p><p>The main challenge for research in the biomedical field is to understand the associations between human diseases. Clinical data contains many important clarifications regarding the occurrence of comorbidity in patients with two or more diseases. To measure a relationship based on disease co-occurrence, we need to quantify the strength of the comorbidity risk. We have adapted two comorbidity measures to quantify the strength of comorbidity associations between two diseases: (i) the Relative Risk-the probability that a number of patients will be diagnosed with both diseases relative to the probability that a number of patients will be similarly diagnosed according to random expectation based on disease prevalence, as the quantified measures of comorbidity tendency of two disease pairs; and (ii) /-correlation-Pearsons correlation for binary variables, to measure the robustness of the comorbidity association.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>969</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.comCytoscape is a widely used Java-based, open-source platform for network visualization and analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Shannon et al., 2003</ref>). The Cytoscape framework is extendable through the implementation of apps. We have developed a Cytoscape app, named CytoCom, that enables a user to visualize the disease–disease network. To the best of our knowledge, CytoCom is the first app to provide a user with the facility to query, analyse and visualize disease–disease dynamic network using clinical information. CytoCom can be started from the control panel in Cytoscape. The main panel is shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Overview</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Network data sources</head><p>Patient medical records offer reliable data on diseases. To achieve a comprehensive study, we identify the comorbidity correlations of diseases based on the clinical information from the US Medicare claims database, http://www.icd9data.com, and collected from<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Hidalgo et al. (2009)</ref>. Demographically, our dataset consists of the medical records of 13,039,018 patients in the ICD-9-CM format. International Classification of Diseases, Ninth Revision codes are 3–5 digits long and have hierarchical structures, with each 4-digit code being a subset of a 5-digit code, both of which also contain a further 3-digit code subset. In total, the ICD-9-CM includes 657 different categories at the 3-digit level. Each digit span for all diseases is then further classified based on gender and race.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Network construction</head><p>To understand the correlations between diseases, the disease–disease pair comorbidity correlations are visualized as a bipartite network graph. Two diseases are connected through an edge if they are associated. CytoCom constructs disease comorbidity network (DCN) in which nodes are diseases and edges indicate the comorbidity associations among them. CytoCom includes edges between disease pairs for which the co-occurrence is significantly greater than the random expectation based on the population prevalence of the diseases. For a pair of diseases i and j, we used two novel statistical measures to quantify the relationship between two diseases: Relative Risk (RR ij ) and /-correlation (/ ij ) based on the<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Hidalgo et al. (2009)</ref>. The two comorbidity measures are not completely independent each other. The RR ij allows us to quantify the co-occurrence of disease pairs compared with the random expectation and / ij allows us to measure the robustness of the comorbidity associations. Users can use integer or decimal numbers as input for both RR ij and / ij. When two diseases co-occur more frequently than expected by chance, we will get RR ij &gt; 1 and / ij &gt; 0. The significance of the RR ij is calculated using the Katz et al. method to estimate confidence intervals (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Katz et al. 1978</ref>). To explore a particular disease, user needs to enter the seed disease code in the search box; CytoCom makes use of Cytoscape to construct the network and create a network view of disease association. The user can filter network using different input parameters based on gender, race and ICD-9 codes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Network visualization</head><p>In the ICD-9 classification, diseases are assigned to different disease categories based on the first three digits of a given ICD-9 code. This classification is represented by a specific colouring of the nodes. The size of the nodes is visualized according to the prevalence of the diseases. More common diseases are represented as larger nodes. Additional associated diseases could be found by double clicking of a disease node of the existing network, which enables to access more association or comorbidity information of that disease. The additional diseases network is added to the existing network dynamically. Herein, the multi-colouring of disease nodes offers a convenient visualization of disease classifications in the networks. In addition, it offers a user-friendly means of conducting a visual exploration. CytoCom automatically creates a database table of mapping ICD-9 codes to disease names. It is also possible to export the</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Conclusion</head><p>Exploring the associations between diseases could greatly enhance our understanding of pathogenesis and eventually lead to better diagnosis and treatment. CytoCom is an easy-to-use app to analyse and investigate the human DCN. This app will help users to advance their knowledge on disease mechanism and disease comorbidities in a quantitative and graphical way. We plan regular updates to the CytoCom app as well as the integration of further data sources.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>V</head><figDesc>C The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Bioinformatics, 31(6), 2015, 969–971doi:10.</head><figDesc>1093/bioinformatics/btu731 Advance Access Publication Date: 7 November 2014 Applications Note</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Cytoscape screenshot of CytoCom. The centre of the screen shows an example of DCN, which is constructed based on clinical data. Each node represents a unique disease; the nodes are coloured according to their disease categories so that diseases of the same category have the same colour. Two nodes are considered to be linked if the diseases are significantly comorbid more than the randomly expected according to their specified RR and / values</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.A.Moni et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A dynamic network approach for the study of human phenotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Hidalgo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS computational biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000353</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Obtaining confidence intervals for the risk ratio in cohort studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Katz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="469" to="474" />
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">comoR: a software for disease comorbidity risk assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Moni</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Liò</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Clinical Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Shannon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2498" to="2504" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">CytoCom</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>