
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:43+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies DADP: the database of anuran defense peptides</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">10 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mario</forename>
								<surname>Novkoví</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Split</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21000</postCode>
									<settlement>Split</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Juraj</forename>
								<surname>Simuní</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Split</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21000</postCode>
									<settlement>Split</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Viktor</forename>
								<surname>Bojoví</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for Informatics and Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ru ¯ der Boškoví c Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10000</postCode>
									<settlement>Zagreb</settlement>
									<country key="HR">Croatia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alessandro</forename>
								<surname>Tossi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Trieste</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>34127</postCode>
									<settlement>Trieste</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Davor</forename>
								<surname>Juretí</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Split</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21000</postCode>
									<settlement>Split</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies DADP: the database of anuran defense peptides</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1406" to="1407"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">10 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts141</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on December 6, 2011; revised on March 2, 2012; accepted on March 20, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [15:31 7/5/2012 Bioinformatics-bts141.tex] Page: 1406 1406–1407 Associate Editor: Burkhard Rost Contact: juretic@pmfst.hr Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Anuran tissues, and especially skin, are a rich source of bioactive peptides and their precursors. We here present a manually curated database of antimicrobial and other defense peptides with a total of 2571 entries, most of them in the precursor form with demarcated signal peptide (SP), acidic proregion(s) and bioactive moiety(s) corresponding to 1923 non-identical bioactive sequences. Search functions on the corresponding web server facilitate the extraction of six distinct SP classes. The more conserved of these can be used for searching cDNA and UniProtKB databases for potential bioactive peptides, for creating PROSITE search patterns, and for phylogenetic analysis. Availability: DADP is accessible at http://split4.pmfst.hr/dadp/</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>With the growing problem of pathogens developing resistance to conventional antibiotics, there is a great interest in antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) as substitute therapeutics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Hancock and Sahl, 2006</ref>). There are several existing databases on many types of AMPs: APD (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Wang et al., 2009</ref>), CAMP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Thomas et al., 2010</ref>), PhytAMP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hammami et al., 2009</ref>), Defensins Knowledgebase (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Seebah et al., 2007</ref>), AMSDb (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Tossi and Sandri, 2002</ref>), BACTIBASE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hammami et al., 2007</ref>), AMPer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Fjell et al. 2007</ref>) and YADAMP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Piotto et al. 2012</ref>). However, these databases tend to focus on the antimicrobial sequences, and the immature precursors from which the active AMPs are cleaved are not always present. DADP is a versatile database for anuran defense peptides that retains all this important information. Some anuran species contain &gt;100 AMPs in their tissues, and especially their skin, as well as other bioactive peptides (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Li et al., 2007</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">, Yang et al., 2012</ref>), but many are endangered, while whole genomes have been decoded for only 2 out of almost 6000 species (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Roelants et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Calboli et al. 2011</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">DATA COLLECTION</head><p>The following query was used in UniProtKB (http://www. uniprot.org/,<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Apweiler et al., 2011</ref>) release 2012_02 (February 22, 2012): (keyword: " Amphibian defense peptide<ref type="bibr">[KW-0878]</ref>" OR * To whom correspondence should be addressed. keyword: " Antimicrobial<ref type="bibr">[KW-0929]</ref>" OR keyword: " Antibiotic<ref type="bibr">[KW-0044]</ref>" ) AND taxonomy: " Amphibia<ref type="bibr">[8292]</ref>" and 2492 results were obtained. All sequences denoted as fragments were omitted. For any region that was not annotated in UniProtKB, the sequence was manually curated and divided into specific regions (signal, acidic and bioactive) based on homology with annotated protein precursors coupled with SignalP prediction (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bendtsen et al., 2004</ref>). Several protein sequences not in accord with cited literature were omitted. The final version of the database contains 1766 full precursor sequences and 805 bioactive peptides with unknown precursor, encompassing a total of 167 anuran species from 12 families (Supplementary Tables S1 and S2). Biogeography data were collected using The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species (www.iucnredlist.org) and Amphibian Species of the World 5.5, American Museum of Natural History (http://research.amnh.org/vz/ herpetology/amphibia/index.php). Classification by biological function includes over 70 different activities, with AMPs being in the majority (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table  S3</ref>). Missing activities field denotes unknown function. Phylogenetic analysis and classification in six classes, based on signal peptide (SP) similarity (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>), was constructed using MEGA software version 5 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Tamura et al., 2007</ref>). Activity and cytotoxicity data were extracted from published papers where the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC, μM) based on microdilution assays was reported for Escherichia coli and/or Staphylococcus aureus. HC 50 refers to peptide concentration, also micromolar, required for 50% haemolysis of red blood cells. MIC data are available for 921 peptide sequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>DADP is hosted on a 64 bit Linux server using Apache (http://www.apache.org/) and PHP (http://www.php.net/). All entries are stored in a MySQL (http://www.mysql.com/) database. The application was written in PHP, using the jQuery JavaScript Library (http://jquery.com/) with the DataTables (http://datatables.net/) plug-in for the tables' implementation, and CSS for web design.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">WEB INTERFACE</head><p>The DADP web interface offers browsing capability for all peptide entries, for SPs and for SP classes in particular. An advanced search option is available for more specific user requests. Each DADP ID entry contains detailed information about peptide names and sequences, tripartite structure, species, SP class, biogeography,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">DISCUSSION</head><p>Bioactive peptides from amphibian species with function, often related to host defense, are a fast growing group in the UniProtKB database and this attempt to collect and order them all can mostly serve to emphasize the incompleteness of our knowledge. For instance, out of 167 species from the DADP, only 28 can be found among 2200 threatened and near threatened anuran species from the IUCN Red List. The DADP focuses on precursors and their conserved SPs and has allowed the individuation of six distinct SP classes (see Supplementary Material and Supplementary Tables S4 and S5). Consensus sequences for the different SP classes are a good foundation for searching protein or DNA databases that might carry precursors with novel AMP sequences, where a direct homology search based on the active region only is unsuccessful (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Jureti´cJureti´c et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Tessera et al., 2012</ref>). The most numerous class of SPs (present in 85% of precursors) has twin lysines at positions 5 and 6, and is denoted as Class-1 in DADP. It is found in Neobatrachia families Ranidae, Hylidae, Hyperoliidae and Rhacophoridae. SP classes 1–6 are associated not only with AMPs but also with mature bioactive peptides having other functions. Precursor structure is informative about origin, function and evolution of mature peptides collected in the DADP, but there are numerous peptides present only as the mature bioactive sequence, where the precursor structure is not reported. The activity data, shown as MIC and HC 50 values, are available for over 900 sequences. These should, however, be considered critically as both are quite sensitive to assay conditions, which vary from lab to lab [e.g. medium, salt concentrations and the size of initial inoculum, which should be at least 10 5 cfu/ml for MIC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Resende et al., 2008</ref>) and at most 1% erythrocytes for HC 50 determinations, limits often either not observed or not defined in published papers]. The conservation of SPs in different suborders and families of anurans, whose relatedness follows continental tectonics and corresponding changes in biogeography, is quite impressive (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>and the DADP web server). This is one of those rare examples when maintenance of the export SPs, which are dispensed with after secretion, is evolutionarily more conserved than the mature exported polypeptide structure. It may be beneficial for the host to have accelerated co-evolution of the mature defense peptide sequences, to keep up with the constantly shifting microbial biota, allowing to maintain the hostpathogen balance (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Peschel and Sahl, 2006</ref>). The number of identical SPs associated with different mature peptides found in different species can be quite large (e.g. 164 identical Class-1 SP sequences encompassing 36 species and associated with 141 different mature peptides). It is also possible to find identical mature peptides associated with SPs that are different in several positions. An example is the antimicrobial granulosusin-D2 and palustrin-2ISa, respectively, belonging to different species (Amolops granulosus from China and Rana ishikawae from Japan). Another is the bradykinin sequence RPPGFSPFR, which is associated with different SP sequences in 15 different species. These bioactive skin peptides from frogs and toads may be effective repellents against macroscopic predators such as fish (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chen et al., 2011</ref>) and snakes. These two cases are possible examples of convergent evolution of the active region to provide for similar functions. The DADP can greatly facilitate using the HMMER tool (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Finn et al., 2011</ref>) to search UniProtKB for amphibian AMPs. In this case the sequence length limitations of the tool require the combined use of the signal sequence and acidic propiece as the query. The DADP can be regularly updated using both keywords and similarity search.</p></div>
			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ongoing and future developments at the Universal Protein Resource</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Apweiler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="214" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved prediction of signal peptides: SignalP 3.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Bendtsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">340</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="783" to="795" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The need for jumpstarting amphibian genome projects</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Calboli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="378" to="379" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fish bradykinin (Arg 0 , Trp 5 , Leu 8-bradykinin) from the defensive skin secretion of the European edible frog, Pelophylax kl. esculentus: structural characterization; molecular cloning of skin kininogen cDNA and pharmacological effects on mammalian smooth muscle</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Peptides</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HMMER web server: interactive sequence similarity searching</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Finn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AMPer : a database and an automated discovery tool for antimicrobial peptides</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Fjell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1148" to="1155" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BACTIBASE: a new web-accessible database for bacteriocin characterization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Hammami</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">89</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PhytAMP: a database dedicated to antimicrobial plant peptides</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Hammami</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="963" to="968" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antimicrobial and host-defense peptides as new anti-infective therapeutic strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Hancock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Sahl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1551" to="1557" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge-based computational methods for identifying or designing novel, non-homologous antimicrobial peptides</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Jureti´cjureti´c</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="371" to="385" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anti-infection peptidomics of amphibian skin</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="882" to="894" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The co-evolution of host cationic antimicrobial peptides and microbial resistance</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Peschel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Sahl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="536" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">YADAMP: yet another database of antimicrobial peptides</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Piotto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="346" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solution NMR structures of the antimicrobial peptides phylloseptin-1,-2, and-3 and biological activity: the role of charges and hydrogen bonding interactions in stabilizing helix conformations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Resende</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Peptides</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1633" to="1644" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global patterns of diversification in the history of modern amphibians</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Roelants</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="887" to="892" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defensins knowledgebase: a manually curated database and information source focused on the defensins family of antimicrobial peptides</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Seebah</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Tamura</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1596" to="1599" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of antimicrobial peptides from teleosts and anurans in EST databases using conserved signal sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Tessera</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FESB J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="724" to="736" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CAMP: a useful resource for research on antimicrobial peptides</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Thomas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="774" to="780" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular diversity in gene-encoded, cationic antimicrobial polypeptides</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Tossi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Sandri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Pharm. Des</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="743" to="761" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">APD2: the updated antimicrobial peptide database and its application in peptide design</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="933" to="937" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extremely abundant antimicrobial peptides existed in the skins of nine kinds of Chinese odorous frogs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="306" to="319" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>