
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:59+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies DeOri: a database of eukaryotic DNA replication origins</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Feng</forename>
								<surname>Gao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tianjin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>300072</postCode>
									<settlement>Tianjin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hao</forename>
								<surname>Luo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tianjin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>300072</postCode>
									<settlement>Tianjin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chun-Ting</forename>
								<surname>Zhang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tianjin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>300072</postCode>
									<settlement>Tianjin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies DeOri: a database of eukaryotic DNA replication origins</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1551" to="1552"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts151</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on December 3, 2011; revised on March 18, 2012; accepted on March 24, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [09:04 7/5/2012 Bioinformatics-bts151.tex] Page: 1551 1551–1552 Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>DNA replication, a central event for cell proliferation, is the basis of biological inheritance. The identification of replication origins helps to reveal the mechanism of the regulation of DNA replication. However, only few eukaryotic replication origins were characterized not long ago; nevertheless, recent genome-wide approaches have boosted the number of mapped replication origins. To gain a comprehensive understanding of the nature of eukaryotic replication origins, we have constructed a Database of Eukaryotic ORIs (DeOri), which contains all the eukaryotic ones identified by genome-wide analyses currently available. A total of 16 145 eukaryotic replication origins have been collected from 6 eukaryotic organisms in which genome-wide studies have been performed, the replication-origin numbers being 433, 7489, 1543, 148, 348 and 6184 for humans, mice, Arabidopsis thaliana, Kluyveromyces lactis, Schizosaccharomyces pombe and Drosophila melanogaster, respectively. Availability: Database of Eukaryotic ORIs (DeOri) can be accessed from</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The initiation of replication is the central event in the cell cycle. In all three domains of life, DNA replication begins at specialized loci termed replication origins. In bacteria, replication initiates from a single replication origin, whereas eukaryotic organisms exploit many replication origins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Costas et al., 2011</ref>). In eukaryotes, the origins of DNA replication in the budding yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae and fission yeast Schizosaccharomyces pombe have been well-characterized (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hayashi et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Heichinger et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Nieduszynski et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Segurado et al., 2003</ref>). Recently, a high-resolution genome-wide map of DNA replication origins in Kluyveromyces lactis has also been generated (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Liachko et al., 2010</ref>). However, only few origins were characterized in the genomes of higher eukaryotes not long ago. Fortunately, recent development of genome-wide approaches has led to a boost in the number of replication origins that have been mapped in eukaryotic genomes, including those in human (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cadoret et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Karnani et al., 2010</ref>), mouse (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cayrou et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Sequeira-Mendes et al., 2009</ref>), Arabidopsis thaliana (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Costas et al., 2011</ref>) and Drosophila melanogaster (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cayrou et al., 2011</ref>). The availability of increasing origins throughout the genomes has created opportunities for analysis of the origins on a genome scale. Up to date, the DNA * To whom correspondence should be addressed. replication origin database for budding yeast (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Nieduszynski et al., 2007</ref>) has been built, whereas the database of other eukaryotic origins has not been available. In order to gain a comprehensive understanding of the nature of eukaryotic replication origins, we have constructed a Database of Eukaryotic ORIs (DeOri), which contains all the eukaryotic DNA replication origins identified by genome-wide analyses currently available.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DATA RETRIEVAL</head><p>The replication origins stored in DeOri include those identified in the genomes of human (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cadoret et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Karnani et al., 2010</ref>), mouse (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cayrou et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Sequeira-Mendes et al., 2009</ref>), A.thaliana (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Costas et al., 2011</ref>), D.melanogaster (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cayrou et al., 2011</ref>), K.lactis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Liachko et al., 2010</ref>) and S.pombe (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hayashi et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Heichinger et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Segurado et al., 2003</ref>). In the human genome, 283 replication origins have been systematically mapped using the HeLa S3 suspension cell line (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cadoret et al., 2008</ref>) and in an independent study, 150 new origins have been identified in adherent HeLa cells in the ENCODE area (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Karnani et al., 2010</ref>). In mouse, identification of preferential sites of DNA replication initiation in 0.4% of the mouse genome has resulted in 97 new ORIs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Sequeira-Mendes et al., 2009</ref>). By performing a genome-wide analysis in both Drosophila and mouse cell lines, up to 2748 ORIs on mouse Chromosome 11 (P19 cells) and 6184 ORIs in the Drosophila genome have been characterized (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cayrou et al., 2011</ref>). In A.thaliana, by high-throughput sequencing of newly synthesized DNA, ∼1500 putative have been identified at the genome-wide level (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Costas et al., 2011</ref>). In K.lactis, a total of 148 ARSs have been identified by a predict-and-verify approach (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Liachko et al., 2010</ref>). In the S.pombe genome, 385 ORIs have been predicted initially from AT content calculation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Segurado et al., 2003</ref>). Subsequent experiments have also confirmed most of the prediction (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hayashi et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Heichinger et al., 2006</ref>). In addition, the whole genome sequences of human (hg17), mouse (mm8, mm9), D.melanogaster (dm2) were downloaded from http://hgdownload.cse.ucsc.edu/downloads.html, and the whole genome sequences of A.thaliana, S.pombe and K.lactis were downloaded from the NCBI FTP server (ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/genomes/). Based on the position information provided in the literatures or by personal communication and the corresponding genome sequences, we have obtained the sequences and other information of the origins. It should be noted that the positions of the origins in A.thaliana and S.pombe have been relocated and mapped to the newest releases of genome sequences from GenBank in order to remove the sequencing errors in the older versions, and the positions of the origins in Mouse_ES_2 have also been relocated and mapped to the genome sequences of mouse (mm9) in order to make the UCSC Genome Browser available.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>Consequently, we have constructed a database DeOri, which contains all the eukaryotic DNA replication origins identified by genome-wide analyses currently available. With the availability of the origins newly identified by genome-wide analyses, we will update DeOri constantly to include more entries and integrate more information for each entry. This database will facilitate the comparative genomic analysis of replication origins, and provide some insight into the nature of replication origins on a genome scale. One of the applications is to predict replication origins based on homologous sequence search against the origins of closely related species in DeOri. For example, if query sequences in the rice genome using BLAST have homologous origins of A.thaliana in DeOri, it is likely that the query sequences are also served as origins in the rice genome. Another application is to find some principles for specific organisms by the genome-wide characterization of the origins in DeOri, which will be useful to develop new algorithms to predict replication origins. For example, we can use some tools for motif discovery to find the conserved elements within the origins of a specific organism.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1. 2011 10 Schizosaccharomyces pombe 348 Hayashi et al., 2007; Heichinger et al., 2006; Segurado et al., 2003</figDesc><table>Contents of DeOri version 1.0 

No. Organism 
ORI no. References 

1 Arabidopsis thaliana 
1543 
Costas et al., 2011 
2 Drosophila melanogaster 
6184 
Cayrou et al., 2011 
3 Human_1 
283 
Cadoret et al., 2008 
4 Human_2 
150 
Karnani et al., 2010 
5 Kluyveromyces lactis 
148 
Liachko et al., 2010 
6 Mouse_ES_1 
2412 
Cayrou et al., 2011 
7 Mouse_ES_2 
98 
Sequeira-Mendes et al., 2009 
8 Mouse_MEF 
2231 
Cayrou et al., 2011 
9 Mouse_P19 
2748 
Cayrou et al., </table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> DATABASE CONTENT All information in DeOri is stored and operated using MySQL relational database management system. One entry in the database corresponds to an origin in a certain organism. The corresponding organism, chromosome, cell type (if any), genomic location, length, GC content, origin sequence and some related links have been displayed. In order to facilitate the comparative genomic analysis and visualize the chromosome context of the origins, the URLs that link to UCSC Genome Browser (Fujita et al., 2011) or NCBI Map Viewer (Sayers et al., 2011) have also been provided. The database access is via a web interface based on PHP script and provides various ways to search for DeOri records, such as DeOri ID, cell type, species and chromosome. In addition, users can also BLAST (Altschul et al., 1997) a query sequence against DeOri to find a homologous one. DeOri will be updated timely and a total of 16 145 eukaryotic DNA replication origins were collected from 6 eukaryotic organisms in genome-wide studies, including 433 human origins, 7489 mouse origins, 1543 A.thaliana origins, 148 K.lactis origins, 348 S.pombe origins and 6184 D.melanogaster origins in the current release (Table 1), which can be accessed from http://tubic.tju.edu.cn/deori/.</note>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3389" to="3402" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide studies highlight indirect links between human replication origins and gene regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Cadoret</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15837" to="15842" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Genome-scale analysis of metazoan replication origins reveals their organization in specific but flexible sites defined by conserved features</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Cayrou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1438" to="1449" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide mapping of Arabidopsis thaliana origins of DNA replication and their associated epigenetic marks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Costas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="400" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The UCSC Genome Browser database: update 2011</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Fujita</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="876" to="882" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide localization of pre-RC sites and identification of replication origins in fission yeast</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hayashi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1327" to="1339" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide characterization of fission yeast DNA replication origins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Heichinger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5171" to="5179" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic study of replication initiation in human chromosomes reveals the influence of transcription regulation and chromatin structure on origin selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Karnani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="393" to="404" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comprehensive genome-wide map of autonomously replicating sequences in a naive genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Liachko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000946</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OriDB: a DNA replication origin database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Nieduszynski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Database resources of the National Center for Biotechnology Information</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Sayers</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide distribution of DNA replication origins at A+T-rich islands in Schizosaccharomyces pombe</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Segurado</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1048" to="1053" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcription initiation activity sets replication origin efficiency in mammalian cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Sequeira-Mendes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000446</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>