
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:31+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology Derivative processes for modelling metabolic fluxes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Justina</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Z ˇ</forename>
								<surname>Urauskiene _</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Associate Editor: Igor Jurisica</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Theoretical Systems Biology Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">South Kensington Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Paul</forename>
								<surname>Kirk</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Associate Editor: Igor Jurisica</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Theoretical Systems Biology Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">South Kensington Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
								<surname>Thorne</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Associate Editor: Igor Jurisica</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Theoretical Systems Biology Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">South Kensington Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<surname>Pinney</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Associate Editor: Igor Jurisica</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Theoretical Systems Biology Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">South Kensington Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<surname>Stumpf</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>m.stumpf@imperial.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Associate Editor: Igor Jurisica</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Theoretical Systems Biology Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">South Kensington Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology Derivative processes for modelling metabolic fluxes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1892" to="1898"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu069</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 20, 2013; revised on December 28, 2013; accepted on January 26, 2014</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Availability and implementation: R code is available from the authors upon request. Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: One of the challenging questions in modelling biological systems is to characterize the functional forms of the processes that control and orchestrate molecular and cellular phenotypes. Recently proposed methods for the analysis of metabolic pathways, for example, dynamic flux estimation, can only provide estimates of the underlying fluxes at discrete time points but fail to capture the complete temporal behaviour. To describe the dynamic variation of the fluxes, we additionally require the assumption of specific functional forms that can capture the temporal behaviour. However, it also remains unclear how to address the noise which might be present in experimentally measured metabolite concentrations. Results: Here we propose a novel approach to modelling metabolic fluxes: derivative processes that are based on multiple-output Gaussian processes (MGPs), which are a flexible non-parametric Bayesian modelling technique. The main advantages that follow from MGPs approach include the natural non-parametric representation of the fluxes and ability to impute the missing data in between the measurements. Our derivative process approach allows us to model changes in metabolite derivative concentrations and to characterize the temporal behaviour of metabolic fluxes from time course data. Because the derivative of a Gaussian process is itself a Gaussian process, we can readily link metabolite concentrations to metabolic fluxes and vice versa. Here we discuss how this can be implemented in an MGP framework and illustrate its application to simple models, including nitrogen metabolism in Escherichia coli.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>It is generally impossible to simultaneously measure the abundance of all the molecular entities making up biological systems. In gene expression assays, for example, we typically measure messenger RNA expression, but not the activity of transcription factors and/or the occupancy of transcription-factor binding sites. Similarly, in metabolomic analyses (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Chou and Voit, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Voit, 2013</ref>), key metabolites can be measured using, e.g. mass spectrometry or nuclear magnetic resonance quantification, but it is rarely possible to comprehensively quantify the metabolites even within a single pathway. Typically, more interesting than metabolite and enzyme abundance are the fluxes through biochemical reactions and metabolic networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Orth et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Schuster et al., 1999</ref>). Fluxes, ¼ ð 1 ,. .. , m Þ T , correspond to the rates at which molecules, x ¼ ðx 1 ,. .. , x n Þ T , are turned over by the m reactions; regulation of fluxes in light of changes in environmental and physiological conditions is also intimately linked to cellular physiology. Although the fluxes are of central concern, they are hard to measure directly. Estimates for intracellular fluxes can be obtained by tracking products from isotope-labeled ( 13 C and 15 N metabolic flux analysis) metabolites through the metabolic network (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Blank and Ebert, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Zamboni, 2011</ref>). However, such an approach is restricted to a metabolically steady-state analysis and is not appropriate for capturing dynamical flux variations. Instead, theoretical analysis has often progressed by assuming stationarity of the metabolic processes, which in turn allows for characterizing the sets of steady-state fluxes under a set of suitable assumptions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Klamt and Stelling, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schwartz and Kanehisa, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Voit and Almeida, 2004</ref>). Flux-balance analysis is the most popular example of this strategy, but it becomes questionable once the steady-state assumption can no longer be upheld. Furthermore, as more data on enzyme abundance become available, we should attempt to include such information and the impact on metabolic processes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Colijn et al, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Rossell et al., 2013</ref>). Here we provide a new framework that allows us to model metabolic fluxes and their dynamics, and which deals with the missing data problem in metabolic analysis in a flexible and consistent manner. Gaussian processes (GP) belong to the armoury of non–parametric Bayesian methods and have been widely used to describe dynamical processes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Kirk and Stumpf, 2009</ref>) and to infer hidden states, e.g. transcription-factor activities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Honkela et al., 2010</ref>). In applications to metabolic modelling, parametric approaches can offer potentially incorrect representations of the underlying fluxes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Voit, 2013</ref>). The strengths of GP models arise from their non-parametric nature, which enables us to put priors directly on a function rather than on the parameters of a parametric function. With a multiple-output GPs (MGPs), single GP framework can be extended to handle many outputs, enabling us to learn the unknown relationships between metabolic species. In turn, MGPs can be used to infill the sparsely sampled data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Boyle and Frean, 2004</ref>). This means that by using MGPs, it is possible to impute the missing data in between the metabolic measurements more efficiently. Here we develop a more general framework that uses so-called derivative GPs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Solak et al., 2003</ref>), which allow us to link *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. metabolite abundance, x (or concentrations) and fluxes. This in turn enables us to also treat time course data on metabolites and monitor the changes that occur in fluxes, e.g. over the course of physiological responses, such as to changes in the environment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bryant et al., 2013</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">GP regression</head><p>Gaussian process regression (GPR) can be applied to recover an underlying dynamical process from noisy observations. A GP defines a prior distribution over all possible functions, and to specify a GP, we need expressions for the mean and covariance function that describe the behaviour of the system output over time (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Haykin and Moher, 2010</ref>). Below we review the standard GPR methodology. In a typical regression problem, we connect inputs x and outputs z via functions, z ¼ fðxÞ, where x ¼ x 1 ,. .. , x n ð Þand z ¼ z 1 ,. .. , z n ð Þare continuous n-dimensional real-valued vectors. The observed values of the dependent variable, z, can be related to the independent variables, fðxÞ through,</p><formula>y i ¼ fðx i Þ þ , i ¼ 1,. .. , n,</formula><p>where is a noise term, which is here assumed to be independent and identically distributed according to a Gaussian distribution, $ N ð0, 2 Þ. In GPR, we place a GP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Haykin and Moher, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">McKay, 1998</ref>) prior over the functions fðxÞ, f $ GP, meaning that at any finite number of input points x 1 ,. .. , x n the values fðx i Þ have a multivariate Gaussian distribution with zero mean and covariance function, K, fðx 1 Þ,. .. , fðx n Þ ½  T $ N 0, Kðx, x 0 Þ ð Þ :</p><p>Different functional forms can be chosen for the covariance function (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Rasmussen and Williams, 2006</ref>), either to simplify computations or to reflect constrains imposed by the data. A flexible and generic choice is to set the covariance function to</p><formula>Kðx p , x q Þ ¼ 2 g exp À 1 2l jx p À x q j 2 ,</formula><p>where ¼ 2 g , l represent a set of unknown hyper-parameters, and x p and x q are inputs. Thus, y ¼ y 1 ,. .. , y n ð Þ T has a multivariate normal distribution with zero mean and covariance matrix CðÞ ¼ K þ 2 I, with I the identity matrix. The unknown set of hyper-parameters, , can be estimated from the data by evaluating the following log-likelihood function, LðÞ ¼ À 1 2 log jCðÞj À 1 2 y T CðÞ À1 y À n 2 log 2, ð1Þ using either a maximum likelihood approach or by sampling from the posterior distribution with Markov chain Monte Carlo methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Neal, 1997</ref>). For any finite number of input (test) points, x ? 1 ,. .. , x ? r , we define the joint prior probability distribution ½y, fðx ? 1 Þ,. .. , fðx ? r Þ T $ N 0,</p><formula>Kðx p , x q Þ þ 2 I Kðx p , x ? q Þ Kðx ? p , x q Þ Kðx ? p , x ? q Þ :</formula><p>With the GP prior, it is possible to evaluate the posterior distribution over the functions; the values of f evaluated at inputs x ? 1 ,. .. , x ? r À Á and conditioned on the observations y are jointly distributed as (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Rasmussen and Williams, 2006</ref>), ½fðx ? 1 Þ,. .. , fðx ? r Þ T jy $ N ðm p , K p Þ, ð2Þ</p><formula>where m p ¼ Kðx ? p , x q Þ½Kðx p , x q Þ þ 2 I À1 y, and K p ¼ Kðx ? p , x ? q Þ À Kðx ? p , x q Þ½Kðx p , x q Þ þ 2 IKðx p , x ? q Þ:</formula><p>Although Equation (2) defines an appropriate GP posterior, which allows us to make predictions about a single variable y, it remains unclear how to deal with several variables simultaneously: if outputs are correlated then the standard GPR framework may fail in providing an adequate description.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Multiple–output GPs</head><p>Boyle and Frean (2004) introduced MGPs, where a set of dependent GPs is constructed via multiple-input multiple-output linear filters. This perspective can capture the dependencies between several variables by solving a convolution integral and specifying a suitable covariance function, which in turn includes the cross and auto correlations among related variables. Our construction of derivative processes below builds on MGPs. Dealing with linear filters is central to signal processing where such filters describe a physical systems that can generate an output signal in response to a given input signal (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Haykin and Moher, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Roberts, 2008</ref>). Linear filters are characterized by their kernel function (an impulse response) h(t), and the output z(t) can be expressed via convolution integral,</p><formula>zðtÞ ¼ hðtÞ xðtÞ ¼ Z 1 À1 hðÞxðt À Þd,</formula><p>where the symbol '' denotes the convolution operator. To transmit the signal that has the mathematical properties of a GP, the kernel function, h(t) must be absolutely integrable, i.e.</p><formula>Z 1 À1 jhðtÞjdt51,</formula><p>Then if the input X(t) is specified to be a Gaussian white noise process, the output process, Z(t), will also be a GP. Specifying a stable linear time-invariant filter with M white noise processes as inputs, X 1 ðtÞ,. .. , X M ðtÞ, K outputs, Z 1 ðtÞ,. .. , Z K ðtÞ and M Â K impulse responses results in a dependent GP model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Boyle and Frean, 2005</ref>). A multiple-input multiple-output filter can thus be defined as</p><formula>Z k ðtÞ ¼ X M m¼1 Z 1 À1 h mk ðÞX m ðt À Þd,</formula><p>where h mk ðtÞ are kernel functions and Z k ðtÞ is the kth output. As discussed previously, the observed variables might differ from expected variables owing to the measurement noise, and we thus consider</p><formula>Y k ðtÞ ¼ Z k ðtÞ þ W k ðtÞ, ð3Þ</formula><p>where W k ðtÞ is a Gaussian white noise process with variance 2 k. Multiple-input multiple-output filters are able to capture the relationships between several variables Y k ðtÞ; in the model, these kind of dependencies are build in via shared input noise sources that enable the specification of valid covariance functions. For the sake of simplicity, let the impulse response be a Gaussian kernel, h mk ðtÞ ¼ v mk expfÀ 1 2 ðtÀ mk Þ 2 A mk g. Then evaluating the convolution integral leads to the following covariance function,</p><formula>C ij ðdÞ ¼ X M m¼1 Z 1 À1 h mi ðÞh mj ð þ dÞd ¼ X M m¼1 ð2Þ 1 2 v mi v mj ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi A mi þ A mj p exp À 1 2 ðd À ½ mi À mj Þ 2 S</formula><p>intermediate matrices C ij permits the definition of a positive definite symmetric covariance matrix C between K variables,</p><formula>C ¼ C 11 þ 2 1 I. .. C 1K .. . .. . .. . C K1 .. . C KK þ 2 K I 0 @ 1 A ½NÂN :</formula><p>Here N ¼ P K i¼1 N i is total number of observations, and N i the number of observations of variable i. Having defined the covariance matrix, we can use the log-likelihood, which has the form (1) for the inference of the hyper-parameters ¼ fv mk , mk , A mk g. Again, following Bayesian framework, we can use the results from the GPR section to evaluate the joint predictive distribution (2) for all outputs. Alternatively, for a particular variable i, predictions can be made using the appropriate marginal distribution, which is Gaussian, with mean m i ðt 0 Þ and variance var i ðt 0 Þ,</p><formula>given by m i ðt 0 Þ ¼ k T C À1 y, var i ðt 0 Þ ¼ À k T C À1 k, ð5Þ where ¼ C ii ð0Þ þ 2 i , k T ¼ ½k T 1 ,. .. , k T K , k T j ¼ ½ðC ij ðt 0 À t j, 1 Þ Á Á Á C ij ðt 0 À t j</formula><p>, Nj Þ:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Derivative processes</head><p>For a GP that is derived through a linear filter, YðtÞ ¼ hðtÞ XðtÞ þ WðtÞ, where X(t) is a white noise GP, h(t) is a kernel function and W(t) is an additive noise, it is easy to formulate the expression of a derivative process. Taking a derivative of Y with respect to t, it is possible to obtain a new process U that is also a GP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Boyle, 2007</ref>),</p><formula>UðtÞ d dt YðtÞ ¼ Z 1 À1 d dt hðt À Þ &amp; ' XðÞd ¼ gðtÞ XðtÞ,</formula><p>Thus, it is possible to construct the derivative process by convolving a white noise GP X(t) with a derivative kernel function g(t). This definition enables us to consider derivative processes and the corresponding original processes as a collection of dependent GPs. This is true because the derivative processes and the original processes are derived from exactly the same input, X(t). To construct a dependent model for several related variables</p><formula>Y ¼ Y 1 ,. .. , Y K ð Þ and their derivatives U ¼ U 1 ,. .. , U K ð</formula><p>Þ , it is necessary to define a suitable covariance structure, which in principal arises from the initial covariance function (4). For example, for a set of four dependent outputs (two original and two derivative processes), the following equations can be applied to compute the covariances (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Girard, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kirk, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Solak et al., 2003</ref>where the ~ C ij matrices contain the correlations between functions Z 1 and Z 2 evaluated at a finite set of test points t 1 ,. .. , t r ; g DC ij the correlations</p><formula>between functions Z ¼ Z 1 , Z 2 ð Þ and derivative variables U ¼ U 1 , U 2 ð Þ</formula><p>evaluated at the same test points; and finally, DDC ij consists of auto/ cross-correlations between derivative variables U 1 and U 2. The matrices R, L and H are building components of the overall covariance matrix K, which is symmetric and positive definite,</p><formula>K ¼ C þ 2 I R L H :</formula><p>At a finite number of input points t 1 ,. .. , t r , the matrix K allows us to place a joint prior over observations Y, functions Z and derivatives U,</p><formula>Y 1 , Y 2 , Z 1 , Z 2 , U 1 , U 2 ½  $ N 0, K ð Þ: Evaluating a GP posterior Z 1 , Z 2 , U 1 , U 2 ½  Y 1 , Y 2 ½ $Nð m post , K post Þ, ð6Þ where m post ¼ L C þ 2 I Â Ã À1 R and K post ¼ H À L C þ 2 I Â Ã À1 Y,</formula><p>enables us to make joint predictions for the original and derivative processes simultaneously. Alternatively, if there is no need to sample from the posterior process, we can use marginal Gaussian distributions to make predictions for individual output. The marginal distributions for output i and its derivative process at any input point t ? ,</p><formula>m Yi ðt ? Þ ¼ k Yi C þ 2 I Â Ã À1 Y, m Ui ðt ? Þ ¼ k Zi C þ 2 I Â Ã À1 Y, var Yi ðt ? Þ ¼ À k Yi C þ 2 I Â Ã À1 k T Yi , var Ui ðt ? Þ ¼ À k Zi C þ 2 I Â Ã À1 k T Zi , ð7Þ</formula><p>where m Yi is the mean of the original process, m Ui the mean of the derivative process, var Yi the variance of the original process and var Ui the variance of the derivative process, and furthermore</p><formula>¼ C ii ð0Þ þ 2 i , ¼ DDC ii ð0Þ k Yi ¼ C i1 ðt ? À t 1, 1 Þ Á Á Á C i1 ðt ? À t 1, N1 Þ C i2 ðt ? À t 2, 1 Þ Á Á Á C i2 ðt ? À t 2, N2 Þ 0 B B B B B B B B @ 1 C C C C C C C C A , k Ui ¼ DC i1 ðt ? À t 1, 1 Þ Á Á Á DC i1 ðt ? À t 1, N1 Þ DC i2 ðt ? À t 2, 1 Þ Á Á Á DC i2 ðt ? À t 2, N2 Þ 0</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">APPLICATIONS AND RESULTS</head><p>To demonstrate the performance of derivative processes, we consider two simulation examples—a system of two oscillating signals and a simple model of linear metabolic pathway—before turning to a more complicated metabolic process and, finally, some real metabolic network data. The derivative processes can be used to address the flux estimation problem from time course data. Here GPs describe the dynamics of metabolites, and the corresponding derivative processes capture the functional forms of the associated fluxes. Below, all examples were implemented using the free statistical computing platform R www.rproject.org.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Oscillating signals</head><p>A simple oscillating signal can be expressed as zðtÞ ¼ A sinð!t þ Þ, where A is the amplitude, ! ¼ 2f the angular frequency and the phase angle. This is a particularly useful example because it is easy to evaluate the performance of derivative processes, as the derivative signals have a known analytic form. We consider a simple system that consists of two oscillating signals, z 1 ðtÞ and z 2 ðtÞ,</p><formula>z 1 ðtÞ ¼ sinð2tÞ, ) _ z 1 ðtÞ ¼ 2 cosð2tÞ,</formula><formula>z 2 ðtÞ ¼ sin 2t þ 4 , ) _ z 2 ðtÞ, ¼ 2 cos 2t þ 4 ,</formula><p>with t 2 ½0, 4. To model real experimental measurements, we add random noise to the simulated trajectories, Y 1 ðtÞ ¼ z 1 ðtÞ þ 1 , Y 1 ðtÞ ¼ z 2 ðtÞ þ 2 , where i $ N ð0, 0:1 2 Þ; we have observations of both signals at regular time intervals,</p><formula>D 1 ¼ ft 1, i , Y 1, i g N1¼10 i¼1</formula><p>and D 2 ¼ ft 2, j , Y 2, j g N2 j¼1 ¼ 10. To build a single model that captures the relationship between the two signals, we apply the dependent GP framework (3) (K ¼ 2) on a combined dataset D ¼ fD 1 , D 2 g; each signal can be expressed as a superposition of three GPs—two of which are constructed via convolution between a noise source and a Gaussian kernel, and the third one is an additive noise. We set parameters A i of each Gaussian kernel to be expðf i Þ and noise levels to 1 ¼ expð 1 Þ, 2 ¼ expð 2 Þ, leading to a set of hyper-parameters</p><formula>¼ ðv i , f i , 1 , 2 , 1 , 2 Þ, i ¼ 1</formula><p>,. .. , 4. To build the model the following priors are chosen: v i , f i $ ð1, 2 2 Þ, j $ N ðÀ2, 2 2 Þ and j $ N ð0:5, 1 2 Þ, j ¼ 1, 2; the maximum a posteriori (MAP) estimate ^ is determined using a multistarting Nelder–Mead optimization algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Nelder and Mead, 1965</ref>). Dependent GP posteriors (6) allow us to make joint predictions about both signals and their derivative processes at any finite number of input points, and the resulting posterior processes are summarized in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 1</ref>. From these posterior processes, it can be seen that the mean behaviour of our model agrees with trajectories of underlying noiseless signals, and to make predictions about derivative processes, it is enough to consider only samples from the original sinusoidal trajectories.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Linear pathway</head><p>Next we consider a linear metabolic pathway with two regulatory signals (see Goel et al.</p><formula>_ x 2 ¼ x 1 V max K m ð1 þ x3 Ki Þ þ x 1 À x 0:5 2 x 3 , _ x 3 ¼ x 0:5 2 x 3 À x 0:5 3 : ð8Þ</formula><p>To apply the derivative process approach, we simulate the ODE model with the following parameter values ðV max , K m , K i Þ ¼ ð18:6819, 9:7821, 0:5992Þ and initial conditions x 2 ð0Þ ¼ 1, x 3 ð0Þ ¼ 1. In this model, the concentration of x 1 is assumed to be constant and equal to 2. The dataset consists of selected points from simulated trajectories with added Gaussian noise N ð0, 0:05 2 Þ. Again we combine the 'noisy' measurements, and fit the dependent GP model to make predictions about the original trajectories and their derivatives.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Branched pathway</head><p>We now turn to an example of metabolic pathway that was originally proposed by Voit (2013) (see Example of actual characterization);<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 3b</ref>illustrates a schematic representation of a branched pathway with two regulatory responses, where x 3 inhibits the conversions of x 1 into x 2 , and x 2 positively regulates reaction v 4. The following ODE model describes the dynamics of the metabolites that are involved in this pathway,</p><formula>_ x 1 ¼ 0:05 À 1:1x 0:5 1 x À0:75 3 À 2:8x 0:8 1 x 0:4 2 , _ x 2 ¼ 1:1x 0:5 1 x À0:75 3 À 1:1x 0:6 2 , _ x 3 ¼ 1:1x 0:6 2 , ð9Þ</formula><p>where x 1 , x 2 , x 3 denote the metabolites. For a given pathway (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 3b</ref>), the change in metabolite concentration can be described by the differences between incoming and outgoing fluxes. For this reason, we are able to obtain the following expressions for fluxes</p><formula>v 1 , v 2 , v 3 and v 4 , _ x 1 ¼ v 1 À v 2 À v 4 , v 1 À v 4 ¼ _ x 1 þ v 2 , _ x 2 ¼ v 2 À v 3 , ) v 2 ¼ _ x 2 þ _ x 3 , _ x 3 ¼ v 3 , v 3 ¼ _ x 3 : ð10Þ</formula><p>These expressions define a system of linear equations that is underdetermined, as we have more fluxes to estimate than available equations, and it cannot be solved using standard Gaussian elimination techniques. For this reason, additional information is required to uniquely determine fluxes v 1 and v 4. In this example, we will focus only on estimation of fluxes v 2 and v 3 from available data rather than try to address a uniqueness problem of v 1 and v 4. The above ODE model enables us to generate simulated time course data using the initial conditions x 1 ð0Þ ¼ 4, x 2 ð0Þ ¼ 1 and x 3 ð0Þ ¼ 2. Next, we apply the dependent GP framework (</p><formula>3) (K ¼ 2) on the combined dataset D ¼ fD 1 , D 2 g, where D 1 ¼ ft 2, i , x 2, i g N1¼20 i¼1 and D 2 ¼ ft 3, i , x 3, i g N1¼20 i¼1 contains</formula><p>the measurements of metabolites x 2 and x 3 with added random Gaussian noise N ð0, 0:01 2 Þ (we chose a low noise level so that predictions with derivative processes could be easily compared with the original fluxes in the example in Voit (2013). For a set of model</p><formula>hyper-parameters ¼ ðv i , f i , 1 , 2 , Þ, i ¼ 1</formula><p>,. .. , 4 we use the following priors,</p><formula>v i $ ð2, 2 2 Þ, f i $ ðÀ3, 2 2 Þ, j $ N ðÀ2, 2 2 Þ, j ¼ 1</formula><p>, 2 and $ N ð0:5, 1 2 Þ, and calculate the MAP estimate ^ as before.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Escherichia coli nitrogen assimilation</head><p>Finally, we apply our technique to the experimental data from E. coli, where we have measurements of the abundance of several key metabolites involved in nitrogen assimilation. Nitrogen is one of the key chemical elements that acts as a nutrient for the cells; ammonium is a preferred source of nitrogen for E. coli growth (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Schumacher et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">van Heeswijk et al., 2013</ref>). In E. coli, ammonium can be absorbed via two pathways: glutamate dehydrogenase (GDH) that operates during cell growth in ammonium-rich environments, and glutamine synthetase-glutamate synthase (GS-GOGAT) that operates during cell growth in lowammonium conditions (van<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Heeswijk et al., 2013</ref>). Here, we are focussing on experimental conditions, where after a period of nitrogen starvation, the bacterial cultures are spiked with ammonium (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Schumacher et al., 2013</ref>);<ref type="figure">Figure 5a</ref>shows experimentally obtained measurements for-ketoglutarade (KG), glutamate (GLU) and glutamine (GLN) metabolites over the time after ammonium spike; red dots correspond to a wild-type (WT) E. coli metabolic measurements, and in squares—isogenic glnG deletion (ÁglnG) measurements. Below we focus on the pathway summarized in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 3c</ref>, which includes both GDH and GSGOGAT. For modelling purposes, we assume that fluxes v 3 and v 4 can be summarized by the overall flux v 3 that describes the flow from GLU to GLN, as there is not enough information to discriminate between them. From the pathway, we can construct a system of linear equations that describe the dependencies between fluxes and metabolites,</p><formula>_ KG ¼ v 1 À v 2 , v 1 ¼ _ KG þ G _ LU þ G _ LN, G _ LU ¼ v 2 À v 3 , ) v 2 ¼ G _ LU þ G _ LN, G _ LN ¼ v 3 , v 3 ¼ G _ LN: ð11Þ</formula><p>We fit a dependent GP model (3) (K ¼ 3) to the WT data and then to ÁglnG data (collected from a strain where glnG is absent). In the model, KG is expressed as a sum of three GPs: the first GP describes KG, the second expresses the relationship between KG and GLU and the third one describes additive noise; GLN is modelled similarly. However, GLU is modelled as the sum of four GPs, where the first three describe GLU; the dependence between GLU and KG; the dependence between GLU and GLN; and the fourth is an additive noise. Choosing kernel functions to be Gaussian h k ðtÞ ¼ v k expfÀ 1 2 t 2 A k g, we obtain the MAP estimate for all hyper-parameters (17 in total). The predictions with posterior process (7) are summarized in<ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>, where solid blue lines describe predictions with dependent GP models for WT E. coli, and green lines for ÁglnG. Using the relationship (11), we can estimate fluxes v 1 , v 2 and v 3 (<ref type="figure">Fig. 5c</ref>). To evaluate our predictions, we can compare flux v 3 and GS protein levels in WT and ÁglnG E. coli (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig.  S1</ref>). In E. coli, glnG encodes the transcription factor, NtrC (nitrogen regulator) that controls GS expression levels, and in its active form, GS catalyses glutamine synthesis (van Heeswijk</p><formula>(a) (b) (c) 1 1 1 1</formula><p>Time(min)<ref type="bibr">et al., 2013</ref>). Experimentally, it was observed that in ÁglnG case protein, GS levels were significantly lower compared with the GS levels in WT E. coli (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S1C</ref>and D). Because there is less enzyme available to catalyse the reaction in ÁglnG, the flux v 3 in the mutant will be noticeably reduced compared with the WT flux v 3 (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S1A</ref>and B).</p><formula>(a) ( b) (c) ( d)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Flux estimation has become central to many analyses into the metabolic processes and mechanisms. Typically, the estimates for a set of fluxes are obtained in a point-wise manner at discrete time points. It is clear that this fails to capture the temporal behaviour of the fluxes and additional consideration of parametric models is compulsory to fully explain the fluxes; further, this approach is susceptible to noise that is present in experimentally measured metabolite data. Here we have addressed these problems and proposed a novel non-parametric Bayesian approach to modelling metabolic fluxes. This is based on MGPs that enable the construction of derivative processes. Because the derivative processes and original processes share the same input source, we can complement the dependent GP model and make joint predictions about original and derivative processes at any finite number of input points. Such derivative processes can be applied to characterize the temporal behaviour of metabolic fluxes from time course data—without having to make reference, e.g. transcriptomic data, to explain temporal variation—and here we have demonstrated the applicability on simple models and a real-world example. GPs, including our approach, propagate uncertainty in line with the assumed covariance structures. This can lead to large confidence intervals, especially if the dependencies among different observations are not considered explicitly. With increasing number of metabolic species within the pathway, the derivative process approach might become computationally costly due to the inference of a large number of hyper-parameters and a matrix inversion step; however, this limitation potentially might be addressed by considering a sparse approximation for the full covariance matrix of all metabolic species (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alvarez and Lawrence, 2009</ref>). These can in principle deal with genome-level data.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>(7) can easily be extended to make predictions about any number of variables. 1894 J.Z ˇ urauskiene _ et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>(2008) Supplementary Material for details), which is summarized in Figure 3a. Here the flow from x 1 to x 2 is negatively regulated by metabolite x 3 , and x 3 increases the transformation of x 2 into x 3. A set of ordinary differential equations (ODEs) can be used to describe the dynamics of these two metabolites, x 2 and x 3 (x 1 is the constant external input),</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>To obtain a functional expressions for fluxes v 1 and v 2 we need to estimate a dynamical variations of metabolic, x 2 , x 3 , derivatives. The derivative processes provide the predictions for the left side of Equation (8) at any finite number of time points, whereas the original GPs describe the solution on the same ODE (8). This enables us to link the metabolite measurements to metabolic fluxes. Figure 2 illustrates the predictions with posterior processes, where solid blue lines correspond to the mean behaviour of the model, dashed lines to the original x 2 and x 3 trajectories and solid green lines to their derivatives. In addition, if we assume that we are able to measure flux v 3 ¼ x 0:5 3 , we can obtain the functional expressions for fluxes v 1 and v 2 that are summarized in Figure 2c and d. The dark pink lines illustrate predicted fluxes from noisy metabolite</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Predictions with MGPs model for two oscillating signals. (a and b) Dashed lines represent true behaviour of noiseless sinðÁÞ trajectories; dots correspond to the noisy observations for both signals (data); solid lines are the mean behaviour of the MGPs model (predictions with original GPs); light areas correspond to two standard deviations at each prediction point. (c and d) Dashed lines represent true behaviour of noiseless cosðÁÞ trajectories; solid lines show the mean behaviour of the MGPs model (predictions with derivative processes); light areas correspond to two standard deviations at each prediction point</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><figDesc>Figure 4 illustrates the predictions with posterior processes using Equation (7); (a and b) graphs summarize metabolite data. The dark blue lines correspond to the mean behaviour of the original GPs and agree well with simulated x 2 and x 3 dynamics; the green lines describe the derivatives of the same metabolites and can be understood as a slope estimates. In Figure 4c and d, dark pink lines illustrate the predicted metabolic fluxes v 2 and v 3 under consideration of pathway Figure 3b. From ODE model (9), we can calculate original fluxes over the time (in real situations this</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Pathway information. (a) A simple linear metabolic pathway; red and green dashed lines correspond to the inhibition and activation signals. (b) Illustrates a branched pathway with positive (green) and negative (red) regulatory signals. (c) Illustrates a metabolic pathway in E.coli, here v i , i ¼ 1:::4 denote the fluxes; KG, GLU and GLN correspond to the metabolites; TCA is a short notation for the citrate cycle in E.coli</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Predictions with MGPs model for linear metabolic pathway. (a and b) Dashed lines represent a simulated x 2 and x 3 trajectories from ODE model; dots correspond to the sparse noisy observations for x 2 and x 3 (data); solid blue/green lines are the mean behaviour of the MGPs model (blue, predictions with original GPs; green, predictions with derivative process); light areas correspond to two standard deviations at each prediction point. (c and d) Dark lines are predicted fluxes, light areas correspond to the confidence region, and dashed lines represent true behaviour of noise-free fluxes v 1 and v 2 (calculated from ODE system)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Predictions with MGP model for a branched metabolic pathway. (a and b) Dashed lines represent simulated x 2 and x 3 trajectories from the ODE model; red dots correspond to the sparse observations for x 2 and x 3 (data); solid lines are the mean behaviour of the MGPs model (blue, predictions with original GPs; green, predictions with derivative process); light areas correspond to two standard deviations at each prediction point. (c and d) Dark lines are predicted fluxes; dashed lines represent true behaviour of fluxes v 2 and v 3 (calculated from the ODE system)</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">&amp; &apos; , ð4Þ where S ¼ A mi ðA mi þ A mj Þ À1 A mj and d ¼ t a À t b is the temporal separation between two input points, (see Boyle and Frean (2004) appendix for derivation and generalization to multidimensions). Constructing 1893 Derivative processes for modelling metabolic fluxes at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">J.Z ˇ urauskiene _ et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sparse convolved Gaussian processes for multi-output regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Alvarez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Lawrence</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Neural Inf. Process. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From measurement to implementation of metabolic fluxes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Blank</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Ebert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Gaussian processes for regression and optimisation. Doctoral dissertation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Boyle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multiple-output Gaussian process regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Boyle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Frean</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dependent Gaussian processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Boyle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Frean</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Neural Inf. Process. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="224" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of metabolic evolution in bacteria using wholegenome metabolic models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Bryant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comp. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="755" to="764" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of dynamic flux profiles from metabolic time series data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I-C</forename>
				<surname>Chou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Voit</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">84</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interpreting expression data with metabolic flux models: predicting Mycobacterium tuberculosis mycolic acid production</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Colijn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">System estimation from metabolic time-series data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Goel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinfromatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2505" to="2511" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Approximate methods for propagation of uncertainty with Gaussian process models. Doctoral dissertation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Girard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Communication Systems Nitrogen assimilation in Escherichia coli: puttin molecular data into a systems perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Haykin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Moher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Asia</forename>
				<surname>Wiley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Van Heeswijk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microbiol. Mol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="628" to="695" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>5th. edn.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model-based method for transcription factor target identification with limited data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Honkela</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7793" to="7798" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parameter estimation of kinetic models from metabolic profiles: two-phase dynamic decoupling method</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Jia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1964" to="1970" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Inferential stability in systems biology. Doctoral dissertation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Kirk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<pubPlace>Imperial College London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gaussian process regression bootstrapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Kirk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P H</forename>
				<surname>Stumpf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1300" to="1306" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two approaches for metabolic pathway analysis?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Klamt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Stelling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction to Gassign processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J C</forename>
				<surname>Mckay</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Neural Networks and Machine Learning. NATO ASI Series</title>
		<editor>Bishop,C.M.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="165" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monte Carlo implementation of Gaussian process models for Bayesian regression and classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Neal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arxiv Preprint Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simplex method for function minimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Nelder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Mead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comp. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">199</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="1965" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is flux balance analysis?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Orth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Gaussian Processes for Machine Learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Rasmussen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K I</forename>
				<surname>Williams</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<publisher>The MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1st. edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fundamentals of Signals and Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Roberts</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>Mc Graw Hill</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1st. edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inferring metabolic state in uncharacterized environments using gene-expression measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Rossell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative elementary mode analysis of metabolic pathways: the example of yeast glycolysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J-M</forename>
				<surname>Schwartz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kanehisa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">186</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Derivative observations in Gaussian process models of dynamic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Solak</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Neural Inf. Process. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1033" to="1040" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nitrogen and carbon status are integrated at the transcriptional level by the nitrogen regulator NtrC in vivo</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Schumacher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MBio</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of elementary flux modes in biochemical networks: a promising tool for pathway analysis and metabolic engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Schuster</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decoupling dynamical systems for pathway identification from metabolic profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Voit</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Almeida</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1670" to="1681" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizability of metabolic pathway systems from time series data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Voit</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">13 C metabolic flux analysis in complex systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Zamboni</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>