
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:52+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Detection of circular permutations within protein structures using CE-CP</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Spencer</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Bliven</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Bioinformatics and Systems Biology Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>San Diego, La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">National Center for Biotechnology Information</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Institutes of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20894</postCode>
									<settlement>Bethesda</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">San Diego Supercomputer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">RCSB Protein Data Bank</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>San Diego, La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Philip</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Bourne</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">National Center for Biotechnology Information</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Institutes of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20894</postCode>
									<settlement>Bethesda</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">San Diego Supercomputer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">RCSB Protein Data Bank</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>San Diego, La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andreas</forename>
								<surname>Prlic´3prlic´prlic´3</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">San Diego Supercomputer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">RCSB Protein Data Bank</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>San Diego, La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Detection of circular permutations within protein structures using CE-CP</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu823</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 14, 2014; revised on November 3, 2014; accepted on December 8, 2014</note>
					<note>Structural bioinformatics *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Contact: sbliven@ucsd.edu or info@rcsb.org.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Circular permutation is an important type of protein rearrangement. Natural circular permutations have implications for protein function, stability and evolution. Artificial circular permutations have also been used for protein studies. However, such relationships are difficult to detect for many sequence and structure comparison algorithms and require special consideration. Results: We developed a new algorithm, called Combinatorial Extension for Circular Permutations (CE-CP), which allows the structural comparison of circularly permuted proteins. CE-CP was designed to be user friendly and is integrated into the RCSB Protein Data Bank. It was tested on two collections of circularly permuted proteins. Pairwise alignments can be visualized both in a desktop application or on the web using Jmol and exported to other programs in a variety of formats. Availability and implementation: The CE-CP algorithm can be accessed through the RCSB website at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Circular permutation describes a relationship between two proteins where the N-terminal portion of one protein is related to the Cterminal portion of the other. While the order of amino acids changes, circularly permuted proteins are generally found to assume the same structure. Circular permutation has been documented to naturally occur in a number of protein families, such as lectins (<ref type="bibr">Cunningham et al., 1979</ref>) and DNA methyltransferases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Jeltsch, 1999</ref>). Two general mechanisms for the evolution of circularly permuted proteins are known, so detecting such events can shed light on the evolutionary history of protein families (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Weiner and Bornberg-Bauer, 2006</ref>). Circular permutation can influence protein folding, dynamics and function (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bliven and Prlic´,Prlic´, 2012</ref>). Synthetic circular permutants have been engineered to alter activity, control regulation and improve stability (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Ostermeier, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Whitehead et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Yu and Lutz, 2011</ref>). Natural circular permutants generally have quite low sequence similarity, with previous studies finding &lt;0.3–2.6% of proteins share &gt;30% identity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Jung and Lee, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Lo and Lyu, 2008</ref>). Thus, including structural information is essential for detecting circular permutations. Many structural alignment algorithms are unable to detect rearrangements in sequence, while general sequence-order independent methods lack a clear evolutionary mechanism by which complex rearrangements could occur. Therefore, algorithms that specifically search for circular permutations are needed. Several existing algorithms have been reported, including SHEBA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Jung and Lee, 2001</ref>) and CPSARST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Lo and Lyu, 2008</ref>). Here we describe a method, Combinatorial Extension with Circular Permutations (CE-CP), for the identification of circular permutations based on protein structure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>CE is a rigid-body structural comparison algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Shindyalov and Bourne, 1998</ref>). It uses dynamic programming to identify regions of local similarity between the alpha carbons of two protein structures, followed by iterative refinement to find a global superposition with low RMSD and high number of aligned residues. To adapt CE to quickly find circular permutations, we use an algorithm analogous to that proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Uliel et al. (1999)</ref>for detecting circular permutations by sequence similarity. The atoms of the shorter structure are virtually duplicated. This allows the alignment of the first protein to wrap around from the carboxyl terminus to the amino terminus of the second protein (see<ref type="figure">Fig. 1b</ref>). Thus, the path with optimal structural similarity will contain some residues from each copy of the duplicated protein, allowing the permutation site to be identified. In the case of structures that are not circular permuted, two equivalent paths are possible. After identifying the highest scoring alignment to the duplicated protein, the result is processed to map the alignment onto the original query. While this is generally unambiguous for high-scoring alignments, it is possible that a single residue in the duplicated protein will align to multiple residues. In this case, a single aligned residue is chosen such that the total alignment length is maximized. This technique is agnostic to the details of the actual alignment algorithm. Thus, it could be easily adapted to allow other sequenceorder dependent alignment algorithms to detect circular permutations. For instance, CE-CP was used in our recent tool CE-Symm for identifying internally symmetric structures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Myers-Turnbull et al., 2014</ref>). To reduce computational time, CE by default limits gap sizes to 30 residues. As terminal insertions are common in protein structures, due to both biological variability in tail regions and experimental tags and artifacts, this limit is often restrictive for circularly permuted proteins, and all gaps are considered used in CE-CP by default. This ensures that the optimal path can be found regardless of insertions and deletions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results and discussion</head><p>CE-CP is integrated into the RCSB PDB Comparison Tool, along with several other algorithms for structural alignment (<ref type="bibr">PrlicétPrlicét al., 2010</ref>). Two user interfaces are available: a web version, and a standalone Java application that can be downloaded or run via Java Web Start. CE-CP results are presented to the user graphically, using the Jmol visualization program, and as a pairwise alignment. The portions before and after the permutation site are displayed in different colors if a permutation is found. The alignment is also available for export in a variety of formats, including a parsable text format or a two-model PDB file containing the two superimposed structures. The standalone application provides additional features, such as the ability to compare custom PDB files and perform full database searches. As shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>, CE-CP is able to identify the conserved structural core between highly divergent structures. It is robust to insertions and deletions, making it suitable for the detection of circular permutations in multi-domain structures. No large, balanced benchmarks of circularly permuted structures are available. However, CE-CP performance was evaluated on the small but accurate RIPC benchmark (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Mayr et al., 2007</ref>), as well as compared to results from the semi-automated circular permutation database (CPDB) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Lo et al., 2009</ref>).</p></div>
			<note place="foot">Bioinformatics, 31(8), 2015, 1316–1318 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btu823 Advance Access Publication Date: 12 December 2014 Applications Note at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">The RIPC dataset is a small benchmark of &apos;challenging&apos; manual alignments, due to the presence of insertions, conformational variability and permutations. All 11 pairs of circularly permuted proteins from the dataset were correctly identified by CE-CP, with most residues matching the reference alignment within 0–4 residues. The CPDB contains 4169 pairs of circularly permuted proteins, as identified by the CPSARST algorithm, followed by manual screening for false positives. Thus, entries contain a plausible circular permutation but are not verified as evolutionarily related. CE-CP identified a circular permutation in 3666 (88%) of CPDB pairs. Of the cases where a permutation was not detected, many are internally pseudosymmetric structures that have reasonable sequential alignments. As both circularly permuted proteins and internally symmetric proteins can evolve through duplication and fusion mechanisms, the high correlation between the two phenomena should be unsurprising. A portion of these symmetric cases may prove to be false positives from CPSARST given additional evolutionary or functional data. CE-CP is a readily available and easy to use tool for detecting circular permutations from protein structures. It is incorporated into the RCSB PDB Comparison Tool, which allows the comparison of structures through a variety of methods both on the RCSB PDB website and via a Java Webstart executable. CE-CP is available as part of the BioJava open source project (PrlicétPrlicét al., 2012).</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">S.E.Bliven et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We would like to thank Guido Capitani for help proofreading the manuscript, and Wei-Cheng Lo and Ping-Chiang Lyu for providing access to the CPDB alignments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by the National Science Foundation<ref type="bibr">[</ref></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circular permutation in proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Bliven</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Prlic´</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Prlic´</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002445</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SCOP:d1jwyb_) and the YjeQ protein (blue and green, SCOP:d1u0la2) N-and C-termini are shown with blue and red spheres. Arrows indicate the positions of the circular permutation. (b) Dotplot of the alignment with YjeQ duplicated. The optimal alignment is shown in black, with the inferred equivalent positions in blue and red Cunningham Favin versus concanavalin A: circularly permuted amino acid sequences</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">B.A. et al</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>PNAS</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3218" to="3222" />
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
			<publisher>PNAS</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>alignment. of the dynamin A GTPase domain</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circular permutations in the molecular evolution of DNA methyltransferases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Jeltsch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="164" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circularly permuted proteins in the protein structure database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Jung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1881" to="1886" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">CPSARST: an efficient circular permutation search tool applied to the detection of novel protein structural relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W.-C</forename>
				<surname>Lo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P.-C</forename>
				<surname>Lyu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CPDB: a database of circular permutation in proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W.-C</forename>
				<surname>Lo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="328" to="332" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Database. issue</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative analysis of protein structure alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Mayr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic detection of internal symmetry in proteins using CE-Symm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Myers-Turnbull</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">426</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2255" to="2268" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Engineering allosteric protein switches by domain insertion</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ostermeier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Eng. Des. Sel</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="364" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pre-calculated protein structure alignments at the RCSB PDB website</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Prlic´</forename>
				<surname>Prlic´</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2983" to="2985" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioJava: an open-source framework for bioinformatics in 2012</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Prlic´</forename>
				<surname>Prlic´</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2693" to="2695" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein structure alignment by incremental combinatorial extension (CE) of the optimal path</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Shindyalov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Bourne</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="739" to="747" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple algorithm for detecting circular permutations in proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Uliel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="930" to="936" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolution of circular permutations in multidomain proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Weiner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Bornberg-Bauer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="734" to="743" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tying up the loose ends: circular permutation decreases the proteolytic susceptibility of recombinant proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Whitehead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Eng. Des. Sel</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="607" to="613" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circular permutation: a different way to engineer enzyme structure and function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Yu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Lutz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>