
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:38+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining Determining conserved metabolic biomarkers from a million database queries</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Kurczy</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Scripps Center for Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Julijana</forename>
								<surname>Ivanisevic</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Scripps Center for Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Caroline</forename>
								<forename type="middle">H</forename>
								<surname>Johnson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Scripps Center for Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Winnie</forename>
								<surname>Uritboonthai</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Scripps Center for Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Linh</forename>
								<surname>Hoang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Scripps Center for Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mingliang</forename>
								<surname>Fang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Scripps Center for Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matthew</forename>
								<surname>Hicks</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Scripps Center for Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anthony</forename>
								<surname>Aldebot</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Scripps Center for Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Duane</forename>
								<surname>Rinehart</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Scripps Center for Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lisa</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Mellander</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Diego</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ralf</forename>
								<surname>Tautenhahn</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Scripps Center for Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gary</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Patti</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Washington University in St. Louis</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63130</postCode>
									<settlement>St. Louis</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Departments of Genetics and Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Washington University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63130</postCode>
									<settlement>St. Louis</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mary</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Spilker</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Pfizer Worldwide Research and Development</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>92121</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">H</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Paul</forename>
								<surname>Benton</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Scripps Center for Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gary</forename>
								<surname>Siuzdak</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Scripps Center for Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Departments of Chemistry, Molecular and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining Determining conserved metabolic biomarkers from a million database queries</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv475</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 18, 2015; revised on July 27, 2015; accepted on August 9, 2015</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Metabolite databases provide a unique window into metabolome research allowing the most commonly searched biomarkers to be catalogued. Omic scale metabolite profiling, or metabolomics, is finding increased utility in biomarker discovery largely driven by improvements in analytical technologies and the concurrent developments in bioinformatics. However, the successful translation of biomarkers into clinical or biologically relevant indicators is limited. Results: With the aim of improving the discovery of translatable metabolite biomarkers, we present search analytics for over one million METLIN metabolite database queries. The most common me-tabolites found in METLIN were cross-correlated against XCMS Online, the widely used cloud-based data processing and pathway analysis platform. Analysis of the METLIN and XCMS common metabolite data has two primary implications: these metabolites, might indicate a conserved metabolic response to stressors and, this data may be used to gauge the relative uniqueness of potential biomarkers. Availability and implementation. METLIN can be accessed by logging on to: https://</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Search analytics is now regularly utilized as an unbiased and anonymous method to survey populations. In a sense each query is a report of some circumstance or set of circumstances that has lead the user to carry out a search. For instance the user might be searching a symptom they are experiencing or the search may reflect a personal bias, in either case this information can be informative within the context of a community. Recent examples include the use of search data to model influenza outbreaks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Ginsberg et al., 2009</ref>), and in another case researchers were able to design a rough measure<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chae et al., 2015</ref>). With this in mind and starting from the premise that the majority of users searching the METLIN database are from the population engaged in metabolomic studies we set out to use analytics to survey the broad range of metabolomics research reflected in METLIN search data and reveal the most commonly encountered biomarkers. The potential impact of biomarker research is far reaching, involving diagnosis, prognosis, drug efficacy and the development of personalized medicine. One particularly intriguing aspect of biomarker discovery is the prospect of reducing the overall cost of health care by increasing the level of medical care through early diagnosis, or through the development of patient specific therapies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Davis et al., 2009</ref>). It is therefore understandable that a significant effort has been dedicated to the discovery of unique disease-specific molecules as evidenced by the thousands of biomarker-related papers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Drucker and Krapfenbauer, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Poste, 2011</ref>). The importance of biomarker discovery coupled to the accessibility of new, high sensitivity analytical technology has contributed to this broad interest (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Poste, 2011</ref>), however a lack of standard best practices has meant that discoveries often have very little practical value. The thousands of papers that have been published on biomarkers have yielded relatively little success (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Poste, 2011</ref>), for example while the number of biomarker publications have increased by over 20% each year, the number of patent applications for clinical biomarkers remains level (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Drucker and Krapfenbauer, 2013</ref>). Metabolomics-based biomarker discovery publications are progressively contributing to this body of work and also show the same trends, with the exception of the robust inborn errors of metabolism screens, there are relatively few new clinical metabolite based tests (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Xia et al., 2013</ref>). Metabolomic experiments, whether they are accomplished through the use of traditional GC/MS technologies (first demonstrated in the early 1970s by Linus Pauling and Horning;<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Horning and Horning, 1971;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Pauling et al., 1971</ref>), or current liquid chromatography mass spectrometry (LC/MS) instrumentation, are well suited for gaining a comprehensive and quantitative view of the metabolome. These approaches have the ability to detect thousands of metabolites from biological samples with high resolution, high sensitivity and a dynamic range typically exceeding four orders of magnitude (). As a result, it is possible to quickly generate datasets rich in metabolite information. A typical workflow for metabolomics involves several steps; first, mass spectral data is collected for each sample in each sample group. Next the data is analyzed by any number of data processing platforms including Metabolic profiler (Bruker), Simca-P (Umetrics), Markerlynx (Waters), Mass Profiler Pro (Agilent), MetAlign (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Lommen, 2009</ref>), MZmine (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Pluskal et al., 2010</ref>), MAVEN (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Melamud et al., 2010</ref>), MetaboAnalyst (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Xia et al., 2012</ref>) and XCMS Online (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Tautenhahn et al., 2012</ref>) to identify the features that significantly change between sample groups. The significantly dysregulated features are then given a putative identification by searching metabolite databases such as METLIN (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). METLIN (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Smith et al., 2005</ref>) is a highly accessed database used for metabolite identification. Since its inception in 2004 METLIN has grown to contain over 240 000 metabolites, 13 000 of which also have MS/MS data in both positive and negative ionization modes at four different collision energies (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). More than 10 000 users and over 600 citations of the original publication are indicators of its wide application. In addition, METLIN has been integrated with XCMS Online, providing metabolite identifications for the users of this cloud-based data processing platform.</p><p>The consistent increase in METLIN use (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>) is largely due to the wide spread adoption of mass spectrometry as an exploratory tool by biologists and biochemists. This has been facilitated by the increased access to mass spectrometry technologies that are sensitive and easy to use. Furthermore, the development of userfriendly bioinformatic platforms and integrated statistical tools (mentioned earlier) has removed a significant technical barrier (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gowda et al., 2014</ref>). Technology has also leveled the playing field so that researchers are typically using similar tools, which for the most part are composed of liquid chromatography coupled to an atmospheric pressure ionization source and either time-of-flight (TOF), quadrupole timeof-flight (QTOF) or quadrupole orbi-trap (Q-Exactive) mass analyzers with a consistent degree of quantitative and mass accuracy. Thus, the masses searched in METLIN provide a representation of the discriminatory metabolites from metabolomic experiments. Here, in order to gain a perspective on the metabolites being searched, METLIN archival data was searched and examined to determine commonly observed metabolites across one million queries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Results and discussion</head><p>Researchers using metabolomics are currently investigating a wide array of biological problems, thus the masses searched in METLIN should be a reflection of the diversity of these experiments. However, because metabolism is to some extent conserved we also expect to find commonly dysregulated metabolites to be searched at a high frequency. This assumption was evaluated using<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, which provides an overview of database queries that were submitted by approximately 5000 researchers. This data represents an). The x-axis represents the m/z searched and the y-axis the number of times that particular m/z has been searched. The inset shows the output of a METLIN query aggregate of one million searches that returned METLIN identifications. Interestingly, while a great diversity of metabolites was searched, we found that there are in fact preferentially searched masses. Additionally, over 80% of the searched metabolites fell into a bimodal distribution between the mass ranges of 150 and 450 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>), consistent with small molecules that are measured in metabolomics. Because commonly dysregulated metabolite masses will be detected at high frequency and therefore will be searched more often, we suggest that the distribution of this 'mass spectrum' is a manifestation of a conserved metabolic response. The results obtained from our analysis of METLIN searches produced a list of masses, the number of times each mass has been searched and the number of metabolite IDs that are returned for each query as represented by their neutral mass (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>). The most frequently searched mass in METLIN was 180.06. We have putatively identified this metabolite as glucose by accurate mass, although this query returns a total of 31 possible metabolites when using the database's default mass accuracy of 30 ppm. This example illustrates an important consideration that is implicit in this kind of meta-data analysis. Some commonly searched masses might be the result of the dysregulation of many isomers as opposed to the dysregulation of one common molecule. Metabolite identification via MS/MS is still obligatory in metabolomics if one wishes to classify a metabolite as either a specific or a nonspecific signal. Indeed, molecule identification is the most critical aspect of untargeted metabolomics when attempting to understand metabolism. The identification process is outlined in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S2</ref>where a search returns possible metabolites based on the input mass accuracy and collision energy and metabolite identification is facilitated by the comparison of research MS/MS data to MS/MS data compiled in the METLIN database by matching the precursor mass followed by MS/MS matching based on x-rank (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Mylonas et al., 2009</ref>). METLIN MS/MS searches were not as frequently performed as accurate mass searches, nor were these searches stored, we instead mined XCMS Online to facilitate the metabolite identifications. To identify core metabolites and further validate (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S2</ref>) our assumption that the masses most often searched in METLIN are related to the most commonly dysregulated biomarkers, we also searched meta-data generated by XCMS Online. We were able to cross-compare the METLIN hit list to the most common biomarkers observed in a subset of 2000 XCMS Online experiments. XCMS Online (xcmsonline.scripps.edu) is a web-based platform that was designed to simplify the data analysis of untargeted metabolomic experiments. In 2012 an email was sent out to all XCMS Online users with an invitation to participate in this communal effort to identify shared metabolites across a heterogeneous population of biological specimens and a wide spectrum of phenotypic conditions. Participation in this meta-analysis was done on an opt-in basis only and all data was masked, anonymized and aggregated for statistical analysis. These experiments show that some of the searched masses are most likely due to the appearance of isomers for example while glucose searched at a high frequency it was not commonly dysregulated in real samples. Using the XCMS data as a guide, we next analyzed a battery of sample types using LC-MS/MS in an attempt to identify the most common biomarkers from real samples. MS/MS data for the most common metabolites encountered in the communal XCMS Online experiments are presented in the Supplementary Material. From the 100 most frequently occurring metabolites with available MS/MS data 24 compounds were identified and listed in Supplementary Table S1, another 24 metabolites were characterized as phospholipids. MS/MS spectra were available for an additional 52 compounds but these have not been identified yet (all spectra and tables are available as Supplementary Material). Comparative analysis across XCMS results and the most common METLIN searches revealed a significant overlap. We found that all XCMS results, with exception of 4 metabolites, are within the 90 th percentile of the most searched masses in METLIN and half of those in the 90 th percentile actually fall within the 99 th percentile. The highest ranked identified molecule in Supplementary Table S1 is linoleic acid. This fatty acid is a useful marker for fat intake and metabolism in humans (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arab, 2003</ref>). Although, it is interesting that this molecule would feature so prominently in our list of common metabolites as we can reasonably exclude the possibility that a disproportionate number of XCMS Online users are investigating nutrition. To understand how often this metabolite is reported as a biomarker we performed an ISI web of knowledge search for the name of the metabolite paired with the word biomarkers. The search produced 273 separate publications and, following a more detailed survey of the literature, we found that there are at least 10 different conditions linked to the dysregulation of linoleic acid. The published reports coupled to the MS/MS data shed light on the high occurrence of searches for m/z 281.24. We find that linoleic acid is a commonly dysregulated metabolite and while there is little doubt that dysregulation of linoleic acid is discriminatory for all the reported conditions, we would argue that this property makes linoleic acid a relatively non-descript biomarker. In contrast, METLIN searches corresponding to the biomarkers choline, betaine and trimethylamine N-oxide amount to a total of 25 searches, and N,N-dimethylsphingosine amounts to 2 search results. The former biomarkers link diet, and gut microflora to cardiovascular disease (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Wang et al., 2011</ref>) and it might be the number of complicated natural relationships that keep these molecules off of the list of the most common dysregulated metabolites. The latter biomarker, N,N-dimethylsphingosine, is linked to pain () but was only found after it was honed in on using a multigroup analysis strategy. In this case the experimental design allowed for the extraction of a subtle metabolite change from the background of nonspecific responses. Another observation from these experiments is the number of unknowns being observed. The XCMS data are summarized in<ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. In this histogram we have plotted the 300 most commonlyConserved metabolic biomarkersdysregulated m/z values (the white bars indicate contaminant ions the black bars show identified metabolites the light gray bars are unknowns with MS/MS data and the dark gray bars are unknowns without MS/MS data). The picture given by this plot is that a significant number of the metabolite features that are commonly encountered are unknown. Additionally, we find a large proportion of the histogram represents known contaminates. This finding underscores the importance of proper sample handling and the identification of contamination sources (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Weber et al., 2012</ref>). These data are highly dynamic and will evolve with technological advances and changes in standard procedures. As technology will define metabolome coverage, it is likely that the current standard practices will be reflected in the METLIN search data. For example a relatively recent occurrence is the use of hydrophilic interaction chromatography (HILIC) separation technologies coupled to mass spectrometry (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Buszewski and Noga, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Spagou et al., 2010</ref>). HILIC is used for the analysis of polar metabolites as an alternative to the dominant reversed-phase liquid chromatography (RPLC). Indeed HILIC has been utilized to study central metabolism (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bajad et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Heiden et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Ivanisevic et al., 2013</ref>). Although RPLC is still by far the most utilized separation method, therefore METLIN search data results are likewise primarily driven by RPLC-MS, which generally involve hydrophobic molecules.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Concluding remarks</head><p>Overall this METLIN-XCMS data provides an opportunity to examine which pathways are commonly related to stress responses and those that reflect more specific responses. For example linoleic acid had a high search frequency in METLIN and appears in 273 manuscripts in the context of biomarkers, a result that is corroborated in our XCMS experimental results making it a conserved biomarker. That is to say it is a general marker for a system under stress that is conserved across many species under various perturbations. By making this data available we are hopefully providing other researchers with a template for biomarker discovery and translation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. A cumulative mass spectrum created from a million searches of the METLIN metabolite database. (Top) representation of queries logged from across the globe. (Bottom) The mass spectrum presents the total output of the searches that return METLIN identifications; queries that returned no METLIN IDs have been excluded from this plot (9 M). The x-axis represents the m/z searched and the y-axis the number of times that particular m/z has been searched. The inset shows the output of a METLIN query</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Top 24 searched metabolites. Putative identifications are based on accurate neutral mass with the number of potential matches are listed in parenthesis</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>This work was supported by The US National Institutes of Health R01 GM114368 &amp; R01CA170737 and The US Department of Energy DE-AC0205EH11231 Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 3721 Bioinformatics, 31(23), 2015, 3721–3724 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv475 Advance Access Publication Date: 13 August 2015 Discovery Note of regional racism across the United States (</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.E.Kurczy et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Fig. 3. Observed m/z values and frequency for the 300 most common metabolites in the meta-analysis of 2000 untargeted metabolomic experiments across a heterogeneous population of biological specimens and a wide spectrum of phenotypic conditions. The inset shows MS/MS matching the feature corrisponding to tryptophan</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biomarkers of fat and fatty acid intake</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Arab</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Nutr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="925" to="932" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Separation and quantitation of water soluble cellular metabolites by hydrophilic interaction chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">U</forename>
				<surname>Bajad</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chromatogr. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1125" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrophilic interaction liquid chromatography (HILIC)-a powerful separation technique</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Buszewski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Noga</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Bioanal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">402</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="247" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association between an Internet-based measure of area racism and black mortality</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Chae</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OUTLOOK The microeconomics of personalized medicine: today&apos;s challenge and tomorrow&apos;s promise</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Davis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Drug Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="286" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pitfalls and limitations in translation from biomarker discovery to clinical utility in predictive and personalised medicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Drucker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Krapfenbauer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EPMA J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting influenza epidemics using search engine query data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Ginsberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">457</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1012" to="1014" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive XCMS online: simplifying advanced metabolomic data processing and subsequent statistical analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Gowda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6931" to="6939" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence for an alternative glycolytic pathway in rapidly proliferating cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G V</forename>
				<surname>Heiden</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">329</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1492" to="1499" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolic profiles—gas-phase methods for analysis of metabolites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Horning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Horning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="802" to="809" />
			<date type="published" when="1971" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward omic scale metabolite profiling: a dual separation-mass spectrometry approach for coverage of lipid and central carbon metabolism</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Ivanisevic</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6876" to="6884" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MetAlign: interface-driven, versatile metabolomics tool for hyphenated full-scan mass spectrometry data preprocessing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Lommen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3079" to="3086" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolomic analysis and visualization engine for LC-MS data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Melamud</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9818" to="9826" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">X-Rank: a robust algorithm for small molecule identification using tandem mass spectrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Mylonas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7604" to="7610" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolomics implicates altered sphingolipids in chronic pain of neuropathic origin</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Patti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="234" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolomics: the apogee of the omics trilogy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Patti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="269" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative analysis of urine vapor and breath by gas–liquid partition chromatography</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Pauling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1971" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2374" to="2376" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MZmine 2: modular framework for processing, visualizing, and analyzing mass spectrometry-based molecular profile data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Pluskal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">395</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bring on the biomarkers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Poste</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">469</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">METLIN: a metabolite mass spectral database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ther. Drug Monitoring</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="747" to="751" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrophilic interaction chromatography coupled to MS for metabonomic/metabolomic studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Spagou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Sep. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="716" to="727" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">XCMS online: a web-based platform to process untargeted metabolomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Tautenhahn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5035" to="5039" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gut flora metabolism of phosphatidylcholine promotes cardiovascular disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">472</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MaConDa: a publicly accessible mass spectrometry contaminants database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J M</forename>
				<surname>Weber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2856" to="2857" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MetaboAnalyst 2.0—a comprehensive server for metabolomic data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Xia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Translational biomarker discovery in clinical metabolomics: an introductory tutorial</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Xia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metabolomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="280" to="299" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>