
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:59+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression Eoulsan: a cloud computing-based framework facilitating high throughput sequencing analyses</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Laurent</forename>
								<surname>Jourdren</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institut de Biologie de l&apos;ENS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">École normale supérieure</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">IBENS</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Inserm</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>U1024</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 8197</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-75005</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Maria</forename>
								<surname>Bernard</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institut de Biologie de l&apos;ENS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">École normale supérieure</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">IBENS</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Inserm</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>U1024</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 8197</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-75005</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Marie-Agnès</forename>
								<surname>Dillies</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Plate-forme Transcriptome et Epigénome</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Institut Pasteur</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>28 rue du Dr. Roux</addrLine>
									<postCode>75724, cedex 15</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Stéphane</forename>
								<surname>Le Crom</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institut de Biologie de l&apos;ENS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">École normale supérieure</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">IBENS</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Inserm</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>U1024</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 8197</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-75005</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Janet</forename>
								<surname>Kelso</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression Eoulsan: a cloud computing-based framework facilitating high throughput sequencing analyses</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1542" to="1543"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts165</idno>
					<note type="submission">Advance Access publication April 5, 2012 Received on November 19, 2011; revised on March 23, 2012; accepted on April 2, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [08:51 7/5/2012 Bioinformatics-bts165.tex] Page: 1542 1542–1543 Associate Editor: Availability and implementation: Eoulsan is implemented in Java, supported on Linux systems and distributed under the LGPL License at: http://transcriptome.ens.fr/eoulsan/ Contact: eoulsan@biologie.ens.fr Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We developed a modular and scalable framework called Eoulsan, based on the Hadoop implementation of the MapReduce algorithm dedicated to high-throughput sequencing data analysis. Eoulsan allows users to easily set up a cloud computing cluster and automate the analysis of several samples at once using various software solutions available. Our tests with Amazon Web Services demonstrated that the computation cost is linear with the number of instances booked as is the running time with the increasing amounts of data.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>High-throughput sequencing data analysis requires large computer clusters associated with expensive costs that are only profitable for large genomics centers. Outsourcing data analysis over cloud computing infrastructure is one alternative. Nevertheless, software that use distributed algorithm are not common among bioinformatics developers, and only few solutions have been made available for sequencing data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Langmead et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">McKenna et al., 2010</ref>). Here we present Eoulsan, an open source framework, to facilitate high-throughput sequencing data by the use of distributed computation. This software has been developed in order to automate the analysis of a large number of samples at once, simplify the configuration of the cloud computing infrastructure and work with various already available analysis solutions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">SOFTWARE IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>We first implemented Eoulsan for differential analysis of transcript expression. The workflow dedicated to this task includes 6 steps (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>). First, the reads generated from the sequencers are subjected to quality control filtering. Second, reads are mapped onto the reference genome. Currently four different mappers are embedded in Eoulsan: BWA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Li and Durbin, 2009</ref>), Bowtie (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Langmead et al., 2009b</ref>), SOAP2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Li et al., 2009</ref>) and GSNAP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Wu and Nacu, 2010</ref>). Third, alignments are filtered to keep only single matches on the genome. Fourth, transcript expression calculation is performed using mapped reads associated to an annotation file. Fifth, a normalization step is applied on the different samples in order to correct for biases with either the scaling normalization implemented in the edgeR R package for technical replicates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Robinson et al., 2010</ref>) or with the DESeq R package when biological replicates are available (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Anders and Huber, 2010</ref>). Sixth, detection of differential expression is carried out on the biological entities described in the annotation file by applying a Fisher's Exact Test for technical replicates or, the DESeq R package for biological replicates. Eoulsan can be run under three modes: standalone, local cluster or cloud computing on Amazon Elastic MapReduce (EMR). The last two execution modes have been implemented using the Hadoop framework, an open source implementation of a MapReduce programming model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Taylor, 2010</ref>). In practice, the distributed mode of Eoulsan performs as described in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CLOUD COMPUTING ASSESSMENT</head><p>We tested Eoulsan on Amazon Web Services (AWS) with 8 mouse samples from RNA-Seq data (for a total of 188 millions reads) using different read mappers embedded in the workflow. We estimated the time needed to perform the calculation process and the cost charged by AWS on three different Elastic Compute Cloud (EC2) virtual machine types (called instance by AWS): m1.large, m1.xlarge and c1.xlarge (see Supplementary Table S1 for instance selection). The results are presented on Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S2</ref>and in Supplementary Table S2. If we compare the time spent, the fastest result is obtained from the c1.xlarge instance whatever the mapper used. In terms of costs, the computation is always more expensive using m1.xlarge instances with m1.large remaining the most economical choice. One interest of using cloud computing facilities is to speed up the calculation process by using a large number of computers at once. To evaluate this possibility, we tested how the number of booked instances influences the calculation process (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>Copyedited by: TRJdown the EC2 cluster and the user gets back the results from S3 to the local computer where the final statistical analysis is performed (normalization and differential analysis). and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S3</ref>). We observed that the whole time spent for the calculations strongly drop with low instance number and remained close to linear with more than five instances booked. However, one question remains. How many instances do we need to use for data analysis? This is critical as each hourly booked EC2 instance costs a fixed price. Our tests demonstrate that the cost per hour is linear over the number of instances used (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>). This means that the number of instances can be increased in order to speed up the data analysis process without the risk to fall in a suboptimal configuration. Finally, we assessed the impact of an increase in raw data on the computation time by running Eoulsan with 16 and 32 samples of 23.5 millions of reads each, respectively, 376 and 752 millions of total reads (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S5</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S4</ref>). We saw that the relationship between running time and number of samples is also linear (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6</ref>). This demonstrates that Eoulsan is able to handle the increase in raw data coming from future evolutions of Illumina sequencing devices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>With our framework, we aimed to facilitate high-throughput sequencing analysis on cloud computing services with an automatic, modular and efficient tool. This approach differs from other solutions already available for distributed calculation such as Myrna, CloudBurst or Crossbow (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Langmead et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Langmead et al., 2009a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Schatz, 2009</ref>), where the cloud computing implementation is made around a unique analysis solution. In addition, Eoulsan is also complementary to the customizable Galaxy server solution as it allows for batch analyses and it contains a full automation process able to handle external file locations and distributed file system.</p><p>More generally, we have first implemented an automated RNA-Seq analysis pipeline but all the tools are already included within Eoulsan for other applications such as SNP calling or ChIP Peak analysis. The Java plug-in system we developed as well as the full documentation we provide, allow for user contribution by the integration of other available solution in Eoulsan. The distributed calculation process we used is based on Hadoop and it can be installed on numerous cluster server configurations. We made our proof of concept using AWS solution as it includes EMR, an advanced service based on EC2 that easily allows Hadoop distributed computation solutions to be deployed. However, we are working to make our software independent of EMR to work directly on EC2 services. Such an evolution will allow Eoulsan to be run on any other cloud computing solutions such as Open Source initiatives like OpenNebula or OpenStack. This would open future possibilities by creating regional genomic computer infrastructures (like iPlant for example) to be shared among several local highthroughput sequencing users. With a dedicated high-speed network, this can speed up the time transfer process. In addition, this could also favor the standardization of analysis pipelines developed from the bioinformatics community, making high-throughput sequencing technologies really accessible for a wide audience.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [08:51 7/5/2012 Bioinformatics-bts165.tex] Page: 1543 1542–1543 Eoulsan Fig. 1. Eoulsan is launched from the user local computer where it uploads to S3 all the data needed to perform the analysis. 1. AWS starts-up the EC2 cluster by booking virtual machines (represented by squares with one master node in gray) and copies the Hadoop distribution using the Amazon EMR system. 2. The data needed for the analysis are transferred from S3 to the EC2 cluster. 3. Eoulsan launches read filtering, mapping and alignment filtering steps. 4. It performs expression estimation. Both these two steps use a MapReduce strategy. 5. Results are downloaded back to S3. 6. AWS shuts</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Anders</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Huber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Searching for SNPs with cloud computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Langmead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">134</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Langmead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloud-scale RNA-sequencing differential expression analysis with Myrna</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Langmead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">83</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast and accurate short read alignment with BurrowsWheeler transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Durbin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1754" to="1760" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SOAP2: an improved ultrafast tool for short read alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1966" to="1967" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genome analysis toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Mckenna</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1297" to="1303" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">edgeR: a bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CloudBurst: highly sensitive read mapping with MapReduce</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Schatz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1363" to="1369" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An overview of the Hadoop/MapReduce/HBase framework and its current applications in bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Taylor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 12</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast and SNP-tolerant detection of complex variants and splicing in short reads</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Nacu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="873" to="881" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>