
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:52+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics ETAscape: analyzing protein networks to predict enzymatic function and substrates in Cytoscape</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Benjamin</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Bachman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departments of Molecular and Human Genetics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Structural and Computational Biology and Molecular Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>One Baylor Plaza</addrLine>
									<postCode>77030</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">W. M. Keck Center for Interdisciplinary Bioscience Training</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>77005</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eric</forename>
								<surname>Venner</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departments of Molecular and Human Genetics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Structural and Computational Biology and Molecular Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>One Baylor Plaza</addrLine>
									<postCode>77030</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rhonald</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Lua</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departments of Molecular and Human Genetics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Serkan</forename>
								<surname>Erdin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departments of Molecular and Human Genetics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Olivier</forename>
								<surname>Lichtarge</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>lichtarge@bcm.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departments of Molecular and Human Genetics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Structural and Computational Biology and Molecular Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>One Baylor Plaza</addrLine>
									<postCode>77030</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">W. M. Keck Center for Interdisciplinary Bioscience Training</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>77005</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics ETAscape: analyzing protein networks to predict enzymatic function and substrates in Cytoscape</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2186" to="2188"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts331</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 21, 2012; revised on May 11, 2012; accepted on May 30, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [19:00 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts331.tex] Page: 2186 2186–2188 Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Availability: The ETA Network Plugin is available publicly for download at http://mammoth.bcm.tmc.edu/networks/. Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Most proteins lack experimentally validated functions. To address this problem, we implemented the Evolutionary Trace Annotation (ETA) method in the Cytoscape network visualization environment. The result is the ETAscape plugin, which builds a structural genomics network based on local structural and evolutionary similarities among proteins and then globally diffuses known annotations across the resulting network. The plugin displays these novel functional annotations, their confidence, the molecular basis for individual matches and the set of matches that lead to a prediction.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The Structural Genomics Initiative (SGI) generates abundant structural data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Erdin et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Valencia, 2005</ref>), but many of these structures lack annotation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Redfern et al., 2008</ref>). Computational methods that match small structural motifs of functionally important residues (a template) and suggest a function when the geometry is close enough (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Laskowski et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Redfern et al., 2009</ref>) are an especially promising way to approach this problem. A template can be constructed from prior knowledge of functional residues and mechanisms, or it can be created de novo by Evolutionary Trace (ET) analysis, which predicts functionally relevant amino acids and pinpoints functional sites using evolutionary principles (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Lichtarge et al., 1996</ref>). ET accuracy has been thoroughly tested both experimentally (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Adikesavan et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Rodriguez et al., 2010</ref>) and computationally (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Mihalek et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Res et al., 2005</ref>). Evolutionary Trace Annotation (ETA) first maps the evolutionary importance of each residue onto a structure and selects a cluster of important surface residues as the template. It then seeks a match that is similar both geometrically and evolutionarily in protein structures with known function. These ETA templates usually overlap with † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. * To whom correspondence should be addressed. catalytic sites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Ward et al., 2008</ref>) and identify function with 87% accuracy at 61% coverage (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kristensen et al., 2008</ref>). Using a network in which structures form the nodes and ETA matches form the edges helps to overcome limitations from sparse functional data. We make predictions by allowing Enzyme Commision (EC) numbers to 'diffuse' through the network according to the cost function:</p><formula>i (y i −f i ) 2 +α i,j w ij (f i −f j ) 2 (1)</formula><p>where the elements of y are 1, 0 or −1 depending on whether a protein is known to have, known not to have or is unknown to have a particular EC number. After minimization, f contains the 'diffused' values. The first term reflects the desire to not lose known information, and penalizes nodes whose function differs before and after diffusion. The second term reflects the fact that we expect neighboring proteins in this network to have similar functions, and punishes neighbors where this is not the case according to the edge weight. Repeating this process for all ECs yields a prediction for each possible function at each node. By normalizing the prediction scores across all nodes with unknown function, we create a prediction confidence. In benchmarks, the accuracy of this ETA diffusion network was &gt;97% at 50% coverage, allowing the prediction and experimental confirmation of the function of an unannotated Staphylococcus aureus protein (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Venner et al., 2010</ref>). This method is now made widely available and more transparent by embedding it into the Cytoscape network visualization environment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Smoot et al., 2011</ref>). The ETAscape plugin allows users to view ETA networks, add proteins, make novel predictions, as well as view annotations, ETA templates and protein structures, adding to a public suite of ET tools that make functional site analysis and function prediction transparent (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lua and Lichtarge, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Ward et al., 2009</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">OVERVIEW OF ETASCAPE</head><p>The plugin is available from mammoth.bcm.tmc.edu/networks. All commands are available as menu options, and a manual and tutorial video are available from the download page. A starting network of ETA matches between a subset of the Protein Data Bank (PDB) filtered for 90% sequence identity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Berman et al., 2000</ref>) is included with the plugin. Node colors are based on known enzymatic function and the layout clusters similar proteins. ETA networks subdivide intoshows the protein structure for 2f2gB and its mutual template match to 1rtwD (2f2gB's template is shown in blue and 1rtwD's is shown in red, purple indicates shared residues) a large number of small networks due to the specificity filters. Rightclicking a node provides links to PDBsum (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Laskowski, 2009</ref>) and the ET Server. The 'Add new node to Network' menu option queries the ETA Server (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Ward et al., 2009</ref>), which opens in a browser and suggests an ET template that the user may customize. This template is then matched against proteins in the network and matches are filtered as described previously (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Ward et al., 2008</ref>). Modified networks may be saved and later reloaded. Structures and ETA templates can be opened in Jmol (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Hanson, 2010</ref>) windows by selecting nodes and running the 'Show Templates' menu option. The 'Run Diffusion' menu option predicts the function of unannotated proteins with our diffusion model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Venner et al., 2010</ref>). Novel annotations and prediction confidences are available in the node attribute browser. The Show Influencing Proteins menu command shows proteins with the largest influence on the predicted function of the selected protein, often including nodes with strong indirect connections. After making predictions, users can export them to a file. As an example, the plugin predicts that a protein expressed from gene locus At3g16990 in Arabidopsis thaliana (PDB ID 2f2gB), an SGI protein of unknown function, is a thiamine pyridinylase with Enzyme Classification number EC 2.5.1.2. (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). Although the direct matches lack functional annotation, the software arrives at this prediction by diffusing the function across the intermediate links. There is one other function present in the subnetwork in proximity to the query protein (Aminopyrimidine aminohydrolase, EC 3.5.99.2). Interestingly, even though they are distinct reactions, both functions share the substrate Thiamine, possibly explaining the detected template similarity. 2f2gBs direct matches are well below the reliable homology range with sequence identities of 16% with 1rtwD and 14% with 1z72B. As observed previously (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Ward et al., 2008</ref>), the direct matches share overall structural similarity: many of the proteins in this cluster belong to the CATH heme oxygenase superfamily.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>The ETAscape plugin extends an existing suite of protein function annotation tools to infer functional residues, identify functional sites and predict protein function (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lua and Lichtarge, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Ward et al., 2009</ref>). This tool pairs state-of-the-art network analysis with network visualization, putting the ability to generate novel predictions into the hands of researchers. Perhaps more importantly, it provides insight into the basis for those predictions.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Screen capture of the plugin. Nodes are proteins, with colors encoding the first two EC numbers. Edges are ETA template matches and indicate local structural and evolutionary similarity. Two unknown protein structures (yellow nodes in center) are highlighted and discussed in the Overview of ETAscape section below. A Jmol window (top right) shows the protein structure for 2f2gB and its mutual template match to 1rtwD (2f2gB's template is shown in blue and 1rtwD's is shown in red, purple indicates shared residues)</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding:</head><p>The authors gratefully acknowledge grant support from the National Institute of Health, the National Science Foundation</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">197</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>bts331. .tex]</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2188" to="2186" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Bachman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">National Institute of Health, NIH GM079656 and GM066099; National Science Foundation, NSF, CCF 0905536 and DBI 1062455; and from the National Library of Medicine NLM T15LM007093 through the Gulf Coast Consortia&apos;s Keck Center</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Conflict. of Interest: none declared</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">REFERENCES</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Separation of recombination and SOS response in escherichia coli RecA suggests LexA interaction sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Adikesavan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002244</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The protein data bank</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Berman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein function prediction: towards integration of similarity metrics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Erdin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="180" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Jmol a paradigm shift in crystallographic visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Hanson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Crystallogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1250" to="1260" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of enzyme function based on 3D templates of evolutionarily important amino acids</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Kristensen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ProFunc: a server for predicting protein function from 3D structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Laskowski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PDBsum new things</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Laskowski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="359" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An evolutionary trace method defines binding surfaces common to protein families</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Lichtarge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">257</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="342" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PyETV: a PyMOL evolutionary trace viewer to analyze functional site predictions in protein complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Lua</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Lichtarge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2981" to="2982" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A family of evolution-entropy hybrid methods for ranking protein residues by importance</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Mihalek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">336</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1265" to="1282" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the structure and function paradigm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Redfern</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="394" to="402" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FLORA: a novel method to predict protein function from structure in diverse superfamilies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Redfern</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000485</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An evolution based classifier for prediction of protein interfaces without using protein structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Res</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2496" to="2501" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolution-guided discovery and recoding of allosteric pathway specificity determinants in psychoactive bioamine receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Rodriguez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci</title>
		<meeting>. Nat. Acad. Sci</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7787" to="7792" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytoscape 2.8: new features for data integration and network visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Smoot</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="432" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic annotation of protein function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Valencia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate protein structure annotation through competitive diffusion of enzymatic functions over a network of local evolutionary similarities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Venner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14286</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">De-orphaning the structural proteome through reciprocal comparison of evolutionarily important structural features</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Ward</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2136</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolutionary trace annotation server: automated enzyme function prediction in protein structures using 3D templates</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Ward</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1426" to="1427" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>