
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:39+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology Evaluating the Drosophila Bicoid morphogen gradient system through dissecting the noise in transcriptional bursts</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">7 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Feng</forename>
								<surname>He</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jie</forename>
								<surname>Ren</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Center of Developmental Biology and Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Cell Proliferation and Differentiation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Peking University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100871</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P.R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wei</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jun</forename>
								<surname>Ma</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Developmental Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Cincinnati Children&apos;s Research Foundation</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3333 Burnet Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>45229</postCode>
									<settlement>Cincinnati</settlement>
									<region>OH</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Olga</forename>
								<surname>Troyanskaya</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology Evaluating the Drosophila Bicoid morphogen gradient system through dissecting the noise in transcriptional bursts</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="970" to="975"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">7 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts068</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on November 20, 2011; revised on January 9, 2012; accepted on January 30, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [12:38 12/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts068.tex] Page: 970 970–975 Associate Editor: Contact: jun.ma@cchmc.org Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: We describe a statistical model to dissect the noise in transcriptional bursts in a developmental system. Results: We assume that, at any given moment of time, each copy of a native gene inside a cell can exist in either a bursting (active) or non-bursting (inactive) state. The experimentally measured total noise in the transcriptional states of a gene in a population of cells can be mathematically dissected into two contributing components: internal and external. While internal noise quantifies the stochastic nature of transcriptional bursts, external noise is caused by cell-to-cell differences including fluctuations in activator concentration. We use our developed methods to analyze the Drosophila Bicoid (Bcd) morphogen gradient system. For its target gene hunchback (hb), the noise properties can be recapitulated by a simplified gene regulatory model in which Bcd acts as the only input, suggesting that the external noise in hb transcription is primarily derived from fluctuations in the Bcd activator input. However, such a simplified gene regulatory model is insufficient to predict the noise properties of another Bcd target gene, orthodenticle (otd), suggesting that otd transcription is sensitive to additional external fluctuations beyond those in Bcd. Our results show that analysis of the relationship between input and output noise can reveal important insights into how a morphogen gradient system works. Our study also advances the knowledge about transcription at a fundamental level.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Transcription is an inherently noisy molecular process that takes place as burst-like events (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Boettiger and Levine, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Eldar and Elowitz, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Friedman et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Ma, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Raj et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">To and Maheshri, 2010</ref>). How the incoherent transcriptional bursts lead to coherent and precise gene expression patterns during development is a fundamental question and a subject of intense investigations (Martinez<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Arias and Hayward, 2006</ref>). It has been suggested that averaging over time and/or space allows a biological system to gain coherence and improve expression boundary precision (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Erdmann et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gregor et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">He et al., 2010a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Okabe-Oho et al., *</ref>To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p><p>2009;<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Tostevin et al., 2007</ref>). To fully understand how precise gene expression patterns are achieved in response to morphogen inputs, it is necessary to have methods that can evaluate the experimentally detected transcriptional bursts before such averaging takes place. Here we develop a statistical model for such a purpose, where we mathematically dissect the experimentally measured total noise into the internal and external components. We use our model to analyze our experimental data extracted from early Drosophila embryos (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al., 2011</ref>), where both the nuclear concentrations of the activator Bicoid (Bcd) and the transcriptional states of its target genes hunchback (hb) and orthodenticle (otd) are simultaneously measured. We show that the dissected external noise in hb transcriptional bursts can be implicitly derived from the measured Bcd input noise. In contrast, additional input noise is required to account for both the measured total noise and the dissected external noise in otd transcription. These results suggest that, although Bcd acts as a direct and sustained input for both otd and hb transcription (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Liu et al., 2011</ref>), these two target genes are distinct from each other. Our findings are consistent with recent studies (<ref type="bibr">Kim et al., 2011a, b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Lohr et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Ochoa-Espinosa et al., 2009</ref>), suggesting that, in addition to Bcd, otd transcription also responds to other input(s) and, thus, is sensitive to additional external fluctuations. Our study provides an example illustrating the use of dissecting experimentally measured transcriptional noise in understanding the mechanistic operations of a native morphogen gradient system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>To obtain our published dataset (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al., 2011</ref>), we combined fluorescence in situ hybridization with immunostaining on 1–4 h w 1118 embryos. Here, we used flattened embryos to maximize the number of nuclei per embryo and we took ∼6 Confocal z-section images in 0.5 μm intervals to capture all the intron dots. Our imaging setting was maintained the same for different embryos on different slides with all images captured in a single imaging cycle. Thus the datasets under our experimental conditions have the same molecule number-to-intensity rescaling factors, which make it possible to combine the data extracted from different embryos and group nuclei according to their A–P positions. In our detection for intron dots, the definition of thresholds is according to<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al. (2011)</ref>and the threshold setting was optimized to detect a stable pattern of the intron dot expression. A comparison between machine-recognized intron dots and human-recognized dots indicates an uncertainty of 8% in our analysis. See<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al. (2011)</ref>for further technical details and intron dot data quality, and<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">He et al. (2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">He et al. ( , 2010a</ref>) for Bcd data quality under our experimental conditions. In our current analysis, we use each detected intron dot to denote a gene copy that is actively</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">A statistical model for evaluating transcriptional noise</head><p>Let us consider a standard diploid cell that has two identical copies of a gene. At a given moment of time, i.e. in a snapshot of the cell, each copy can exist in either an actively-transcribing (bursting) or non-transcribing (non-bursting) state. Experimentally, actively transcribing gene copies can be detected as 'intron dots' (see Section 2 and further on for experimental details). We define gene copies that are actively transcribing as active copies and those that are not as inactive copies. We assume that both copies of the gene in this cell are independent of each other. They have an identical probability p of existing as active copies. Thus, the probability of this cell to have k active copies of the gene in a snapshot can be expressed as in Equation (1). The mean and noise (i.e. fractional variance) of the numbers of active copies in this cell are ρ = 2p and η 2 = (1−p)/2p.</p><formula>p(k) = 2 k p k (1−p) 2−k , for k ∈ {0, 1, 2} (1)</formula><p>We then consider a population of N cells. We assume that all copies of the gene in this population are independent. For the i-th cell in this population, we denote the probability of its gene copies existing as active copies by p i. We now evaluate all copies of the gene in all the cells in this population. The mean and noise of number of active copies per cell can be expressed, respectively, as in Equations (2)</p><p>and (3).</p><formula>ρ ≡ 2p = 2 N i=N 1 p i (2)</formula><formula>η 2 tot ≡ 1 ρ 2 N i=N 1 k=2 0 2 k p k i (1−p i ) 2−k (k −2p i ) 2 (3) = 4 ρ 2 N i=N 1 (p i −p) 2 + 2 ρ 2 N i=N 1 p i (1−p i ) = p 2 −p 2 p 2 + p− p 2 2p 2 ≡ η 2 ext +η 2 int In Equation (3)</formula><p>, the total noise of the stated system, η tot , is a simple sum of two components. One component is from the noise in p, which is induced by cell-to-cell differences that we define as external noise, η ext. The other contribution, which we define as internal noise, η int , is proportional to the variance of the intrinsic binomial distribution of the binary states, which is calculated for each cell and then averaged over the entire population of cells. The quantity p 2 can be calculated as:</p><formula>p 2 = ρ 2 (1+η 2 tot )−ρ.</formula><formula>(4)</formula><p>By experimentally measuring the mean number of active copies (ρ) and its total noise (η tot ), we can obtain both η ext and η int as:</p><formula>η 2 ext =− 2 ρ +1+2η 2 tot (5)</formula><formula>η 2 int =</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Propagation of activator input noise to transcriptional noise</head><p>We now consider the external noise in an ideal, simplified gene regulatory system where an activator is the only input for its target gene's transcriptional output. As before (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gregor et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">He et al., 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al., , 2011</ref>), we use a Hill function to describe the relationship between the expected probability of a gene copy to exist as an active copy (p) and the activator concentration inside the nucleus of a cell (B):</p><formula>p(B) = p max 1+(B/K) −h ,</formula><formula>(7)</formula><p>where p max , K and h are, respectively, the maximal burst probability, the activator concentration at half maximal burst probability and the Hill coefficient. These values can be adjusted in theoretical studies for evaluating the behavior of different target genes or different transcription system. They can also be calculated directly from experimental data (see below). Equation</p><p>(7) makes it possible, similar to propagation of errors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gregor et al., 2007</ref>), to directly convert fluctuations in activator concentration, η B = δB/B, to the variance of the burst probability of its target gene:</p><formula>δ p = δB d p dB ≈ η B hp(1− p p max ). (8)</formula><p>Copyedited<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1A</ref>shows that η ext increases as the normalized noise strength (v/K) increases.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1B</ref>shows that, at a given v/K, the effect of h on η ext is sensitive to ρ.</p><p>As defined in Equation (3), the external noise (η ext ) in the transcriptional bursts of the target gene is the noise in p:</p><formula>η ext ≡ δ p p ≈ η B h(1− ρ ρ max ), (9)</formula><p>where ρ max = 2 p max. To facilitate calculations in a theoretical analysis, we assume (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">He et al., 2010a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Tkacik et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Tostevin et al., 2007</ref>) that the noise in the nuclear concentration of this activator, B, is Poissonian,</p><formula>η 2 B = v/B</formula><p>, where v is referred to as the noise strength. Applying this distribution of η B to Equation (9) leads to the expression of η ext as a function of ρ:<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>shows η ext , converted from activator input noise according to Equation (10), as a function of ρ/ρ max .<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1A</ref>and B show the effects of v/K and h, respectively, on η ext. Thus, η ext can be calculated by two distinct methods: one that is based on the active and inactive states of the gene copies with the noise in transcription dissected according to Equation (5), and another that is based on the activator input noise that is converted to η ext using the input– output relationship in Equation (10). These two calculations should arrive at the same η ext value in the ideal, simplified gene regulatory system. We will use this property of an ideal, simplified system to evaluate those of the real biological systems. In particular, if the η ext values calculated from these two methods are similar, it would suggest that the actual biological system can be approximated by the simplified gene regulatory system, but a significant deviation between these two values would be indicative of oversimplification of the real biological system.</p><formula>η 2 ext = vh 2 K ( ρ max ρ −1) 1/h (1− ρ ρ max ) 2 .</formula><formula>(10)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Evaluation of hb transcription data suggests a dominant role of Bcd input</head><p>We now evaluate experimental data extracted from early Drosophila embryos (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al., 2011</ref>). Bcd is a transcriptional activator that forms an anterior-to-posterior (A–P) gradient (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Driever and Nusslein-Volhard, 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Houchmandzadeh et al., 2002</ref>). It instructs embryonic patterning by activating its target genes in a concentration-dependent manner (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Ephrussi and St Johnston, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Grimm et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Liu et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Porcher and Dostatni, 2010</ref>). During the period of Bcd action (i.e. at the syncytial stage of embryonic development), all nuclei undergo synchronous mitotic divisions and, thus, nuclear Bcd concentration represents a primary source of nucleus-to-nucleus differences relevant to Bcd target gene transcription. In our simplified gene regulatory model, cell-to-cell differences arise solely from activator concentration differences. In addition, our previous analyses of hb expression profiles in embryos with perturbed Bcd gradient properties suggest that Bcd acts as a dominant input at early nuclear cycle 14, a time for our current analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cheung et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">He et al., 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">He et al., , 2010a</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">He et al., , 2010b</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al., , 2011</ref>;<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Liu and Ma, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Liu et al., 2011</ref>). At earlier cycles, maternal Hb acts as an additional input for zygotic hb transcription (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Porcher et al., 2010</ref>). In our simplified gene regulatory model, the activator is the only input for the active copies of its target gene. These considerations suggest that hb represents an excellent candidate of a native Bcd target gene suitable for evaluation against the simplified gene regulatory model. As detailed previously (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al., 2011</ref>), our experimental dataset consists of the Bcd concentration (in arbitrary units) and the hb transcriptional states of individual nuclei of fixed wild-type (wt) embryos. Currently this is the only high-quality combined dataset that contains both the Bcd input data and the hb transcriptional states in embryos. In our experiments, we used an intronic probe to detect the nascent hb transcripts, with a simultaneous detection of Bcd through immunostaining. Images of these embryos thus capture, as in snapshots, distinct fluorescent dots, referred to as the hb intron dots (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al., 2011</ref>). The reliability of both Bcd input data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">He et al., 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">He et al., , 2010a</ref>) and the intron dot data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al., 2011</ref>) under our experimental conditions has been described previously. For our current analysis, we count the number of the hb intron dots in individual nuclei from the relevant parts of individual embryos. Here, we use a detected hb intron dot to denote an active copy of the hb gene. We sort our data by binning them according to the A–P position, and calculate the mean (ρ) and noise (η tot ) of active copies for nuclei within the bins. Using Equations (5) and</p><p>(6), we dissect η tot into η ext and η int for each bin.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2A</ref>shows a scatter plot (on log–log scale) of the measured η tot (blue circles) and the dissected η ext (green diamonds) and η int (red squares) as a function of ρ.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2A</ref>also shows our theoretical predictions (solid lines) calculated from Equation (10) using the following values that are derived from fitting the experimental data (see legends): h = 6, v = 0.5 and K = 6. Our results show a resemblance between the measured/dissected noise profiles and those calculated theoretically. They suggest that the experimentally measured (and dissected) noise properties for hb transcription are broadly similar to those predicted theoretically in a simplified gene regulatory model (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>legend for adjusted R 2-values and below for an experimental system with contracting behaviors). In our theoretical predictions shown as solid lines in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure  2A</ref>, a Poissonian distribution of Bcd concentration fluctuations is assumed. To evaluate whether our conclusions are dependent on this assumption, we directly converted experimentally measured Bcd input noise to η ext using Equation (9) without such an assumption.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2B</ref>shows<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al., 2011</ref>). Since fluctuations in Bcd concentration are dominated by Poisson-like molecular noise (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">He et al., 2010a</ref>), we perform a simple fitting of the experimentally measured Bcd noise to Poissonian distribution for extracting v-values.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2B</ref>and D are scatter plots of dissected η ext (same as in Figures 2A and C but showing data only from the activation boundary regions for better data spread) against converted η ext (see text for details). Here, Figures 2B and C are for hb and otd, respectively. A linear regression line is also shown (with the equation in the inset box) for each panel.. The two η ext values at individual A–P positions exhibit good agreement with each other, suggesting that, consistent with a previous study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">He et al., 2010a</ref>), molecular (Poissonian) fluctuations in Bcd concentration are a dominant source of the measured Bcd noise in relevant parts of the embryos under our experimental conditions. Furthermore, as discussed above, the experimentally measured (and dissected) noise properties of the hb transcription system are well approximated by our simplified gene regulatory model. Together, they further support the suggestion that the nucleus-to-nucleus fluctuations in Bcd concentration are a dominant source of the external noise in hb transcriptional bursts (see also<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Holloway et al., 2011</ref>). A recent theoretical study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Saunders and Howard, 2009</ref>) has suggested that an exponential morphogen gradient may be evolutionarily advantageous because of its ability to balance between the external and internal sources of noise for achieving precise target gene expression boundaries. Our results show that the hb boundary position (marked by an arrowhead in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2A</ref>) coincides with a convergence of noise profiles that results in a more balanced contribution of η ext and η int. These results suggest that, based on Saunders and<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Howard (2009)</ref>, the Bcd gradient system in wt embryos may be optimal for the hb boundary precision.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Drosophila Bicoid morphogen gradient system</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>η</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Dissection of otd transcriptional noise suggests a role of additional input(s)</head><p>In addition to hb, Bcd also activates the expression of another target gene otd in early Drosophila embryos (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Gao and Finkelstein, 1998</ref>). Unlike hb, the Bcd-activated otd expression boundary position is much closer to the anterior of the embryo. Although Bcd also acts as a direct and sustained input for otd transcription (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al., 2011</ref>), recent studies suggest that otd expression is subject to regulation by both the Bcd gradient and the terminal system inputs mediated by a mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway (<ref type="bibr">Kim et al., 2011a, b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Lohr et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Ochoa-Espinosa et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Porcher and Dostatni, 2010</ref>). Thus, the otd transcriptional system may significantly deviate from our simplified gene regulatory model, where an activator is assumed to be the only input for its target gene transcription. To test this idea, we analyze our otd data in a manner identical to our hb analysis described above. As discussed in Supplementary Material and above, male embryos have a single copy of otd (i.e. c = 1) and, thus, such data are not suitable for the noise dissection. Here, we present our analysis of the otd intron dot data from female embryos.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2C</ref>shows the measured η tot (blue circles) and dissected η int (red squares) and η ext (green diamonds) in otd intron dot number. It also shows the theoretically predicted noise profiles (solid lines) for otd transcription based on our simplified gene regulatory model using the following values derived from fitting the experimental data (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>legend): h = 4, v = 0.5 and K = 15. These results show that, in contrast to hb (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2A</ref>), the external noise in otd transcription dissected from experimental data (green diamonds) is significantly higher than what is theoretically predicted (green line). As discussed above, these results suggest that, in addition to the Bcd input noise, otd transcription is sensitive to other source(s) of input (external) noise missing in our simplified gene regulatory model.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2C</ref>further shows that, unlike the hb transcriptional system, theoretically predicted η tot and η int also deviate from the measured/dissected values. To further evaluate the otd transcriptional system, we plot in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2D</ref>the dissected η ext against the converted η ext , values calculated by the two different methods for different A–P positions (see above). While dissected η ext is much higher than converted η ext in absolute values, they are correlated with each other. These results suggest that the proposed additional input (external) noise for otd transcription is correlated with Bcd input noise. We currently do not know the exact source of this noise. It is interesting to note that recent studies have revealed a retroactive regulatory mechanism where Bcd, a MAPK substrate, can in turn affect MAPK activity and its availability to other substrates (<ref type="bibr">Kim et al., 2011a, b</ref>). It remains to be investigated whether the retroactivity of Bcd on MAPK may represent a potential mechanism that can lead to an 'amplification' of the Bcd input noise in term of otd transcription.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F.He et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Our analysis of the noise properties of transcriptional bursts in response to an activator input provides a useful framework for investigating how developmental decisions are made. An important feature of our statistical model is that it does not require knowledge about, or modeling of, the specific molecular steps leading to such stochastic bursts. The feasibility to capture the actively-transcribing copies of a variety of native genes in early Drosophila embryos (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Boettiger and Levine, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Pare et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Wilkie et al., 1999</ref>) suggests that our model may be of general use in evaluating other transcriptional systems. As shown in our current study, dissection of noise in transcription, coupled with the simultaneous measurement of the activator input noise, can provide critical insights—at a systems level—into whether the activator in hand is a dominant input for a gene's transcription in a native developmental system. Understanding the relationship between the morphogen input and target genes' transcriptional output is crucial to advancing the morphogen concept, a cornerstone of developmental biology (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kerszberg and Wolpert, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Lander, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Wartlick et al., 2009</ref>). These results suggest that, consistent with our recent studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cheung et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">He et al., 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">He et al., , 2010a</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">He et al., , 2010b</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">He et al., , 2011</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Liu et al., 2011</ref>), Bcd is a dominant input for hb expression at the time of our analysis. The observed properties for hb contrast with those of otd, suggesting the contribution of another input(s) for otd transcription. Together, our findings represent an important step toward enhancing our knowledge of morphogen action at a systems level. Our study also advances our knowledge about transcription at a fundamental level. As discussed recently (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hilfinger and Paulsson, 2011</ref>), in dual-reporter studies performed in single cell systems, cellto-cell differences other than activator concentration differences, e.g. cell cycle stage differences, are also included in the extrinsic component of transcriptional noise. The nuclei in the embryos that we analyzed are nearly synchronous with regard to cell cycle stage. This special property has contributed to our ability to document experimentally, for the first time to our knowledge, that the external noise of a gene's transcription can be explained by the activator input noise.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Parameters affecting noise propagation. Activator input noise is converted to external noise (η ext ) in target gene transcription based on Equation (10) in a simplified gene regulatory model. Here, η ext is shown as a function of ρ i , the mean number of active copies. The effects of parameters that affect noise propagation are also shown. Such parameters include the activator noise strength (v), the activator threshold concentration (K) and the Hill coefficient (h). Figure 1A shows that η ext increases as the normalized noise strength (v/K) increases. Figure 1B shows that, at a given v/K, the effect of h on η ext is sensitive to ρ.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>a scatter plot of η ext values calculated by two distinct methods (see above): one from the measured noise in hb intron dot number through Equation (5) (shown as the dissected Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [12:38 12/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts068.tex] Page: 973 970–975</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. hb and otd have distinct noise properties in relation to the Bcd input noise. The experimentally measured η tot (blue circles) in hb (A) and otd (C) intron dot numbers is dissected into η ext (green diamonds) and η int (red squares) according to Equations (5) and (6), and the results are plotted against ρ. Solid lines are theoretical predictions based on Equation (10) in the simplified gene regulatory model. The adjusted R 2-values of fitting the experimental data with the model for η ext ,η int and η tot of hb are, respectively: 0.85, 0.99 and 1.00; the adjusted R 2-values for η ext , η int and η tot of otd are, respectively: −0.48, 0.97 and 0.98. The negative R 2 suggests that, constrained by the measured parameter values, the model cannot predict η ext of otd. Arrowheads show the boundary positions of ρ = ρ max /2. Here, K–values are measured as the mean Bcd concentrations at the marked boundary positions and h–values are extracted by fitting Equation (7) with the experimentally measured B–ρ profiles (He et al., 2011). Since fluctuations in Bcd concentration are dominated by Poisson-like molecular noise (He et al., 2010a), we perform a simple fitting of the experimentally measured Bcd noise to Poissonian distribution for extracting v-values. Figure 2B and D are scatter plots of dissected η ext (same as in Figures 2A and C but showing data only from the activation boundary regions for better data spread) against converted η ext (see text for details). Here, Figures 2B and C are for hb and otd, respectively. A linear regression line is also shown (with the equation in the inset box) for each panel.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><figDesc>ext in figure) and another converted from the experimentally measured Bcd noise through Equation (9) (shown as the converted η ext in figure)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [12:38 12/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts068.tex] Page: 974 970–975</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> ρ −1−η 2 tot. (6) In Supplementary Material, we present a general case of noise dissection in cells with c identical copies of a gene. As discussed there, for genes with a single copy per cell (c = 1), such as X-linked genes in Drosophila males, the quantity p 2 cannot be measured and, consequently, η ext and η int cannot be dissected in our model. The approach described above for noise dissection is broadly analogous to the previous concepts developed for single-cell systems (Elowitz et al., 2002; Hilfinger and Paulsson, 2011; Raser and O&apos;Shea, 2004; Raser and O&apos;Shea, 2005; Swain et al., 2002; Thattai and van Oudenaarden, 2001), but it has several important features. In particular, the noise defined here is based on the active and inactive copies of a gene, data that can be extracted from snapshots without the need to acquire live-imaging data. In addition, it is based on the endogenous copies of the gene (see Section 2 and further on for experimental details) and does not require engineered reporters such as dual reporters. The dual-reporter analysis requires an assumption that the two reporters and their products are identical because differences between the two reporters and products can falsely contribute to the internal noise component. The use of the endogenous gene copies as in our study does not require this assumption because both copies and their products are identical. Furthermore, as discussed below, our experimental system is an entire embryo, where technically cells have not yet been formed at the time of analysis. Thus, the external source of fluctuations estimated in our study includes both embryo-to-embryo and nucleusto-nucleus variances. For this reason, we use the terms &apos;internal&apos; and &apos;external&apos; as opposed to &apos;intrinsic&apos; and &apos;extrinsic&apos;.</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>J.R. performed experiments; F.H., J.R. and W.W. analyzed the data; F.H. and W.W. developed the theoretical methods; F.H. and J.M. interpreted the data and wrote the article; all approved the article. We thank Jingyuan Deng of CCHMC for specific discussions and suggestions, Drs Michael Wagner and Timothy E. Saunders for critical comments on the manuscript, and Dr Bo Zhang of Peking University for supporting J.R. and the work.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synchronous and stochastic patterns of gene activation in the Drosophila embryo</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Boettiger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Levine</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">325</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="471" to="473" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scaling of the Bicoid morphogen gradient by a volumedependent production rate</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Cheung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2741" to="2749" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A gradient of bicoid protein in Drosophila embryos</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Driever</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Nusslein-Volhard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional roles for noise in genetic circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Eldar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Elowitz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">467</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stochastic gene expression in a single cell</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Elowitz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">297</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1183" to="1186" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Seeing is believing: the bicoid morphogen gradient matures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ephrussi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">St</forename>
				<surname>Johnston</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="152" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of spatial averaging in the precision of gene expression patterns</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Erdmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">258101</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linking stochastic dynamics to population distribution: an analytical framework of gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Friedman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">168302</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Targeting gene expression to the head: the Drosophila orthodenticle gene is a direct target of the Bicoid morphogen</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Gao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Finkelstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4185" to="4193" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probing the limits to positional information</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Gregor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="164" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modelling the Bicoid gradient</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Grimm</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2253" to="2264" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probing intrinsic properties of a robust morphogen gradient in Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="558" to="567" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shaping a morphogen gradient for positional precision</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="697" to="707" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distance measurements via the morphogen gradient of Bicoid in Drosophila embryos</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">80</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multiscale investigation of bicoid-dependent transcriptional events in Drosophila embryos</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19122</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Separating intrinsic from extrinsic fluctuations in dynamic biological systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Hilfinger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Paulsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12167" to="12172" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression noise in spatial patterning: hunchback promoter structure affects noise amplitude and distribution in Drosophila segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Holloway</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1001069</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Establishment of developmental precision and proportions in the early Drosophila embryo</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Houchmandzadeh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">415</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="798" to="802" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Specifying positional information in the embryo: looking beyond morphogens</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kerszberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Wolpert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene regulation by MAPK substrate competition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="880" to="887" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Substrate-dependent control of MAPK phosphorylation in vivo</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">467</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morpheus unbound: reimagining the morphogen gradient</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Lander</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="256" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fates-shifted is an F-box protein that targets Bicoid for degradation and regulates developmental fate determination in Drosophila embryos</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Ma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morphogen gradient formation and action: insights from studying Bicoid protein degradation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fly (Austin)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="242" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antagonistic action of Bicoid and the repressor Capicua determines the spatial limits of Drosophila head gene expression domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<surname>Lohr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21695" to="21700" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptional activators and activation mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Ma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="879" to="888" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Filtering transcriptional noise during development: concepts and mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Martinez</forename>
				<surname>Arias</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Hayward</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anterior-posterior positional information in the absence of a strong Bicoid gradient</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ochoa-Espinosa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3823" to="3828" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable, precise, and reproducible patterning of bicoid and hunchback molecules in the early Drosophila embryo</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Okabe-Oho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000486</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of individual Scr mRNAs during Drosophila embryogenesis yields evidence for transcriptional bursting</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Pare</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2037" to="2042" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The bicoid morphogen system</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Porcher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Dostatni</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="254" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The time to measure positional information: maternal hunchback is required for the synchrony of the Bicoid transcriptional response at the onset of zygotic transcription</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Porcher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2795" to="2804" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stochastic mRNA synthesis in mammalian cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Raj</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control of stochasticity in eukaryotic gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Raser</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Shea</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">304</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1811" to="1814" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bioinformatics-bts068.tex] Page: 975</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="50" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Drosophila Bicoid morphogen gradient system</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Noise in gene expression: origins, consequences, and control</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Raser</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Shea</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">309</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2010" to="2013" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morphogen profiles can be optimized to buffer against noise</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Saunders</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Howard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E Stat. Nonlin. Soft Matter Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41902</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intrinsic and extrinsic contributions to stochasticity in gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Swain</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12795" to="12800" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intrinsic noise in gene regulatory networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Thattai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Van Oudenaarden</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8614" to="8619" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of input noise in transcriptional regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Tkacik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2774</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Noise can induce bimodality in positive transcriptional feedback loops without bistability</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>To</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Maheshri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">327</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1142" to="1145" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fundamental limits to position determination by concentration gradients</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Tostevin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">78</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morphogen gradient formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Wartlick</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cold Spring Harb. Perspect. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1255</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcribed genes are localized according to chromosomal position within polarized Drosophila embryonic nuclei</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Wilkie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1263" to="1266" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>