
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:47+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology Exploring metabolic pathways in genome-scale networks via generating flux modes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">A</forename>
								<surname>Rezola</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Biomedical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">CEIT and TECNUN</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Navarra</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Manuel de Lardizabal 15</addrLine>
									<postCode>20018</postCode>
									<settlement>San Sebastian, Spain</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">L</forename>
								<forename type="middle">F</forename>
								<surname>De Figueiredo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Friedrich-Schiller-University Jena</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07743</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">PhD Program in Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Instituto Gulbenkian de Ciência</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2780-156</postCode>
									<settlement>Oeiras</settlement>
									<country key="PT">Portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">M</forename>
								<surname>Brock</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Junior Research Group of Microbial Biochemistry and Physiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Leibniz Institute for Natural Product Research and Infection Biology -Hans Knöll Institute (HKI)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07745</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">J</forename>
								<surname>Pey</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Biomedical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">CEIT and TECNUN</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Navarra</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Manuel de Lardizabal 15</addrLine>
									<postCode>20018</postCode>
									<settlement>San Sebastian, Spain</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">A</forename>
								<surname>Podhorski</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Biomedical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">CEIT and TECNUN</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Navarra</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Manuel de Lardizabal 15</addrLine>
									<postCode>20018</postCode>
									<settlement>San Sebastian, Spain</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">C</forename>
								<surname>Wittmann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biochemical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Technical University Braunschweig</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>38106</postCode>
									<settlement>Braunschweig</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">S</forename>
								<surname>Schuster</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Friedrich-Schiller-University Jena</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07743</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">A</forename>
								<surname>Bockmayr</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">DFG-Research Center Matheon</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">FB Mathematik und Informatik</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Arnimallee 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">F</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Planes</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Biomedical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">CEIT and TECNUN</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Navarra</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Manuel de Lardizabal 15</addrLine>
									<postCode>20018</postCode>
									<settlement>San Sebastian, Spain</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology Exploring metabolic pathways in genome-scale networks via generating flux modes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="534" to="540"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq681</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 16, 2010; revised on November 12, 2010; accepted on December 7, 2010</note>
					<note>[12:52 22/1/2011 Bioinformatics-btq681.tex] Page: 534 534–540 Associate Editor: Trey Ideker Contact: fplanes@tecnun.es Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The reconstruction of metabolic networks at the genome scale has allowed the analysis of metabolic pathways at an unprecedented level of complexity. Elementary flux modes (EFMs) are an appropriate concept for such analysis. However, their number grows in a combinatorial fashion as the size of the metabolic network increases, which renders the application of EFMs approach to large metabolic networks difficult. Novel methods are expected to deal with such complexity. Results: In this article, we present a novel optimization-based method for determining a minimal generating set of EFMs, i.e. a convex basis. We show that a subset of elements of this convex basis can be effectively computed even in large metabolic networks. Our method was applied to examine the structure of pathways producing lysine in Escherichia coli. We obtained a more varied and informative set of pathways in comparison with existing methods. In addition, an alternative pathway to produce lysine was identified using a detour via propionyl-CoA, which shows the predictive power of our novel approach. Availability: The source code in C++ is available upon request.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>During the last decade, different approaches have been proposed to explore the structure of complex metabolic networks from a pathway-oriented perspective (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Klamt and Stelling, 2003</ref>). As in other methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Price et al., 2004</ref>), these approaches are mainly built upon the steady state condition and irreversibility (thermodynamic) constraints, which define a polyhedral cone, typically referred to as the flux cone. In particular, pathway-based methods search for solutions in the flux cone that satisfy a simplicity condition, technically the non-decomposability condition. These properties were condensed in the definition of elementary flux mode (EFM) in the work of Schuster and Hilgetag (1994). Since its introduction, the concept of EFM has received much attention, showing that a wide range of questions in bioengineering and bioinformatics can be addressed using such an approach (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Schuster et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Trinh et al., 2009</ref>). In particular, the prediction of novel biologically meaningful pathways constitutes one of the most important applications of EFM analysis. An example is the in silico prediction via EFM analysis of the PEP-glyoxylate cycle (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Liao et al., 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Schuster et al., 1999</ref>), which was later confirmed experimentally (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Fischer and Sauer, 2003</ref>). However, due to combinatorial explosion (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Klamt and Stelling, 2002</ref>), the computation of EFMs is not easy and, until recently, their analysis has been restricted to small metabolic networks. In this context,<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Terzer and Stelling (2008)</ref>, have presented an improved method that expands the applicability of the EFMs approach to moderate-size metabolic networks; however, large metabolic networks remain beyond the capabilities of current algorithms. We have recently shown that the K-shortest EFMs (for small K values) can be calculated in large networks, even at the genome scale, using integer linear programming (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">de Figueiredo et al., 2009</ref>). The use of optimization introduces more flexibility into EFM computation and, therefore, the direct exploration of a particular subset of EFMs of interest can be accomplished without having first to compute the full set of EFMs. This represents a clear advantage with respect to previous methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Klamt et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schilling et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Schuster et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Terzer and Stelling, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Urbanczik and Wagner, 2005</ref>). A concept related to EFMs is that of convex basis. First introduced in<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Pfeiffer et al. (1999)</ref>, it was defined as a minimal set of EFMs that generate the solution space. This means that any vector in the flux cone, in particular any other EFM not included in this minimal set, can be written as a non-negative linear combination of the elements of the basis. For this reason, a convex basis is typically referred to as a minimal generating set and elements of this basis as generating flux modes, GFMs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Wagner and Urbanczik, 2005</ref>). However, the convex<ref type="bibr">[</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exploring metabolic pathways via generating flux modes</head><p>basis is generally non-unique and does not necessarily involve all biochemical relevant pathways. Consequently, other mathematical descriptions of metabolism have been preferred over GFMs. In particular, special interest has been attracted by the extreme pathway approach (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schilling et al., 2000</ref>), in which the network configuration is modified to overcome the non-uniqueness issue. Moreover, the number of GFMs and extreme pathways is lower than the number of EFMs. The comparison between EFMs, extreme pathways and GFMs has been extensively addressed in the literature (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Klamt and Stelling, 2003</ref>;<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Wagner and Urbanczik, 2005</ref>). This discussion is less relevant in large metabolic networks, since the full computation of EFMs and GFMs (and extreme pathways) is not possible due to combinatorial explosion. Instead, current research has been more devoted to identify novel methods to deal with such complexity and explore the EFM and GFM solution spaces (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">de Figueiredo et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kaleta et al., 2009</ref>). This is in fact the main purpose of this article, namely to present a new method for computing a subset of GFMs in large-scale metabolic networks. Recently, Larhlimi and Bockmayr (2009) have presented a new constraint-based description of the flux cone. Based on the concept and properties of 'minimal metabolic behaviours' introduced in that paper, we adapted the K-shortest EFMs method presented in<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">de Figueiredo et al. (2009)</ref>, to calculate GFMs. Similarly to the K-shortest EFM approach, our method can be (in theory) applied to enumerate a full set of GFMs. However, it is particularly useful for large networks, where classical methods are not applicable (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Urbanczik and Wagner, 2005</ref>). In these cases, our method allows the effective computation of a subset of GFMs by directly calculating only those GFMs that involve a particular reaction or metabolite of interest. We present below the details of our mathematical optimization model for calculating GFMs. We used the standard network configuration and convex basis definition presented in<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Pfeiffer et al. (1999)</ref>, as will become apparent in Section 2. Our approach, however, can be easily adapted to calculate extreme pathways just by changing the network configuration as defined in<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schilling et al. (2000)</ref>. We then examine the predictive power of our GFMs approach to find pathways producing the commercially important amino acid L-lysine in the genome-scale metabolic network of Escherichia coli (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Feist et al., 2007</ref>). The results are analyzed and compared with our previous method presented in de<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Figueiredo et al., 2009</ref>. We show that our GFM approach presents a more descriptive and varied set of pathways than the K-shortest EFMs method. As a result of our analysis, we hypothesize a novel pathway to produce L-lysine in E.coli using propionyl-CoA (ppcoa).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>In this section, we present a novel mathematical method to calculate a subset (and, in principle, even a full set) of GFMs, i.e. a convex basis. Before describing this method, a brief introduction to metabolic network theory is carried out.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Definitions</head><p>Consider a metabolic network that comprises R reactions and C metabolites. Each reaction is associated with a flux variable v r ,r=1,...,R where v=<ref type="bibr">[v 1 ,...,v R ]</ref>is the flux vector. Irr denotes the set of irreversible reactions, which satisfy the (qualitative) thermodynamic constraints, i.e. v r ≥0, r ∈ Irr.</p><p>Note that reversible reactions are not split into forward and backward reactions, as opposed to other approaches, e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schilling et al., 2000</ref>, where splitting into two irreversible steps is accomplished. The set of metabolites is divided into two subsets, namely external (E) and internal (I) metabolites. For internal metabolites, it is assumed that no accumulation or depletion is possible, therefore steady-state condition holds, i.e. R r=1 s cr v r =0, c ∈ I, where s cr is the stoichiometric coefficient associated with compound c (c=1,...,C) in reaction r (r=1,...,R). As usual in the literature (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schilling et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Schuster et al., 2000</ref>), substrates and products have negative and positive stoichiometric coefficients, respectively. External metabolites are typically considered as sources and sinks. The set of flux vectors that satisfy the thermodynamic and steady state constraints defines a polyhedral cone, P, defined as</p><formula>P = v| R r=1 s cr v r = 0, c ∈ I; v r ≥ 0, r ∈ Irr</formula><formula>(1)</formula><p>Aside from being contained in the flux cone P, EFMs are solutions that satisfy a simplicity condition, namely the non-decomposability condition, which establishes that any subset of the reactions involved in an EFM cannot carry flux in steady state (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Schuster et al., 2000</ref>). As in<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Pfeiffer et al., 1999</ref>, a convex basis is defined here as a minimal set of EFMs that generates the solution space. Elements of a convex basis were termed above generating flux modes, GFMs. A convex basis defines two different subsets of GFMs, namely B reversible GFMs and G irreversible GFMs. While an irreversible GFM involves at least one irreversible reaction, a reversible GFM involves no irreversible reactions. Reversible and irreversible GFMs are denoted here in vectorial form, b j ,j=1,...,B and g i ,i=1,...,G, respectively. Any flux vector v in the polyhedral cone P can be generated as a linear combination with non-negative coefficients λ i for irreversible GFMs and with unrestricted signed coefficients µ j for reversible GFMs.</p><formula>v = G i=1 λ i g i + B j=1 µ j b j ,</formula><formula>(2)</formula><formula>v ∈ P, λ i ≥ 0, i = 1</formula><p>,...,G; −∞&lt;µ j &lt;∞, j = 1,...,B;</p><p>We describe below how reversible and irreversible GFMs can be separately determined.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Reversible GFMs</head><p>The determination of the reversible GFMs of a convex basis can be accomplished using the concept of reversible metabolic space (RMS), as introduced in<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Larhlimi and Bockmayr, 2009</ref>. RMS is defined as the linear subspace in which the irreversible reactions carry no flux:</p><formula>RMS ={v ∈ P | v r =0, ∀r ∈ Irr} (3)</formula><p>Accordingly, the set of reversible GFMs (b j ,j=1,...,B) is a linear basis of RMS, namely:</p><formula>v = B j=1 µ j b j , v ∈ RMS, −∞&lt;µ j &lt;∞, j = 1</formula><p>,...,B;</p><formula>(4)</formula><p>Finding a linear basis is a simple task and it can be easily performed using classic linear algebra. Note that B is the number of reversible GFMs in a convex basis and it represents the dimension of RMS. Interestingly, if B=0, then the flux cone is pointed and the convex basis is unique up to multiplication by non-negative numbers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Pfeiffer et al., 1999</ref>). However, genome-scale metabolic networks typically have B =0. In the extreme pathway approach (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schilling et al., 2000</ref>), for example, the network configuration is modified to have B=0.</p><p>Page: 536 534–540</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.Rezola et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Irreversible GFMs</head><p>The determination of irreversible GFMs is the actual challenge in computing a convex basis. To illustrate how to calculate such a set, we will use the concept of minimal metabolic behavior (MMB) introduced in Larhlimi and Bockmayr (2009). A metabolic behavior is any non-empty set of irreversible reactions able to carry flux together in a steady state flux vector. A metabolic behavior D is minimal if there is no proper subset of D with this property. For a more rigorous definition of MMB, see Larhlimi and Bockmayr (2009). According to Theorem 9 in Larhlimi and Bockmayr (2009), each irreversible GFM in a convex basis involves a different MMB and therefore the number of irreversible GFMs in a convex basis is equal to the number of MMBs. We can then define the set of irreversible GFMs in a convex basis as a subset of EFMs with the property that each EFM in this subset involves a different MMB. Observe that in non-pointed flux cones we may have more than one EFM involving a particular MMB. Indeed, for this reason we can have a nonunique convex basis. However, in terms of determining a particular convex basis, we only need to select one such EFM for each MMB. We here selected the EFM with the minimum number of reversible reactions. The rest of EFMs involving the same MMB (but not included in the convex basis) can be generated by the EFM selected for the convex basis and the reversible GFMs. More details on MMBs and GFMs can be found in<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Larhlimi and Bockmayr (2009)</ref>. In this light, we propose a general optimization-based method to enumerate MMBs and their associated GFMs. Our method starts from the assumption that the flux mode involving the minimum number of irreversible reactions will involve the shortest MMB. By abuse of language, we here refer to an EFM involving the shortest MMB with the minimal use of reversible reactions as the shortest GFM. Accordingly, we first define the constraints and the objective function to be optimized that allows the calculation of the shortest GFM. Based on this optimization model, we then show how to calculate the K-shortest GFMs. Finally, extensions to other problems of interest will be presented. We mean here by 1-shortest GFM, the EFM involving the minimum number of irreversible reactions, i.e. the shortest MMB, with the minimal use of reversible reactions; 2-shortest GFM, the EFM containing the second shortest MMB with the minimal use of reversible reactions; K-shortest GFM, the EFM containing the K-shortest MMB with the minimal use of reversible reactions. Note that we may have multiple GFMs containing the same number of irreversible reactions, i.e. MMBs with the same length. If this occurs, they are counted separately with different K values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1">Shortest GFM</head><p>Let z r be a binary variable associated with each reaction r (r=1,...,R), where z r =1 if the reaction is active in the shortest GFM, 0 otherwise. As noted above, v r represents the flux variable for reaction r. Equation (5) introduces the constraints needed to relate the reaction variables z r and v r , where M is a large positive constant value, which represents the bounds for the reaction fluxes.</p><formula>−Mz r ≤ v r ≤ Mz r , r=1,...,R (5)</formula><p>Equations (6) and</p><p>(7) define the thermodynamic and steady state constraints, as introduced above.</p><formula>v r ≥ 0, r ∈ Irr (6) R r=1 s cr v r =0, c ∈ I (7)</formula><p>In order to ensure that at least one irreversible reaction occurs in the shortest GFM, we need Equation (8), which avoids the trivial solution,</p><formula>(v r =0, r=1,...,R). R r=1, r∈Irr v r ≥ 1 (8)</formula><p>In order to calculate the shortest GFM, we pose the following objective function:</p><formula>Minimize W R r=1, r∈Irr z r + R r=1, r ∈ Irr z r (9)</formula><p>which involves two terms to be minimized. The first one is the number of active irreversible reactions multiplied by a large positive constant value, W ; the second one is the number of active reversible reactions. We give W times more weight to the sum of active irreversible reactions to guarantee that the flux mode involves the minimum number of irreversible reactions and, therefore, the shortest MMB participates in the solution. The second term guarantees that (i) the flux mode containing the shortest MMB is elementary, i.e. non-decomposable, as defined for EFMs ; and (ii) the minimal use of reversible reactions as defined for the shortest GFM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2">K-shortest GFMs</head><p>Similarly to<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">de Figueiredo et al. (2009)</ref>, we need constraints to remove all the previous k-shortest GFMs (k=1,...,K−1) from the set of solutions in order to calculate the K-shortest GFM. We already know that the K-shortest GFM involves the K-shortest MMB. Since the convex basis needs only one EFM for each MMB, we need to guarantee that the K-shortest GFM does not involve the previous k-shortest MMBs (k=1,...,K−1), but only the K-shortest MMB. To do this, let Z k r be the binary solution associated with the k-shortest GFM (k=1,...,K−1), where Z k r =1 if reaction r is active in the k-shortest GFM, 0 otherwise, and we impose the following constraint:</p><formula>R r=1, r∈Irr Z k r z r ≤ ⎛ ⎝ R r=1, r∈Irr Z k r ⎞ ⎠ −1, k = 1,...,K −1 (10)</formula><p>where the term in the left-hand side of Equation (10) determines the number of irreversible reactions in the new solution (z r ) that were active in the k-shortest GFM (k=1,...,K−1), and the right-hand side is the number of irreversible reactions that were active in the k-shortest GFM (k=1,...,K−1) less one. The inequality states that the number of irreversible reactions repeating from the k-shortest GFM (k=1,...,K−1) in the new solution should be strictly smaller than the total number of active irreversible reactions in the k-shortest GFM (k=1,...,K−1). In essence, Equation (10) ensures that, once we solve our model, the k-shortest MMBs are prevented from appearing again in the solution, for k=1,...,K−1. This guarantees that the solution will involve the K-shortest MMB, and therefore the K-shortest GFM is obtained.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3">Extensions to K-shortest GFMs</head><p>The procedure described above can be applied (in theory) to enumerate a full set of irreversible GFMs (g i , i=1,...,G) for a given metabolic network. However, our optimization method is not particularly efficient in small-scale metabolic networks when compared with classical methods. Indeed, the main advantage of our method is the enumeration of a subset of GFMs (K=10−10000) in large metabolic networks. In addition, the use of optimization allows the user to directly analyze those subsets of GFMs that may be of interest, as in de<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Figueiredo et al. (2009)</ref>. This makes our approach a suitable tool for exploring EFMs (GFMs) in large metabolic networks. To illustrate this, our method can be used to explore the K-shortest GFMs that involve a particular reaction ξ of interest, namely by imposing their flux v ξ to be non-zero<ref type="bibr">[ Equation (11)]</ref>. Note here that Y is a scalar coefficient (Y =−1 or Y =1), whose value decides the direction of the flux of reaction ξ in the case the reaction is reversible.</p><formula>Yv ξ ≥ 1, Y =−1 or Y = 1 ( 1 1 )</formula><p>The application of the K-shortest GFM method here, Equations (5)– (10) plus Equation (11), requires to consider if reaction ξ is reversible or irreversible. If the reaction is irreversible, then our method will calculate a subset of irreversible GFMs containing this reaction (Y =1). At the same time, if the reaction is reversible but it is not involved in any reversible GFM, i.e. a pseudo-irreversible reaction, as defined in<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Larhlimi and Bockmayr (2009)</ref>, then our optimization method will produce GFMs containing thisPage: 537 534–540</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exploring metabolic pathways via generating flux modes</head><p>reversible reaction. Note that Y can be −1 or +1 depending on the direction we want irreversible GFMs to occur. On the other hand, if the reaction is reversible and it participates in reversible GFMs, our current method might fail. To overcome this issue, a possible strategy would be to split this reversible reaction into two irreversible steps. Note that we can only include one constraint based on Equation (11). For example, if we apply constraint (11) to reactions ξ 1 and ξ 2 , i.e. finding solutions to our model that involve reactions ξ 1 and ξ 2 , then we might obtain solutions containing two EFMs, namely one using ξ 1 and another using ξ 2. Therefore, the non-decomposability condition is not guaranteed. In addition, as in de<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Figueiredo et al. (2009)</ref>, it is possible to define a growth medium. Extracellular metabolites not included in the growth medium can only be balanced/produced, but not consumed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.4">Implementation</head><p>The mathematical optimization model given above for computing the K-shortest irreversible GFMs, consisting of objective function (9) subject to Equations (5)–(8), plus elimination constraints (10) and perhaps constraint (11), is a mixed-integer linear program. Algorithmically, such programs are solved via branch and bound and cutting planes methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Pardalos and Resende, 2002</ref>). Various free and commercial software tools are available to perform this task. We used ILOG CPLEX. To reinforce the understanding of our method, Supplementary Material details the application of our method to the (toy) metabolic network presented in Larhlimi and Bockmayr (2009).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>In this section, we present results corresponding to the application of our K-shortest GFMs to analyze the pathway structure of E.coli to produce lysine. We used the genome-scale metabolic network of E.coli K-12 MG1665 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Feist et al., 2007</ref>), which involves 2082 reactions and 1668 metabolites. As noted above, our method is particularly useful for networks of this size, since the computation of a convex basis via traditional methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Pfeiffer et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Terzer and Stelling, 2008</ref>;<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Wagner and Urbanczik, 2005</ref>) is not applicable in these networks. A minimal medium based on glucose, ammonium and oxygen was utilized. We neglected constraints from proton and cofactor (ATP, NADH, NADPH, etc.) balances, fixing them as external metabolites. One may question the validity of this hypothesis for NADP and NADPH, since NADPH is required in stoichiometric amounts for lysine production and, as discussed in<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wittmann and Becker (2007)</ref>, its supply has substantial impact in metabolism. In this work, for the sake of simplicity, we focused on pathways for the supply of the carbon backbone of lysine. Moreover, extending the current work to consider the role of cofactors in lysine production can be accomplished without loss of generality, as shown in<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">de Figueiredo et al. (2009)</ref>. See Supplementary Material for the exact definition of the medium and cofactors set. The reaction transporting lysine from the periplasm compartment to the external compartment (<ref type="bibr">LYStex, see Feist et al., 2007</ref>) is pseudo-irreversible, i.e. no reversible GFMs exist that produce lysine. Thus, we need only to focus on irreversible GFMs producing lysine. Our K-shortest GFMs method was then applied with K=100 and constraint (11) for lysine. We also computed the K-shortest EFMs, as described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">de Figueiredo et al., 2009</ref>, in order to compare the results. We selected M=100 to guarantee that no pathway information is missed, similarly to<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">de Figueiredo et al. (2009)</ref>. In a 64 Bits, 2.00 GHz, 12 GB RAM PC, CPLEX 12.1 took approximately 30 and 100 min to compute the 100 shortest EFMs and GFMs, respectively. Therefore, though computation time is acceptable, our method is less efficient than the K-shortest EFMs method. Note that, by setting cofactors as external metabolites, we may find solutions that use some cofactors as carbon source, which are irrelevant for the biosynthesis of lysine using glucose as carbon source. As it can be observed in the Supplementary Material, we found this issue in longer pathways using AMP as carbon source. To prevent these solutions from appearing, we constrained the adenine pool formed by ATP, ADP and AMP to be in balance by adding the following constraint to our previous formulation:</p><formula>R r=1 s ATPr v r + R r=1 s ADPr v r + R r=1 s AMPr v r =0, where s ATPr , s ADPr and</formula><p>s AMPr are the stoichiometric coefficients of ATP, ADP and AMP, respectively, for reaction r.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. First, the 100 shortest EFMs and 100 shortest GFMs involve 54 and 132 reactions, respectively. In addition, while the maximum length for 100 shortest EFMs is 26, this is 37 for the 100 shortest GFMs, which just indicates that the K-shortest GFMs method produce a set of longer pathways. We also used the Hamming distance to evaluate the differences between each pair of solutions of the 100 shortest EFMs (GFMs), finding that the average Hamming distance is higher for GFMs, which just indicates that the shortest EFMs approach determine a less diverse set of solutions. Furthermore, it can be observed from<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>that from 54 reactions that participate in the 100 shortest EFMs, 49 are included in the 100 shortest GFMs. This implies that most information in the shortest EFMs is included in the shortest GFMs and, therefore, the GFMs approach is more informative. To validate this, we created a subnetwork with the reactions forming the 100 shortest EFMs and computed the full set of EFMs for this subnetwork via efmtool (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Terzer and Stelling, 2008</ref>). As observed incytosol, nitrogen metabolism, the balancing of succinate (succ) and succinyl-CoA (succoa) and the production of dha. With respect to the 100 shortest GFMs, we have longer routes than the 100 shortest EFMs, though they are still short (maximum 37 reactions). The set of pathways is now much more varied (see Supplementary Figs S4 and S5). For instance, the pentose phosphate (PP) pathway and the glyoxylate shunt are now recovered. Moreover, we obtain several routes around the switch node per-pyr-oaa, which is known to be responsible for the distribution of the carbon flux among catabolism, anabolism and energy supply in several bacteria (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Sauer and Eikmanns, 2005</ref>). Overall, most of previous biochemical knowledge on the production of lysine is recovered in the 100 shortest GFMs. A relevant mechanism appearing in the 100 shortest GFMs is the metabolic cycle shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2a</ref>, which suggests a novel pathway to produce lysine. This metabolic cycle consumes one molecule of oaa and produces one molecule of pyr and co2 each, making a detour through propionyl-CoA (ppcoa). This cycle is an alternative mechanism to the OAADC reaction: oaa → pyr + co2. However, it is less efficient than the OAADC reaction, since it involves six reactions and consumes one molecule of ATP to carry out the conversion. We refer to it as the ppcoa cycle. To the best of our knowledge, this cycle has not been previously described. Note here that other routes for the conversion of oaa to pyr have been previously described in the literature (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wittmann and Becker, 2007</ref>). The importance of the ppcoa cycle in the production of lysine is however questionable. The decarboxylation of oaa is generally counterproductive, since the overexpression of genes associated with enzymes producing oaa as well as the deletion of genes encoding enzymes that withdraw oaa are well-known strategies to increase the yield of lysine (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wittmann and Becker, 2007</ref>). A counterexample here is the decarboxylation of oaa via malate (reactions MDH and ME2) that converts NADH into NADPH, which, as mentioned above, is important for lysine production. On the other hand, it is known from studies in Aspergillus nidulans that ppcoa inhibits the activity of pyruvate dehydrogenase and thus, its presence decreases the flux through the tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Brock and Buckel, 2004</ref>). This may be of interest for lysine production, since the increase in the yield of lysine is linked to a decrease in the flux through TCA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kiss and Stephanopoulos, 1992</ref>). The overall effect requires experimental validation. We discuss below the functional feasibility of this cycle in E.coli.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Comparison between K-shortest EFMs and GFMs</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Physiological feasibility of ppcoa cycle in E.coli</head><p>As observed in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2a</ref>, the ppcoa cycle comprises a route linking succinyl-CoA (succoa) to propionyl-CoA (ppcoa), which is part of Page: 539 534–540</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exploring metabolic pathways via generating flux modes</head><p>(a) (b)<ref type="bibr">, 1997</ref>) which is not present in the genome-scale network of E.coli. Ellipses represent metabolites and arrows reactions. Light gray ellipses are external metabolites, dark gray are dead-end metabolites and black are source and sink metabolites. the methylmalonyl-CoA pathway, and a route linking propionylCoA to pyruvate accompanied by a reduction of oxaloacetate to succinate (succ), as a part of the 2-methylcitric acid cycle. These two routes are joined by succinyl-CoA synthetase, which belongs to the TCA cycle. We describe below the feasibility of the coexistence of the methylmalonyl-CoA pathway and the 2-methylcitric acid cycle in E.coli. The unidirectional 2-methylcitric acid cycle has been shown to be essential for propionyl-CoA degradation in several bacteria and fungi and an impairment of the cycle prohibits growth on propionate, odd chain fatty acids and propionyl-CoA generating amino acids (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Brock and Buckel, 2004</ref>). An alternative pathway for propionyl-CoA degradation is the coenzyme B12-dependent methylmalonyl-CoA pathway, which is also operative in the direction of propionyl-CoA formation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Buckel et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Michenfelder et al., 1987</ref>). Despite a functional 2-methylcitric acid cycle in E.coli, genes encoding proteins of the methylmalonyl-CoA pathway were recently discovered in this organism (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Froese et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Haller et al., 2000</ref>). Although the contribution of the latter pathway to propionyl-CoA degradation is unknown, all genes encode functional enzymes as shown by heterologous integration of the pathway for secondary metabolite production in Salmonella enterica serovar thyphimurium (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Aldor et al., 2002</ref>) and polypetide production in E.coli (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Aldor et al., 2002</ref>). Assuming a coexistence of both pathways, they can be integrated into the central carbon metabolism. Thus, we conducted additional simulations to examine this hypothesis, which resulted in novel potential pathways linking glycolysis and TCA cycle. Results are given in the Supplementary Material. Besides the general functionality of proteins involved in the methylmalonyl-CoA pathway, an important aspect of the methylmalonyl-CoA pathway not reflected in the genome-scale network of E.coli refers to the fact that the methylmalonyl-CoA mutase (MMM2) requires 5-deoxyadenosylcobalamin (adocbl) as prosthetic group (cf. (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Banerjee, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Ludwig and Matthews, 1997</ref>). Detailed reaction mechanisms, as in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2b</ref>for MMM2, are not usually included in genome-scale networks. In particular, when a cofactor is essential for cell growth, which is not the case for adobcl, constraint-based methods, such as flux balanced analysis (FBA), include its consumption in the biomass equation to simulate its requirement (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Feist et al., 2007</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Feist et al., , 2009</ref>). In contrast, in metabolic pathway analysis the biomass equation is not typically included and, consequently, these interactions are not taken into account. To deal with this issue in metabolic pathway analysis, a possible strategy is to create an additional layer of logical interactions containing the interdependency between prosthetic groups and enzymes, reflecting that if a given cofactor cannot be de novo synthesized (which can be tested with EFM analysis or FBA) and it is not supplied in the growth medium, then the reaction requiring such cofactor cannot take place.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>In this article, we have presented a novel theoretical method to compute a convex basis based on the recent work of de<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Figueiredo et al. (2009)</ref>and Larhlimi and Bockmayr (2009). Our method was effectively applied to determine a subset of GFMs in large metabolic networks, where classical approaches fail. Though the computation of K-shortest GFMs is more expensive than the K-shortest EFMs method presented in<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">de Figueiredo et al. (2009)</ref>, we here obtained a more diverse and informative set of pathways. In the analysis of pathways producing lysine obtained by the K-shortest GFMs method, we identified a new cycle via propionylCoA that produces one molecule of pyruvate and consumes one Page: 540 534–540</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.Rezola et al.</head><p>molecule of oxaloacetate. This cycle integrates part of two metabolic pathways that have an important biotechnological application. Experimental validation of the cycle is needed to examine its functional feasibility and biotechnological impact, but it shows the potential of our K-shortest GFMs method in predicting novel metabolic pathways and generating hypotheses.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>[12:52 22/1/2011 Bioinformatics-btq681.tex]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure1is</head><figDesc>Figure 1 is an overview representation of the 100-shortest EFMs and GFMs. It can be seen that the 100-shortest GFMs present a more diverse and varied set of pathways than the 100-shortest EFMs. This hypothesis is further confirmed in Table 1. First, the 100 shortest EFMs and 100 shortest GFMs involve 54 and 132 reactions, respectively. In addition, while the maximum length for 100 shortest EFMs is 26, this is 37 for the 100 shortest GFMs, which just indicates that the K-shortest GFMs method produce a set of longer pathways. We also used the Hamming distance to evaluate the differences between each pair of solutions of the 100 shortest EFMs (GFMs), finding that the average Hamming distance is higher for GFMs, which just indicates that the shortest EFMs approach determine a less diverse set of solutions. Furthermore, it can be observed from Table 1 that from 54 reactions that participate in the 100 shortest EFMs, 49 are included in the 100 shortest GFMs. This implies that most information in the shortest EFMs is included in the shortest GFMs and, therefore, the GFMs approach is more informative. To validate this, we created a subnetwork with the reactions forming the 100 shortest EFMs and computed the full set of EFMs for this subnetwork via efmtool (Terzer and Stelling, 2008). As observed in Table 1, we obtained 1665 EFMs, 1636 of which produce L-lysine. We did the same for the 100 shortest GFMs, finding 354 238 EFMs in total, 25 007 of which produce L-lysine. The difference in the number of pathways is clearly significant. If the RMS is included in the subnetworks designed, the difference is much more important, though efmtool was not capable of calculating the number of EFMs for the subnetwork created with the reactions participating in the 100 shortest GFMs plus RMS. From the biochemical point of view, though difficult to observe in Figure 1 (see Supplementary Figs S2, S4 and S5 for a clearer picture), different insights can be gained. The interpretation of the network graphs in the Supplementary Material becomes easier when we focus on pyruvate (pyr) and oxolacetate (oaa), since the variability in the set of EFMs and GFMs is mainly related to the production and use of those metabolites, mainly due to the fact that they are the precursors of lysine. Among the 100 shortest EFMs (see Supplementary Figs S2 and S5), the main difference is the degradation of glucose into pyruvate. As we are producing shorter pathways, we obtain the shortest routes to do this function, namely glycolysis, the Entner– Doudoroff (ED) pathway, the methylglyoxal bypass and some variations of these pathways such as a detour via dihydroxyacetone (dha). Minor differences relate to the transportation of glucose into</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. (a) Novel ppcoa cycle detected in the GFMs; (b) Interdependency of 5-deoxyadenosylcobalamin (adocbl) synthesis and the ppcoa cycle. Schematic representation of the reaction mechanism associated to methylmalonyl-Coa mutase (MMM2)–cobalamin dependent (adapted from Banerjee, 1997) which is not present in the genome-scale network of E.coli. Ellipses represent metabolites and arrows reactions. Light gray ellipses are external metabolites, dark gray are dead-end metabolites and black are source and sink metabolites.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1, we obtained</figDesc><table>Page: 538 534–540 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1.</figDesc><table>Information about the 100 shortest GFMs/EFMs 

NoR LI 
OvR 
AHD No EFMs 
No EFMs(R) 

100 
90.74% 
shortest 54 
25–26 (49/54) 
12.79 1665 
5398 
EFMs 
Lys: 1636 
Lys: 3960 

100 
37.12% 
5×10 5 − 
shortest 132 
25–37 (49/132) 16.21 354238 
− 5×10 10 

GFMs 
Lys: 25007 Lys:  *  

NoR, number of reactions; LI, length interval; OvR, overlapping percentage of reactions 
of the 100 shortest EFMs (GFMs) in the shortest GFMs (EFMs); AHD, average 
hamming distance; No EFMs, number of EFMs emerging from the network formed 
by the 100 shortest EFMs (GFMs); No EFMs (R), number of EFMs emerging from the 
network formed by the 100 shortest EFMs (GFMs) and the reversible metabolic space 
(RMS); Lys, L-lysine. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="100"> shortest GFMs, finding 354 238 EFMs in total, 25 007 of which produce L-lysine. The difference in the number of pathways is clearly significant. If the RMS is included in the subnetworks designed, the difference is much more important, though efmtool was not capable of calculating the number of EFMs for the subnetwork created with the reactions participating in the 100 shortest GFMs plus RMS. From the biochemical point of view, though difficult to observe in Figure 1 (see Supplementary Figs S2, S4 and S5 for a clearer picture), different insights can be gained. The interpretation of the network graphs in the Supplementary Material becomes easier when we focus on pyruvate (pyr) and oxolacetate (oaa), since the variability in the set of EFMs and GFMs is mainly related to the production and use of those metabolites, mainly due to the fact that they are the precursors of lysine. Among the 100 shortest EFMs (see Supplementary Figs S2 and S5), the main difference is the degradation of glucose into pyruvate. As we are producing shorter pathways, we obtain the shortest routes to do this function, namely glycolysis, the Entner– Doudoroff (ED) pathway, the methylglyoxal bypass and some variations of these pathways such as a detour via dihydroxyacetone (dha). Minor differences relate to the transportation of glucose into</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head><p>The authors would like to acknowledge the helpful comments made by the two anonymous reviewers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Spanish entities Funding:</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolic engineering of a novel propionate-independent pathway for the production of poly(3-hydroxybutyrate-co-3-hydroxyvalerate) in recombinant Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Aldor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3848" to="3854" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The yin-yang of cobalamin biochemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Banerjee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the mechanism of action of the antifungal agent propionate</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Brock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Buckel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">271</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3227" to="3241" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stabilisation of methylene radicals by cob(II)alamin in coenzyme B12 dependent mutases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Buckel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="352" to="362" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computing the shortest elementary flux modes in genome-scale metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>De Figueiredo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3158" to="3165" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A genome-scale metabolic reconstruction for Escherichia coli K-12 MG1655 that accounts for 1260 orfs and thermodynamic information</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Feist</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">121</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reconstruction of biochemical networks in microorganisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Feist</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel metabolic cycle catalyzes glucose oxidation and anaplerosis in hungry Escherichia coli</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Fischer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<surname>Sauer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">278</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46446" to="46451" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sleeping beauty mutase (sbm) is expressed and interacts with ygfd in Escherichia coli</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Froese</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microbiol. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">164</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovering new enzymes and metabolic pathways: conversion of succinate to propionate by Escherichia coli</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Haller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4622" to="4629" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Can the whole be less than the sum of its parts? Pathway analysis in genome-scale metabolic networks using elementary flux patterns</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Kaleta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1872" to="1883" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolic characterization of a L-lysineproducing strain by continuous culture</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Kiss</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Stephanopoulos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnol. Bioeng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="565" to="574" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combinatorial complexity of pathway analysis in metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Klamt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Stelling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two approaches for metabolic pathway analysis?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Klamt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Stelling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithmic approaches for computing elementary modes in large biochemical reaction networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Klamt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="255" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new constraint-based description of the steadystate flux cone of metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Larhlimi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Bockmayr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Discr. Appl. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2257" to="2266" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathway analysis, engineering, and physiological considerations for redirecting central metabolism</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Liao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnol. Bioeng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure-based perspectives on B12dependent enzymes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Ludwig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Matthews</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="313" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative measurement of the error in the cryptic stereospecificity of methylmalonyl-CoA mutase</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Michenfelder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">168</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="659" to="667" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Handbook of Applied Optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Pardalos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Resende</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metatool: for studying metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Pfeiffer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="257" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-scale models of microbial cells: evaluating the consequences of constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Price</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="886" to="897" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The pep-pyruvate-oxaloacetate node as the switch point for carbon flux distribution in bacteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<surname>Sauer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Eikmanns</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEMS Microbiol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="765" to="794" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theory for the systemic definition of metabolic pathways and their use in interpreting metabolic function from a pathway-oriented perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Schilling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">203</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On elementary flux modes in biochemical reaction systems at steady state</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Schuster</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Hilgetag</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of elementary flux modes in biochemical networks: a promising tool for pathway analysis and metabolic engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Schuster</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general definition of metabolic pathways useful for systematic organization and analysis of complex metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Schuster</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="332" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding the roadmap of metabolism by pathway analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Schuster</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">358</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale computation of elementary flux modes with bit pattern trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Terzer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Stelling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2229" to="2235" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Elementary mode analysis: a useful metabolic pathway analysis tool for characterizing cellular metabolism</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Trinh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="813" to="826" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An improved algorithm for stoichiometric network analysis: theory and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Urbanczik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Wagner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1203" to="1210" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The geometry of the flux cone of a metabolic network</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Wagner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Urbanczik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3837" to="3845" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The L-lysine story: from metabolic pathways to industrial production Amino Acid Biosynthesis-Pathways, Regulation and Metabolic Engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Wittmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Becker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Wendisch,V.F.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Heidelberg, Germany</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>