
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:50+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis Fast and accurate imputation of summary statistics enhances evidence of functional enrichment</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">20 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bogdan</forename>
								<surname>Pasaniuc</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>bpasaniuc@mednet.ucla.edu or aprice@hsph.harvard.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">David Geffen School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California Los Angeles</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>90024</postCode>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Bioinformatics Interdepartmental Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California Los Angeles</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>90024</postCode>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Noah</forename>
								<surname>Zaitlen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Lung Biology Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Francisco</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine>
									<postCode>94143</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Huwenbo</forename>
								<surname>Shi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Bioinformatics Interdepartmental Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California Los Angeles</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>90024</postCode>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gaurav</forename>
								<surname>Bhatia</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Genetic Epidemiology and Statistical Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Departments of Epidemiology and Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Medical and Population Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alexander</forename>
								<surname>Gusev</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Genetic Epidemiology and Statistical Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Departments of Epidemiology and Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Medical and Population Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
								<surname>Pickrell</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Medical and Population Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics Harvard Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joel</forename>
								<surname>Hirschhorn</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Medical and Population Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Strachan</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nick</forename>
								<surname>Patterson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Medical and Population Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alkes</forename>
								<forename type="middle">L</forename>
								<surname>Price</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Genetic Epidemiology and Statistical Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Departments of Epidemiology and Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Medical and Population Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Janet</forename>
								<surname>Kelso</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis Fast and accurate imputation of summary statistics enhances evidence of functional enrichment</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2906" to="2914"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">20 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu416</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 22, 2013; revised on June 24, 2014; accepted on June 25, 2014</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER and 8 Division of Population Health Sciences and Education, St George&apos;s, University of London, UK Associate Editor: Availability and implementation: Publicly available software package available at http://bogdan.bioinformatics.ucla.edu/software/. Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary materials are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Imputation using external reference panels (e.g. 1000 Genomes) is a widely used approach for increasing power in genome-wide association studies and meta-analysis. Existing hidden Markov models (HMM)-based imputation approaches require individual level genotypes. Here, we develop a new method for Gaussian imputation from summary association statistics, a type of data that is becoming widely available. Results: In simulations using 1000 Genomes (1000G) data, this method recovers 84% (54%) of the effective sample size for common (45%) and low-frequency (1–5%) variants [increasing to 87% (60%) when summary linkage disequilibrium information is available from target samples] versus the gold standard of 89% (67%) for HMM-based imputation, which cannot be applied to summary statistics. Our approach accounts for the limited sample size of the reference panel, a crucial step to eliminate false-positive associations, and it is computationally very fast. As an empirical demonstration, we apply our method to seven case–control phenotypes from the Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium (WTCCC) data and a study of height in the British 1958 birth cohort (1958BC). Gaussian imputation from summary statistics recovers 95% (105%) of the effective sample size (as quantified by the ratio of 2 association statistics) compared with HMM-based imputation from individual-level genotypes at the 227 (176) published single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the WTCCC (1958BC height) data. In addition, for publicly available summary statistics from large meta-analyses of four lipid traits, we publicly release imputed summary statistics at 1000G SNPs, which could not have been obtained using previously published methods, and demonstrate their accuracy by masking subsets of the data. We show that 1000G imputation using our approach increases the magnitude and statistical evidence of enrichment at genic versus non-genic loci for these traits, as compared with an analysis without 1000G imputation. Thus, imputation of summary statistics will be a valuable tool in future functional enrichment analyses.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) are the prevailing approach for finding disease risk loci, having successfully identified thousands of variants associated to complex phenotypes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hindorff et al., 2009</ref>). An important component of the GWAS analysis toolkit is genotype imputation, an approach that leverages publicly available data [e.g. 1000 Genomes (1000G;<ref type="bibr">The 1000</ref><ref type="bibr">Genomes Project Consortium, 2012</ref>)] to estimate genotypes at markers untyped in the study to increase power for finding new risk loci (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Browning and Browning, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Howie et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Li et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Marchini and Howie, 2010a</ref>). In addition to GWAS, genotype imputation is a key component in meta-analysis of studies that use different genotyping platforms, where single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) that were genotyped in one study can be imputed in the other studies, thus increasing the association power (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Estrada et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Lango Allen et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Liu et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Morris et al., 2012</ref>). Many approaches for genotype imputation have been proposed, with methods based on hidden Markov models (HMM) showing the highest accuracy in simulations and empirical data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Browning and Browning, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Howie et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Li et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Marchini and Howie, 2010a</ref>). However, privacy and logistic constraints often prohibit access to individual-level genotype data, thus precluding HMM-based imputation, whereas summary association statistics are becoming widely available. For example, summary statistics are required to be publicly released for any GWAS published in Nature Genetics and have been *To whom correspondence should be addressed. publicly released for many traits (<ref type="bibr">Nature Genetics, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Schork et al., 2013</ref>). In this work, we propose methods for testing association at SNPs untyped in the study when only summary association statistics are available at the typed SNPs. Unlike HMM-based imputation from individual-level genotypes, our proposed approach requires only the association statistics at typed variants as input. To accomplish this, we approximate the distribution of association statistics at a given locus using a multivariate Gaussian. Previous studies have shown that a Gaussian approximation of linkage disequilibrium (LD) leads to accurate inference across a wide range of problems (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Conneely and Boehnke, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Han et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">McPeek, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wen and Stephens, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Zaitlen et al., 2010</ref>). In particular, (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wen and Stephens, 2010</ref>) highlighted the potential utility of Gaussian imputation methods for individual-level and pooled data, but that study did not provide methods or software for imputation from summary association statistics (see Section 4). Through extensive simulations based on 1000G data, we show that our approach is almost as powerful as the gold standard of HMM-based imputation from individual-level genotypes, and is able to avoid an increase in false-positive associations by accounting for the limited size of the reference panel. Our approach recovers 84% (54%) of the effective sample size for common (45%) and low-frequency (1–5%) variants versus 89% (67%) for HMM-based imputation, with a reduction in running time of several orders of magnitude. When summary information on the pairwise LD structure among typed variants in GWAS samples is made available [as is also recommended in other contexts (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Lee et al., 2013b)]</ref>, our method recovers 87% (60%) of the effective sample size, again with no increase in false-positive associations. We validate our approach using real GWAS data from Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium (WTCCC) across seven phenotypes as well as a height GWAS from the 1958 Birth Cohort (1958BC), where we show that Gaussian imputation from summary statistics recovers the same signal as HMM-based imputation from individual-level genotypes, with no increase in false-positive rate. For example, we attain an average 2 association statistic of 18.28 as compared with 19.17 for HMM-based imputation at the 227 published SNPs in the WTCCC data and 4.76 (versus 4.55 for HMM-based imputation) at the 176 published SNPs in the 1958BC height data. For publicly available summary statistics from large metaanalyses of four lipid traits [triglycerides (TG), total cholesterol (TC), high density lipoprotein (HDL) and low density lipoprotein (LDL)], we publicly release imputed summary statistics at 1000G SNPs, which could not have been obtained using previously published methods. We validate the accuracy of the imputed statistics across the four studies using a masking approach and show that we attain a correlation of 0.98 (0.95) to masked summary statistics for common (low-frequency) variants, consistent with simulations. Finally, we explore the utility of imputed association statistics to functional enrichment analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Schork et al., 2013</ref>). For the four lipid traits, we find that imputed data increase the magnitude and statistical evidence of enrichment at genic versus non-genic loci, as compared with an analysis without 1000G imputation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Schork et al., 2013</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Overview of Gaussian imputation of summary statistics</head><p>We assume that summary association statistics consist of z-scores known to be normally distributed with mean 0 and variance 1 under the null model of no association. LD between SNPs i and j induces a covariance between their observed z-scores, according to the correlation r ij between the two SNPs. Thus, under null data, the vector Z of z-scores at all SNPs in a locus is approximately distributed as a Gaussian distribution, Z$Nð0; SÞ, with S being the correlation matrix among all pairs of SNPs induced by LD (S ij =r ij ) (see Supplementary Note). In a given study, we only observe z-scores at the typed SNPs (Z t ), with no information about untyped SNPs. We estimate S using reference panels of haplotypes (e.g. 1000G) and analytically derive the posterior mean of z-scores at unobserved SNPs (Z i ) given Z t and S (ImpG-Summary). We use the conditional variance to estimate the imputation accuracy (r 2 pred), in a manner similar to the r 2 hat estimator in HMM-based imputation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Li et al., 2010</ref>). The finite sample size of the reference panel adds statistical noise to the estimate of S. We account for noisy estimates at distant SNPs by using a windowing strategy that models distant SNPs as uncorrelated. This strategy also leads to efficient computational runtime (a smaller matrix needs to be inverted for each window in the genome). In particular, we partition the genome into non-overlapping windows (e.g. 1 Mb), and for each window independently, we estimate the LD matrix S using the reference panel of haplotypes. To account for SNPs at the boundaries of these windows, we include SNPs within a buffer around the window in the computation (e.g. 250 kb on either side). We also account for statistical noise in estimates at proximal SNPs by adding I to the LD matrix estimated from the data S. This procedure is similar to ridge regression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Hoerl and Kennard, 1970</ref>) and can also be interpreted in a Bayesian context as adding a prior of Nð0; IÞ to the typed SNP coefficients (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hastie et al., 2001</ref>). Accounting for this statistical noise is necessary to eliminate false-positive associations (see below). The imputed z-scores (from the conditional Gaussian distribution) can be viewed as a linear combination of typed z-scores with weights precomputed from the reference panel. Therefore, the variance of the imputed z-score can be estimated on the basis of the weights and the LD among typed SNPs. We estimate the LD structure among typed SNPs using the reference panel as above (accounting for statistical noise in the reference panel) and normalize the imputed z-scores such that their theoretical variance under the null is 1 [in a real scan, the observed variance may be41 because of polygenic effects (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Yang et al., 2011)]</ref>. The computational time of our approach scales linearly with the number of windows across the genome and can be further reduced by precomputing the inverse S for each genotyping array platform at each window, although special requirement is required for typed SNPs that are removed by quality control (QC). In particular, matrix inversion should be repeated at windows where typed SNPs used in the imputation are removed by QC. If summary LD statistics (pairwise LD among typed SNPs within a window in GWAS samples) are also available, they can be directly used to estimate the variance of each imputed z-score (which can be viewed as a linear combination of typed z-scores). This produces an accurate estimate of the expected variance under the null for the imputed z-scores, with no need of adjustment for the statistical noise in the reference panel (ImpG-SummaryLD). This leads to well-calibrated association statistics under the null with increased power relative to ImpG-Summary. Association statistics in GWAS. A standard test for association in GWAS is the normalized difference in frequencies between cases and controls (z-score z) defined as z= ffiffiffiffi</p><formula>N p f + Àf À ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi 2fð1ÀfÞ p where f + (f À )</formula><p>denotes the frequency in cases (controls), f is the overall frequency and N the number of samples. This statistic extends to continuous phenotypes by considering ffiffiffiffi N p times the correlation between the vector of genotypes (0,1,2) and phenotype. In the case of imputed data, this statistic extends by using genotype dosages in the computation of the correlation of dosages to phenotype. LD between pairs of SNPs s and s 0 induces a correlation among the observed z-scores at these SNPs, which can be expressed through the correlation coefficient rðs; s 0 Þ (see Supplementary Note). Multivariate Gaussian approximation. Similar to other works (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Conneely and Boehnke, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Han et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wen and Stephens, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Zaitlen et al., 2010</ref>), we approximate the full distribution of association statistics Z at n SNPs in LD using a multivariate Gaussian distribution with probability density function depending on the mean and variance covariance S. Let the vector Z be partitioned into two components Z t and Z i corresponding with the typed and imputed SNPs, where Z t is a vector of size m (assuming m SNPs have been typed) and Z i has n – m elements. Similarly, we will partition the mean vector and variance– covariance matrix into ð t ; i Þ T corresponding to the means at typed and imputed SNPs, covariances among imputed (S i;i ), covariances among typed and imputed (S i;t ) and covariance among typed data (S t;t ). Then the conditional random variable Z i jZ t follows a Gaussian distribution with mean ZijZt = i +S i;t S À1 t;t ðZ t À t Þ and variance S ijt =S i;i À S i;t S À1 t;t S T i;t .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Gaussian imputation of association statistics (ImpG-Summary)</head><p>When estimating the variance–covariance matrix S, we adopt a windowing strategy aimed at decreasing runtime (a smaller matrix needs to be inverted for each window in the genome) and at reducing statistical noise that can show distant SNPs to be spuriously correlated. In particular, we partition the genome into non-overlapping windows of 1 Mb (with a buffer of 250 kb on either side to account for LD at boundaries). For each window independently, we estimate S from the reference panel of haplotypes, with an adjustment for sampling noise (see below). Let Z t be the set of observed z-scores restricted to current window. We impute Z i as Z ijt =S i;t S À1 t;t Z t. To speed up computation, we precompute S À1 t;t for all genotyping array platforms. For windows where QC has removed part of the typed SNPs used in imputation S À1 t;t needs to be reestimated. Because the window length is fixed across the genome, the overall computational runtime can be thought of linear in the number of SNPs (when S À1 t;t has been precomputed already). The imputed z-scores at SNP i Z ijt can be viewed as a linear combination of typed z-scores Z t with weights W=S i;t S À1 t;t precomputed from the reference panel. Let A denote the variance–covariance matrix among typed SNPs in the population. Because we assume Z t $Nð0; AÞ, it follows that Z ijt has variance WAW T. Therefore, we use Zijt ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi allele frequency across the three deposits (P50.0001 on pairwise comparisons). Preimputation phasing was performed using Mach (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Li et al., 2010</ref>). Imputations against the March 2012 release of 1000genomes all-ethnicities reference haplotypes were performed using Minimac (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Howie et al., 2012</ref>). Associations of imputed allele dosages with standing height, as measured at the 44–45-year follow-up, were analyzed using ProbAbel (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Aulchenko et al., 2010</ref>). Publicly available summary statistics for four lipid traits. Publicly available GWAS summary data across four blood lipids phenotypes (TG, TC, HDL and LDL) were downloaded from public access Web sites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Teslovich et al., 2010</ref>). These data have been recently used in a study of overlap of GWAS findings and functional data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Schork et al., 2013</ref>); all QC steps are described elsewhere (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Teslovich et al., 2010</ref>). The data comprised roughly 2.7 M summary statistics based on $100 000 samples for each of the four phenotypes. To remove strand ambiguity, we removed all A/T and C/G SNPs ($15.4% of all SNPs); we also removed all SNPs with meta-analysis sample sizes under 80 000, leaving $2.0 M SNPs for each of the phenotypes. We imputed to 1000G using ImpG-Summary under three scenarios. In the first scenario, we removed 10% of the SNPs at random. In the second scenario, we removed all SNPs not present on the Illumina 610 genotyping platform ($600 k in total). In both of these scenarios, we imputed from the remaining SNPs and assessed accuracy using the previously masked SNPs. As a metric of accuracy, we computed the correlation between imputed and previously masked association statistics. In the third scenario, we imputed from all 2.0 M SNPs to obtain the summary statistics at 7.3 M SNPs that we publicly release. Enrichment analysis for four lipid traits. We used an analysis similar to<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Schork et al. (2013)</ref>to quantify enrichment per classes of SNPs. We categorized each SNP according to its distance to genes using the all SNPs track (snp137) (http://genome.ucsc.edu/cgi-bin/hgTables). All SNPs within an exon, up to 5 kb upstream and up to 5 kb downstream, located in the 3 0 UTR or in the 5 0 UTR were labeled as genic. SNPs with no annotation in the data were considered as being Intergenic. For each dataset, we normalized the association statistics using genomic control attained only over the Intergenic SNPs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Schork et al., 2013</ref>), followed by computation of average variance across SNPs within each functional class. We estimate the variance as the average of the squared association z-scores minus 1 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Schork et al., 2013</ref>). We compared the magnitude of enrichment in association statistics across different functional classes within the same dataset (either the public data or the imputed one) using the median of the Kolmogorov–Smirnov (KS) test statistic at 100 random draws each of 10 000 random SNPs across the genome. This conservative computation avoids correlations due to LD and does not account for the larger number of SNPs in the 1000G imputed data, which would further increase statistical significance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Gaussian imputation of individual genotypes</head><p>Although we focus primarily on imputation of summary statistics, for completeness, we also discuss Gaussian imputation when individual-level data are available. We compare two different approaches. The first approach is to apply ImpG-SummaryLD as described above, relying only on summary association statistics and summary LD statistics. The second approach (which attains slightly worse results) is similar to the approach proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wen and Stephens (2010)</ref>. As described in that study, we can impute allele frequencies and treat each genotype as a sample of size 2. Following<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wen and Stephens (2010)</ref>, we set to be the observed allele frequency in the reference panel and S½i; j to be the covariance between SNP i and j. Next, we apply the same windowing approach above to each sample independently to impute individual-level genotypes. Although rare, in practice Gaussian imputation can output values 50 or 42; we adjust these values to 0 and 2, respectively. As association statistic, we use the 2 1 df statistic N 2 ðG 0 ; Þ, where N is the number of samples and 2 ðG 0 ; Þ is the squared correlation between the vectors of imputed genotypes and the phenotype.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Simulations</head><p>To explore the effectiveness of Gaussian imputation using summary statistics (ImpG-Summary and ImpG-SummaryLD), we simulated case–control datasets at various effect sizes across a wide range of SNPs (see Section 2). To assess the performance of imputation at recovering the true association signal when present, we used the relative effective sample size, defined as the ratio of average imputed 2 statistics at untyped SNPs versus 2 statistics computed from true genotypes. Here 2 statistics refer to the squared z-score, which has a 2 with 1 df distribution under the null hypothesis. We envision that real scans will restrict their analyses to variants with high-estimated imputation accuracy [r 2 pred40:6, analogous to the r 2 hat estimator in HMMbased imputation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Li et al., 2010</ref>), Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>], but we computed the relative effective sample size with all values of r 2 pred included to provide an appropriate assessment of power. However, we restricted most of our analyses of false positives to accurately imputed variants (r 2 pred40:6), as these are the variants that would be analyzed in a real scan. We first explored the robustness of imputation from summary statistics. ImpG-Summary attains genomic control GC of 0.94 (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S2</ref>), with no increase in false-positive rate at the tail of the distribution (Supplementary Tables S1–S3). Although ImpG-Summary attains a slight deflation (because of the adjustment procedure that has the effect of shrinking the predictor weights), this is necessary to avoid false positives. As expected from the conditional distribution, Gaussian imputation with no variance normalization is deflated ( GC =0:86), while the naive normalization that does not account for the statistical noise in the LD matrix is also susceptible to false positives [we observe a near 4-fold increase in P-values510 À4 as compared with a wellcalibrated statistic in null data simulations (Supplementary Tables S1 and S2 and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S2)]</ref>. Similar results are obtained at different QC thresholds based on r 2 pred (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). However, when pairwise correlations among typed SNPs are available from the GWAS data, the expected variance under null of the imputed statistics can be accurately estimated and used for normalization (<ref type="bibr">ImpGSummaryLD)</ref>. This removes the need for adjusting the LD matrix estimated from the reference panel leading to distributed association statistics with no susceptibility to false positives ( GC =1:00, Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S2</ref>). Recent work in parallel to ours has also investigated the use of Gaussian models for summary association imputation but do not propose an adjustment for the statistical noise in the reference panel (DIST;<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Lee et al., 2013a</ref>). DIST shares many similarities to the version of our approach that does not perform an adjustment for the statistical noise in estimating S. Because we caution that adjusting for the statistical noise in the reference panel is required to avoid false positives when using our method (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S2</ref>), we investigated whether such an adjustment would also be needed for DIST. We simulated a null GWAS by randomly partitioning the 1000G European data, computed z-scores as above and performed Gaussian imputation of summary statistics from SNPs present on a standard genotyping array using both DIST(v0.1.4) and ImpG-Summary (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). We observe that DIST, which does not adjust for statistical noise in the reference panel, is susceptible to false positives at these reference panel sizes (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>); this is consistent to simulations for the variant of our approach that does not adjust S (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S2</ref>). Thus, an adjustment is needed to control the false-positive rate at small reference panel sizes; it is possible that the adjustment factor could be reduced at larger reference panel sizes. We next assessed the ability of ImpG-Summary to identify truepositive associations by measuring the decrease in effective sample size.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>shows the relative effective sample size in 1000G simulations with target and reference haplotypes randomly sampled from 762 European haplotypes (i.e roughly matched for ancestry). As a gold standard for imputation accuracy, we used Beagle, an HMM-based method that requires individuallevel data (<ref type="bibr">Browning, 2007, 2009</ref>). Beagle has previously been shown to achieve similar accuracy as other HMMbased methods, with far superior accuracy compared with tagging-based imputation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Browning and Browning, 2009</ref>;<ref type="bibr">Marchini and Howie, 2010b</ref>). At an odds ratio of 1.5, ImpGSummary recovers 84% (54%) of the effective sample size for common (45%) and low-frequency (1–5%) variants versus 89% (67%) for Beagle imputation. Interestingly, when LD information among the typed variants from the GWAS is available, ImpGSummaryLD recovers 87% (60%) of the effective sample size, nearly as high as Beagle.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>also shows the decrease in effective sample size across a wide array of odds ratios showing that the results are robust to different effect sizes. Thus, imputation from summary statistics can recover most of the association power available from GWAS with individual-level data. We also tested the effect of a mismatch in ancestry between the reference haplotype panel and the target population. We simulated case–control GWAS using the GBR haplotypes for target samples and the remaining 1000G European haplotypes as reference haplotypes.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>shows only marginal decrease in performance for each of HMM, ImpG-Summary and ImpGSummaryLD as compared with previous results, with no excess of false positives (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table S2</ref>). We note that both ImpG-Summary and ImpG-SummaryLD are computationally very fast, with running times several orders of magnitude lower than HMM-based methods for imputation from individual-level genotypes.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>shows a reduction in running time of several orders of magnitude for ImpGSummary as compared with HMM-based approaches. The magnitude of the difference in running time will only increase with larger studies (such as the N = 100 000 studies analyzed below), as the running time of ImpG-Summary is independent of the number of target samples, while the running time of HMMbased imputation is linear in this quantity. However, we note that all of the methods listed in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>can be parallelized across regions of the genome for faster wall-clock running time. Although our work focuses on imputation from summary statistics, for completeness we also investigate Gaussian imputation when individual-level data are available. This has been proposed in (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wen and Stephens, 2010</ref>) and shown to achieve similar accuracy as HMM-based imputation in the context of HapMap 3 data. In simulations from 1000G, we find that our implementation of the (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wen and Stephens, 2010</ref>) approach (see Section 2) achieves slightly but significantly lower accuracy than ImpGSummaryLD (Supplementary Tables S7 and S8) across a wide range of effect sizes. The slight improvement of ImpG-SummaryLD over Gaussian imputation using individual-level genotypes suggests that there is an advantage to phenotype-aware imputation. When individual-level genotypes are available, HMM-based imputation remains the approach of choice because of its slightly higher accuracy, but we recommend the use of ImpG-SummaryLD in preference to previous methods for performing Gaussian imputation when rapidly prioritizing regions for HMM-based analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Application to WTCCC and height datasets</head><p>We explored whether similar results could be attained in real empirical GWAS data. We validated our approach using aNote: The column corresponding to OR = 1 shows the average 2 association statistic under the null model of no association.Note: The 381 European individuals from 1000G were randomly split in half; one half was used as reference panel, while the other half was used to simulate a null GWAS by randomly assigning 85(85) samples as cases(controls). We performed Gaussian imputation using DIST (v0.1.4) and ImpG-Summary with default parameters starting from the variants present on the Illumina 610 genotyping platform and that attained a MAF 45% in both cases and controls (464 897 in total). We kept only accurately imputed variants (MAF41%, r 2 pred40:6 for ImpG-Summary and info 40:6; 0:9 for DIST). WTCCC study spanning seven diseases (Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium, 2007) [roughly 2000 cases for each disease and 3000 shared controls genotyped on Affymetrix 500K array (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table S4</ref>)], and a study of height involving 6500 individuals from the British 1958 birth cohort (1958BC) genotyped on the Affymetrix 6.0 array (see Section 2). Starting from the real genotype data, we used as reference all 758 European haplotypes of the 1000G phase 2 data to accurately impute $4.3 million SNPs with minor allele frequency 41% either using an HMM-based method [IMPUTE2 with prephasing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Howie et al., 2012)]</ref>or ImpG-Summary (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table S4</ref>). We compared association statistics at accurately imputed SNPs with either the HMM-based method or using ImpG-Summary (with the latter assuming no access to individual-level data). We observed an average correlation of 0.94 between the two set of association statistics for both WTCCC and 1958BC phenotypes (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>), showing high similarity between the two approaches (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S4</ref>for each WTCCC phenotype). In general, we observe that the QQ and Manhattan plots show similar behavior for HMM-based association as compared with ImpG-Summary imputation, emphasizing no excess of false positives when only summary data are used in imputation (Supplementary Figs S5–S13). In some instances, we observe differences that we hypothesize represent false positives for the HMM-based imputation, likely because of insufficient QC filtering for the HMM-based approach (Supplementary Figs S10–S12). Importantly, statistics at known associated SNPs from the NHGRI GWAS catalog for each of the considered phenotypes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hindorff et al., 2009</ref>;<ref type="figure">Table 5</ref>) show similar association power across the two compared methods (e.g. an average 2 of 19.17 for HMM-based imputation versus 18.28 across the WTCCC data and 4.55 versus 4.76 for the height phenotype;<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 2</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S5</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Application to publicly available summary statistics for four lipid traits</head><p>We investigated the performance of ImpG-Summary on publicly available summary association statistic datasets of four blood lipid traits (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Teslovich et al., 2010</ref>). These data have been imputed using HMM-based imputation to an average of 2.0 M markers (see Section 2). We imputed this data to 7.3 M 1000G markers.<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Howie et al., 2012</ref>). Beagle runtime extrapolated from an average of 3 CPU h runtime for N = 300 samples across a 5 Mb window in the genome. ImpG-Summary takes 510 h for imputation starting from 600k typed variants and under 4 CPU days for imputation from 2 M typed variants with no precomputation.We randomly masked 10% of the data, reimputed using ImpG-Summary and assessed accuracy by comparing ImpGSummary with the masked data. As expected, we observe a high correlation between the two sets of summary statistics [correlation r = 0.98 (0.95) at common (low-frequency) variants; see<ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S14</ref>]. To quantify the expected accuracy when imputation is performed from array-based association statistics, we also masked all association statistics not present on a standard genotyping array and reimputed using ImpG-Summary. We again observe a high correlation [r = 0.97 (0.91) at common (low-frequency) variants; see<ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S14</ref>], thus showing that our approach recovers association statistics similar to those obtained by HMM-based imputation requiring individual-level genotypes. We have publicly released imputed summary association statistics obtained using the full set of 2.0 M markers, without masking (see Web Resources). As expected, we observed lower GC for ImpG-Summary data as compared with original data (e.g. 0.92 versus 0.98 for HDL phenotype, see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S9</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Enrichment analysis for four lipid traits</head><p>We categorized each SNP according to functional classes (see Section 2). We performed genomic control correction using GC estimated from only the Intergenic SNPs, as in (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Schork et al., 2013</ref>). After normalization, we estimated the average excess variance for each functional class as the average square of the association z-score minus 1 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Schork et al., 2013</ref>). We observe that 1000G imputation using ImpG-Summary increases the average variance for each functional class, with Genic SNPs (and in some cases, Intronic SNPs) showing larger increases than Intergenic SNPs (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 4</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S15</ref>). The increase in mean for each functional class, even after normalization by GC , indicates that 1000G imputation increases the ratio mean / GC , i.e. causes true signals to be more concentrated at the tail of the distribution. 1000G imputation using ImpG-Summary increases statistical evidence of enrichment at Genic versus Intergenic SNPs, both because the magnitude of the enrichment is larger and because of the increased number of SNPs. We focus here on just the former effect by computing KS test statistics at random subsets of 10 000 SNPs, a conservative computation that avoids correlations because of LD (see Section 2). Across all four phenotypes, median KS test statistics were more significant in the 1000G imputed data versus the original dataset (e.g. 4.75E-08 versus 7.63E-05 for HDL; see Supplementary Table S10 for all phenotypes). This highlights the increased utility of the 1000G imputed summary statistics that we have publicly released for analyses of functional enrichment. expanded to the set of all 1000G variants. In particular, we have publicly released imputed association statistics at 1000G variants for four lipid traits. We show that for these four lipid traits, 1000G imputed summary statistics show a consistently larger and more statistically significant signal of enrichment in genic versus non-genic regions as compared with the original publicly available data. Thus, 1000G imputed summary statistics can be used to increase power in studies of functional enrichment. The Gaussian approximation for LD among SNPs has previously been used in a wide range of problems (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Conneely and Boehnke, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Han et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">McPeek, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wen and Stephens, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Zaitlen et al., 2010</ref>). We showed that an adjustment similar to ridge regression removed the false-positive associations in imputed summary statistics that occurred when unadjusted estimates of LD were used. As reference panels become larger, we expect a smaller adjustment factor to be needed, thus increasing accuracy. Large reference panels of typed SNPs could potentially also be used to reduce the adjustment factor needed for avoiding false positives (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Yang et al., 2012</ref>). Other recent works have proposed to reduce the computational burden of imputation using a technique similar to matrix completion; however, that approach does not extend to imputation from summary statistics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Chi et al., 2013</ref>). Our proposed procedure relies on accurate estimates of pairwise LD that match the population of the GWAS sample, in contrast to HMM-based approaches that use cosmopolitan reference panels that include all available haplotype data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Howie et al., 2012</ref>). Our method is directly applicable to admixed populations such as African Americans and Latino Americans for which 1000G reference panels are currently available (<ref type="bibr">The 1000</ref><ref type="bibr">Genomes Project Consortium, 2012</ref>), but is not applicable to samples of uncertain ethnicity or samples for which reference panels are not available. The method proposed here relies on a windowing approach to reduce the number of pairwise LD parameters to be estimated from the reference panels. Although this procedure reduces dramatically the number of pairwise LD parameters, our choice of window size (1 cM) may still allow for overestimation of pairwise LD because of finite reference panel sizes. Recent work has shown that population genetic principles can be used to derive shrinkage factors based on recombination maps and reference panel sizes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wen and Stephens, 2010</ref>). A potentially fruitful direction for future work is to combine such derivations with window-based approaches to increase accuracy. The work of Wen and Stephens (2010) presented methods for Gaussian imputation from allele frequencies in cases and controls or from individual-level genotypes. There are many key differences between that work and this study. First, we impute association statistics (i.e. z-scores) rather than allele frequencies. For case–control traits, it is unclear how to use imputed allele frequencies in cases and controls (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wen and Stephens, 2010</ref>) to obtain association statistics that are robust to false positives; for quantitative traits, imputation of allele frequencies does not apply. Thus, the methods and software of Wen and Stephens (2010) cannot be used to impute association statistics, as we have done here. Second, we evaluate our approach in simulations based on 1000G data (<ref type="bibr">The 1000</ref><ref type="bibr">Genomes Project Consortium, 2012</ref>), assessing both power and false-positive associations. Third, we validate our approach using real empirical data across several GWAS involving both discrete and continuous phenotypes, including the four lipid traits for which we have publicly released imputed association statistics at 1000G variants. We note that recent parallel work has also proposed to use summary statistics with reference panels of haplotypes for imputation<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[(Lee et al., 2013a</ref>); a related approach is proposed in (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hu et al., 2013)]</ref>, but that work does not provide a strategy to address false-positive associations arising from the limited size of the reference panel, as we do here. We conclude with several limitations for the approaches we presented here. First, when summary LD statistics from the study are not available, our adjustment procedure leads to a slight deflation of association statistics under null data. This could hamper efforts to assess confounding because of population stratification or cryptic relatedness via genomic control (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Devlin and Roeder, 1999</ref>). However, it is now widely recognized that genomic control is not an effective approach for assessing confounding in large studies, because of the expected inflation from polygenic effects (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Yang et al., 2011</ref>). Second, application of our approach to summary statistics with inappropriate levels of QC is a potential concern because of the possibility of introducing false positives. Therefore, we caution that appropriate QC should be performed on typed variants before estimation ofsummary association statistics, as is standard procedure in any GWAS. Third, recent work has shown that low-coverage sequencing is a more powerful alternative to genotyping arrays per unit of cost invested (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Flannick et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Li et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Nielsen et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Pasaniuc et al., 2012</ref>). The extension of Gaussian imputation to low-coverage sequencing data remains a direction for future work. Finally, as with all imputation approaches, the methods presented here are more accurate for common variants than for low-frequency variants. Accuracy will be even lower at rare variants, although GWAS involving single-variant associations are generally focused on common and low-frequency variants.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>2.</head><figDesc>Relative effective sample size at imputed SNPs (ratio of the average 2 association statistics attained at imputed versus typed SNPs) in simulated case–control studies at different effect sizes (OR 41)Low-frequency SNPs (1–5%) Beagle 0.997 0.808 0.667 0.640 0.620 ImpG-Summary 0.881 0.685 0.539 0.512 0.491 ImpG-SummaryLD 0.997 0.768 0.597 0.565 0.542</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Average variance per SNP (average association z 2 – 1) binned by different functional classes for all four blood phenotypes. Left displays the absolute numbers attained across the original data and the ImpG-Summary imputation to 1000G (r2pred 40.8). Right figure shows the absolute difference between original data and 1000G imputed association statistics</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Table</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Number of variants attaining a given confidence level in a simulated null GWAS</figDesc><table>Method 
All SNPs 
Significance level 

1E-3 
1E-4 
1E-5 
5E-8 

Simulated data 
5 961 977 
4747 
451 
56 
0 
DIST(v0.1.4, info 40.6) 
5 620 505 
6954 
946 
186 
22 
DIST(v0.1.4, info 40.9) 
4 969 996 
5133 
584 
78 
1 
ImpG-Summary 
5 469 489 
1806 
103 
4 
0 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 4.</figDesc><table>Estimated runtimes for 1000G imputation for various numbers 
of individuals (N) in imputation 

Method 
N = 1000 
N = 10 000 
N = 50 000 

IMPUTE1 
893.8 
8,937.5 
44,687.5 
IMPUTE2 (sampling) 
100 
1000 
5000 
IMPUTE2 (prephasing) 
4.2 
41.7 
208.3 
IMPUTE2 (prephasing) a 
21.5 
215.3 
1,076.4 
Beagle 
250 
2,500 
12,500 
ImpG-Summary 
0.4 
0.4 
0.4 
ImpG-SummaryLD 
0.4 
0.4 
0.4 

Note: Runtimes given in central processing unit (CPU) days needed to impute across 
the whole genome (11.6 million SNPs polymorphic in Europeans). Runtimes for all 
versions of IMPUTE extrapolated from Howie et al. (2012). a Includes GWAS 
phasing time of 25 min per individual (</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 5.</figDesc><table>Average association statistics ( 2 ) over known associated SNPs 
from NHGRI GWAS Catalog for the eight studied phenotypes 

Phenotype 
SNPs 
HMM 
ImpG-Summary 
Ratio 

BD 
9 
7.02 
6.66 
0.95 
CAD 
32 
13.39 
13.11 
0.98 
CD 
70 
20.78 
19.74 
0.95 
HT 
7 
4.47 
3.95 
0.88 
RA 
22 
20.36 
19.00 
0.93 
T1D 
36 
36.39 
34.98 
0.96 
T2D 
51 
12.08 
11.45 
0.95 
All WTCCC 
227 
19.17 
18.28 
0.95 
Height 1958 BC 
176 
4.55 
4.76 
1.05 

Note: The average across all SNPs except HLA region (chr6:20–35 Mb) in WTCCC 
data consisting of 216 SNPs in a total of 16.02 for HMM versus 15.29 for ImpG-
Summary. All WTCCC denotes averages across all WTCCC data. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 3.</figDesc><table>Relative effective sample size at imputed SNPs (ratio of the 
average 2 association statistics attained at imputed versus typed SNPs) 
when imputation is performed in a random subsample of the 1000G 
European data or over only Great Britain haplotypes (odds ratio is set 
to 1.5) 

Method 
Rand 
Great Britain 

Common SNPs (45%) 
Beagle 
0.885 
0.880 
ImpG-Summary 
0.841 
0.835 
ImpG-SummaryLD 
0.867 
0.860 
Low-frequency SNPs (1–5%) 
Beagle 
0.667 
0.671 
ImpG-Summary 
0.539 
0.549 
ImpG-SummaryLD 
0.597 
0.603 

Fig. 1. HMM-imputed (x-axis) versus ImpG-Summary (y-axis) associ-
ation statistics (z-scores) for the BD phenotype in WTCCC Data (left) 
and over height phenotype in 1958 Birth Cohort Data (right). Results for 
all other WTCCC phenotypes can be found in Supplementary Figure S4 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Imputation of summary statistics at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">WAW T p as the imputation z-score at imputed SNP i. To account for the statistical noise, while also making sure that S is invertible we adopt a procedure similar to ridge regression (Hoerl and Kennard, 1970) and use S=S unadj +I in both S i;t and S t;t in the estimation of W (we use =0:1 as default; see Supplementary Tables S1–S3 for results across other values of ). We approximate A with S t;t using LD information from reference panel (ImpG-Summary). An alternative is to use the true A, i.e. the summary LD statistics from the GWAS sample, if they are available; in this case, a more substantial adjustment for statistical noise in S is not needed because A is derived from the GWAS sample, and we set =0:001 to make sure that S is invertible in the estimation of W (ImpG-SummaryLD). We do not use the summary LD statistics across typed SNPs in the sample for estimation of W in ImpG-SummaryLD, to maintain consistency among pairwise LD statistics between typed and imputed SNPs. Software implementing the ImpG-Summary and ImpG-SummaryLD methods has been made publicly available. We propose a metric for imputation accuracy based on the variance of the conditional random variable Z i jZ t : we define r 2 pred=1 À S ijt. Supplementary Figure S1 shows that r 2 pred behaves similarly to the standard imputation accuracy metric r 2 hat(Li et al., 2010; correlation of 0.90 to the true r 2 accuracy as compared with 0.92 for r 2 hat). 2.3 Simulation framework We simulated data starting from the 381 diploid European individuals from the phase 2 release of the 1000 Genomes Project (June 2011; The 1000 Genomes Project Consortium, 2012). The 381 individuals include 87 CEPH individuals of North European ancestry, 93 Finnish individuals from Finland, 89 British individuals from England and Scotland (GBR), 98 Tuscan individuals and 14 individuals from the Iberian peninsula. Genotype calls and haplotypic phase had been previously inferred from low-coverage sequencing (4Â) using an imputation strategy that borrowed information across samples and loci (The 1000 Genomes Project Consortium, 2012). The set haplotypes were split at random between a set of 178 (number chosen to match the 89 samples of British ancestry) haplotypes used to build simulated data, and the other set was used as an imputation reference panel. Starting from the simulation panel of haplotypes, we used HAPGEN (Su et al., 2011) to simulate 10 000 diploid individuals. All simulation results were generated over 50 distinct 1 Mb regions (total of 50 Mb) randomly chosen across Chromosome 1 totaling 321 226 SNPs. For each of the SNPs with MAF 41% in the reference panel (133 025 in total), we simulated case–control datasets by randomly choosing a subset of 1000 controls, and then choosing 1000 cases from the remaining samples so that samples with 0:1:2 reference alleles have relative probabilities 1: OR: OR 2 of being chosen (for a given odds ratio (OR)). For null simulations, we randomly selected 1000 samples as cases and 1000 samples as controls. 2.4 Real data WTCCC dataset. We examined data from the WTCCC phase 1 comprising GWAS studies of seven diseases: Bipolar disorder (BD), Coronary heart disease (CAD), Crohn&apos;s disease (CD), Hypertension (HT), Rheumatoid arthritis (RA), Type 1 diabetes (T1D) and Type 2 diabetes (T2D) (see Supplementary Table S4 for detailed sample sizes; Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium, 2007). We removed all SNPs that had overall deviation from Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium at a P-value below 0.01. Then, we removed any SNP that had differential missigness (P50.01) in any of the case–control cohort, overall missingness 40.001 or minor allele frequency 50.01. This yielded 325 553 SNPs. We performed HMM-based imputation using the prephasing approach of (Howie et al., 2012); we used HAPI-UR (Williams et al., 2012) to infer haplotypes from genotypes and then ran IMPUTE2 (Howie et al., 2012) using default parameters on the inferred haplotypes. Unless otherwise noted, we filtered out imputed SNPs using an imputation accuracy cutoff of 0.6, as well as SNPs that had 45% of the individual imputed calls missing at a posterior probability level of 0.9. This procedure yielded $4.7 M SNPs for the considered phenotypes (Supplementary Table S4). 1958 Birth Cohort data. The British 1958 birth cohort is an ongoing follow-up of all persons born in England, Scotland and Wales during 1 week in 1958. At the age of 44–45 years, the cohort was followed up with a biomedical examination and blood sampling (Strachan et al., 2007), from which a DNA collection was established as a nationally representative reference panel (http://www.b58cgene.sgul.ac.uk/). Non-overlapping subsets of the DNA collection were genotyped by the Wellcome Trust Case–Control Consortium (WTCCC; Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium, 2007), the Type 1 Diabetes Genetics Consortium (T1DGC; Barrett et al., 2009) and the GABRIEL consortium (Moffatt et al., 2010). Genotyping by the WTCCC used both the Affymetrix 500K array and the Illumina 550K (version 1) array. Because the T1DGC used the Illumina 550K (version 3) array and GABRIEL used the Illumina 610K array, a combined dataset was created of SNPs in common across these three panels. SNPs were excluded from subsequent imputation if they had MAF 51%, call rate 595%, HWE P50.0001 or differences in</note>

			<note place="foot">B.Pasaniuc et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> DISCUSSION We have introduced an approach for imputation of association statistics at untyped variants directly from summary association statistics using publicly available reference panels of haplotypes such as 1000G (The 1000 Genomes Project Consortium, 2012), in contrast to widely used HMM-based approaches that require individual-level genotypes (Howie et al., 2012). Through extensive simulations and real data analyses, we show that our approach is almost as powerful as imputation from individual-level genotypes (for both common and low-frequency variants) with no excess of false positives. We have described a method that uses summary association statistics (ImpG-Summary), as well as a method that uses summary association statistics and summary LD statistics (ImpG-SummaryLD). Because summary LD statistics are not currently widely shared, we expect that ImpGSummary will be of greatest practical value in the immediate future. However, the slightly higher power attained by ImpGSummaryLD provides a motivation for sharing of summary LD statistics to become a widely accepted practice. This is likely to also prove valuable in other settings, such as conditional analysis or rare variant testing (Lee et al., 2013b; Yang et al., 2012). It is often the case that privacy and logistic constraints prohibit the sharing of individual-level data. On the other hand, summary association statistics from large-scale association studies are often readily available (Schork et al., 2013; Teslovich et al., 2010), despite the fact that privacy concerns may extend to summary data (Homer et al., 2008; Sankararaman et al., 2009). For example, a recent study used publicly available summary association statistics over a wide range of phenotypes to draw inferences about the enrichment of disease-associated variants in several functional categories (Schork et al., 2013). Using the methods introduced here, such analyses can be Fig. 3. HMM-imputed (x-axis) versus ImpG-Summary (y-axis) association statistics (z-scores) for the TG phenotype in the blood lipids data. Left denotes imputation of 10% of the z-scores using the remaining 90%, while right shows imputation results starting from all variants present on the Illumina 610 array. Results for all blood lipids phenotypes can be found in Supplementary Figure S13. ImpG-Summary took 4 CPU days for the 10% data and under 10 CPU h for the array-based imputation Fig. 2. HMM-imputed (x-axis) versus ImpG-Summary (y-axis) association statistics (z-scores) at known associated SNPs from NHGRI GWAS Catalog in WTCCC (left) and height in 1958 Birth Cohort Data (right)</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabel package for genome-wide association analysis of imputed data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Aulchenko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">134</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide association study and meta-analysis find that over 40 loci affect risk of type 1 diabetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Barrett</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="703" to="707" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A unified approach to genotype imputation and haplotype-phase inference for large data sets of trios and unrelated individuals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Browning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Browning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="210" to="223" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid and accurate haplotype phasing and missing data inference for whole genome association studies using localized haplotype clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Browning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Browning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1084" to="1097" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genotype imputation via matrix completion</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Chi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="518" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">So many correlated tests, so little time! Rapid adjustment of P values for multiple correlated tests</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Conneely</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Boehnke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1158" to="1168" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic control for association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Devlin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Roeder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="997" to="1004" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide meta-analysis identifies 56 bone mineral density loci and reveals 14 loci associated with risk of fracture</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Estrada</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="491" to="501" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficiency and power as a function of sequence coverage, snp array density, and imputation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Flannick</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002604</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid and accurate multiple testing correction and power estimation for millions of correlated markers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Han</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000456</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Elements of Statistical Learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Hastie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Potential etiologic and functional implications of genome-wide association loci for human diseases and traits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Hindorff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9362" to="9367" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ridge regression: biased estimation for nonorthogonal problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Hoerl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Kennard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Resolving individuals contributing trace amounts of dna to highly complex mixtures using high-density SNP genotyping microarrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Homer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast and accurate genotype imputation in genome-wide association studies through pre-phasing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Howie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="955" to="959" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meta-analysis of gene-level associations for rare variants based on single-variant statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y.-J</forename>
				<surname>Hu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="236" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hundreds of variants clustered in genomic loci and biological pathways affect human height</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Lango Allen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">467</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="832" to="838" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dist: direct imputation of summary statistics for unmeasured SNPs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2925" to="2927" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">General framework for meta-analysis of rare variants in sequencing association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mach: using sequence and genotype data to estimate haplotypes and unobserved genotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="816" to="834" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low-coverage sequencing: implications for design of complex trait association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="940" to="951" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide meta-analyses identify three loci associated with primary biliary cirrhosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="658" to="660" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genotype imputation for genome-wide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Marchini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Howie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blup genotype imputation for case-control association testing with related individuals and missing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Mcpeek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="756" to="765" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A large-scale, consortium-based genomewide association study of asthma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Moffatt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N. Engl. J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">363</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1211" to="1221" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale association analysis provides insights into the genetic architecture and pathophysiology of type 2 diabetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Morris</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="981" to="990" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asking for more</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Genetics. Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="733" to="831" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genotype and SNP calling from next-generation sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Nielsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extremely low-coverage sequencing and imputation increases power for genome-wide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Pasaniuc</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="631" to="635" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic privacy and limits of individual detection in a pool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Sankararaman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="965" to="967" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">All snps are not created equal: genome-wide association studies reveal a consistent pattern of enrichment among functionally annotated SNPs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Schork</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003449</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lifecourse influences on health among british adults: effects of region of residence in childhood and adulthood</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Strachan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="522" to="531" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hapgen2: simulation of multiple disease SNPs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Su</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2304" to="2305" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biological, clinical and population relevance of 95 loci for blood lipids</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Teslovich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">466</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="707" to="713" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated map of genetic variation from 1,092 human genomes</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The 1000 Genomes Project Consortium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="65" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide association study of 14,000 cases of seven common diseases and 3,000 shared controls</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<editor>Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">447</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="661" to="678" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using linear predictors to impute allele frequencies from summary or pooled genotype data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Wen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Stephens</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Appl. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1158" to="1182" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phasing of many thousands of genotyped samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Williams</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic inflation factors under polygenic inheritance</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="807" to="812" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conditional and joint multiple-SNP analysis of GWAS summary statistics identifies additional variants influencing complex traits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="375" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leveraging genetic variability across populations for the identification of causal variants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Zaitlen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>