
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology FastMEDUSA: a parallelized tool to infer gene regulatory networks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Serdar</forename>
								<surname>Bozdag</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Neuro-Oncology Branch</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Diseases and Stroke</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">National Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Institute of Neurological</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Aiguo</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Neuro-Oncology Branch</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Diseases and Stroke</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">National Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Institute of Neurological</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Stefan</forename>
								<surname>Wuchty</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Neuro-Oncology Branch</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Diseases and Stroke</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">National Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Institute of Neurological</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Howard</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Fine</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>hfine@mail.nih.gov</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Neuro-Oncology Branch</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Diseases and Stroke</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">National Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Institute of Neurological</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Olga</forename>
								<surname>Troyanskaya</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">National Center for Biotechnology Information</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Institutes of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20892</postCode>
									<settlement>Bethesda</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology FastMEDUSA: a parallelized tool to infer gene regulatory networks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1792" to="1793"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq275</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on January 19, 2010; revised on April 21, 2010; accepted on May 21, 2010</note>
					<note>[10:57 16/6/2010 Bioinformatics-btq275.tex] Page: 1792 1792–1793 Associate Editor: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: In order to construct gene regulatory networks of higher organisms from gene expression and promoter sequence data efficiently, we developed FastMEDUSA. In this parallelized version of the regulatory network-modeling tool MEDUSA, expression and sequence data are shared among a user-defined number of processors on a single multi-core machine or cluster. Our results show that FastMEDUSA allows a more efficient utilization of computational resources. While the determination of a regulatory network of brain tumor in Homo sapiens takes 12 days with MEDUSA, FastMEDUSA obtained the same results in 6 h by utilizing 100 processors. Availability: Source code and documentation of FastMEDUSA are available at https://wiki.nci.nih.gov/display/NOBbioinf/FastMEDUSA Contact:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Among the numerous ways to determine gene regulatory networks of higher organism (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bussemaker et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Elemento et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Segal et al., 2003</ref>), MEDUSA is a well-known and powerful computational tool (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kundaje et al., 2008</ref>). Utilizing a boosting algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Freund and Shapire, 1997</ref>), MEDUSA models promoter sequences and gene expression data from various experimental conditions. Providing a global predictive model of condition-specific expression states of target genes, MEDUSA has been successfully used to discover novel regulators in oxygen and heme regulatory networks in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kundaje et al., 2008</ref>). Although MEDUSA is a powerful computational tool for inferring gene regulatory networks, it has certain limitations. MEDUSA requires the commercially available software package, MATLAB. In addition, the execution time of MEDUSA increases dramatically with larger sizes of input data sets. For example, MEDUSA needed &gt;4 weeks for the modeling and analysis of about 7000 genes using 1000 iterations. Parallel computing has been used to solve the latter problem for several bioinformatics applications to date (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Xiaohong et al., 2009</ref>). Here we introduce FastMEDUSA, a fast, parallelized, open source implementation of MEDUSA in C++ that uses freely available libraries. Our benchmark results showed that</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Benchmarking</head><p>We tested the performance of FastMEDUSA and MEDUSA utilizing discretized expression and promoter sequences of 6291 genes, 501 regulators in 18 samples of yeast (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kundaje et al., 2008</ref>) and 14 819 genes, 1268 regulators in 159 samples of human brain tumor (glioma) data set (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Li et al., 2009</ref>). Human regulators and promoter sequences were obtained from MatBase (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cartharius et al., 2005</ref>) and Gene2Promoter (http://www.genomatix.de), respectively. We ran both tools on the Biowulf Linux cluster (1 Gb/s Ethernet network, 4-core 2.8 GHz AMD Opteron(tm) Processor 290 and 8 GB memory) at the National Institutes of Health. To obtain comparable ADTs, we used the same default parameters, disabled all random choices and reduced the precision of some double variables in both tools (see Supplementary Material for modified M files of MEDUSA).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>We tested the performance of FastMEDUSA and MEDUSA by controlling for the number of iterations and the number of processors used. Specifically, we defined the performance increase of FastMEDUSA utilizing i iterations and n processors</p><formula>as PI i,n = t MEDUSA i t FastMEDUSA i,n</formula><p>, where t is the execution time. The results on the yeast and human data sets show that FastMEDUSA consistently outperforms MEDUSA (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>). For instance, MEDUSA takes about 12 days to analyze the human glioma data set utilizing 400 iterations, whereas FastMEDUSA analyzes the same data set and obtains the same ADTs in about 6 h utilizing 100 processors. FastMEDUSA is also about 30% faster than MEDUSA in serial mode. The slope of the performance increase reduces for increasing computing resources because of the increase in the cost of inter-process communications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Through the implementation of FastMEDUSA, a parallelized version of the gene regulatory-network modeling tool MEDUSA, we solve two problems inherent in the original implementation. First, we provide an open source implementation in C++ that uses freely available libraries. More importantly, we show that FastMEDUSA allows a dramatically more efficient utilization of computational resources. We expect that FastMEDUSA will be used on single multi-core machines, distributed systems or cloud computing facilities to model large data sets of complex organisms that would have been highly cumbersome using the serial implementation of the original algorithm.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FastMEDUSAFig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. In (a), we show the flowchart of FastMEDUSA, highlighting parallelized steps. (b) Testing the performance, we ran FastMEDUSA and MEDUSA on yeast and human data sets for 200 and 400 iterations. We observed that FastMEDUSA consistently outperforms MEDUSA. The graphs and raw data of output ADTs are reported in Supplementary Figures S1–S8 and Supplementary Tables S1–S8.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. FastMEDUSA allows to model gene sets about 40 times faster than the original implementation of MEDUSA, utilizing 100 processors. 2 METHODS 2.1 Algorithm In MEDUSA, a training set consists of a matrix of discretized expression pairs (g,e) of a gene g in experiment e. MEDUSA applies boosting on the training set to iteratively build an alternating decision tree (ADT), which consists of weighted weak classifiers. A weak classifier, which consists of a motif m, regulator r and expression state s of r, classifies a set of examples (g,e) where motif m is present in the promoter of gene g and the expression state of regulator r is s in experiment e. A weak classifier with maximum classifier score is added to the ADT iteratively. Each element in the training set is reweighted for the next iteration where misclassified elements get a higher weight than accurately classified elements. In a final ADT, the total weight (i.e. prediction score) of the weak classifiers that satisfy an element in the test set represents the overall prediction for this element. Initially, MEDUSA computes all motifs (i.e. k-mers and optionally dimers) from promoter sequences of genes (Fig. 1a). At each iteration, first, optimum weak classifier and its optimum position in the ADT are computed based on a classifier score. Subsequently, the algorithm generates probabilistic motifs by clustering the top n motifs that optimize classifier score, where n is a user-defined parameter. After computing pairwise distances, motifs are clustered iteratively. In each clustering step, classifier score of the clustered motif is computed by scanning the motif against the promoter sequences. If a clustered motif has a higher score than the motif in the weak classifier has, the motif is replaced by this clustered motif. The final weak classifier is added to the ADT, and each element in the training set is reweighted for the next iteration. For algorithmic details of MEDUSA, see Kundaje et al. (2007) and Middendorf et al. (2005). FastMEDUSA, a parallelized implementation of the MEDUSA algorithm, designates one of the processors as the root processor to manage interprocessor communication and compute global results. The root processor assigns a unique subtree of the ADT to each remaining processor, which computes optimum weak classifier and its position for the assigned subADT and sends results back to the root processor. In addition, the root processor partitions genes among remaining processors equally to parallelize gene-wise operations. For instance, each processor scans the clustered motif against promoter sequences of the assigned genes in each clustering step in parallel. Parallelizing reweighting elements, each processor reweights only the assigned genes. Summarizing all parallelized steps, we present a flowchart of FastMEDUSA in Figure 1a. 2.2 Implementation FastMEDUSA was implemented in C++, utilizing the message passing interface (MPI) implementation MPICH2 for inter-process communication (http://www.mcs.anl.gov/research/projects/mpich2/) and GotoBLAS2</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from [10:57 16/6/2010 Bioinformatics-btq275.tex]</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We would like to thank Dr Christina Leslie and Steve Lianoglou for their useful discussion about MEDUSA.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulatory element detection using correlation with expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Bussemaker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MatInspector and beyond: promoter analysis based on transcription factor binding sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Cartharius</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2933" to="2942" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A universal framework for regulatory element discovery across all genomes and data types</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Elemento</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="350" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A decision-theoretic generalization of on-line and an application of boosting</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Freund</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Shapire</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comp. Syst. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning regulatory programs that accurately predict differential expression with MEDUSA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Kundaje</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. N Y Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A predictive model of the oxygen and heme regulatory network in yeast</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Kundaje</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unsupervised analysis of transcriptomic profiles reveals six glioma subtypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2091" to="2099" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motif Discovery Through Predictive Modeling of Gene Regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Middendorf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">RECOMB 2005</title>
		<editor>Miyano,S. et al.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="358" to="552" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide discovery of transcriptional modules from DNA sequence and gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Segal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloud technologies for bioinformatics applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Xiaohong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2nd Workshop on Many-Task Computing on Grids and Supercomputers</title>
		<meeting>the 2nd Workshop on Many-Task Computing on Grids and Supercomputers<address><addrLine>Portland, Oregon</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>