
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies footprintDB: a database of transcription factors with annotated cis elements and binding interfaces</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alvaro</forename>
								<surname>Sebastian</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics and Plant Production</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Estació n Experimental de Aula Dei/ CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Av. Montañ ana 1005</addrLine>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bruno</forename>
								<surname>Contreras-Moreira</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics and Plant Production</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Estació n Experimental de Aula Dei/ CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Av. Montañ ana 1005</addrLine>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<surname>Fundació</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics and Plant Production</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Estació n Experimental de Aula Dei/ CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Av. Montañ ana 1005</addrLine>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Paseo</forename>
								<forename type="middle">María</forename>
								<surname>Araid</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics and Plant Production</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Estació n Experimental de Aula Dei/ CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Av. Montañ ana 1005</addrLine>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<surname>Agustín</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics and Plant Production</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Estació n Experimental de Aula Dei/ CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Av. Montañ ana 1005</addrLine>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Spain</forename>
								<surname>Zaragoza</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics and Plant Production</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Estació n Experimental de Aula Dei/ CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Av. Montañ ana 1005</addrLine>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jonathan</forename>
								<surname>Associate</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics and Plant Production</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Estació n Experimental de Aula Dei/ CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Av. Montañ ana 1005</addrLine>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<surname>Wren</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics and Plant Production</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Estació n Experimental de Aula Dei/ CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Av. Montañ ana 1005</addrLine>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies footprintDB: a database of transcription factors with annotated cis elements and binding interfaces</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="258" to="265"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt663</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on September 4, 2013; revised on October 22, 2013; accepted on November 8, 2013</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Traditional and high-throughput techniques for determining transcription factor (TF) binding specificities are generating large volumes of data of uneven quality, which are scattered across individual databases. Results: FootprintDB integrates some of the most comprehensive freely available libraries of curated DNA binding sites and systematically annotates the binding interfaces of the corresponding TFs. The first release contains 2422 unique TF sequences, 10 112 DNA binding sites and 3662 DNA motifs. A survey of the included data sources, organisms and TF families was performed together with proprietary database TRANSFAC, finding that footprintDB has a similar coverage of multicellular organisms, while also containing bacterial regulatory data. A search engine has been designed that drives the prediction of DNA motifs for input TFs, or conversely of TF sequences that might recognize input regulatory sequences, by comparison with database entries. Such predictions can also be extended to a single proteome chosen by the user, and results are ranked in terms of interface similarity. Benchmark experiments with bacterial, plant and human data were performed to measure the predictive power of footprintDB searches, which were able to correctly recover 10, 55 and 90% of the tested sequences, respectively. Correctly predicted TFs had a higher interface similarity than the average, confirming its diagnostic value. Availability and implementation: Web site implemented in PHP, Perl, MySQL and Apache. Freely available from http://floresta.eead.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Transcription is one of the most important processes in gene expression, and it is modulated primarily by the binding of regulatory proteins called transcription factors (TFs) to short DNA sequences, called cis elements or DNA binding sites (DBSs). The DBS recognition mechanism is generally degenerate, as one TF can usually bind to a collection of similar but different cis elements, which can be grouped together to define a DNA motif.</p><p>Motifs are most frequently represented as position-specific scoring matrices (PSSM) that capture the occurrence of nucleotides in aligned positions of the underlying DBSs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Stormo, 2000</ref>). Furthermore, motifs are frequently plotted as sequence logos, which graphically summarize the binding specificities and/or affinities of TFs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Schneider and Stephens, 1990</ref>) (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). Traditional experimental methods to identify DBSs are technically challenging and have been frequently limited to determining cis-regulatory sites for one TF at a time. These methods such as DNA footprinting or electrophoretic mobility shift assays (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Galas and Schmitz, 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Garner and Revzin, 1981</ref>; O'<ref type="bibr">Neill and Turner, 1996</ref>) yield high-quality data and have been the primary source of data for expert-curated databases such as RegulonDB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Salgado et al., 2013</ref>). However, these approaches do not scale well and are currently being replaced by protocols that allow high-throughput discovery of DBSs, such as protein binding microarrays, ChIP-chip or ChIP-Seq experiments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Berger and Bulyk, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Johnson et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Ren et al., 2000</ref>). These procedures produce large volumes of raw sequence data, which must be preprocessed and filtered to derive DNA motifs. Databases such as JASPAR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Portales-Casamar et al., 2010</ref>) and TRANSFAC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Matys et al., 2006</ref>) are increasingly annotating DBSs produced by such protocols, fueled by articles that report experimentally derived DBSs and motifs for large repertoires of TFs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Down et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Jolma et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Noyes et al., 2008</ref>) On other side there are experimental approaches for characterizing the interface residues of TFs, those in charge of recognizing the nucleotide bases of target cis elements. Beyond site-directed mutagenesis (O'<ref type="bibr">Neill et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Shortle et al., 1981</ref>), the most accurate methods are X-ray crystallography and nuclear magnetic resonance studies of protein–DNA complexes. The resulting structures are maintained and published at the Protein Data Bank (PDB) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Berman et al., 2000</ref>). By further digesting these structural models, the 3D-fooprint database routinely annotates the interfaces of all DNA binding proteins contained therein, following simple geometrical criteria: interface residues must form hydrogen bonds or hydrophobic contacts with nitrogen bases or else locate heavy atoms within 4.5 A ˚ of any nitrogen base (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Contreras-Moreira, 2010</ref>). Here we present footprintDB, a meta-database, which integrates the most comprehensive freely available libraries of curated DBSs and systematically annotates, for the first time, *To whom correspondence should be addressed. the binding interfaces of the corresponding TFs. Furthermore, we survey the redundancy of all included databases and compare them with TRANSFAC, a subscription-based commercial alternative. Besides allowing users to compare DNA sequences/ motifs with records in the database, as most included repositories do, footprintDB can also interrogate complete proteomes to identify which TFs are likely to recognize input cis elements. Annotated interfaces are particularly valuable for the second type of query, as our benchmarks indicate that TFs with similar interface residues are more likely to bind to similar DBSs. The three unique features of footprintDB are as follows: (i) the possibility to search against multiple curated databases at the same time or to add custom databases, (ii) the annotation of interface residues within DNA binding protein domains and (iii) the support for browsing TFs within user-provided proteomes, which are most likely to bind a DBS of interest. This resource is available at http://floresta.eead.csic.es/footprintdb.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data sources</head><p>FootprintDB is by design a meta-database of TFs attached to their experimentally determined DNA binding preferences (PSSMs and/or DBSs). Therefore it does not incorporate other databases that contain only TF, DBS or predicted regulatory sequences. The first building block is 3D-footprint (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Contreras-Moreira, 2010</ref>), a database for the structural analysis of protein–DNA complexes, for two reasons: (i) it is to our knowledge the only up-to-date source of annotated binding interfaces of TFs, and (ii) it contains structure-based PSSMs, motifs inferred from cis elements captured in X-ray and nuclear magnetic resonance complexes, that have been independently validated (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">AlQuraishi and McAdams, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Lin and Chen, 2013</ref>). The remaining databases and repositories currently integrated in footprintDB are as follows:</p><p>(1) JASPAR CORE (2009 version, all species redundant set): a highquality collection of TF DNA binding preferences, modeled as PSSMs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Portales-Casamar et al., 2010</ref>).</p><p>(2) UniPROBE (Universal PBM Resource for Oligonucleotide Binding Evaluation, Sep 2012 version): it contains in vitro DNA binding specificities of proteins measured with universal protein binding microarrays (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Robasky and Bulyk, 2011</ref>).</p><formula>(3)</formula><p>'HumanTF': a sequence-specific binding preferences of human TFs obtained by high-throughput SELEX and ChIP sequencing. It includes a total of 830 binding profiles, describing 239 distinctly different binding specificities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Jolma et al., 2013</ref>).</p><p>(4) Athamap: a genome-wide map of potential TF binding sites in Arabidopsis thaliana (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bulow et al., 2009</ref>).</p><p>(5) RegulonDB (7.5 version): it contains curated data of the transcriptional regulatory network of Escherichia coli K12, including PSSMs and DBSs for many TFs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Salgado et al., 2013</ref>).</p><p>(6) DBTBS (Database of transcriptional regulation in Bacillus subtilis): a database of transcriptional regulation in B.subtilis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Sierro et al., 2008</ref>).</p><p>(7) 'DrosophilaTF': motifs for 56 Drosophila melanogaster TFs built from in vitro binding site selection experiments and compiled genomic binding site sequences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Down et al., 2007</ref>). In addition to these freely available data sources, we also tested TRANSFAC (2012.1 version), a subscription database with TFs, their experimentally proven binding sites and the corresponding PSSMs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Matys et al., 2006</ref>). TRANSFAC is a popular resource in this community and was thus included in our benchmarks. All these data sets were retrieved, curated, completed when necessary (for instance by searching for TF sequences for GenBank/Uniprot identifiers) and imported into our meta-database using custom Perl scripts. To standardize these tasks, we created the footprintDB data format, which bundles together TF and DBS sequences, motifs and links to supporting literature and original sources. This format is a blending of 'matrix.dat', 'factor.dat' and 'site.dat' TRANSFAC files in a single file, as shown in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S2</ref>. By adopting these formats, a friendly web interface allows users to update and insert data for their own private applications, or rather make them available to the community. Along the article we will refer to footprintDB as the sum of the formerly listed data sources, excluding TRANSFAC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Database structure and web application</head><p>Different aspects were considered when conceiving the database, some of them biological and some relevant for data modeling. Transcription control is a complex mechanism, still not completely understood, and this must be considered in the design. For instance, a single TF can bind to several possibly degenerate DBSs within the same or different genomic regions, or often the same cis element is recognized by several TFs. Other relevant questions are redundancy among sources, miscellaneous annotation formats, incomplete annotation of entries and availability of data retrieval systems. All these factors made footprintDB have a complex relational schema, shown in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure S3</ref>. The web application is written in PHP and JavaScript, with Perl scripts running the queries. Sequence logos are built with Weblogo (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Crooks et al., 2004</ref>). The database runs a MySQL engine on an Apache server. A SOAP web services interface is available at http://floresta.eead.csic.es/foot printdb/ws.cgi. The online documentation includes examples on how to query it.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Annotation of TF interfaces and Pfam domains</head><p>TF sequences in footprintDB have their DNA binding interfaces annotated by means of BLASTP alignments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Altschul et al., 1990</ref>) against the 3D-footprint library (http://floresta.eead.csic.es/3dfootprint/download/ list_interface2dna.txt) with an E-value threshold of 10. Aligned interface positions from one or more protein–DNA complexes are thus transferred to entries in the database. A benchmark with 127 TFs comparing other machine learning interface-inference tools showed that this straightforward BLAST-based strategy is the most accurate among sequence-based methods, as shown in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S4</ref>. Pfam domains (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Punta et al., 2012</ref>) were also annotated for all TF sequences using HMMSCAN from the HMMER 3.0 suite (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Finn et al., 2011</ref>). Family-specific E-value thresholds were optimized to reduce falsepositive matches, according to benchmark experiments summarized in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S5</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Analysis of data redundancy</head><p>Two kinds of redundancy were defined and measured: internal and external. Internal redundancy is defined as the number of redundant DNA motifs (PSSMs) and TF sequences from the same source, whereas external redundancy is estimated with respect to other sources. Internal redundancy of DNA motifs was measured aligning all PSSMs from the same data source against each other with STAMP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Mahony and Benos, 2007</ref>), taking the best hit to define nearest neighbor clusters of similar DNA motifs. Two E-value thresholds were tested to define redundancy, 1E-10 and 1E-5; motifs with lower E-values were clustered together and labeled as redundant. Internal redundancy of TF sequences was measured running CD-HIT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Li and Godzik, 2006</ref>). Two sequence identity thresholds were tested, 90 and 50%, so that aligned sequences with higher identity percentages were clustered together. External redundancy of either DNA motifs or TFs was estimated comparing PSSMs or protein sequences across data sources. External redundancy values estimate how many data entries from each database have similar values in the other databases. These values are asymmetrical because comparisons can be made in both ways: A versus B and B versus A. Redundant data among footprintDB, TRANSFAC and JASPAR CORE were clustered and Euler diagrams drawn with eulerAPE v2.0 (available from http:// www.eulerdiagrams.org/eulerAPE), as depicted in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>. These diagrams illustrate data redundancy among the three main repositories, considering that JASPAR CORE is by design contained in footprintDB.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Protein sequence and DNA motif search</head><p>The search engine of footprintDB relies on a Perl script that implements protein sequence searches with BLASTP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Altschul et al., 1990</ref>) and DNA motif scans with STAMP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Mahony and Benos, 2007</ref>). Protein searches take FASTA format sequences as input and by default accept hits with a maximum E-value of 1. Results can be ordered by increasing E-value or by decreasing interface similarity. Interface similarity is calculated using a scoring matrix that gives score 1 to amino acids with similar physicochemical properties and 0 to the rest (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6</ref>). Motif searches are carried out by STAMP using as input a PSSM in TRANSFAC format. Other accepted inputs are single or multiple DNA sequences, which will be internally converted to PSSMs. The alignment algorithm is an ungapped Smith–Waterman implementation, which extends matched motifs with a maximum E-value of 1. The scoring function is the Pearson Correlation Coefficient of aligned matrix columns. Motif similarity is defined as the sum of column Pearson Correlation Coefficient values. Results can be ordered by increasing E-value or by decreasing motif similarity. Besides these standard alignment scores, the output table resulting from DNA searches is colored according to twilight thresholds: green matches correspond to reliable motif alignments, whereas motifs over a red background cannot be guaranteed to be correctly aligned (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Sebastian and Contreras-Moreira, 2013</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">External proteome search</head><p>A remarkable feature of footprintDB is that it allows extending database searches to external proteomes. By doing this, users can transfer search results, which only consider annotated TFs and DNA motifs, to other species of interest. This extension step requires running BLASTP with a default E-value threshold of 0.01. Note that this parameter can be tuned. When possible, resulting hits have their interface residues predicted, so that they can be sorted with respect to the original annotated TFs in the database.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7">Benchmark</head><p>Three test datasets and three representative species were chosen to benchmark the predictive ability of footprintDB: (i) A.thaliana data from Athamap; (ii) E.coli data from RegulonDB and (iii) a subset of 100 randomly selected DNA motifs and their associated TFs from 'HumanTF'. Each dataset consisted of DNA motifs recognized by a single TF and TFs recognizing a single DNA motif. Benchmark searches were performed by setting aside each test set from the meta-database, first excluding and then including annotated data for the corresponding species. Both protein and DNA searches were evaluated:</p><p>(1) The TF benchmark consisted in scanning protein sequences against footprintDBþTRANSFAC and then comparing the predicted motifs to the cognate DNA motif of the query. If one of the matched PSSMs is significantly similar to the cognate motif (STAMP E 1E-5), the result is stored together with its rank, E-value, motif similarity, BLASTP E-value, interface similarity, organism and data source.</p><p>(2) The DNA benchmark was done by searching input motifs from all three test datasets looking for putative binding homologous TFs within the corresponding proteomes (versions: A.thaliana TAIR9, E.coli U000096.2 and Homo sapiens GRCh37.58). Hits were compared with the TF associated to the query and defined as correct with a percent sequence identity 490.<ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>illustrates how the benchmark was done, and the sets of obtained predictions are provided as Supplementary Material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Database contents</head><p>The first release of footprintDB contains 2422 unique TF sequences, 3662 PSSMs and 10 112 DBSs. As we added the contents of TRANSFAC version 2012.1 to the analysis, these numbers increased significantly to 4923, 5349 and 21 988, respectively (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). In the next section, redundancy analyses are performed to fairly evaluate the richness of each data source. The most populated species among footprintDB sources, as compared with TRANSFAC and JASPAR CORE, are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1A</ref>, together with the corresponding number of TF sequences annotated in each data source (full statistics are reported as Supplementary Material). We notice that the TF binding preferences of a few organisms are widely covered, such as human, mouse, yeast, fly or E.coli. This coverage could already be sufficient for many applications in the case of human or mouse, considering current estimations of the repertoire of TFs in the human genome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Vaquerizas et al., 2009</ref>). However, other species such as A.thaliana, maize or rice (among plants) or mammals like cow, pig and sheep have a shallow coverage. Moreover, the analysis unveils that some organisms are better covered by TRANSFAC (for instance Gallus gallus, Rattus norvegicus or Xenopus laevis), whereas others, such as bacteria, are only considered by open-access libraries such as DBTBS. In the Section 2.7, we assess to what extent well-explored species can help make predictions on the remaining. The most frequent DNA binding domains found in the analyzed databases are also summarized in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1B</ref>(see also Supplementary Material). It can be seen that Homeobox andZinc fingers, widely studied in the literature, are overrepresented. Furthermore, we note that prokaryotic RegulonDB and DBTBS databases do not contain such proteins; instead they are enriched in typical bacterial regulatory proteins, such as helix-turn-helix TFs. One of the unique features of footprintDB is the annotation of interface residues of TFs. This annotation relies on the 3D-footprint database, which routinely dissects the interfaces of protein–DNA complexes deposited at the PDB, as explained in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2A</ref>. Alignments between amino acid sequences of TFs and homologous protein–DNA complexes thus drive the transfer of experimentally determined interface residues to equivalent residues of footprintDB entries. Overall, 97% of the total TFs are annotated with this procedure, with most resulting interfaces comprising 7–16 amino acid residues (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2B</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Survey of data redundancy</head><p>To estimate the degree of redundancy of the data sources integrated in footprintDB, we compared data entries within and between databases, as explained in Section 2. When checking internal redundancy, it turns out that some of the largest repositories such as TRANSFAC, JASPAR CORE, HumanTF, UniPROBE and the whole footprintDB contain from 20 to 40% redundant DNA motifs, depending on the similarity cutoff E-values used to compare PSSMs (1E-5 and 1E-10, respectively, see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S3</ref>). For TF sequences, we report an even higher redundancy: 40–70% within footprintDB, TRANSFAC and 3D-footprint entries and slightly lower percentages in HumanTF (24–53%) due to proteins with percent sequence identity higher than the 90 and 50% cutoffs, respectively (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S4</ref>). JASPAR motif redundancy was anticipated as we analyzed on purpose the all-species redundant set for completeness. External redundancy is even more relevant to evaluate the added value of each data source. The data in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>summarize the performed comparisons in terms of DNA motifs, indicating that all eukaryotic data sources contain a large fraction of redundant entries among them. This is expected, as databases such as JASPAR and TRANSFAC are built, at least in part, by curating the same literature, and therefore overlap substantially. In fact, TRANSFAC contains 438 DNA motifs identical to JASPAR entries (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S5</ref>). This number increases to 1332 if we consider TRANSFAC PSSMs that align to JASPAR entries with STAMP E 1E-10, which we considered as a cutoff for nearly identical motifs. Besides, these analyses confirm the minimum redundancy between bacterialSecond, a matrix of interacting residues and their target bases is generated. Third, interface residues are marked as uppercase letters in the sequence and are further transferred to homologous sequences by means of BLASTP alignments. Note that several PDB complexes can often be used to annotate a single footprintDB entry. (B) Histogram of length of predicted interfaces in footprintDB. Large interfaces usually correspond to proteins with several DNA binding domains sources (RegulonDB and DBTBS) and the rest. Note that external redundancy estimates are asymmetrical, as different results are obtained depending on the direction of the comparison. The picture arising from the comparison of TF sequences across data sources reveals their analogous levels of redundancy (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S6</ref>). For instance, 368 TRANSFAC TFs have identical amino acid sequences in JASPAR; this figure increases to 1062 if we apply a 90% sequence identity redundancy cutoff. After reviewing the full set of comparisons in Supplementary Tables S5 and S6, it can be concluded that there is an 'eclipse effect': as we relax the redundancy thresholds, eukaryotic datasets progressively overlap till most of their contents turn to be shared. This behavior is shown in the Euler diagrams in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>for the three main databases footprintDB, TRANSFAC and JASPAR CORE (which is included in footprintDB). Perhaps the most interesting case is the overlap between footprintDB and TRANSFAC (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>,<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>and Supplementary Tables S5 and S6). They share 22% of motifs and 14% of TRANSFAC TFs (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3A</ref>and D). If nearly identical DNA motifs (E 1E-10) and TFs (with percent sequence identity 90) are considered, these percentages increase to 71% of motifs and 56% of TFs (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3B</ref>and E). Further relaxing these thresholds to E 1E-5 (short motifs or motifs that share a common pattern but not the whole motif) and sequence identity 50% (proteins with common domain architecture) then both databases are almost equivalent, as they seem to share 95% of motifs and 98% of TFs (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3C</ref>and F). Such data overlap is also noticeable for JASPAR.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Web site</head><p>The web interface of footprintDB displays the main menu on the left side, which provides access to the current list of publicly available data sources and to the search engine, in addition to the documentation (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S7</ref>). By default anonymous users can perform any of these tasks:</p><p>(1) Listing the included repositories, their versions, references and authors, with links to the original Web sites. From this table it is possible to browse TFs, DNA binding motifs (PSSMs) and DBSs curated in each individual data source.</p><p>(2) Accessing a single entry (TF, PSSM or DBS) to display all the available information for that record, including references to primary literature and experimental evidence, and download them in TRANSFAC format (example in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S8</ref>).</p><p>(3) Key word search of TF, PSSM or DBS accessions. The form supports filtering by database, organism or related TF domain and results can be downloaded in TRANSFAC format.</p><p>(4) Sequence search, to scan protein or DNA sequences and PSSMs. The search process is explained in the next section.</p><p>In addition, registered users have access to the following extra features:</p><p>(1) Storing and reusing previous searches.</p><p>(2) Inserting/removing their own databases in TRANSFAC or footprintDB formats.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Search engines and external proteomes</head><p>The main purpose of footprintDB is to support searching for annotated TFs and/or regulatory sequences, as depicted in<ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>. The search engine is designed primarily to receive two types of queries: (i) a DNA consensus motif, PSSM or site and (ii) a protein sequence of a putative DNA binding protein. Therefore, two kinds of output will be produced, respectively, (i) a list of DNA binding proteins predicted to bind a similar DNA motif and (ii) a list of DNA motifs recognized by similar proteins annotated in any of the included data sources. Search results can be sorted by E-value, motif similarity or interface similarity. Moreover, the user can also look for homologs in a third party species, by simply specifying an appropriate proteome in the formulary dropdown list or by uploading a custom proteome in FASTA format. Together with the standard search results, this option produces a list of homologous proteins with their interfaces annotated. Interface predictions can then be used to filter out BLASTP hits displaying a significantly different set of. Motifs aligned with STAMP E-values51E-10 were called redundant. Second row corresponds to the union of all individual data sources that contribute to footprintDB. Note that a large fraction of 3D-footprint entries are not called redundant within footprintDB because their short DNA motifs fail to produce alignments with E-values51E-10. DNA binding residues. This kind of search is useful to scan TFs within a particular organism of interest, for instance to design laboratory experiments. We further illustrate this kind of search in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Example of footprintDB search</head><p>Imagine that we have obtained a set of cis elements regulated by a bZIP TF in the genome of Antirrhinum majus. Take for instance motif bZIP910, annotated in JASPAR and AthaMap, shown in Supplementary Table S8. Now, we have just found out that some of these DBSs are also conserved in A.thaliana, and want to identify the endogenous TFs that might recognize them, so that we can test them in the laboratory. To perform such a query, we first paste the input DNA sequences in the search formulary to obtain a list of similar motifs in the database. Among the top four results are bZIP910, XBP1 and TGA1, annotated in different sources and species (snapdragon, human, thale cress and tobacco). All of them are motifs bound by TFs of the bZIP family (basic leucine zipper domain), using a similar binding interface. However, as we go down the list, motifs start to diverge and hence have associated higher E-values. If we extend this search by scanning proteins within the A.thaliana TAIR9 proteome, we find 30 proteins with interfaces identical to that of the query (bZIP910, with interface signature RNRSASR), which should be the best candidates to be tested in the laboratory for binding. In addition, these results could guide site-directed mutagenesis experiments targeting interface residues. The second hit (human XBP1) produces a list of 21 A.thaliana TFs, but an inspection of their interfaces (RKNRAAARK) shows clearly that these are a different subfamily of TFs. Furthermore, these interfaces are in all cases similar but not identical to that of the corresponding human TF. For these reasons, the second row of results should be handled with care. Finally, the third and fourth hits, TGA1 from A.thaliana and tobacco, link to up to 10 endogenous proteins with identical interfaces (RQNRAASR), which are similar to the first 30 candidate TFs, and therefore should also be considered for further analyses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">Search benchmark</head><p>The first benchmark consisted in scanning A.thaliana TF sequences and DNA motifs from Athamap against footprintDBþTRANSFAC, after excluding all A.thaliana entries.<ref type="figure">Figure 5A</ref>and B summarize both experiments, and can be extended to the second and third benchmarks explained below. Overall, 31 out of the 56 tested TFs (55%) were recovered in the TF search, and 27 out of 48 DNA motifs (56%). Among recovered TFs and motifs, 24/31 and 13/27 were first hits, respectively. It is remarkable that most hits were annotated in TRANSFAC, mainly from other plants, human or mouse. In both experiments, the average interface similarities of correctly recovered TFs were 80 and 91%, compared with overall values of 58 and 78%, respectively, as shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 5C</ref>. When all A.thaliana records were put back in footprintDB (still excluding Athamap), the percentages of recovered TFs and motifs increased to 70 and 83%, respectively. Again most results were derived from TRANSFAC, suggesting that, together with Athamap, it is the most comprehensive source of plant regulatory data. The second benchmark consisted in scanning E.coli sequences from RegulonDB against footprintDBþTRANSFAC, after excluding all E.coli records. In total, only 9 of 82 tested TFs (12%) were successfully retrieved in the TF search, and 8 of 82 DNA motifs (10%). Among these, 6/9 and 5/8 were first hits, respectively. Most matches were from B.subtilis entries annotated in DBTBS and 3D footprint. In both cases, average interface similarities of recovered TFs were 69 compared with 54% among all predictions. When E.coli records were included back in footprintDB, the percentages of recovered TFs and motifs increased to 18 and 20%, respectively. The third benchmark consisted in scanning TF sequences and DNA motifs from 'HumanTF' against footprintDBþ TRANSFAC, after excluding all human records. In total, 100 of 100 tested TFs, and 90 of 100 DNA motifs, were recovered. Overall, 87/100 and 69/90 were first hits, respectively. Matched records were from model multicellular organisms, mostly mouse, but also fly, worm or frog, generally annotated in TRANSFAC<ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>. Main search types supported by footprintDB. Light arrow (top): if the input data are a DNA sequence or motif, the search is powered by STAMP, and the output are proteins likely to bind sequence similar to the input. These proteins might be primary entries in footprintDB or rather endogenous TFs of a proteome of choice, after a secondary call to BLASTP. Dark arrow (bottom): when the input is a protein sequence, a BLASTP search is performed instead and the user gets a list of putative DNA target sites for it or JASPAR. In both experiments, average interface similarities of recovered TFs were 86 and 96% compared with 52 and 91% for all predictions. When human records were added back to footprintDB, the percentages of recovered TFs and motifs remain the same, but now some best hits were human. in terms of the intrinsic redundancy of the PDB. With respect to 'HumanTF', the observed redundancy is due to the fact that this source includes both complete protein sequences and domains of orthologous TFs from mouse and human. A similar explanation is valid for TRANSFAC, which appears to frequently annotate orthologous TFs from relates species. Inspection of the resulting clusters suggests that most redundant TFs at 90% of sequence identity are probably inparalogs and orthologs from phylogenetically close organisms. Inspection of relaxed clusters (50% sequence identity cutoff) unveils that they gain more divergent homologous proteins of the same family, which bind to regulatory elements using the same Pfam domains. Although our survey reveals a comprehensive coverage of human and murine TFs, both in TRANSFAC and in openaccess repositories, it also shows that prokaryotes are still only served by specialized expert-curated resources such as RegulonDB and DBTBS. In fact these organism-specific repositories are reported to be the least redundant (as also observed for DrosophilaTF). By combining freely available data sources, footprintDB aims to be a reference meta-database covering bacteria, plants and animals, although our benchmark clearly shows that its predictive power is greater for multicellular organisms. Despite the wide coverage of this meta-database, our benchmarks encourage the addition of any other relevant high-quality resources/datasets, as we found out with the plant regulatory data. For this reason the web interface allows users to import their own data collections, which can optionally be shared with other users, and we hope that the adoption of this tool by the community will translate into a richer set of curated data repositories.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Species and domain composition of footprintDB entries compared with TRANSFAC and JASPAR CORE. (A) Most represented species among database entries. (B) Most frequent DNA binding domains</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Annotation of interface residues. (A) 3D-footprint interface of PDB entry 9ANT, which corresponds to Homebox protein Antennapedia in complex with a cis element. First, interatomic distances are calculated among atoms of amino acid side chains and nitrogen bases. Second, a matrix of interacting residues and their target bases is generated. Third, interface residues are marked as uppercase letters in the sequence and are further transferred to homologous sequences by means of BLASTP alignments. Note that several PDB complexes can often be used to annotate a single footprintDB entry. (B) Histogram of length of predicted interfaces in footprintDB. Large interfaces usually correspond to proteins with several DNA binding domains</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Euler diagrams representing redundancy for DNA motifs (A–C) and TF sequences (D–F) annotated in footprintDB, TRANSFAC and JASPAR CORE databases</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Number of unique TF sequences, DNA motifs and DBSs in footprintDB sources</figDesc><table>Source 
TFs 
Motifs 
Sites 

TRANSFAC 
2919 
2163 
11 949 
footprintDB 
2422 
3662 
10 112 
JASPAR CORE 
715 
1312 
2388 
3D-footprint 
605 
802 
722 
HumanTF 
528 
818 
0 
UniPROBE 
401 
415 
2963 
RegulonDB 
82 
82 
1862 
Athamap 
74 
84 
84 
DBTBS 
70 
88 
1234 
DrosophilaTF 
57 
61 
863 
Total unique 
4923 
5349 
21 988 

Note: TRANSFAC data are included as a reference. Second row corresponds to the 
union of all individual data sources that contribute to footprintDB. </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>), in agreement with previous values calculated for Homeobox and Zinc finger families (Contreras-Moreira et al., 2009) (full interface length statistics are reported as Supplementary Material). As we show later, annotated interfaces are a good filter to decide whether two TFs might be recognizing the same DBS, as required when extending footprintDB searches to external proteomes.</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. External redundancy of DNA motifs across data sources integrated in footprintDB TRANSFAC footprintDB JASPAR a 3D footprint HumanTF UniPROBE RegulonDB Athamap DBTBS DrosophilaTF</figDesc><table>TRANSFAC 
2163 
2111 
963 
78 
577 
401 
8 
49 
5 
30 
footprintDB 
1531 
3662 
1295 
446 
818 
412 
81 
84 
76 
57 
JASPAR a 
1332 
2299 
1312 
60 
536 
359 
5 
21 
3 
20 
3D footprint 
154 
672 
89 
802 
96 
22 
4 
5 
3 
7 
HumanTF 
651 
1453 
386 
45 
818 
174 
4 
11 
1 
14 
UniPROBE 
628 
1086 
386 
7 
265 
415 
3 
5 
2 
6 
RegulonDB 
13 
116 
10 
4 
8 
8 
82 
0 
5 
0 
Athamap 
108 
130 
22 
6 
14 
3 
0 
84 
1 
0 
DBTBS 
6 
94 
4 
6 
1 
3 
3 
1 
88 
0 
DrosophilaTF 
64 
142 
31 
6 
34 
14 
0 
0 
0 
61 

a 

A redundant version of JASPAR was tested. 
Note: The main diagonal shows the total number of PSSMs in each source (bold)</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">footprintDB at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">A.Sebastian and B.Contreras-Moreira at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> DISCUSSION FootprintDB is an effort to group and unify the most important, diverse and well-annotated open access databases of experimentally obtained TF binding preferences. Although a few other resources have a similar philosophy (Portales-Casamar et al., 2010; Riva, 2012), footprintDB goes one step further by systematically annotating interface residues, those that capture the binding specificity of DNA binding proteins. This allows linking motif similarity with TF similarity and supports scanning TFs with conserved interfaces in external proteomes. The observed high values of interface similarity among correctly recovered TFs in our benchmarks, compared with the average values among all predictions, confirm their value as a quality control when transferring regulatory annotations by homology. The search engine is perhaps the most remarkable feature of footprintDB. It can drive the prediction of DNA binding motifs for unknown TF sequences, and also the opposite search, assigning putative TFs to input DNA motifs, which might have been found during in silico promoter analyses. Our benchmarks suggest that footprintDB has predictive power, as it was able to correctly recover TFs and motifs from E.coli, A.thaliana and H.sapiens. However, the performance was better with eukaryotes than with bacteria, as the tested data sources are evidently more redundant for multicellular organisms. This observation exposes that the predictive ability of footprintDB is proportional to the richness of its data sources. In our experience, correct results are obtained most frequently when TF sequences or DNA motifs from phylogenetically related organisms are available in the database. For instance, in our A.thaliana TF benchmark, first hits captured the correct TF in 24 of 31 cases. Overall, 21 of these 24 matches were to plant sequences, including species such as Zea mays, Helianthus annuus, Nicotiana tabacum, Brassica napus, A.majus, Hordeum vulgare, Solanum lycopersicum, Daucus carota and Oryza sativa. In contrast, the E.coli test had limited success, as the only available reference organism was B.subtilis, which in fact is only remotely related. Beyond these benchmark experiments, footprintDB has already been profitably applied for identifying endogenous rice TFs (OsEREBP1 and OsEREBP2) that bind specifically to a target sequence within the OsRMC promoter (Serra et al., 2013). Furthermore, footprintDB has also been extensively tested during the in silico identification of drought stress regulatory proteins in A.thaliana, which have been later validated with yeast one-hybrid experiments. Preliminary results further confirm that correct predictions are provided by phylogenetically related entries, which are annotated in the database, otherwise results are not reliable (data not shown). Another important result of this unpublished work, which is relevant in this context, is that DNA searches seem to be more sensitive with single cis elements as input than with PSSMs. This study is also an up-to-date comprehensive comparison of TF databases. Fogel et al. made a statistical analysis of an early version of TRANSFAC (Fogel et al., 2005), whereas other articles have studied the similarity of motifs annotated in TRANSFAC and JASPAR (Kielbasa et al., 2005; Schones et al., 2005). In our study, we find significant data redundancy between TRANSFAC and JASPAR databases. However, the most significant overlap found is between footprintDB and TRANSFAC, as summarized in Figure 3. These analyses suggest that footprintDB and TRANSFAC contain overall almost equivalent data, so footprintDB can be currently used as an open-access alternative, bearing in mind that organism coverage is also an important factor, as already discussed in the A.thaliana benchmark. It remains to be seen whether available funding will allow footprintDB (and its integrated datasets) to keep the pace of scheduled updates of commercial alternatives such as TRANSFAC. Significant internal redundancy is observed among TF sequences of 3D footprint, &apos;HumanTF&apos; and TRANSFAC, as well as footprintDB. In the first case, this is mostly explained Fig. 5. Benchmark of footprintDB performance using A.thaliana data annotated in Athamap. (A) One TF sequence from Athamap is searched against footprintDB. (B) A DNA motif from Athamap is scanned against footprintDB. In both cases, red arrows represent the comparison of predictions to the cognate sequences, which are taken to be correct or false in terms of STAMP E-value (A) and percent sequence identity (B), as explained in Section 2. In the TF experiment (A), 31 of 56 Athamap sequences (55%) were successfully recovered. In the corresponding experiment with DNA motifs (B), the footprintDB pipeline recovered 27 of 48 (56%) Athamap motifs. (C) Interface similarity of correct hits and of all predictions among A.thaliana, E.coli and human test sets used during the benchmark</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank our colleagues from the STREG project (L. Buïow, R. Hehl, G. Huep, B. Weisshaar, C. Dubos, L. Lepiniec and A.Koller) for their feedback and support while developing this resource. They would also like to acknowledge the authors of the databases integrated in footprintDB for their feedback and permissions to use their data: L. Buïow, R. Hehl (Athamap), C. Bergman (DrosophilaTF), J. Taipale (HumanTF), A. Sandelin (JASPAR), J. Collado-Vides (RegulonDB) and M. Bulyk (UniPROBE).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct inference of protein-DNA interactions using compressed sensing methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Alquraishi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Mcadams</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14819" to="14824" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basic local alignment search tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">215</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="410" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein binding microarrays (PBMs) for rapid, high-throughput characterization of the sequence specificities of DNA binding proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Berger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Bulyk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">338</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="260" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Protein Data Bank</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Berman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AthaMap, integrating transcriptional and post-transcriptional data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Bulow</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="983" to="986" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">3D-footprint: a database for the structural analysis of protein-DNA complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Contreras-Moreira</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of DNA binding across protein superfamilies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Contreras-Moreira</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WebLogo: a sequence logo generator</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Crooks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1188" to="1190" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale discovery of promoter motifs in Drosophila melanogaster</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Down</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HMMER web server: interactive sequence similarity searching</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Finn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A statistical analysis of the TRANSFAC database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Fogel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biosystems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNAse footprinting: a simple method for the detection of protein-DNA binding specificity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Galas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Schmitz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3157" to="3170" />
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A gel electrophoresis method for quantifying the binding of proteins to specific DNA regions: application to components of the Escherichia coli lactose operon regulatory system</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Garner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Revzin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3047" to="3060" />
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide mapping of in vivo protein-DNA interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Johnson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">316</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1497" to="1502" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA-binding specificities of human transcription factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Jolma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="327" to="339" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring similarities between transcription factor binding sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Kielbasa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">237</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cd-hit: a fast program for clustering and comparing large sets of protein or nucleotide sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Godzik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1658" to="1659" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PiDNA: predicting protein-DNA interactions with structural models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="523" to="530" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">STAMP: a web tool for exploring DNA-binding motif similarities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Mahony</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Benos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TRANSFAC and its module TRANSCompel: transcriptional gene regulation in eukaryotes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Matys</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="108" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of homeodomain specificities allows the familywide prediction of preferred recognition sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Noyes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1277" to="1289" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunoprecipitation of chromatin</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Neill</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Turner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Enzymol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="197" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Localization of a protein-DNA interface by random mutagenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Neill</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7118" to="7127" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">JASPAR 2010: the greatly expanded open-access database of transcription factor binding profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Portales-Casamar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Pfam protein families database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Punta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide location and function of DNA binding proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Ren</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">290</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2306" to="2309" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The MAPPER2 Database: a multi-genome catalog of putative transcription factor binding sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Riva</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UniPROBE, update 2011: expanded content and search tools in the online database of protein-binding microarray data on protein-DNA interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Robasky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Bulyk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="124" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RegulonDB v8.0: omics data sets, evolutionary conservation, regulatory phrases, cross-validated gold standards and more</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Salgado</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="213" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequence logos: a new way to display consensus sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Schneider</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Stephens</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6097" to="6100" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Similarity of position frequency matrices for transcription factor binding sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Schones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="313" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The twilight zone of cis element alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Sebastian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Contreras-Moreira</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1438" to="1449" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OsRMC, a negative regulator of salt stress response in rice, is regulated by two AP2/ERF transcription factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Serra</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Directed mutagenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Shortle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="294" />
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DBTBS: a database of transcriptional regulation in Bacillus subtilis containing upstream intergenic conservation information</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Sierro</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA binding sites: representation and discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Stormo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A census of human transcription factors: function, expression and evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Vaquerizas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="252" to="263" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>