
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:48+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sara</forename>
								<surname>Aibar</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">CSIC/USAL/IBSAL)</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Bioinformatics and Functional Genomics Research Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Cancer Research Center (Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Universidad de Salamanca and Instituto de Investigació n Biomé dica de Salamanca</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Salamanca</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Celia</forename>
								<surname>Fontanillo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">CSIC/USAL/IBSAL)</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Bioinformatics and Functional Genomics Research Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Cancer Research Center (Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Universidad de Salamanca and Instituto de Investigació n Biomé dica de Salamanca</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Salamanca</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Conrad</forename>
								<surname>Droste</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">CSIC/USAL/IBSAL)</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Bioinformatics and Functional Genomics Research Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Cancer Research Center (Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Universidad de Salamanca and Instituto de Investigació n Biomé dica de Salamanca</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Salamanca</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Javier</forename>
								<surname>De</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">CSIC/USAL/IBSAL)</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Bioinformatics and Functional Genomics Research Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Cancer Research Center (Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Universidad de Salamanca and Instituto de Investigació n Biomé dica de Salamanca</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Salamanca</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Las</forename>
								<surname>Rivas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">CSIC/USAL/IBSAL)</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Bioinformatics and Functional Genomics Research Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Cancer Research Center (Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Universidad de Salamanca and Instituto de Investigació n Biomé dica de Salamanca</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Salamanca</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu864</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 20, 2014; revised on December 16, 2014; accepted on December 29, 2014</note>
					<note>Functional Gene Networks: R/Bioc package to generate and analyse gene networks derived from functional enrichment and clustering *To whom correspondence should be addressed. † Present address: Celgene Institute for Translational Research Europe (CITRE), Sevilla, Spain Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Contact: jrivas@usal.es Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Functional Gene Networks (FGNet) is an R/Bioconductor package that generates gene networks derived from the results of functional enrichment analysis (FEA) and annotation clustering. The sets of genes enriched with specific biological terms (obtained from a FEA platform) are transformed into a network by establishing links between genes based on common functional annotations and common clusters. The network provides a new view of FEA results revealing gene modules with similar functions and genes that are related to multiple functions. In addition to building the functional network, FGNet analyses the similarity between the groups of genes and provides a distance heatmap and a bipartite network of functionally overlapping genes. The application includes an interface to directly perform FEA queries using different external tools: DAVID, GeneTerm Linker, TopGO or GAGE; and a graphical interface to facilitate the use. Availability and implementation: FGNet is available in Bioconductor, including a tutorial.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Due to the increasing number of omic studies, efficient functional analysis of large lists of genes or proteins is essential to understand the biological processes in which they are involved. Functional enrichment analysis (FEA) is the most popular bioinformatic methodology to obtain significant functional information from sets of cooperating genes. FEA methods search in biological databases (such as Gene Ontology and KEGG pathways, among others) and use statistical testing to find biological terms and functional annotations that are significantly enriched in a list of genes. However, in most cases the results of these analyses are very long lists of biological terms associated to genes that are difficult to digest and interpret. Some tools cluster the FEA results, like DAVID-FAC (<ref type="bibr">Huang et al., 2009</ref>) and GeneTerm Linker (<ref type="bibr">Fontanillo et al., 2011</ref>), but their output is provided as large tables and there are not many tools to integrate and visualize these results. Here we present Functional Gene Networks (FGNet), an R/ Bioconductor package that uses FEA results to perform networkbased analyses and visualization. The main network is built by establishing links between genes annotated to similar functional terms. In this way, FGNet generates and provides a network representing the links and associations between the clusters of genes and enriched terms. The network summarizes and facilitates the interpretation of the biological processes significantly enriched in the initial list of genes, revealing important information such as: distance and overlap V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1686</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.combetween clusters, identification of modules and hubs. The tool can also help to disclose new associations among genes cooperating in hidden biological processes not annotated yet, which can be revealed by the topology of the functional network.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Input: functional enrichment and clustering</head><p>FGNet builds functional networks based on the groups obtained from clustering gene-term sets (gtsets, genes and terms associated by an enrichment p-value) returned by a FEA. The package includes an interface to do queries with gene lists using four FEA tools: DAVID with Functional Annotation Clustering (that returns clustered gtsets, Cl); GAGE (that also provides clusters) (<ref type="bibr">Luo et al., 2009</ref>); GeneCodis with GeneTerm Linker (that returns metagroups, Mg) and TopGO (that only returns gtsets) (<ref type="bibr">Alexa et al., 2010</ref>). The package can be also applied to the results from other EA tools, as long as the input results are transformed into tables of genes and associated terms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Construction of the functional network</head><p>The functional network is built based on the analysis of all the gtsets provided by the FEA tool. These sets allow to generate a boolean matrix M of genes by gtsets, in which each element m g;s ¼ 1 if gene g is in set s. This membership matrix is then transformed into an adjacency matrix A n Â n; being n the total number of genes and a i;j the number of gtsets s in which a gene-pair is included: a i;j ¼ X s ðm i;s Â m j;s Þð1 À d i;j Þ, where d is a Kronecker delta (d i;j ¼ 1 if i ¼ j, d i;j ¼ 0 if i 6 ¼ j). This adjacency matrix is used to generate the functional network by establishing a weighted link between each pair of genes (g i , g j ) in which a i;j 6 ¼ 0. Finally, the clustering of gtsets provided by the FEA tool is used to generate a second genes' adjacency matrix with the number of common clusters/metagroups (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1A</ref>), that is used to define and allocate gene groups. The network produced is provided as an igraph object for further analysis, and can be exported to other network-based tools like Cytoscape.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Visualization and plots of the functional network</head><p>The main plot of the network presents the functionally associated genes (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1B</ref>). Edges link the genes that are in the same gtsets. Nodes within the same Cl/Mg are placed together using a forcedirected Fruchterman–Reingold layout, within a common background colour. Genes in only one Cl/Mg are plotted with the colour of such group, while genes that are included in more than one Cl/ Mg are left white.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Analysis of functional modules in the network</head><p>To facilitate the analysis and quantification of the modules and the overlap between groups, FGNet also provides a distance matrix and a heatmap (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1C</ref>), plus an intersection network (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1D</ref>). The distance matrix is calculated based on the pairwise binary distance in the adjacency matrix of common Cls/Mgs. These distances are analysed by hierarchical average linkage and plotted as a heatmap that reveals the proximity and similarity between the groups of genes (Cls/Mgs). The intersection network is a bipartite network which includes only the genes associated to several Cls/Mgs (white nodes in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1B</ref>,D), showing their connectivity to such Cls/Mgs. This intersection network facilitates the identification of multifunctional genes. (For more details see FGNet documentation in Bioconductor).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Example of use</head><p>We applied the method to several datasets and confirmed that the functional network greatly facilitates the analysis of enrichment results.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>shows the results of FGNet for a list of 175 genesFunctional gene networksdifferentially expressed in human samples of entorhinal cortex neurons from Alzheimer's disease (AD) patients (obtained from Gene Expression Omnibus database, GEO: dataset GSE4757). Performing a FEA through GeneTerm Linker, we obtained six metagroups that we labelled according to their main annotations: (Mg1) cell adhesion; (Mg2) voltage-gated ion/potassium channels; (Mg3) axon and cell projection; (Mg4) dendrite and neuronal cell body; (Mg5) synaptic neuroactive ligand-receptor interaction and (Mg6) MAPK signaling and Alzheimer. The network of these six Mgs (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.  1B</ref>) provides a global overview of the functionally overlapping genes and allows to identify hub genes that interconnect groups. For example, CNTNAP1 and NLGN4X appear as hubs in Mg1. CNTNAP1 (that regulates distribution of Kþ channels) links Mg1 and 2; and NLGN4X (that facilitates synaptic neurotransmission) links Mg1 with 4 and 5. NLGN4X is the gene with highest betweenness centrality in this network. Another important hub is APOE, recently associated to Alzheimer. The distance matrix (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1C</ref>) allows to quantify the similarity between gene groups, showing that the closest Mgs are 3, 4 and 6, sharing eight nodes. This is also presented in the intersection network (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1D</ref>). Finally, the functional network can reveal further information about some Mgs. For example, if a Mg shares many genes with several other Mgs, it will indicate that such Mg brings the most common features that define the studied biological state. This is the case for Mg6, which, in fact, is annotated to Alzheimer's Disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by the " Accion Estrategica en Salud " (AES) of the " Instituto de Salud Carlos III " (ISCiii) from the Spanish Government (projects granted to J.D.L.R.: PS09/00843 and PI12/00624); and by the " Consejeria de Educació n " of the " Junta Castilla y Leon " (JCyL) and the European Social Fund (ESF) with grants given to S.A. and C.D. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>References</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Bioinformatics, 31(10), 2015, 1686–1688doi:10.</head><figDesc>1093/bioinformatics/btu864 Advance Access Publication Date: 18 January 2015 Applications Note</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Schematic workflow. A query gene list is analysed through a FEA tool and the generated gene-term sets are used to build: (A) gene's adjacency matrices; (B) a functional network (general view); (C) a distance heatmap and (D) an intersection network (to highlight multifunctional genes)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Alexa,A. and Rahnenfuhrer,J. (2010). topGO: Enrichment analysis for Gene Ontology. R package version 2.18.0. Fontanillo,C. et al. (2011). Functional analysis beyond enrichment: nonredundant reciprocal linkage of genes and biological terms. PLoS One, 6, e24289. Huang,D. et al. (2009). Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID Bioinformatics Resources. Nat. Protoc., 4, 44–57. Luo,W. et al. (2009). GAGE: generally applicable gene set enrichment for pathway analysis. BMC Bioinformatics, 10, 161.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>