
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:47+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Genome-wide association studies pipeline (GWASpi): a desktop application for genome-wide SNP analysis and management</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Fernando</forename>
								<surname>Muñiz-Fernandez</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institut de Biología Evolutiva</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Biomedical Research Park (PRBB)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitat Pompeu Fabra</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Population Genomics Node (GNV8)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute for Bioinformatics (INB)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Angel</forename>
								<surname>Carreño-Torres</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institut de Biología Evolutiva</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Biomedical Research Park (PRBB)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitat Pompeu Fabra</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Population Genomics Node (GNV8)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute for Bioinformatics (INB)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Carlos</forename>
								<surname>Morcillo-Suarez</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institut de Biología Evolutiva</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Biomedical Research Park (PRBB)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitat Pompeu Fabra</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Population Genomics Node (GNV8)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute for Bioinformatics (INB)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">National Genotyping Centre (CeGen)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Arcadi</forename>
								<surname>Navarro</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>arcadi.navarro@upf.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institut de Biología Evolutiva</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Biomedical Research Park (PRBB)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitat Pompeu Fabra</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Population Genomics Node (GNV8)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute for Bioinformatics (INB)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">National Genotyping Centre (CeGen)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Institucio Catalana de Recerca i Estudis Avançats</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">ICREA, Barcelona</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Departament de Ciències</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Experimentals i de la Salut</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Universitat Pompeu Fabra</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Dr Aiguader 88</addrLine>
									<postCode>08003</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Genome-wide association studies pipeline (GWASpi): a desktop application for genome-wide SNP analysis and management</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1871" to="1872"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr301</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on January 3, 2011; revised on April 26, 2011; accepted on May 9, 2011</note>
					<note>[11:29 2/6/2011 Bioinformatics-btr301.tex] Page: 1871 1871–1872 Associate Editor: Dmitrij Frishman Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) based on single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) arrays are the most widely used approach to detect loci associated to human traits. Due to the complexity of the methods and software packages available, each with its particular format requiring intricate management workflows, the analysis of GWAS usually confronts scientists with steep learning curves. Indeed, the wide variety of tools makes the parsing and manipulation of data the most time consuming and error prone part of a study. To help resolve these issues, we present GWASpi, a user-friendly, multiplatform, desktop-able application for the management and analysis of GWAS data, with a novel approach on database technologies to leverage the most out of commonly available desktop hardware. GWASpi aims to be a start-to-finish GWAS management application, from raw data to results, containing the most common analysis tools. As a result, GWASpi is easy to use and reduces in up to two orders of magnitude the time needed to perform the fundamental steps of a GWAS. Availability: Freely available on the web at http://www.gwaspi.org. Implemented in Java, Apache-Derby and NetCDF-3, with all major operating systems supported.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have come to be the choice method to detect loci associated with human hereditary traits, especially diseases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">McCarthy et al., 2008</ref>). The number of studies published yearly based on these arrays, has constantly increased from 3 in 2003 to 384 in 2010 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Yu et al., 2008</ref>). In parallel, reference databases such as HapMap (<ref type="bibr">International and Consortium, 2003</ref>), HGDP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cavalli-sforza, 2005</ref>) and the 1000 Genomes Project (<ref type="bibr">The 1000</ref><ref type="bibr">Genomes Project Consortium, 2010</ref>) are being released together with an ever-growing range of analytical methods and software packages. The most common freely available tools in the field, however, leave it to the user to tackle the jungle of formats and the bulk of raw * To whom correspondence should be addressed. data generated by GWAS. Also, learning how to apply the methods commonly used in GWASs takes significant time, extending an already lengthy and arduous data gathering phase. Thus, the steep learning curve and the burden of manipulation of the raw data still makes the access to GWAS a costly endeavour for researchers or institutions without Bioinformatics personnel. To contribute to solve this problem and make GWAS an achievable effort for smaller teams, as well as for the sake of speeding up raw data management in a consistent, self-contained way for the general researcher community, we have developed the GWAS Pipeline (GWASpi). GWASpi has not been designed to replace other well-established applications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Purcell et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Browning and Browning, 2007</ref>) insofar as it does not offer the whole breadth of statistical analysis methods used in GWAS. Instead, the current version of GWASpi focuses in case–control studies and offers a solution for teams in need of concise and quickly obtained results as well as compact, comprehensive and agile dataset management to complement existing analysis packages. Some basic quality-control features are also integrated in GWASpi.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">APPROACH</head><p>Genotype data consists of dense, static information, in the sense that it is formed by large numbers of genotypes (up to billions) that may need to be accessed many times but do not change once they have been ascertained. Subsets of data may be required some times for separate analysis, but they can be generated easily and quickly as new, independent datasets that, again, will be static. The NetCDF-3 database technology developed by the University Corporation for Atmospheric Research (UCAR, http://www2.ucar.edu) and originally intended for meteorological data storage has proven to be well suited to this kind of data. On top of this database, Java's LinkedHashMap objects are used to retrieve slabs of data in an ordered list fashion that is searchable by index.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">METHODS</head><p>The efficient storage of genotypes and the posterior retrieval of specific subsets of this data is a highly desirable feature for the types of analysis that are being performed on these datasets. Generally, this type of functionality is achieved through the use of Relational Databases (RDB) with the help of SQL language. Nevertheless, RDB technologies have poor scaling properties for the type of data that composes genome-wide studies. GWASpi makes</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F.Muñiz-Fernandez et al.</head><p>use of an embedded JavaDB SQL database for its internal management as well as for storage of data related to samples (such as their disease status or geographic origin). However, a crucial feature of GWASpi is that all genotype data and analysis results, which constitute the bulk of information in a GWAS, are stored in the Array-oriented Scientific Data Format (http://www.unidata.ucar.edu/software/netcdf/). Among the existing implementations of this technology, NetCDF-3 was chosen over others for the availability of a pure Java implementation of its API, which ensures cross-platform portability in conjunction with the availability of many highperformance libraries and tools (JfreeChart, Apache Derby). Plots and charts are handled by the JFreeChart library.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Common usage</head><p>From the point of view of the user, GWASpi is a cross-platform Java application with integrated tools and features that make the processing of genotype data more agile and speedy. All the features included in GWASpi are accessible through a self-teaching, user-friendly, graphical interface, while the heaviest functionalities can also be launched via a command-line interface. The basic usage of GWASpi starts by uploading raw genotype data exported from a proprietary genotyping platform or standard formats such as Affymetrix GW6.0, Illumina, PLINK, HapMap, etc. Once the data has been imported into GWASpi's database, the standard quality controls are performed, such as computing the number of missing genotypes per sample and per SNP, controlling for allelic mismatch and measuring individual heterozygosity. Next, a genotype frequency count is executed, which automatically includes a Hardy–Weinberg quality control. Finally, allelic, genotypic and trend association tests are performed, which generate tables, reports and their corresponding Manhattan and QQ-plots. A navigator is available to view the detail of a chromosome area around a given marker, providing a first glimpse of the results of the GWAS. These tables and plots also link each marker to a selection of reference databases such as Ensembl, NCBI's dbSNP and the UCSC genome browser among others.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Performance</head><p>The general application performance parameters benchmark as follows: RAM usage: GWASpi, as a Java application, gets assigned a fixed size of the system's RAM and will never request more than this number. The application has been designed to work on common desktop or laptop hardware, typically using 2 GB of RAM per 10 6 SNPs with the number of samples only being limited by available disk space. Disk usage: the disk usage increase is proportional to the number of genotypes, which is equal to the number of SNPs times the sample size. A genotype matrix 2×10 6 SNPs and 1000 samples large occupies about 4 GB on disk. Speed: depending on the format and the number of genotypes, the loading of a dataset into the GWASpi can take as little as a few minutes (using GWASpi's own format) up to hours. As a guideline, a study with 900.000 SNPs and 1000 samples in Affymetrix GW 6.0 format takes a total of about 4 h for data load, quality control, Hardy–Weinberg and association tests as well as for producing the corresponding reports and charts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>The integration of key pre-processing, quality control, data management, analysis and reporting steps within a single application is a distinctive advantage we present in GWASpi. With this application, we want to offer a solid and scalable platform, even if the current version focuses in basic case–control designs. New qualitycontrol and analysis methods as well as new formats are scheduled to be added into GWASpi. High-quality charts and reports sorted by relevance are generated automatically, delivering the results visually and in tables. Reference databases and chart navigation tools are integrated in the application providing an agile starting point for continuing research. For the user, GWASpi simplifies drastically the cumbersome workflows so common in GWAS pipelines and the many intermediate data files to be generated, checked and reprocessed. The learning curve for GWASpi's usage is very accessible as all available operations are documented in an online contextual help page.</p></div>
			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We are indebted to Francesc Calafell and Hafid Laayouni for their valuable discussion. Thanks are given to UCAR's NetCDF team for providing a method to suit GW matrices.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid and accurate haplotype phasing and missing-data inference for whole-genome association studies by use of localized haplotype clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Browning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Browning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1084" to="1097" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Human Genome Diversity Project: past, present and future</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Cavalli-Sforza</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The International HapMap Project</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International HapMap Consortium Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">426</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="789" to="796" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide association studies for complex traits: consensus, uncertainty and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Mccarthy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="356" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and populationbased linkage analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Purcell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="559" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A map of human genome variation from population-scale sequencing</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The 1000 Genomes Project Consortium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1061" to="1073" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HuGE Watch: tracking trends and patterns of published studies of genetic association and human genome epidemiology in near-real time</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Yu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Hum. Genet. EJHG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1155" to="1158" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>