
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:41+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Goldilocks: a tool for identifying genomic regions that are &apos;just right&apos;</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Samuel</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Nicholls</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aberystwyth University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Human Genetics Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Amanda</forename>
								<surname>Clare</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aberystwyth University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joshua</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Randall</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Human Genetics Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Goldilocks: a tool for identifying genomic regions that are &apos;just right&apos;</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw116</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 11, 2015; revised on February 8, 2016; accepted on February 26, 2016</note>
					<note>Sequence analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: John Hancock Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present Goldilocks: a Python package providing functionality for collecting summary statistics, identifying shifts in variation, discovering outlier regions and locating and extracting interesting regions from one or more arbitrary genomes for further analysis, for a user-provided definition of interesting. Availability and implementation: Goldilocks is freely available open-source software distributed under the MIT licence. Source code is hosted publicly at https://github.com/SamStudio8/goldilocks and the package may also be installed using pip install goldilocks. Documentation can be found at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Goldilocks is a Python package designed to take a census of sequence data in order to find regions that meet some criteria that are 'just right' for further analysis. It can be used by importing the package into a standalone script or via the command line tool. The tool accepts sequence data which could be from one or more individuals (with one or more sequences from each), organized into chromosomes or contigs and stored as FASTA. Goldilocks must also be supplied with a desired census strategy defining the criteria of interest, such as occurrences of individual nucleotide bases, motifs, deviations from a reference or GC-content. Chromosomes (or contigs) are slid beneath a window of a user-defined length and overlap and the strategy is applied over all input genomes. Goldilocks was developed as part of a quality control study to first determine what constitutes 'bad' quality data. For a large study, a pipeline was constructed to repeatedly perform variant calling, withholding one sample from the analysis in turn. A given sample's downstream effect could then be quantified by measuring the difference in the accuracy of a run in the absence of that sample. However, repeated application of computationally expensive and time consuming analysis of whole genomes was unsustainable.</p><p>The problem space needed to be reduced to a representative region: the genome's Goldilocks. For our study, we defined a 1 Mb region as 'just right' if it contained within 610 percentiles of the median number of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) appearing over all regions of our genome wide association study. These regions were then sorted by the number of SNPs appearing within the corresponding regions in a separate genotyping chip study. This allowed us to maximize the number of sites at which to check consensus between a run of our quality control pipeline and the SNP chip. Goldilocks was originally designed to return regions that matched these explicit criteria across multiple samples. The package has since been made more flexible and can be used to find regions of interest based on any arbitrary criteria such as GC-content, density of target motifs, pre-defined metrics and uncalled nucleotides (N's).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Features</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Customizable and interchangeable strategies</head><p>Criteria defining the metric for 'interesting' are held by Goldilocks in a user-selected strategy. Strategies are responsible for annotating V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2047</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.regions of sequence data as interesting (or not) and quantifying the result as a summary statistic that can be used later for ranking. Whilst Goldilocks includes a number of simple strategies for counting nucleotides, motifs, consensus to a reference and GC-content, the package offers a simple framework that allows one to customize or create strategies of their own (for an example refer to the supplement). Strategies implement the same interface and are thus all interchangeable, replacing the need for multiple stand-alone tools and data processing steps.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Simple sorting and flexible filtering</head><p>Goldilocks provides a simple but powerful query function capable of filtering and sorting regions by their absolute or percentile distance from the result of a mathematical operation over the whole set of regions, such as max, min, mean, median or proximity to an arbitrary target value. Candidates can be excluded based on the start or end position of the region, chromosome (or contig) and simple expressions on the strategy values themselves. Queries can be chained, allowing users to build up more complex queries to find regions with more specific criteria of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Plotting and exporting</head><p>Goldilocks provides several functions for extracting collected region metadata and the results of queries on that data. Sequences that lie on regions identified as interesting can be exported as FASTA, regions themselves can be output as BED. The package can output publication-ready graphs via matplotlib, or region metadata as a 'melted' dataframe for easy plotting with external packages such as R's ggplot2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Wickham, 2009</ref>). Data may also be exported in an arbitrarily delimited format for import into virtually any other tool, including Circos (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Krzywinski et al., 2009</ref>). For examples, please refer to the supplement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Multiprocessed census and efficient input</head><p>The census step can be executed over a user specified number of processes to improve performance on both desktops and servers. Sequence FASTA files are not read into physical RAM but instead mapped to virtual memory and accessed via indices stored in their corresponding index, avoiding expensive input reading operations. On a Core i5 laptop using four processes, Goldilocks can calculate GC-content over a whole human genome (hs37d5) with a window size of 100 kbp (and overlap of 50 kbp) in 3 min while using less than 2 GB of memory. On the same machine Goldilocks could simultaneously take a census of 10 short nucleotide motifs with regular expressions and overlaps in 15 min or 50 simple motifs in just over 5 min and using less than 3 GB of memory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Discussion</head><p>TheAlternative counting mechanisms, such as those available in Galaxy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Giardine et al., 2005</ref>) through EMBOSS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Rice et al., 2000</ref>) or various statistics tools in the Galaxy Toolshed, can accomplish similar functionality. However, as different tools require specific input formats and produce a variety of output formats, additional data handling steps are required as part of any pipeline, making it difficult to customize or swap counting plugins. Goldilocks is not intended to replace already existing dedicated software for counting tasks that require specific optimized data structures such as khmer (<ref type="bibr">Crusoe et al., 2014</ref>) for counting k-mers, but instead provides a general suite of swappable counters. Genome browsers such as the UCSC Genome Browser (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kent et al., 2002</ref>) allow the user to view a variety of tracks displaying the locations of different genomic properties. Interpreting large amounts of sequencing data by eye in such browsers can be difficult. Alternative browsers that allow zoomed browsing of interesting regions, such as the LayerCake (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Correll et al., 2015</ref>) visualization tool, attempt to ameliorate this problem. Goldilocks will automatically find regions of interest, suitable for further browsing or plotting if required. Epiviz and Epivizr (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Chelaru et al., 2014</ref>) combine both statistical analysis and visualization, connecting a web-based browsing environment to an R/Bioconductor-based calculation environment. Users interactively add more tracks or plots to further explore the areas surrounding the regions of interest in the genome. Their platform is comprehensive and provides a far larger scope for analysis than Goldilocks. We see Goldilocks as a lightweight Python solution for straightforward queries, and a useful addition to existing bioinformatics pipelines. Goldilocks has minimal dependencies: the core requires just NumPy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Oliphant, 2007</ref>) and matplotlib (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Hunter, 2007</ref>) to enable plotting. We provide a command line tool that offers access to the base functionality of the package to users without having to write a script of their own (for example usage see the supplement). Goldilocks is packaged with a testing suite, results and coverage of which are available online along with documentation. Source code is publicly available under an open source licence for review and community contribution.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Bioinformatics, 32(13), 2016, 2047–2049doi:10.</head><figDesc>1093/bioinformatics/btw116 Advance Access Publication Date: 7 March 2016 Applications Note</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Funding</head><figDesc>S.N. and A.C. report no external funding but thank Aberystwyth University for its support. J.R. is supported by Wellcome Trust [098051]. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>flexibility of Goldilocks lends itself for use in many different scenarios, for example: @BULLET Summarizing genomes Tabulate or plot variation in some statistic such as GC-content across one or more genomes for inspection. @BULLET Exploring extremes Find regions demonstrating unusual extremes with respect to the rest of the sequence data, such as high numbers of repeating subsequences or low GC-content.</figDesc><table>@BULLET Identifying shifts 
Detect shifts in variation in some statistic along a sequence, such 
as identification of chimeric activity within contigs. 
@BULLET Discovering outliers 
Detect regions of sequences with properties indicative of data 
quality issues. 
@BULLET Seeding sequences 
Locate subsequences to use as appropriate seeds for execution of 
other tools and algorithms. 
@BULLET Extracting subsets 
From a large set of regions of sequence, extract a subset which 
meets some desired arbitrary criteria for further analysis. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">S.M.Nicholls et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epiviz: interactive visual analytics for functional genomics data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Chelaru</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="938" to="940" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LayerCake: a tool for the visual comparison of viral deep sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Correll</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="3522" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The khmer software package: enabling efficient nucleotide sequence analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Crusoe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="0900" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Galaxy: a platform for interactive large-scale genome analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Giardine</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1451" to="1455" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Matplotlib: a 2d graphics environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hunter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Sci. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human genome browser at UCSC</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Kent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="996" to="1006" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circos: an information aesthetic for comparative genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Krzywinski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1639" to="1645" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Python for scientific computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Oliphant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Sci. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EMBOSS: The European Molecular Biology Open Software Suite</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Rice</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Wickham</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Goldilocks</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2049" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>