
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:43+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology GPU-Meta-Storms: computing the structure similarities among massive amount of microbial community samples using GPU</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">7 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xiaoquan</forename>
								<surname>Su</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Computational Biology Group of Single Cell Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Associate Editor: Igor Jurisica</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Shandong Key Laboratory of Energy Genetics, CAS Key Laboratory of Biofuels and Bioenergy Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Qingdao Institute of Bioenergy and Bioprocess Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>266101</postCode>
									<settlement>Qingdao</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P. R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xuetao</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Computational Biology Group of Single Cell Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Associate Editor: Igor Jurisica</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Shandong Key Laboratory of Energy Genetics, CAS Key Laboratory of Biofuels and Bioenergy Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Qingdao Institute of Bioenergy and Bioprocess Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>266101</postCode>
									<settlement>Qingdao</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P. R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gongchao</forename>
								<surname>Jing</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Computational Biology Group of Single Cell Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Associate Editor: Igor Jurisica</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Shandong Key Laboratory of Energy Genetics, CAS Key Laboratory of Biofuels and Bioenergy Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Qingdao Institute of Bioenergy and Bioprocess Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>266101</postCode>
									<settlement>Qingdao</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P. R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kang</forename>
								<surname>Ning</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Computational Biology Group of Single Cell Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Associate Editor: Igor Jurisica</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Shandong Key Laboratory of Energy Genetics, CAS Key Laboratory of Biofuels and Bioenergy Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Qingdao Institute of Bioenergy and Bioprocess Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>266101</postCode>
									<settlement>Qingdao</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P. R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology GPU-Meta-Storms: computing the structure similarities among massive amount of microbial community samples using GPU</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1031" to="1033"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">7 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt736</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 31, 2013; revised on November 29, 2013; accepted on December 15, 2013</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Contact: ningkang@qibebtaccn</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The number of microbial community samples is increasing with exponential speed. Data-mining among microbial community samples could facilitate the discovery of valuable biological information that is still hidden in the massive data. However, current methods for the comparison among microbial communities are limited by their ability to process large amount of samples each with complex community structure. Summary: We have developed an optimized GPU-based software, GPU-Meta-Storms, to efficiently measure the quantitative phylogen-etic similarity among massive amount of microbial community samples. Our results have shown that GPU-Meta-Storms would be able to compute the pair-wise similarity scores for 10 240 samples within 20 min, which gained a speed-up of 417 000 times compared with single-core CPU, and 42600 times compared with 16-core CPU. Therefore, the high-performance of GPU-Meta-Storms could facilitate in-depth data mining among massive microbial community samples, and make the real-time analysis and monitoring of temporal or conditional changes for microbial communities possible. Availability and implementation: GPU-Meta-Storms is implemented by CUDA (Compute Unified Device Architecture) and Cþþ. Source code is available at http://www.computationalbioenergy.org/meta-storms.html.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Because most microbes are not isolatable and cultivatable (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Jurkowski et al., 2007</ref>), metagenomic methods have been used to analyze a microbial community as a whole. Next-generation sequencing techniques (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Mardis, 2008</ref>) have enabled the fast profiling of structures for a large number of microbial communities. Thus, a rapidly increasing amount of metagenomic profiles for microbial communities have been archived in public repositories and research laboratories around the world, such as MG-RAST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Meyer et al., 2008</ref>) and CAMERA2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Seshadri et al., 2007</ref>), while NCBI (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/) also contains thousands of metagenomic related projects with 4100 000 samples. With such a large volume of metagenomic profiling data, it has become possible and important to compare the complex structures of microbial communities in large scale for in-depth data mining to discover precious biological patterns hidden in those massive data. A number of methods have been proposed for comparison of different metagenomic samples. MEGAN (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Huson et al., 2011</ref>) can compare multiple samples based on taxonomy levels without considering phylogenetic relationships among taxa. STAMP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Parks and Beiko, 2010</ref>), METAREP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Goll et al., 2010</ref>) and MetaRank (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Wang et al., 2011</ref>) process metagenomic data using standard statistical tests (mainly t-tests and principal component analysis with some modifications). Some 16S rRNA amplicon analysis toolkits, such as Mothur (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Schloss et al., 2009</ref>) and QIIME (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Caporaso et al., 2010</ref>), include UniFrac (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Lozupone and Knight, 2005</ref>) and Fast UniFrac (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Hamady et al., 2010</ref>) algorithms, which use distances among species to make phylogenetic beta diversity measurement more effective at showing ecological patterns. Nevertheless, the restriction in the amount of samples for comparison, as well as running speed, limits the extension of these tools on analysis of huge number of microbial community samples. Moreover, current needs for real-time monitoring of temporal or conditional changes for microbial communities in environment and energy research areas have made these methods inadequate. Recently, we have proposed a more efficient method, MetaStorms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Su et al., 2012a</ref>), for quantitative comparison between microbial community samples based on a binary phylogenetic tree with a time complexity of Nlog(N) (N is the number of species in one sample). However, as the amount of samples increases, the overall time complexity of M 2 Â Nlog(N) (M is the number of samples) for the pair-wise comparison always leads to an unacceptable running time. Therefore, such computingintensive tasks require novel ultra-high processing throughput.*To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>y</head><p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Non-recursive transformation</head><p>The scoring function of Meta-Storms compares two microbial community samples' structures by bottom–up recursive traversal to their common weighted phylogenetic tree, in which edge weight represents the phylogenetic distance and node weight represents the species abundance, and calculates an overall similarity score (between 0 and 100%). Though GPU hardware and CUDA technology are good at efficient processing of computing-intensive works in parallel, the above recursive traversal would be limited by the stack size in GPU. Therefore, MetaStorms scoring function needs to be transformed into non-recursive format (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Segovia et al., 2009</ref>). Here, we re-sorted all nodes by postorder traversal to the phylogenetic tree, so that all calculations can be processed by serially accessing the sorted nodes without recursive overlap.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">CUDA-based parallel programming implementation</head><p>Benefited by the many-core architecture of GPU, scoring function can be invocated in parallel by large number of threads to compute the similarities among massive amount of samples. For the synchronization of many-core programming, we map all samples to Greengenes CoreSet tree (release date: May 2009) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">DeSantis et al., 2006</ref>) as the reference phylogenetic tree. To calculate the pair-wise similarity scores (also referred to as 'similarity matrix') of N samples, NÂN threads are launched in GPU to make each similarity score in the matrix processed by one independent thread. Abundance values of species of each sample and phylogenetic distances are firstly loaded from the file system and initialized in RAM by CPU, then sent to graphics processing unit (GPU) on-board RAM for parallel computing. After all threads of GPU finish the tasks, all elements of similarity matrix are sent back to RAM, and stored in file system on hard disk.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">CUDA-based optimization</head><p>Limited by the low I/O bandwidth of GPU on board RAM (also referred to as 'global memory' in CUDA), we have designed the following optimization methods to improve the execution efficiency of GPUMeta-Storms on CUDA.</p><p>(1) Global memory alignment: Because all threads calculate the same phylogenetic tree with the same nodes order, their abundance values can be sorted in the same order for global memory alignment to accelerate both the transmission from RAM to GPU and the global memory access by GPU.</p><p>(2) Register recycling allocation: All temporary results of internal nodes of the phylogenetic tree are kept into registers, of which the I/O speed is %100 times faster than global memory. The register recycling strategy reduces the required register number to only 10 to adapt to the CUDA.</p><p>(3) Application of shared memory: For all threads calculating on the same phylogenetic tree, distance values are stored into shared memory, which can be accessed by all threads with low I/O latency.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Input and output</head><p>GPU-Meta-Storms accepts each microbial community sample as an identical plain-text file with the identified reference phylogenetic tree IDs of all species in it, which can be generated by Parallel-META (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Su et al., 2012b</ref>) from metagenomic shotgun or 16S rRNA sequence data. GPUMeta-Storms outputs the pair-wise similarity scores of all input samples into a plain-text file, in which each element is a float number that represents the similarity for a pair of samples between 0 and 100%. Based on permutation test results (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Su et al., 2012a</ref>), a similarity score of 85% or higher indicates significant similarity between two samples. samples based on GPU and CUDA with very high speed. Such acceleration techniques based on GPU make it possible to perform in-depth data mining from massive number of samples, thus making real-time analysis and monitoring of temporal or conditional changes for microbial communities possible.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>GPU-Meta-Storms implements the scoring function of Meta-Storms (Su et al., 2012a) with non-recursive transformation, CUDA (Compute Unified Device Architecture)-based parallel programming and optimizations. The synergy of these techniques enabled ultra-high processing speed to evaluate the similarities among large amount of microbial community samples.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> RESULTS AND DISCUSSIONS Different number of human habitat microbial community samples from the project &apos;Moving pictures of human microbiome&apos; (Caporaso et al., 2011) have been randomly selected (samples are available on the software website) to evaluate the performance of GPU-Meta-Storms in comparison of microbial community samples. All experiments in this work were completed on a rack server with dual Intel Xeon E5-2650 CPU, 64GB DDR3 ECC RAM, NVIDIA M2075 GPU and 1TB hard drive in RAID 1. 3.1 Running time comparison with CPU-based computation In this work, we compared the running time of GPUMeta-Storms with CPU based Meta-Storms (version 1.2, single core and 16 cores) using the same non-recursive algorithm based on different number of samples to show the speed acceleration of GPU-Meta-Storms. Because the similarity matrix with large number of samples cannot be completed in short time for CPU computing, we calculated the expected running time of CPU for 42000 samples based on linear-increase estimation (error rate of 6.81E-12). From Figure 1, it was observed that GPU-Meta-Storms had a maximum speed-up of 17 332 times compared with single-core CPU and 2640 times to 16-core CPU. For real time cost, GPUMeta-Storms constructed the similarity matrix of 10 240 samples within 20 min, whereas the expected running time of 16-core CPU is 45 days. 3.2 Peak computing throughput of GPU-Meta-Storms This experiment evaluated the peak computing throughput of double-floating-point of GPU-Meta-Storms and scaled in GFLOPS (Giga Floating-point Operations Per Second). We observed that the peak computing throughput of GPU-MetaStorms rose up to a stable status of 110 GFLOPS, indicating that 4610 000 pair-wise sample similarity scores could be obtained per second. 4 CONCLUSION GPU-Meta-Storms provides a parallel computing solution for the comparison among massive amount of microbial community Fig. 1. Overall running time of similarity matrix computing by GPU and CPU. The Y-axis is in 10-based log scale. Framed bars indicate the estimated running time</note>

			<note place="foot">X.Su et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">GPU-Meta-Storms at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head><p>The authors thank NVIDIA for their support through CUDA Research Center in QIBEBT-CAS.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">QIIME allows analysis of high-throughput community sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Caporaso</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="336" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moving pictures of the human microbiome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Caporaso</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Greengenes, a chimera-checked 16S rRNA gene database and workbench compatible with ARB</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Z</forename>
				<surname>Desantis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5069" to="5072" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">METAREP: JCVI metagenomics reports–an open source tool for high-performance comparative metagenomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Goll</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2631" to="2632" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast UniFrac: facilitating high-throughput phylogenetic analyses of microbial communities including analysis of pyrosequencing and PhyloChip data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hamady</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ISME J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrative analysis of environmental sequences using MEGAN4</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Huson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1552" to="1560" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metagenomics: a call for bringing a new science into the classroom (while it&apos;s still new)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Jurkowski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">CBE Life Sci. Educ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="260" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UniFrac: a new phylogenetic method for comparing microbial communities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Lozupone</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Knight</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8228" to="8235" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of next-generation sequencing technology on genetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Mardis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The metagenomics RAST server-a public resource for the automatic phylogenetic and functional analysis of metagenomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Meyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">386</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying biologically relevant differences between metagenomic communities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Parks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Beiko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="715" to="721" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introducing mothur: open-source, platform-independent, community-supported software for describing and comparing microbial communities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Schloss</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7537" to="7541" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Iterative layer-based raytracing on CUDA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Segovia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE 28th International Performance Computing and Communications Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="255" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CAMERA: a community resource for metagenomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Seshadri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">75</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meta-Storms: efficient search for similar microbial communities based on a novel indexing scheme and similarity score for metagenomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Su</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2493" to="2501" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parallel-META: efficient metagenomic data analysis based on high-performance computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Su</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">16</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MetaRank: a rank conversion scheme for comparative analysis of microbial community compositions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3341" to="3347" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>