
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:32+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Graphics processing unit implementations of relative expression analysis algorithms enable dramatic computational speedup</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andrew</forename>
								<forename type="middle">T</forename>
								<surname>Magis</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Biophysics and Computational Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Earls</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Youn-Hee</forename>
								<surname>Ko</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioengineering</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">James</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A Eddy</forename>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nathan</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Price</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Biophysics and Computational Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Illinois</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>61801</postCode>
									<settlement>Urbana</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Graphics processing unit implementations of relative expression analysis algorithms enable dramatic computational speedup</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="872" to="873"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr033</idno>
					<note type="submission">Gene expression Advance Access publication January 20, 2011 Received on October 26, 2010; revised on December 19, 2010; accepted on January 15, 2011</note>
					<note>[10:38 3/3/2011 Bioinformatics-btr033.tex] Page: 872 872–873 USA Associate Editor: Trey Ideker Availability: http://www.igb.illinois.edu/labs/price/downloads/. Contact: ndprice@illinois.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The top-scoring pair (TSP) and top-scoring triplet (TST) algorithms are powerful methods for classification from expression data, but analysis of all combinations across thousands of human transcriptome samples is computationally intensive, and has not yet been achieved for TST. Implementation of these algorithms for the graphics processing unit results in dramatic speedup of two orders of magnitude, greatly increasing the searchable combinations and accelerating the pace of discovery.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Rapidly improving technologies have made large amounts of gene expression data available for analysis and classification. The NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database contains hundreds of thousands of samples representing a wide range of diseased and healthy tissue for which gene expression has been measured. As next-generation RNA sequencing technology (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cloonan et al., 2008</ref>) becomes ubiquitous, GEO and other databases will further increase in size and accuracy of information. Researchers have sought to use this expression data to identify distinct gene relationships that classify disease states, allowing for accurate diagnosis of diseases given the expression patterns of a few genes. Such methods include support vector machines (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Brown et al., 2000</ref>), decision trees (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Zhang et al., 2003</ref>) and neural networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Khan et al., 2001</ref>). The top-scoring pair (TSP) algorithm and its variants have demonstrated similar accuracies to these methods while remaining relatively simple, resistant to overfitting and consistent across data normalization methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Geman et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Lin et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Price et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Tan et al., 2005</ref>). Classifiers identified using these algorithms have been used to predict cancer outcomes and model disease progression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Eddy et al., 2010</ref>). Despite these advantages, the TSP and especially the top-scoring triplet (TST) algorithm are computationally intensive and therefore slow. Because increasing the accuracy of predictions may require analysis of thousands of samples across tens of thousands of transcripts, it is important to improve the speed of * To whom correspondence should be addressed. these algorithms. Faster algorithms also enable more comparisons to be made, including automated data mining across many sample sets. While primarily known for gaming applications, the graphics processing unit (GPU) is increasingly applied to computationally challenging scientific problems including molecular dynamics simulations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Stone et al., 2010</ref>), quantum chemistry (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ufimtsev and Martinez, 2008</ref>), and medical imaging (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Stone et al., 2008</ref>). The GPU is designed for massive parallelism involving thousands of simultaneous executing threads, but requires different coding than that which runs on CPUs. Algorithms well suited for such parallelism can run tens to hundreds of times faster on GPUs than a corresponding CPU implementation. GPUs are also now widely available to researchers via National Center for Supercomputing Applications (NCSA) clusters and businesses such as Amazon Web Services EC2 Cloud Computing. Here, we present implementations of the TSP algorithm and the TST algorithm on the GPU. As the TST algorithm is particularly computationally demanding, this GPU implementation enables the first comprehensive search of all possible TSTs for classification.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">ALGORITHMS</head><p>Given two classes of samples C = {C 1 , C 2 } with expression values for Ngenes {x 1 ,...,x N }, the TSP algorithm identifies the marker gene pair (x i ,x j ) in which the TSP score</p><formula>i,j = Pr[x i &lt; x j |C = C 1 ]−Pr[x j &lt; x i |C = C 2 ] ,i = j</formula><p>is maximized. The algorithm performs all pairwise comparisons between the genes of the dataset and calculates the TSP score for each, then selects the maximum or set of maximum scores. Multiple pairs may then be combined to improve classification (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Tan et al., 2005</ref>). The TSP algorithm exhibits O(N 2 ) time complexity. The TST algorithm extends the TSP algorithm to triplets of genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Lin et al., 2009</ref>). The TST algorithm is calculated similarly to TSP: all possible triplets of gene ranks are compared, and the probabilities of each permutation within each triplet are calculated and scored. The algorithm finds the maximum TST score from all triplets in O(N 3 ) time complexity. Extended details of both algorithms can be found in the Supplementary Material.each thread is executed by a single core, and runs in parallel with all other threads currently being executed on the SM. The GPU implements the single instruction, multiple data (SIMD) design: each parallel thread in a multiprocessor executes the same instruction simultaneously, but on different data. Threads are logically organized into thread blocks, which map loosely onto each streaming multiprocessor. The TSP and TST algorithms exhibit characteristics that make them ideal for a GPU implementation: there is no data dependence between individual scores; therefore each score may be calculated in parallel (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). Detailed descriptions of the implementation of these algorithms on the GPU are in the Supplementary Material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Graphics processing unit implementations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">RESULTS</head><p>The algorithms described above have been implemented in C with CUDA extensions and compiled into MEX files for use within the MATLAB computing environment; a standalone application is also available. Two existing CPU implementations of the TSP algorithm, tspair (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Leek, 2009</ref>) and RXA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Lin et al., 2009</ref>) were used for speed comparisons with the GPU code. One existing CPU implementation of the TST algorithm (RXA) was used for speed comparisons. Both CPU software packages are implemented in the C programming language as packages for the statistical environment R. All CPU speed tests were performed on an Intel Xeon x5680 3.33 GHz 6-core processor. The GPU tests were performed on a NVIDIA Tesla T10 and an NVIDIA GeForce GTX480. Source code and executables for all GPU implementations are available at http://www.igb.illinois. edu/labs/price/downloads/.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>shows the results of the running time comparisons. The results for RXA and tspair are plotted separately due to the fact that RXA implements the Wilcoxon rank sum test to filter for only the most differentially expressed genes, whereas tspair does not. As the number of genes increases, the speedup on the GPU improves, therefore further speedup might be expected for larger tests. All GPU timings include the device data transfer as well as computation times. The Tesla T10 executes the algorithms 77X to 255X faster than the corresponding CPU implementations, and the GTX480 executes the algorithms 228X to 455X faster. Processing 10 000 genes on the CPU version of the TST algorithm would take over 6.5 months, while the GPU implementation of the TST algorithm on this dataset was completed in &lt;9 h. Using the GPU enables the discovery of accurate marker gene pairs and triplets thatare infeasible with the CPU implementations, while also allowing more stringent error estimation methods than are currently possible due to previous computational time constraints.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Modern (compute 1.2 and higher) NVIDIA CUDA GPU architectures contain multiple (2–30) streaming multiprocessors (SM), each consisting</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Logical organization of the TSP algorithm on the GPU. Each portion of the output TSP matrix is calculated independently of the others by each thread block. Each thread outputs a single element of the TSP matrix. of multiple cores. Each core can execute one floating point or integer instruction per clock cycle in parallel with all other cores of that SM. Programming this device involves organizing executing code into threads; each thread is executed by a single core, and runs in parallel with all other threads currently being executed on the SM. The GPU implements the single instruction, multiple data (SIMD) design: each parallel thread in a multiprocessor executes the same instruction simultaneously, but on different data. Threads are logically organized into thread blocks, which map loosely onto each streaming multiprocessor. The TSP and TST algorithms exhibit characteristics that make them ideal for a GPU implementation: there is no data dependence between individual scores; therefore each score may be calculated in parallel (Fig. 1). Detailed descriptions of the implementation of these algorithms on the GPU are in the Supplementary Material.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Plot of RXA TSP algorithm versus GPU implementation (left). Both algorithms filter for most differentially expressed genes using the Wilcoxon rank-sum test. Maximum speedup is 255X (Tesla T10) and 455X (GTX480). Plot of tspair TSP algorithm versus GPU implementation. Maximum speedup is 83X (Tesla T10) and 228X (GTX480) (center). Plot of RXA TST algorithm versus GPU implementation. Maximum speedup is 77X (Tesla T10) and 301X (GTX480) (right). The dataset used had 350 samples in Class 1 and 306 samples in Class 2. All data points are the mean of three independent runs of the software. Dotted lines indicate extrapolation from previous data points using a quadratic (TSP) or cubic (TST) polynomial fit.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from [10:38 3/3/2011 Bioinformatics-btr033.tex]</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors acknowledge the National Center for Supercomputing Applications (NCSA) AC cluster for CPU and GPU speed tests.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge-based analysis of microarray gene expression data by using support vector machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Brown</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="267" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stem cell transcriptome profiling via massive-scale mRNA sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Cloonan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="619" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relative expression analysis for molecular cancer diagnosis and prognosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Eddy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technol. Cancer Res. Treat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classifying gene expression profiles from pairwise mRNA comparisons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Geman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Appl. Genet. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classification and diagnostic prediction of cancers using gene expression profiling and artificial neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Khan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="673" to="679" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The tspair package for finding top scoring pair classifiers in R</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Leek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1203" to="1204" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ordering of expression among a few genes can provide simple cancer biomarkers and signal BRCA1 mutations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">256</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Highly accurate two-gene classifier for differentiating gastrointestinal stromal tumors and leiomyosarcomas</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Price</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3414" to="3419" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GPU-accelerated molecular modeling coming of age</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Stone</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Graph Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="116" to="125" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accelerating advanced MRI reconstructions on GPUs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Stone</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Parall. Dist Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1307" to="1318" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simple decision rules for classifying human cancers from gene expression profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Tan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3896" to="3904" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graphical processing units for quantum chemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Ufimtsev</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Martinez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Sci. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cell and tumor classification using gene expression data: construction of forests</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4168" to="4172" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>