
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies HippDB: a database of readily targeted helical protein–protein interactions</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christina</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Bergey</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Anthropology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andrew</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Watkins</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">New York University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10003</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Paramjit</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Arora</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">New York University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10003</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies HippDB: a database of readily targeted helical protein–protein interactions</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2806" to="2807"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt483</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 1, 2013; revised on July 11, 2013; accepted on August 15, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Burkhard Rost/p/helidb, implemented in Perl and supported on Linux. Contact: arora@nyu.edu</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>HippDB catalogs every protein–protein interaction whose structure is available in the Protein Data Bank and which exhibits one or more helices at the interface. The Web site accepts queries on variables such as helix length and sequence, and it provides computational alanine scanning and change in solvent-accessible surface area values for every interfacial residue. HippDB is intended to serve as a starting point for structure-based small molecule and peptidomi-metic drug development. Availability and implementation: HippDB is freely available on the web at http://www.nyu.edu/projects/arora/hippdb. The Web site is implemented in PHP, MySQL and Apache. Source code freely available for download at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Protein–protein interactions (PPIs) mediate fundamental signaling pathways and cellular processes. Although PPIs are highly promising pharmaceutical targets, they are not preferred targets in conventional drug development because of their extended flat interfaces. In particular, compound libraries for high-throughput screening that offer attractive lead compounds for enzymatic targets lack the topological and functional complexity necessary for PPI inhibition (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hajduk and Greer, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Raj et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Wells and McClendon, 2007</ref>). One successful method to inhibit PPIs is the mimicry of secondary structure motifs that contribute to complex formation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Azzarito et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Boersma et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Jochim and Arora, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Moellering et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Patgiri et al., 2011</ref>). Often a subset of the residues at a protein–protein interface can contribute significantly to the binding interaction (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Clackson and Wells, 1995</ref>). Because solubility and specificity are eternal problems in drug design, it is advantageous to identify and prioritize most important residues, leaving less important positions free for fine-tuning (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bullock et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Jochim and Arora, 2010</ref>). Conventional computational methods to predict important residues include alanine scanning (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Jochim and Arora, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Kortemme and Baker, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Kortemme et al., 2004</ref>) and solvent-accessible surface area (ÁSASA) analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Koes and Camacho, 2012</ref>). Alanine scanning provides the change in ÁG resulting from a contact residue being mutated to alanine, while a ÁSASA value describes how much of the residue is buried from solvent on binding. We have previously developed a scoring strategy to rank protein interfaces by their promise for synthetic inhibition (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bullock et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Jochim and Arora, 2010</ref>) and designed inhibitors of formerly 'undruggable' PPIs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Patgiri et al., 2011</ref>). To follow-up this work, we sought to derive a readily accessible resource for the chemical biology community. Research groups with potent small-molecule scaffolds might be interested in small interfaces with hotspot residues in two consecutive positions or in the i and iþ4 positions, whereas those developing peptoid or beta-peptide foldamers might be more interested in long interfaces with high total ÁÁG. HippDB—a database of helical interfaces in PPIs—lists all the helical PPIs in the Protein Data Bank (PDB) and catalogs computational alanine scanning results (ÁÁG in Rosetta energy units) and ÁSASA for each interfacial residue. We expect this dataset will be a useful resource for PPI inhibition.<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>depicts a typical workflow in HippDB. The user might first search for interface helices found in humans by constraining the organism name. Next, the user might trim the results for complexes with exactly three hotspot residues, then for helices 510 residues long, then for a ÁÁG average 42. By clicking on the PDB codes that result, the user can view any of the five complexes fitting these criteria in JMol, with their hotspot residues displayed in wireframe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>Structures of multi-entity protein complexes' asymmetric units were obtained from the PDB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Berman et al., 2000</ref>). We identified all interacting interface chains within each PDB file and created a new PDB file for each chain and each pair of interacting chains. If the original PDB file contained more than one model, only the lowest-scoring model was used (according to Rosetta's 'Relax' protocol). Each qualifying pair of chains was analyzed using the RosettaScripts AlaScan filter, averaging 100 runs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baker and Sali, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Fleishman et al., 2011</ref>). Following alanine scanning, we isolated all interface helices containing two or more hotspot residues (ÁÁG 41.0 Rosetta energy units, which approximately scale as 1 kcal/mol) and computed ÁSASA using NACCESS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hubbard and Thornton, 1993</ref>). Interface helices were required to possess at least four consecutive residues, each assigned as helical by Dictionary of Secondary Structure Prediction acquired from the Center for Molecular and Biomolecular Informatics Web site (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kabsch and Sander, 1983</ref>). For each interface helix, parameters including average and total ÁÁG and ÁSASA, the percentage of the complex's ÁÁG and ÁSASA contributed by the helix, the helix length, hotspot *To whom correspondence should be addressed. y The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. distance and sequence and the organism of origin are recorded in the database. The Web site interface uses original JavaScript for constructing queries, a standard AJAX protocol to execute the queries and a JQuery extension (DataTables) to format the query results (<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>From 11 818 multiprotein entries in the PDB, 379 877 files of two protein chains were produced and subjected to alanine scanning. Of these interfaces, we found 7308 helices of four residues or longer with the two hotspots necessary to qualify for the database. A qualifying alpha helix is, on average, 13.2 residues long and contains 2.7 hotspots. The end-to-end distance separating these hotspots is 7.3 residues. On average, the three best hotspot residues sum to a ÁG of 3.9 in Rosetta energy units, and the helix overall contributes 48% of the chain's total ÁÁG and 37% of its ÁSASA. The rational design of PPI inhibitors involves a systematic analysis of native interactions. By cataloging the results of this analysis for every known structure, and by describing secondorder metrics to help prioritize design efforts, this database will eliminate often-reduplicated effort and greatly accelerate the design process. In this way, HippDB complements existing resources such as PocketQuery and HotSprint, the former of which catalogues regions of high solvent burial and the latter of which highlights evolutionary conservation to evaluate the role, functional or structural, of individual hotspots (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Camacho and Koes, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Guney et al., 2008</ref>).<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. A typical HippDB query. The five resulting complexes are depicted with the qualifying chain in green and the partner chain in orange. 1YCR is the native p53/mdm2 complex; 3FDO and 3JZO are complexes of p53-like synthetic peptides with mdm4 and 3G03 and 3JZR are complexes of synthetic peptides with mdm2</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. A selection of the fields found in HippDB a</figDesc><table>Field name 
Description 

Average ÁÁG, helix 
Average ÁÁG contributed by a residue in 
the helix 
Percentage ÁÁG, helix 
Percentage of the chain's total ÁÁG due to 
the helix 
Percentage ÁSASA, helix 
Percentage of the chain's total ÁSASA due 
to the helix 
Helix sequence 
Sequence of the interface helix 
Hotspot IDs 
List of hotspot residues with residue type 
and ÁÁG 
MimeticScore 
Sum of the top three hotspot ÁÁG values 

a 

HippDB includes standard search fields such as the PDB code, organism along 
with specific fields listed above. The fields are searchable and sortable. </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">HippDB at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank Andrea Jochim for her work on the project that inspired HippDB.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inhibition of [alpha]-helix-mediated protein-protein interactions using designed molecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Azzarito</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein structure prediction and structural genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Baker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Sali</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">294</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Protein Data Bank</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Berman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of diverse alpha/beta-backbone patterns for fnctional alpha-helix mimicry: analogues of the Bim BH3 domain</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Boersma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="323" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing helical protein interfaces for inhibitor design</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Bullock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14220" to="14223" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PocketQuery: protein–protein interaction inhibitor starting points from protein–protein interaction structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Camacho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Koes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="387" to="392" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A hot-spot of binding-energy in a hormone-receptor interface</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Clackson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Wells</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">267</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="383" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RosettaScripts: a scripting language interface to the Rosetta macromolecular modeling suite</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Fleishman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20161</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HotSprint: database of computational hot spots in protein interfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Guney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="662" to="666" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A decade of fragment-based drug design: strategic advances and lessons learned</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Hajduk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Greer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Drug Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Hubbard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Thornton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NACCESS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic analysis of helical protein interfaces reveals targets for synthetic inhibitors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Jochim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Arora</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACS Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="919" to="923" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dictionary of protein secondary structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Kabsch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Sander</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biopolymers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2577" to="2637" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Small-molecule inhibitor starting points learned from protein-protein interaction inhibitor structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Koes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Camacho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="784" to="791" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple physical model for binding energy hot spots in protein-protein complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Kortemme</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Baker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14116" to="14121" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational alanine scanning of protein-protein interfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Kortemme</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. STKE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct inhibition of the NOTCH transcription factor complex</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Moellering</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">462</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An orthosteric inhibitor of the Ras-Sos interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Patgiri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="585" to="587" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plucking the high hanging fruit: a systematic approach for targeting protein-protein interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Raj</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioorg. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4051" to="4057" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reaching for high-hanging fruit in drug discovery at protein-protein interfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Wells</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Mcclendon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">450</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1001" to="1009" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>