
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:31+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology HyperModules: identifying clinically and phenotypically significant network modules with disease mutations for biomarker discovery</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alvin</forename>
								<surname>Leung</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Donnelly Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>160 College Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>M5S 3E1</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gary</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Bader</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Donnelly Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>160 College Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>M5S 3E1</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jü</forename>
								<surname>Ri Reimand</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Donnelly Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>160 College Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>M5S 3E1</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Donnelly Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>160 College Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>M5S 3E1</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology HyperModules: identifying clinically and phenotypically significant network modules with disease mutations for biomarker discovery</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2230" to="2232"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu172</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on December 20, 2013; revised on February 25, 2014; accepted on March 25, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Availability and implementation: HyperModules is available in Cytoscape App Store and as a command line tool at www.baderlab. org/Sofware/HyperModules. Contact: Juri.Reimand@utoronto.ca or Gary.Bader@utoronto.ca Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Correlating disease mutations with clinical and phenotypic information such as drug response or patient survival is an important goal of personalized cancer genomics and a first step in biomarker discovery. HyperModules is a network search algorithm that finds frequently mutated gene modules with significant clinical or phenotypic signatures from biomolecular interaction networks.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Establishing functional links between genetic variation and human disease is a key goal of cancer genome sequencing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Gonzalez-Perez et al., 2013</ref>) and genome-wide association studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hardy and Singleton, 2009</ref>). Complex diseases like cancer are often driven by infrequent changes in multiple genes in pathways (<ref type="bibr">Vogelstein et al., 2013</ref>). Network analysis helps interpret mutations in systems context and find disease genes, pathways and biomarkers for precision medicine (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Barabasi et al., 2011</ref>). Discovery of modules (subnetworks) in biological networks helps isolate systems with disease-related properties and reduces interactome complexity. A growing number of methods are available for this purpose. A landmark paper combines gene expression signatures with protein–protein interactions (PPI) to find predictive modules of cancer outcome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chuang et al., 2007</ref>). The NETBAG method studies genetic associations and copy number variants to find autism-related modules (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Gilman et al., 2011</ref>). HotNet detects frequently mutated pathways in networks (<ref type="bibr">Vandin et al., 2011</ref><ref type="bibr">Vandin et al., , 2012</ref>). Net-Cox builds prognostic cancer signatures in network analysis of gene expression data (<ref type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2013</ref>). The Reactome FI Cytoscape plugin uncovers prognostic gene modules from networks and gene expression data (<ref type="bibr">Wu and Stein, 2012</ref>). Network-based stratification predicts tumor subtypes from mutations in network regions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hofree et al., 2013</ref>). Such modules maximize a feature of genes such as differential expression, disease mutation frequency or enrichment of interactions. Because clinical profiles of patients are increasingly available in cancer genomics efforts such as the The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) pan-cancer project (<ref type="bibr">Weinstein et al., 2013</ref>), new methods are needed to discover multivariate biomarkers in networks. We recently analyzed cancer mutations in phosphorylation signaling and found that kinase–substrate networks are informative of patient survival and therapy response (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Reimand and Bader, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Reimand et al., 2013</ref>). In particular, we found network modules with rare mutations in ovarian cancer patients with improved prognosis. We created the HyperModules method to systematically discover clinically correlated modules from gene and protein networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Reimand and Bader, 2013</ref>) based on our earlier work on functional subnetwork discovery (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Altmae et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Reimand et al., 2008</ref>). Here we present the previously unavailable software in open-source Java as a command line tool for automated work and a Cytoscape app for interactive graphical analysis. type of clinical analysis and columns in data table (survival time or variable such as tumor relapse). Survival analysis requires follow-up time and vital status of patients. Detected modules are studied further with network visualization, survival curves and data export. We tested HyperModules on protein networks to find survival modules with cancer mutations. We extracted three human PPI networks of variable size from iRefWeb (<ref type="bibr">Turner et al., 2010</ref>), and five cancer mutation datasets from the International Cancer Genome Consortium portal version 12 (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S1</ref>). For example, network analysis of 30 000 interactions with 121 liver cancer patients, 686 mutated genes and 10 000 permutations takes 10 min on an 8-core computer with 16 GB RAM. HyperModules is thus applicable to a range of networks and mutation datasets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">EXAMPLE ANALYSIS</head><p>An example dataset is provided in Supplementary File S1. It comprises 183 ovarian cancer patients from the TCGA study (Cancer Genome Atlas Research<ref type="bibr">Network, 2008</ref>) and the network of 4823 kinase–substrate interactions from our earlier study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Reimand and Bader, 2013</ref>). The ovarian cancer mutations are restricted to 163 proteins with single nucleotide variants affecting protein phosphorylation sites or kinase domains. Two sets of modules were computed with 10 000 network permutations and are shown in Supplementary Figures S2–S3. First, the search for survival correlations in the kinase–substrate network with log-rank test identified 19 modules, where associated patients have significantly different survival rates compared with other patients in the cohort (empirical P 0:05). Second, the categorical variable search with Fisher's exact test revealed fivemodules with significant enrichment of alive patients (empirical P 0:05). The modules are also summarized in Supplementary Table S1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>HyperModules is a biological network-mining algorithm that reveals modules of interacting genes with clinically informative disease mutations. Diverse biomolecular interaction networks can be analyzed, including PPI networks, gene regulatory networks and curated biological pathways. Disease mutations are also broadly defined. Although we initially studied cancer point mutations, other types of alterations such as copy number and gene expression changes can be used. HyperModules finds correlations with groups of genes where mutations may be infrequent but the signature strengthens through network integration. Such modules are not often directly usable as biomarkers because of small sample size; however, we believe that our approach helps discover genes and pathways as potential multivariate biomarkers for further experiments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3) INTERACTION NETWORK</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2232</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. HyperModules requires three inputs—(1) mutated genes in patients, (2) patient clinical information and (3) protein or gene network. Search is performed for all mutated genes as seeds (4). Network visualization, clinical variable statistics and data export facilitate further analysis (5)</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> SOFTWARE HyperModules assumes that clinically informative mutations of complex disease occur in systems of closely interacting genes. The greedy network search algorithm focuses on a local network area, defined by a central seed node (a mutated gene) and its surrounding subnetwork. All mutated genes are sequentially considered as seeds in module discovery. Search starts from the seed and grows the module toward increased benefit by adding connected genes that best improve clinical significance. This objective is driven by statistical tests where patients defined by the module are compared with other patients. Categorical clinical variables are studied with Fisher&apos;s exact test and survival times with log-rank test. Cox regression is currently not supported; however, we plan to add this feature in the future. To establish statistical significance of detected modules, we build a null distribution by searching networks with permuted gene names. Each module of the true network is quantified with an empirical P-value reflecting the fraction of seed-specific modules from shuffled networks exceeding the significance of the true module. This removes artifacts of the greedy strategy and corrects for topological features such as highly connected nodes. The analysis pipeline is outlined in Figure 1. Interaction networks are loaded into Cytoscape using standard features (Shannon et al., 2003). HyperModules requires gene mutations and patient clinical information in two tables. The user selects *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research resource: interactome of human embryo implantation: identification of gene expression pathways, regulation, and integrated regulatory networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Altmae</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Endocrinol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="217" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network medicine: a network-based approach to human disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Barabasi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrated genomic analyses of ovarian carcinoma</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network. Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">474</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="609" to="615" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network-based classification of breast cancer metastasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Chuang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">140</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rare de novo variants associated with autism implicate a large functional network of genes involved in formation and function of synapses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Gilman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="898" to="907" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational approaches to identify functional genetic variants in cancer genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Gonzalez-Perez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="723" to="729" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomewide association studies and human disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Hardy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Singleton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N. Engl. J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">360</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1759" to="1768" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network-based stratification of tumor mutations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hofree</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1108" to="1115" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic analysis of somatic mutations in phosphorylation signaling predicts novel cancer drivers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Reimand</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Bader</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">637</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GraphWeb: mining heterogeneous biological networks for gene modules with functional significance</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Reimand</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="452" to="459" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mutational landscape of phosphorylation signaling in cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Reimand</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2651</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>