
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:44+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Identification of novel phosphorylation modification sites in human proteins that originated after the human–chimpanzee divergence</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">18 2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dong</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Seon</forename>
								<surname>Kim</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Biological Sciences (BK21 Program) and Research Center for Biomolecules and Biosystems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chung-Ang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>156-756</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yoonsoo</forename>
								<surname>Hahn</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Biological Sciences (BK21 Program) and Research Center for Biomolecules and Biosystems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chung-Ang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>156-756</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Biological Sciences (BK21 Program) and Research Center for Biomolecules and Biosystems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chung-Ang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>156-756</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Identification of novel phosphorylation modification sites in human proteins that originated after the human–chimpanzee divergence</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2494" to="2501"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">18 2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr426</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 16, 2011; revised on June 30, 2011; accepted on July 13, 2011</note>
					<note>[09:50 19/8/2011 Bioinformatics-btr426.tex] Page: 2494 2494–2501 Contact: hahny@cau.ac.kr Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Phosphorylation modifications of specific protein residues are involved in a wide range of biological processes such as modulation of intracellular signal networks. Here, we present the development and application of a bioinformatics procedure for systematic identification of human-specific phosphorylation sites in proteins that may have occurred after the human–chimpanzee divergence. Results: We collected annotated human phosphorylation sites and compared each site to orthologous mammalian proteins across taxa including chimpanzee, orangutan, rhesus macaque, marmoset, mouse, dog, cow, elephant, opossum and platypus. We identified 37 human-specific gains of annotated phosphorylation sites in 35 proteins: 22 serines, 12 threonines and 3 tyrosines. The novel phosphorylation sites are situated in highly conserved segments of the protein. Proteins with novel phosphorylation sites are involved in crucial biological processes such as cell division (AURKB, CASC5, MKI67 and PDCD4) and chromatin remodeling (HIRA, HIRIP3, HIST1H1T, NAP1L4 and LRWD1). Modified phosphorylatable residues produce novel target sites for protein kinases such as cyclin-dependent kinases and casein kinases, possibly resulting in rewiring and fine-tuning of phosphorylation regulatory networks. The potential human-specific phosphorylation sites identified in this study are useful as candidates for functional analysis to identify novel phenotypes in humans.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Humans have many distinct phenotypic traits compared with the other great apes, such as loss of body hair, upright posture, accelerated brain expansion and more complex cognitive abilities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Varki and Altheide, 2005</ref>). These traits must have originated as genetic modifications and undergone subsequent natural selection in the human lineage after humans diverged from their closest living relatives, the chimpanzees. The accelerated sequence substitution * To whom correspondence should be addressed. of proteins may be associated with the evolution of certain humanspecific traits: for example, genes implicated in nervous system development were found to display significantly higher rates of protein evolution in the human lineage (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Dorus et al., 2004</ref>). The FOXP2 protein, which is known to be associated with speech and language in humans, acquired two amino acid substitutions specific to humans after the human–chimpanzee divergence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Enard et al., 2002</ref>). The human FOXP2 protein has been reported to differentially regulate genes involved in central nervous system development compared with the chimpanzee ortholog (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Konopka et al., 2009</ref>). Interestingly, loss of proteins has also been implicated in the development of human-specific traits (<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Olson, 1999</ref>). For example, inactivation of the MYH16 gene in humans may be related to the reduction of the masticatory muscle and expansion of the brain (<ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Stedman et al., 2004</ref>). Other proteins that became inactive only in humans include BASE, SERPINA13 and MOXD2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hahn and</ref><ref type="bibr">Lee, 2005, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hahn et al., 2007</ref>). Phosphorylation is a fundamental post-translational modification (PTM) of proteins that acts in many important biological processes, such as cellular signaling pathways through the modulation of protein function, stability, interaction and localization (<ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Pawson and Scott, 2005</ref>). Several tens of thousands of phosphorylation modification sites have been characterized in human proteins using high-throughput proteomic analyses (<ref type="bibr">Beausoleil et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Olsen et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Oppermann et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Wang et al., 2008</ref>). Data regarding phosphorylation modification sites in human proteins are available via databases, such as UniProtKB/Swiss-Prot (<ref type="bibr">UniProt Consortium, 2010</ref>), PHOSIDA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Gnad et al., 2007</ref>) and dbPTM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Lee et al., 2006</ref>). It is likely that biologically important phosphorylation sites are evolutionarily conserved (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Malik et al., 2008</ref>).<ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Tan et al. (2009a)</ref>identified 479 phosphorylation sites in 344 human proteins that appear to be positionally conserved between human and at least one species of fly, worm or yeast and proposed that these sites are involved in fundamental cellular processes. Nevertheless, the gain and loss of protein phosphorylation sites may rewire biological networks and be regarded as a motive force for adaptive evolution (<ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Shou et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Vener, 1990</ref>). The gain or loss of phosphorylation sites in Cdk1 substrates in yeasts may have facilitated the evolution of kinase-signaling circuits (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Holt et al., 2009</ref>).<ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Tan et al. (2009b)</ref>reported that tyrosine residues have been selectively lost through metazoan evolution to remove deleterious tyrosine phosphorylations as tyrosine kinases have been expanded. It is argued that evolution<ref type="bibr">[09:50 19/8/2011 Bioinformatics-btr426.tex]</ref>Page: 2495 2494–2501</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Human-specific phosphorylation modification sites</head><p>of phosphorylation regulatory network could play a prime role in generating phenotypic changes during organismal evolution (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Moses and Landry, 2010</ref>). It has been proposed that the human-specific serine residue in the human FOXP2 protein may provide a novel phosphorylation site for protein kinase C (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Enard et al., 2002</ref>), although there is no supporting experimental evidence for this hypothesis. In this study, we hypothesize that novel phosphorylation sites in the human proteins that originated after the human–chimpanzee divergence may have been involved in the evolution of humanspecific traits through the strengthening and/or rewiring of existing protein interaction networks. To address this possibility, we developed a bioinformatics procedure to systematically identify novel human-specific phosphorylation sites. Using this procedure, we identified 37 novel phosphorylation sites that have arisen in human proteins. We also identified 31 phosphorylation sites that are conserved in humans and other mammals, but have been lost in the chimpanzee proteins.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Datasets and bioinformatics tools</head><p>To identify annotated phosphorylation modification sites in human proteins, we downloaded the human UniProtKB/Swiss-Prot records from the UniProt database (http://www.uniprot.org/). The HomoloGene database of the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/homologene) was consulted for the initial collection of RefSeq accession numbers of orthologous mammalian protein sequences for each human protein, which were then retrieved from the NCBI RefSeq database (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/RefSeq/). The data analyzed in this study were downloaded on January 4, 2011. Since the HomoloGene database includes only six mammalian species (human, chimpanzee, mouse, rat, dog and cow), we also accessed the mammalian genome assemblies available in the University of California Santa Cruz (UCSC) Genome Browser database (http://genome.ucsc.edu) to verify and predict more orthologous proteins in orangutan, rhesus macaque, marmoset and other nonprimate mammals. The genome assemblies analyzed in this study include hg19 (human), panTro2 (chimpanzee), ponAbe2 (orangutan), rheMac2 (rhesus macaque), calJac3 (marmoset), mm9 (mouse), rn4 (rat), canFam2 (dog), felCat4 (cat), bosTau4 (cow), susScr2 (pig), equCab2 (horse), loxAfr3 (elephant), monDom5 (opossum) and ornAna1 (platypus). The MUSCLE program (http://www.drive5.com/muscle/) was used to construct multiple sequence alignments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Edgar, 2004</ref>), which were then decorated using the BOXSHADE server (http://www.ch.embnet .org/software/BOX_form.html). Pairwise alignments between cDNAs and genomic sequences were performed to identify exons using the SIM4 program (http://globin.cse.psu.edu/dist/sim4/) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Florea et al., 1998</ref>). We wrote some ad hoc PERL scripts to manipulate sequences, database records and software outputs.To identify potential human-specific phosphorylation sites, we performed multiple sequence alignments for each human protein with orthologous mammalian proteins including chimpanzee proteins. We used the RefSeq accession numbers in UniProt records as keys to identify the corresponding HomoloGene datasets. The non-human RefSeq proteins for each HomoloGene dataset were extracted from the RefSeq protein database and combined with the UniProt human protein sequence to construct an orthologous protein sequence set. A total of 6425 orthologous protein sets were prepared. Multiple sequence alignments were produced using the MUSCLE program. For each aligned human phosphorylation site, when the orthologous chimpanzee sequence was not one of three phosphorylatable residues (serine, threonine or tyrosine), the position was identified as a potential human-specific phosphorylation site. A total of 90 annotated human phosphorylation sites were found to differ from the orthologous chimpanzee sequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Selection</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Manual inspection of datasets</head><p>As a final step, we manually scrutinized the 90 candidate human phosphorylation sites to identify human-specific gains or chimpanzeespecific losses of phosphorylation sites. The mammalian ortholog sequences were retrieved from the HomoloGene database, the NCBI protein sequence database or predicted from genome assemblies available through the UCSC Genome Browser database. The sequencing qualities of the chimpanzee codons corresponding to the human phosphorylated amino acid residues were examined to ensure that any sequence differences between human and chimpanzee proteins were not due to sequencing errors. When chimpanzee and orangutan sequences lacked a phosphorylatable residue at an aligned human phosphorylation site, we concluded that the human protein acquired the phosphorylation site after the human– chimpanzee divergence. When non-chimpanzee primates or other mammals exhibited the same amino acid sequence as the human phosphorylation site but the chimpanzee protein had a different sequence, we concluded that the chimpanzee protein had lost the phosphorylation site after the human– chimpanzee divergence. Of the 90 candidate sites, 37 were identified as unique to human proteins and 31 as lost in chimpanzee proteins. The remaining 22 cases were discarded due to ambiguous orthology relationship, incorrect prediction of the chimpanzee protein or low sequence quality of the orthologous chimpanzee codons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Polymorphisms among modern humans and Neanderthal alleles</head><p>To identify possible polymorphisms in the codons for human-specific phosphorylation sites, we examined human polymorphism information available via the UCSC Genome Browser database. The polymorphism data were drawn from the simple nucleotide polymorphism database (dbSNP) build 132 and personal genomes including two anonymous Yoruban Africans (UCSC track name NA19240 and NA18507), three anonymous Europeans (NA12878, NA12891 and NA12892), J. Craig Venter (Venter), James Watson (Watson), one anonymous Han Chinese (YH) and one anonymous Korean (SJK). Detailed information on the SNP data was obtained from dbSNP (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/). We also analyzed the Neanderthal sequence data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Green et al., 2010</ref>) available in the UCSC Genome Browser (the 'Neandertal Alleles in Human/Chimp Coding Non-synonymous Differences in Human Lineage' track) to examine Neanderthal alleles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Novel phosphorylation sites in human proteins</head><p>We</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.S.Kim and Y.Hahn</head><p>sites in 35 proteins that presumably originated after the human– chimpanzee divergence (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). Multiple sequence alignments of phosphorylation sites and the surrounding regions of the representative proteins are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 1</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hall et al., 2001</ref>). Eight sites were detected in more than two independent experiments. None of these 37 sites has yet been assigned a biological function. Interestingly, the regions surrounding human-specific phosphorylation sites are strongly conserved among mammalian orthologs, including those of the non-placental mammals opossum (marsupial) and platypus (monotreme). Representative proteins are ABCF1, ADNP, BAIAP2L1, HIRA, NAP1L4, NOP2, PDCD4, RUSC2, SNRPA, TARBP1, TP53BP1 and USP7 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S1</ref>). The human ABCF1 protein, for example, has a phosphorylated threonine residue at position 108, where an alanine residue is found in all other mammals including opossum and platypus. Proteins that are highly conserved across mammalian taxa or at least among primates but that have undergone accelerated amino acid substitution during human evolution are proposed to be involved in the development of adaptive human phenotypes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Clark et al., 2003</ref>). The proteins identified in this study exhibit not only human-specific amino acid changes but also novel phosphorylation sites, possibly resulting in dramatic effects on the functions of the proteins themselves, as well as those of their associated protein networks. In four cases (HIRIP3, LRWD1, PAG1 and PDXDC1 serine 737), human phosphorylation sites produce the same amino acid residues in non-primate mammals but not in other primates. The human LRWD1 protein, for example, has a phosphorylated serine at position 259, where other primates have glycines (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S1</ref>, No. 14). In contrast, some non-primate mammals including mouse, cat, horse, pig and cow exhibit a serine residue at this position. Mouse and primates belong to Euarchontoglires and cat, horse, pig and cow to Laurasiatheria. Therefore, in these cases, it is probable that phosphorylation sites were acquired in ancestral proteins before divergence of Euarchontoglires and Laurasiatheria but were lost in primate ancestors, again becoming phosphorylatable during human evolution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Notable cases of human-specific gains of phosphorylation sites</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">ABCF1</head><p>The human ABCF1 (also known as ABC50) protein, which is a member of the superfamily of ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporters, has a human-specific phosphorylated threonine residue at position 108 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1A</ref>). The ABCF1 protein was reported to interact with eukaryotic initiation factor eIF2 and promote translation initiation in mammalian cells by binding to ribosomes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Paytubi et al., 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Paytubi et al., , 2009</ref>). Serine 109 and serine 140 of the ABCF1 protein were found to be phosphorylated by casein kinase 2 (CK2), and mutations of these sites resulted in marked decreases in the association of eIF2 with ribosomes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Paytubi et al., 2008</ref>). Currently, the human ABCF1 protein has nine annotated phosphorylation sites. It is possible that modification of the human-specific phosphorylation site threonine 108 can positively or negatively affect the function of the adjacent CK2 target serine 109.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">AURKB and CASC5</head><p>The human AURKB and CASC5 proteins acquired novel phosphorylation sites serine 7 and serine 1076, respectively (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S1</ref>, Nos 3 and 7). The human AURKB protein or aurora kinase B is a serine/threonine kinase that functions in the attachment of the mitotic spindle to the centromere during cell division for accurate chromosome segregation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Lampson et al., 2004</ref>). AURKB interacts with many proteins including INCENP, BIRC5 (also known as Survivin) and NINL (also known as Nlp) and modulates their functions via phosphorylation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Honda et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Yan et al., 2010</ref>). CASC5 (also known as KNL1) has been reported to oppose AURKB activity by promoting dephosphorylation of AURKB substrates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Liu et al., 2010</ref>). Interestingly, CASC5 itself is a substrate for AURKB and is down-regulated by phosphorylation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Welburn et al., 2010</ref>). Both the AURKB and CASC5 proteins exhibit many phosphorylation targets, with 13 and 21 annotated sites, respectively. The human-specific phosphorylation of the AURKB serine 7 and CASC5 serine 1076 might result in fine adjustments in protein interaction networks and in the human cell division process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.3">HIRA, HIRIP3 and NAP1L4</head><p>The HIRA protein is an evolutionarily conserved histone chaperone that preferentially places the variant histone H3.3 in nucleosomes and that plays an important role in the formation of senescence-associated heterochromatin foci (<ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Zhang et al., 2005</ref>). The HIRIP3 protein is also a histone-binding protein (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Lorain et al., 1998</ref>). The human HIRA and HIRIP3 proteins are heavily phosphorylated, with 14 and 35 annotated sites, respectively. Interestingly, the human HIRA and HIRIP3 proteins acquired novel phosphorylation targets serine 687 and serine 300, respectively (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1B</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S1</ref>, No. 10, respectively). HIRA and HIRIP3 proteins have been reported to directly interact with each other (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Lorain et al., 1998</ref>). The humanspecific HIRA serine 687 is located in the H2B-binding region (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Lorain et al., 1998</ref>) and reported to be phosphorylated by the cyclin-dependent kinase 2 (CDK2) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hall et al., 2001</ref>). NAP1L4 is also a histone chaperone that belongs to the nucleosome assembly protein (NAP) family and can interact with both core and linker histones (<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Okuwaki et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Rodriguez et al., 1997</ref>). The human NAP1L4 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1C</ref>) has 13 phosphorylation sites with one human-specific site, serine 139. Modifications of human HIRA, HIRIP3 and NAP1L4 proteins might be implicated in chromatin-remodeling evolution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.4">LWRD1</head><p>The human LRWD1 [also known as origin recognition complex-associated (ORCA)] protein mediates the origin recognition complex (ORC) in chromatin which is critical for the initiation of pre-replication complex assembly in G1 and chromatin organization in post-G1 cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Shen et al., 2010</ref>). The human LRWD1 has seven annotated phosphorylation sites, of which the serine 259 site is human-specific. Other primates have a glycine residue at this position (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S1</ref>, No 14).Residues that were identical in ≥50% of the aligned proteins are highlighted with black backgrounds. Opossum NAP1L4 and platypus USP7 exhibit the same phosphorylatable amino acid residue as does the respective human protein, probably reflecting independent gains.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Human-specific phosphorylation modification sites</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.S.Kim and Y.Hahn</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.5">MKI67 and PDCD4</head><p>The human MKI67 (also known as Ki-67) is a nuclear protein that is associated with and may be necessary for cellular proliferation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Gerdes et al., 1991</ref>). Overexpression of MKI67 is associated with many cancers, including neuroendocrine carcinomas and colorectal cancers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Erler et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Ma et al., 2010</ref>). The human MKI67 protein, which has 124 phosphorylation sites, acquired two novel phosphorylation sites, serine 1256 and serine 3042 (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S1</ref>, Nos 15 and 16, respectively). In contrast, the PDCD4 protein is a tumor suppressor (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Göke et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Yang et al., 2006</ref>). The human PDCD4 protein acquired a novel phosphorylation site, serine 80, resulting in a total of nine phosphorylation sites. All other mammals that have been studied, including opossum and platypus, have an asparagine residue at this site (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1D</ref>). The mammalian PDCD4 proteins show strong sequence conservation, indicating that they play important roles in mammalian biology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.6">SNRPA and TARBP1</head><p>The SNRPA protein (also known as U1A) is associated with stem/loop 2 of the U1 small nuclear RNA (snRNA) and forms the spliceosomal U1 small nuclear ribonucleoprotein (snRNP), which is required for mRNA splicing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Law et al., 2006</ref>). The SNRPA proteins are highly conserved in mammals, and the human SNRPA has a single novel phosphorylation site, threonine 131 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1E</ref>). TARBP1 is also an RNA binding protein that was initially identified as a binding protein of the human immunodeficiency virus-1 (HIV-1) trans-activation-responsive (TAR) RNA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Sheline et al., 1991</ref>). TARBP1 binds directly to DICER1 and loads small interfering RNA into the RNA-induced silencing complex (RISC) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">MacRae et al., 2008</ref>). The human TARBP1 protein also acquired a single novel phosphorylation site, serine 1442. These modifications may alter RNA biology in humans.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Page: 2499 2494–2501</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Human-specific phosphorylation modification sites</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.7">USP7 and USP36</head><p>The USP7 and USP36 proteins are cysteine proteases that function as deubiquitinating enzymes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">de Bie et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Endo et al., 2009</ref>). Protein ubiquitination is one of the fundamental regulatory PTMs that control intracellular protein signal networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Komander, 2009</ref>). The human USP7 and USP36 proteins acquired human-specific phosphorylation sites, threonine 54 and tyrosine 874, respectively (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1F</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S1</ref>, No 36, respectively). It is notable that the threonine 54 of the USP7 protein is embedded in a strongly conserved region. The newly acquired phosphorylatable residues of these deubiquitinating enzymes may provide novel regulatory phosphorylation targets in human cells.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Polymorphisms among modern humans and Neanderthal alleles</head><p>Human polymorphism data drawn from the UCSC Genome Browser database were examined to identify possible amino acid-altering polymorphisms in codons encoding phosphorylated residues. We found non-synonymous SNPs at the phosphorylation sites in C1orf131 and NOP2 proteins. The first base of the codon for the C1orf131 protein position 163 shows an A/G polymorphism (dbSNP accession number rs115635619). The allelic codons are ACA and GCA, encoding threonine and alanine, respectively. Interestingly, the corresponding chimpanzee codon is ATA, encoding isoleucine which is common in other primates, indicating that the both ACA (threonine) and GCA (alanine) are derived alleles. The frequency data available in dbSNP show that the ACA (threonine) allele frequency is 98.3% in Africans, indicating that the phosphorylatable allele is prevalent. The second base of the codon for the NOP2 protein position 140 exhibits a C/T polymorphism (rs35556146). The codon variants are ACG and ATG, encoding threonine (derived) and methionine (ancestral), respectively. The derived phosphorylatable allele is prevalent in modern humans: 92.5% in Africans and 100% in both Europeans and Asians. In a modern human-Neanderthal genome comparison, we have found that 20 derived sites are shared with Neanderthal DNA, indicating that the acquisition of these phosphorylatable residues occurred before the divergence of modern humans and Neanderthals. No information is available for the rest of the cases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Losses of phosphorylation sites in chimpanzee proteins</head><p>When annotated human phosphorylation sites are shared with other primates and mammals, but different non-phosphorylatable residues are found in chimpanzees compared with those in the other animals, we conclude that the phosphorylation site was lost in chimpanzees after the human–chimpanzee divergence. By applying this condition, we identified 31 chimpanzee proteins with losses of annotated phosphorylation sites (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). Multiple sequence alignments surrounding the mutated sites are shown in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S2</ref>. In most cases, the annotated phosphorylation sites are conserved across mammals except in the chimpanzee, implying that phosphorylation at the corresponding position was acquired early in mammalian evolution. For example, the human ASPM protein residue number 1103 is serine, which is conserved across mammals including opossum and platypus (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>, No. 2). However, the chimpanzee protein has a cysteine residue at the corresponding position. The original phosphorylated amino acid sequences lost in chimpanzee proteins include 20 serines, 10 threonines and 1 tyrosine.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>We identified 37 cases of novel phosphorylation site gains in 35 human proteins that likely arose after the human–chimpanzee divergence. Human proteins with novel phosphorylation modification sites are involved in various biological processes: for example, AURKB, CASC5, MKI67, PDCD4 in the cell cycle; HIRA, HIRIP3, HIST1H1T, NAP1L4 and LRWD1 are involved in chromatin remodeling; SNRPA and TARBP1 are involved in RNA biology; and USP7 and USP36 are involved in protein deubiquitination. The number of novel phosphorylation sites in human proteins and the number of lost sites in chimpanzee proteins are very similar, 37 versus 31, indicating that gain and loss events occurred at comparable rates in both taxa. The distributions of changed residues are also similar. The amino acid residues of the 37 novel human phosphorylation sites include 22 serines, 12 threonines and 3 tyrosines. In chimpanzee proteins, 20 serines, 10 threonines and 1 tyrosine have been mutated to non-phosphorylatable residues. The conversion to or from serine is more frequent than other conversions. This difference may be explained in terms of the numbers of codons in the genetic code. There are six codons for serine, four for threonine and two for tyrosine. If a mutation is completely random, it is likely that the serine codon will appear more often than will threonine or tyrosine. The distribution of the lost phosphorylatable residues may simply be due to the frequencies of the phosphorylated residues in the proteome. The human protein dataset analyzed in this study contains 23 977 phosphoserines, 5610 phosphothreonines and 3163 phosphotyrosines. Because phosphoserine is more common than phosphothreonine or phosphotyrosine, it is expected that phosphoserine is lost more often at similar mutation rates. However, we cannot rule out the possibility that there could be evolutionary constraints regarding the gain or loss of phosphorylation sites. It is possible that the relatively small number of gain or loss of phosphotyrosine sites reflects the fact that phosphotyrosine sites are involved in more biologically important processes than are phosphothreonine or phosphoserine sites. It has been proposed that, as tyrosine kinases have been expanded during metazoan evolution, tyrosine residues have been selectively removed to minimize possibly deleterious tyrosine phosphorylations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Tan et al., 2009b</ref>). The casein kinase 1 (CK1) family of protein kinases functions as signal transduction pathway regulators in eukaryotic cells and recognizes the motif S-X-X-S/T* (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Gnad et al., 2007</ref>). The three novel phosphorylation sites of ABCF1, MKI67 (serine 1256) and TARBP1 match the CK1 motif. CK2 has been implicated in several cellular processes including cell-cycle control and DNA repair, and it recognizes the motif S/T*-X-X-E, where E is aspartic acid (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Gnad et al., 2007</ref>). There are six human-specific phosphorylation sites (ABCF1, ADNP, PDXDC1 serine 737 and serine 779, RUSC2 and USP7) that match the CK2 motif. We assume that the advent of new target sites for the various kinases in these proteins may result in evolution of protein regulatory networks. There are four CK1 sites</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>examined 32 750 annotated phosphorylation modification sites in 6950 human proteins to identify 37 human-specific phosphorylation Page: 2496 2494–2501</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>. Alignments for all of the cases are shown in Supplementary Figure S1. Two proteins, MKI67 and PDXDC1, each acquired two novel phosphorylation sites, while the remaining 33 proteins acquired one site each. The amino acid residues of the novel phosphorylation sites in human proteins include 22 serines, 12 threonines and 3 tyrosines. Among 37 annotated phosphorylation sites, 36 were experimentally identified either by large-scale analyses using mass spectrometry (35 sites) or by conventional molecular biology method (HIRA serine 687) (</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>[09:50 19/8/2011 Bioinformatics-btr426.tex] Page: 2497 2494–2501</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Multiple sequence alignments of representative cases of human-specific gains of phosphorylation sites. The human-specific phosphorylation sites (*), shared sites (+) and the surrounding regions (20 aligned positions on both sides) for each case are presented. Residues that were identical in ≥50% of the aligned proteins are highlighted with black backgrounds. Opossum NAP1L4 and platypus USP7 exhibit the same phosphorylatable amino acid residue as does the respective human protein, probably reflecting independent gains.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1. Gains of phosphorylation modification sites in the human proteins that were identified in this study 2006; Wang et al., 2008; Daub et al., 2008; Dephoure et al., 2008; Mayya et al., 2009</figDesc><table>No Gene 
UniProt 
Position Amino acid a 
Human RefSeq Refs. b 
Title 

1 
ABCF1 
ABCF1_HUMAN 108 
T ? A A A A NM_001025091 Beausoleil et al., 2004; Kim et al., 
2005; Olsen et al., 2006; Imami 
et al., 2008; Dephoure et al., 
2008; Gauci et al., 2009; Mayya 
et al., 2009 

ATP-binding cassette, sub-family F 

2 
ADNP 
ADNP_HUMAN 
921 
S S L L L L NM_015339 
Gauci et al., 2009 
Activity-dependent neuroprotector 
homeobox 
3 
AURKB 
AURKB_HUMAN 7 
S ? A A A A NM_004217 
Nousiainen et al., 2006; Wang 
et al., 2008; Daub et al., 2008 

Aurora kinase B 

4 
BAIAP2L1 BI2L1_HUMAN 
416 
T T A A A A NM_018842 
Gauci et al., 2009 
BAI1-associated protein 2-like 1 
5 
C1orf131 
CA131_HUMAN 
163 
T ? I I I I NM_152379 
Matsuoka et al., 2007 
Chromosome 1 open reading frame 131 
6 
C14orf50 
CN050_HUMAN 
392 
Y Y H H H H NM_172365 
Molina et al., 2007 
Chromosome 14 open reading frame 50 
7 
CASC5 
CASC5_HUMAN 1076 
S S N N N N NM_170589 
Nousiainen et al., Cancer susceptibility candidate 5 

8 
FASN 
FAS_HUMAN 
2198 
S S N N N S NM_004104 
Dephoure et al., 2008 
Fatty acid synthase 
9 
HIRA 
HIRA_HUMAN 
687 
S S G G G G NM_003325 
Hall et al., 2001 
HIR histone cell–cycle regulation 
defective homolog A (S.cerevisiae) 
10 HIRIP3 
HIRP3_HUMAN 
300 
S S G G G G NM_003609 
Molina et al., 2007 
HIRA interacting protein 3 
11 HIST1H1T H1T_HUMAN 
160 
T S A A A V NM_005323 
Olsen et al., 2006 
Histone cluster 1, H1t 
12 KRT8 
K2C8_HUMAN 
438 
S ? G G G G NM_002273 
Wang et al., 2008 
Keratin 8 
13 LDHA 
LDHA_HUMAN 
10 
Y ? H H H H NM_005566 
Mayya et al., 2009 
Lactate dehydrogenase A 
14 LRWD1 
LRWD1_HUMAN 259 
S S G G G G NM_152892 
Cantin et al., 2008; Dephoure 
et al., 2008; Gauci et al., 2009; 
Mayya et al., 2009 

Leucine-rich repeats and WD repeat 
domain containing 1 

15 MKI67 
KI67_HUMAN 
1256 
S S P P P P NM_002417 
Dephoure et al., 2008 
Antigen identified by monoclonal 
antibody Ki-67 
16 MKI67 
KI67_HUMAN 
3042 
S ? P P P P NM_002417 
Wang et al., 2008 
Antigen identified by monoclonal 
antibody Ki-67 
17 NAP1L4 
NP1L4_HUMAN 
139 
S S N N N N NM_005969 
Molina et al., 2007 
NAP 1-like 4 
18 NOP2 
NOP2_HUMAN 
140 
T T M M M M NM_001033714 Olsen et al., 2006 
NOP2 nucleolar protein homolog 
(yeast) 
19 PAG1 
PAG1_HUMAN 
380 
S ? G G G G NM_018440 
Phosphoprotein associated with 
glycosphingolipid microdomains 1 
20 PDCD4 
PDCD4_HUMAN 80 
S S N N N N NM_014456 
Dephoure et al., 2008 
Programmed cell death 4 (neoplastic 
transformation inhibitor) 
21 PDXDC1 
PDXD1_HUMAN 737 
S ? G G G G NM_015027 
Olsen et al., 2006 
Pyridoxal-dependent decarboxylase 
domain containing 1 
22 PDXDC1 
PDXD1_HUMAN 779 
S S P P P P NM_015027 
Olsen et al., 2006; Matsuoka et al., 
2007 

Pyridoxal-dependent decarboxylase 
domain containing 1 
23 RCSD1 
CPZIP_HUMAN 
284 
S ? P A A A NM_052862 
Mayya et al., 2009 
RCSD domain containing 1 
24 RIF1 
RIF1_HUMAN 
1148 
S S A A A T NM_018151 
Gauci et al., 2009 
RAP1 interacting factor homolog 
(yeast) 
25 RREB1 
RREB1_HUMAN 1315 
T ? K E K K NM_001003698 Dephoure et al., 2008 
ras responsive element binding 
protein 1 
26 RRP8 
RRP8_HUMAN 
223 
S ? P P P P NM_015324 
Beausoleil et al., 2006; Dephoure 
et al., 2008 

Ribosomal RNA processing 8, 
methyltransferase, homolog (yeast) 
27 RUSC2 
RUSC2_HUMAN 1368 
S ? P P P P NM_001135999 Dephoure et al., 2008 
RUN and SH3 domain containing 2 
28 SNRPA 
SNRPA_HUMAN 131 
T ? A A A A NM_004596 
Dephoure et al., 2008 
snRNP polypeptide A 
29 SVIL 
SVIL_HUMAN 
270 
S S P P S P NM_021738 
Zahedi et al., 2008; Cantin et al., 
2008 

Supervillin 

30 TARBP1 
TARB1_HUMAN 1442 
S S P P P P NM_005646 
Daub et al., 2008 
TAR (HIV-1) RNA binding protein 1 
31 TCOF1 
TCOF_HUMAN 
581 
T T A A A A NM_001135243 Dephoure et al., 2008 
Treacher Collins-Franceschetti 
syndrome 1 
32 TERF1 
TERF1_HUMAN 434 
S S C C C C NM_017489 
Dephoure et al., 2008 
Telomeric repeat binding factor 
(NIMA-interacting) 1 
33 TJP2 
ZO2_HUMAN 
1131 
T ? P L L L NM_004817 
Molina et al., 2007, Dephoure 
et al., 2008 

Tight junction protein 2 (zona 
occludens 2) 
34 TP53BP1 
TP53B_HUMAN 
394 
T ? M M M M NM_005657 
Gauci et al., 2009 
Tumor protein p53 binding protein 1 
35 USP7 
UBP7_HUMAN 
54 
T ? N N N N NM_003470 
Mayya et al., 2009 
Ubiquitin-specific peptidase 7 (herpes 
virus-associated) 
36 USP36 
UBP36_HUMAN 874 
Y Y H H H H NM_025090 
Olsen et al., 2006 
Ubiquitin-specific peptidase 36 
37 ZNF638 
ZN638_HUMAN 
809 
T ? A A A A NM_014497 
Oppermann et al., 2009 
Zinc finger protein 638 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">a Amino acid sequences of primate species: human, Neanderthal, chimpanzee, orangutan, rhesus macaque and marmoset. ?, unknown. b References to experimental evidence of phosphorylation.</note>

			<note place="foot">RAD52, TP53BP1, WDR62 and WRAP53) match the strong and weak consensus sequences, respectively. The similar rate of phosphorylation site gain in humans and loss in chimpanzees is consistent with the previous report that CDK consensus sites in clusters turn over rapidly (Moses et al., 2007). When we examined surrounding regions of the phosphorylation sites, either gained in humans or lost in chimpanzees, we found at least one additional phosphorylation site within a 20-residue distance in 26 human-specific gains and in 21 chimpanzee-specific losses. And hence, in about two-thirds of the cases, gain or loss of phosphorylation site occurred in clusters. Nevertheless, gain of novel phosphorylation sites may drive regulatory evolution as demonstrated that acquisition of CDK consensus sites in a replication protein Mcm3 is associated with the evolution of CDK-mediated shuttling of mini-chromosome maintenance complex in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (Moses et al., 2007). The UniProt database annotation records include phosphorylation sites of non-human proteins. In a parallel study, we surveyed sites to identify human-specific loss of ancestral phosphorylation sites. We retrieved data for 21 374 phosphorylation sites (14 328 serines, 3714 threonines and 3332 tyrosines) in 5618 non-human proteins. However, we were unable to identify any instances of human-specific loss, probably because most of the annotated phosphorylation sites in non-human proteins available in the UniProt database were not determined in independent experiments, but were deduced based on sequence similarities to human protein phosphorylation data. Use of high-throughput analysis data for non-human mammals, such as recently reported phosphorylation data for mouse tissues (Huttlin et al., 2010), may enable us to collect human-specific loss of phosphorylation sites in the future. We also encountered limitations of the HomoloGene and RefSeq databases. We found that many of the predicted chimpanzee protein sequences in the RefSeq database are not complete or are not accurate, possibly due to the draft quality of the current chimpanzee assembly (Taudien et al., 2006). If high-quality chimpanzee protein sequences are eventually obtained, we may be able to identify more instances of gain and loss of phosphorylation sites and other PTM sites. The procedure presented in this study may be applied to other PTM sites such as N-glycosylation, O-glycosylation, acetylation, methylation, SUMOylation, ubiquitination, glycosylphosphatidylinositol anchoring and proteolytic cleavage sites. We are currently researching these modifications. Recent advancements in large-scale analyses of the human proteomes have greatly increased the amount of PTM data that is available (Gnad et al., 2007; Lee et al., 2006). Through the analysis of these large datasets, our knowledge of the evolution of PTM sites and associated protein networks will be greatly expanded. In conclusion, we identified 37 novel phosphorylation sites in human proteins that arose after the human–chimpanzee divergence. We propose that functional study of these humanspecific phosphorylation candidates may explain the molecular mechanism of some human-specific phenotypes.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">09</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>btr426. .tex]</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NEK1 and PLEKHG3) and three CK2 sites (BSN, CENPF and PRR11) that are lost in chimpanzee proteins. The CDKs recognize the consensus sequence is the phosphorylated serine or threonine, P is proline, X is any amino acid, K is lysine and R is arginine They also weakly recognize the sequence Among 37 novel human-specific phosphorylation sites, two cases (BAIAP2L1 and HIRA) match the strong consensus and 12 cases Large-scale characterization of HeLa cell nuclear phosphoproteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Pagekim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S / T *-P-X-K / R</forename>
				<surname>Hahn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S / T *</forename>
				<surname>Moses</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">and TJP2) match the weak consensus. Similarly, out of 31 sites lost in chimpanzee, two (GBF1 and MELK) and 10 cases Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<editor>Beausoleil,S.A. et al.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>C17orf56, EIF4G1 ; BAIAP2L1, CASC5, HIRA, HIST1H1T, LRWD1, RCSD1, RRP8, RUSC2, SNRPA, SVIL ; C17orf56, CCNO, COPB2, EIF4G1, EPN1, MEK1, REFERENCES</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2500" to="2494" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A probability-based approach for high-throughput protein phosphorylation analysis and site localization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Beausoleil</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1285" to="1292" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combining protein-based IMAC, peptide-based IMAC, and MudPIT for efficient phosphoproteomic analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Cantin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1346" to="1351" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inferring nonneutral evolution from human-chimp-mouse orthologous gene trios</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Clark</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">302</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1960" to="1963" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinase-selective enrichment enables quantitative phosphoproteomics of the kinome across the cell cycle</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Daub</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="438" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulation of the Polycomb protein RING1B ubiquitination by USP7</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>De Bie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">400</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="395" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A quantitative atlas of mitotic phosphorylation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Dephoure</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10762" to="10767" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accelerated evolution of nervous system genes in the origin of Homo sapiens</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Dorus</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1027" to="1040" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Edgar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1792" to="1797" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular evolution of FOXP2, a gene involved in speech and language</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Enard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">418</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="869" to="872" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nucleophosmin/B23 regulates ubiquitin dynamics in nucleoli by recruiting deubiquitylating enzyme USP36</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Endo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27918" to="27923" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CD117, Ki-67, and p53 predict survival in neuroendocrine carcinomas, but not within the subgroup of small cell lung carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Erler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tumour Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A computer program for aligning a cDNA sequence with a genomic DNA sequence</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Florea</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="967" to="974" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lys-N and trypsin cover complementary parts of the phosphoproteome in a refined SCX-based approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Gauci</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4493" to="4501" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunobiochemical and molecular biologic characterization of the cell proliferation-associated nuclear antigen that is defined by monoclonal antibody Ki-67</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Gerdes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Pathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="867" to="873" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Programmed cell death protein 4 (PDCD4) acts as a tumor suppressor in neuroendocrine tumor cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Göke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. NY Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1014</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="220" to="221" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PHOSIDA (phosphorylation site database): management, structural and evolutionary investigation, and prediction of phosphosites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Gnad</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">250</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A draft sequence of the Neandertal genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Green</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">328</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="710" to="722" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of nine human-specific frameshift mutations by comparative analysis of the human and the chimpanzee genome sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Hahn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="194" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human-specific nonsense mutations identified by genome sequence comparisons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Hahn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inactivation of MOXD2 and S100A15A by exon deletion during human evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Hahn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2203" to="2212" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HIRA, the human homologue of yeast Hir1p and Hir2p, is a novel cyclin-cdk2 substrate whose expression blocks S-phase progression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Hall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1854" to="1865" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global analysis of Cdk1 substrate phosphorylation sites provides insights into evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Holt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">325</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1682" to="1686" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the functional interactions between Aurora B, INCENP, and survivin in mitosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Honda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3325" to="3341" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">098</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2501" to="2494" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human-specific phosphorylation modification sites</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A tissue-specific atlas of mouse protein phosphorylation and expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Huttlin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1174" to="1189" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automated phosphoproteome analysis for cultured cancer cells by two-dimensional nanoLC-MS using a calcined titania/C18 biphasic column</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Imami</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global phosphoproteome of HT-29 human colon adenocarcinoma cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1339" to="1346" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The emerging complexity of protein ubiquitination</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Komander</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. Soc. Trans</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="937" to="953" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human-specific transcriptional regulation of CNS development genes by FOXP2</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Konopka</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">462</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="217" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correcting improper chromosome-spindle attachments during cell division</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Lampson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of RNA structure in the interaction of U1A protein with U1 hairpin II RNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Law</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RNA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1168" to="1178" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">dbPTM: an information repository of protein post-translational modification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="622" to="627" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulated targeting of protein phosphatase 1 to the outer kinetochore by KNL1 opposes Aurora B kinase</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">188</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="809" to="820" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Core histones and HIRIP3, a novel histone-binding protein, directly interact with WD repeat protein HIRA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Lorain</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5546" to="5556" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunohistochemical analysis revealed CD34 and Ki67 protein expression as significant prognostic factors in colorectal cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Ma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med. Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="304" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vitro reconstitution of the human RISC-loading complex</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Macrae</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="512" to="517" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative conservation analysis of the human mitotic phosphoproteome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Malik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1426" to="1432" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ATM and ATR substrate analysis reveals extensive protein networks responsive to DNA damage</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Matsuoka</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">316</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1160" to="1166" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative phosphoproteomic analysis of T cell receptor signaling reveals system-wide modulation of protein-protein interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Mayya</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Signal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">46</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global proteomic profiling of phosphopeptides using electron transfer dissociation tandem mass spectrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Molina</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2199" to="2204" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moving from transcriptional to phosphoevolution: generalizing regulatory evolution?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Moses</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Landry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="467" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulatory evolution in proteins by turnover and lineagespecific changes of cyclin-dependent kinase consensus sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Moses</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17713" to="17718" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phosphoproteome analysis of the human mitotic spindle</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nousiainen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5391" to="5396" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional characterization of human nucleosome assembly protein 1-like proteins as histone chaperones</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Okuwaki</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Cells</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global, in vivo, and site-specific phosphorylation dynamics in signaling networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Olsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="635" to="648" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When less is more: gene loss as an engine of evolutionary change</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Olson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale proteomics analysis of the human kinome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Oppermann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1751" to="1764" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein phosphorylation in signaling–50 years and counting</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Pawson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Scott</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Biochem. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="286" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The N-terminal region of ABC50 interacts with eukaryotic initiation factor eIF2 and is a target for regulatory phosphorylation by CK2</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Paytubi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">409</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="231" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ABC50 promotes translation initiation in mammalian cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Paytubi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24061" to="24073" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional characterization of human nucleosome assembly protein-2 (NAP1L4) suggests a role as a histone chaperone</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Rodriguez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two distinct nuclear transcription factors recognize loop and bulge residues of the HIV-1 TAR RNA hairpin</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Sheline</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2508" to="2520" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A WD-repeat protein stabilizes ORC binding to chromatin</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Shen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring the evolutionary rewiring of biological networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Shou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1001050</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myosin gene mutation correlates with anatomical changes in the human lineage</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Stedman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">428</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="415" to="418" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative analysis reveals conserved protein phosphorylation networks implicated in multiple diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Tan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Signal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">39</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positive selection of tyrosine loss in metazoan evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Tan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">325</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1686" to="1688" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Should the draft chimpanzee sequence be finished?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Taudien</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="125" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Universal Protein Resource (UniProt) in 2010</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparing the human and chimpanzee genomes: searching for needles in a haystack</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Varki</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Altheide</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1746" to="1758" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein phosphorylation: a motive force for adaptive evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Vener</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biosystems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of the low-specificity protease elastase for large-scale phosphoproteome analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9526" to="9533" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aurora B phosphorylates spatially distinct targets to differentially regulate the kinetochore-microtubule interface</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Welburn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="383" to="392" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aurora B interaction of centrosomal Nlp regulates cytokinesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Yan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">285</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40230" to="40239" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tumorigenesis suppressor Pdcd4 down-regulates mitogenactivated protein kinase kinase kinase kinase 1 expression to suppress colon carcinoma cell invasion</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1297" to="1306" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phosphoproteome of resting human platelets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Zahedi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="526" to="534" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Formation of MacroH2A-containing senescence-associated heterochromatin foci and senescence driven by ASF1a and HIRA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>