
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:30+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics iFUSE: integrated fusion gene explorer</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Saskia</forename>
								<surname>Hiltemann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Urology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Mcclellan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jos</forename>
								<surname>Van Nijnatten</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sebastiaan</forename>
								<surname>Horsman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ivo</forename>
								<surname>Palli</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ines</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Teles</forename>
								<surname>Alves</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Urology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Erasmus MC</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3015 GE</postCode>
									<settlement>Rotterdam</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
								<surname>Hartjes</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Urology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jan</forename>
								<surname>Trapman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Erasmus MC</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3015 GE</postCode>
									<settlement>Rotterdam</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Peter</forename>
								<surname>Van Der Spek</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Guido</forename>
								<surname>Jenster</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Urology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andrew</forename>
								<surname>Stubbs</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics iFUSE: integrated fusion gene explorer</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1700" to="1701"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt252</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on January 7, 2013; revised on April 15, 2013; accepted on May 1, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Martin Bishop</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present iFUSE (integrated fusion gene explorer), an online visualization tool that provides a fast and informative view of structural variation data and prioritizes those breaks likely representing fusion genes. This application uses calculated break points to determine fusion genes based on the latest annotation for genomic sequence information, and where relevant the structural variation (SV) events are annotated with predicted RNA and protein sequences. iFUSE takes as input a Complete Genomics (CG) junction file, a FusionMap fusion detection report file or a file already analysed and annotated by the iFUSE application on a previous occasion. Results: We demonstrate the use of iFUSE with case studies from tumour-normal SV detection derived from Complete Genomics whole-genome sequencing results. Availability: iFUSE is available as a web service at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Structural variation analysis is a common requirement in the study of cancer where many fusion genes have been implicated in the progression of cancer (<ref type="bibr">Kumar-Sinha et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mitelman et al., 2007</ref>). The use of next-generation sequencing for fusion gene detection in cancer (<ref type="bibr">Edgren et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ge et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">McPherson et al., 2011</ref>), structural variation in non-cancerous diseases (<ref type="bibr">Levy et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sanders et al., 2011</ref>) and in normal genomes (The 1000 Genomes Project Consortium, 2010) has expanded knowledge of the importance of these events. In a recent study, the use of de novo assembly in association with SV detection suggests that SVs account for more diversity between individuals than do single-nucleotide polymorphisms (<ref type="bibr">Li et al., 2011</ref>). Complete Genomics uses de novo assembly during SV, single-nucleotide variation and copy number variation determination (<ref type="bibr">Carnevali et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Drmanac et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Reumers et al., 2011</ref>). Traditionally, for a given SV, a user can visualize the individual (sides of the) breaks in viewers, such as IGV (<ref type="bibr">Robinson et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Thorvaldsdo´ttirThorvaldsdo´ttir et al., 2012</ref>), but not the resulting event or fusion gene as a whole, and must manually retrieve the sequence of the resulting event based on the exons from both genes of the proposed fusion gene and determine the orientation and frame of the predicted transcript and encoded polypeptide sequences. Other applications also offer visualization, but with the caveat that the user must process their data within the application, e.g. inGAP-SV (<ref type="bibr">Qi et al., 2011</ref>), or that a bioinformatician is required to render the visualization using, e.g. Circos (<ref type="bibr">Krzywinski et al., 2009</ref>). Our aim is to deliver a web-based application that allows scientists to visualize all detected SV events and fusion genes determined in their results and to provide the concomitant candidate transcripts and polypeptide sequences associated with the detected fusion genes (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). No other application exists at the moment to categorize and visualize the candidate fusion genes and to determine the proposed sequence for gDNA, RNA and polypeptides from standard SV files.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>iFUSE is a PHP-coded application running on an Apache web server with a mySQL database for user management and R for data analysis. Gene-based feature annotation is provided using the UCSC gene tables (hg18 and hg19). Documentation details, including full application configuration, are available from the website (http://ifuse.erasmusmc.nl). iFUSE takes as input either a Complete Genomics (CG) junctions file or a fusion detection report as generated by the FusionMap tool (<ref type="bibr">Ge et al., 2011</ref>). To perform a comparison of two or more genomes, the Complete Genomics tool Junctions2Events can be used before visualization within iFUSE. The input file is validated and then analysed using R, after which a graphical representation for each event is generated. This representation displays the promotor, introns, exons and the junction site, and additional information, including DNA, RNA and protein sequences, is presented to the user. These events can be filtered and sorted by the user, either using general properties or by zooming in on a single event and filtering for nearby junctions or events with similar properties. The input files uploaded to iFUSE are annotated in R using information retrieved from UCSC gene tables and the input files. The resulting output file can be retrieved from iFUSE for manual inspection and can also be used directly as input to iFUSE. Example input files can be downloaded from the downloads section of the iFUSE website, and users can test the application without registration by selecting the option to start an anonymous session. Any files uploaded by the user will be deleted at the end of the anonymous session. iFUSE accounts are password protected, the application has been tested for security risks, such as SQL injections, and our servers undergo periodical CERT vulnerability scans (http://www.cert.org). Furthermore, *To whom correspondence should be addressed. when a user deletes a file via the iFUSE web interface, it is purged completely from our systems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DISCUSSION</head><p>Two public cancer genomes have been used to demonstrate the use of iFUSE for the prediction of fusion genes. Genomes were downloaded from Complete Genomics (ftp2.completegenomics. com). The results can be found in<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>. An event is labelled as a fusion gene if the break point has two different genes on either side. If the two sides also have the same orientation (are on the same strand, or in the case of an inversion on opposite strands) and are also in frame, the event is called a fusion protein.</p></div>
			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> CONCLUSION iFUSE provides scientists with a convenient method to visualize, categorize and filter structural variation analysis output using Complete Genomics junction files or the FusionMap fusion detection report files as input to the application.</note>

			<note place="foot">Note: Sample 1 (S1): HCC1187, Sample 2 (S2): HCC2218, public datasets downloadable from Complete Genomics. (ftp://ftp2.completegenomics.com/Cancer_ pairs/)</note>

			<note place="foot">iFUSE at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>