
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:46+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">IgSimulator: a versatile immunosequencing simulator</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yana</forename>
								<surname>Safonova</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Center of Algorithmic biotechnology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Translational Biomedicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">St. Petersburg State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Russia</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Algorithmic Biology Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">St. Petersburg Academic University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>St. Petersburg</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alla</forename>
								<surname>Lapidus</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Center of Algorithmic biotechnology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Translational Biomedicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">St. Petersburg State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Russia</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Algorithmic Biology Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">St. Petersburg Academic University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>St. Petersburg</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jennie</forename>
								<surname>Lill</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Protein Chemistry</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 DNA Way, South San Francisco</addrLine>
									<postCode>94080</postCode>
									<settlement>Genentech</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">IgSimulator: a versatile immunosequencing simulator</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv326</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 11, 2014; revised on May 18, 2015; accepted on May 19, 2015</note>
					<note>Sequence analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: John Hancock Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The recent introduction of next-generation sequencing technologies to antibody studies have resulted in a growing number of immunoinformatics tools for antibody repertoire analysis. However, benchmarking these newly emerging tools remains problematic since the gold standard datasets that are needed to validate these tools are typically not available. Results: Since simulating antibody repertoires is often the only feasible way to benchmark new immunoinformatics tools, we developed the IgSimulator tool that addresses various complications in generating realistic antibody repertoires. IgSimulator&apos;s code has modular structure and can be easily adapted to new requirements to simulation. Availability and implementation: IgSimulator is open source and freely available as a Cþþ and Python program running on all Unix-compatible platforms. The source code is available from</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The recent introduction of next-generation sequencing (NGS) technologies to antibody studies have resulted in a growing number of immunoinformatics tools for antibody repertoire analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Boyd et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Weinstein et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Shugay et al., 2014</ref>). However, benchmarking these newly emerging tools remains problematic since the gold standard datasets that are needed to validate these tools are typically not available. Since simulating antibody repertoires is often the only feasible way to benchmark new immunoinformatics tools, many immunoinformatics groups have developed their own antibody repertoire simulators of various complexity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bonissone and Pevzner, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Weinstein et al., 2009</ref>). Lack of a publicly available immunoinformatics simulator makes it difficult to benchmark multiple antibody analysis tools and forces every new immunoinformatics researcher to invest efforts into development of a yet another simulator. We argue that the time has come to develop a comprehensive publicly available immunoinformatics simulator, similar to the widely used ART (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Huang et al., 2012</ref>) read simulator for NGS studies. Developing an immunoinformatics simulator is a more complex task than developing ART since it should reflect a complex process of forming antibody repertoires in a realistic statistical setting. These complications are further amplified by the fact that similar but distinct antibodies within a repertoire often differ from each other by only a small number of mutations, thus, making it difficult to distinguish them from sequencing errors. Moreover, antibody repertoires often feature a few large clusters (occurring as a result of in vivo clonal selection) accompanied by a large number of smaller clusters, presenting a challenge for the repertoire analysis algorithms that attempt to separate small clusters from often similar large clusters. Below we describe the IgSimulator tool that addresses various complications in generating realistic antibody repertoires. IgSimulator simulates repertoires and uses ART to simulate reads resulting from this repertoire.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Simulating individual antibodies</head><p>Antibody repertoires are generated by complex processes: V(D)J recombination, intergenic insertions and somatic hypermutations. IgSimulator models all these processes and generates repertoires based on the following features (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Murphy, 2012</ref>). Distribution of the clone frequencies contains few overrepresented clones and plenty of low abundant clones. The lengths of exonuclease removals do not exceed 10 nt and are distributed uniformly. The lengths of N nucleotides, or non-genomic intergenic insertions, do not exceed 10 nt and are distributed uniformly. The lengths of P nucleotides, or inverted palindromic intergenic insertions, do not exceed 4 nt and are distributed uniformly. Frequencies of SHM in CDRs (per nucleotide) are higher than frequencies of SHM in FRs. SHMs are generated as a mix of motif based (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Rogozin and Kolchanov, 1992</ref>) and random changes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Simulating antibody repertoires</head><p>The repertoire simulation proceeds in the following five steps illustrated in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. IgSimulator generates a set of the base antibody sequences using simulation of the V(D)J recombination mechanisms, somatic deletions of start and end of the gene segments and insertions of the non-genomic P and N nucleotides (step 1 in<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). By default, IgSimulator uses the IMGT database of human Ig germline genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Brochet et al., 2008</ref>; user can provide different set of germline genes if necessary) and selects among equally likely V/D/J gene segments candidates to simulate the V(D)J recombination. IgSimulator randomly assigns the frequency to each base antibody sequence using the power law distribution (step 2 in<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). Evidence of this distribution was shown recently (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Weinstein et al., 2009</ref>). IgSimulator introduces the somatic mutations into each base antibody sequences resulting in mutated antibody sequences (step 3 in<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). To generate an antibody repertoire, IgSimulator randomly assigns the frequency to each mutated antibody sequence using the power law distribution (step 4 in<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). The frequencies represent the number of times each mutated antibody sequence will be present in the antibody repertoire. The resulting antibody repertoire is further subjected to an NGS read simulation using ART (step 5 on<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). To configure the diversity rate, IgSimulator uses the following parameters: # base sequences, # mutated sequences and repertoire size. A small difference between # mutated sequences and # base sequences leads to simulation of low abundant families of mutated antibodies. In contrast, big difference between # mutated sequences and # base sequences leads to simulation of highly repetitive repertoires that include large mutated groups (see Supplementary).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Simulating Ig-seq library</head><p>IgSimulator uses a simulated repertoire as a reference and runs ART to simulate an Ig-seq library with reads featuring realistic and technology-specific error profiles. The user has an option to generate reads with errors that follow the specifics of Illumina. IgSimulator selects parameters of ART in such a way that the following conditions hold: (i) reads (or read-pairs) in the simulated library cover the variable region of the antibody (in the case of Illumina reads, IgSimulator generates paired-end overlapping reads with insert size similar to the length of the variable region), and (ii) the coverage of antibody sequences is uniform. As a result, IgSimulator creates an idealized repertoire for simulated library that can be used for further repertoire studies and benchmarking various repertoire analysis tools.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Conclusions</head><p>Many immunoinformatics algorithms have been developed for the challenging problem of antibody repertoire analysis. Our antibody repertoire simulator IgSimulator will help scientists to assess various immunoinformatics software tools and to choose the best pipeline for their research. The initial version of IgSimulator addresses most but not all aspects of modeling the antibody repertoires. In the future, it will be extended to address the following issues: (i) a datadriven modeling of the distribution of mutation across CDRs and FRs based on analyzing multiple immunoinformatics datasets, (ii) probabilistic model for modeling SHM motifs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bonissone and Pevzner, 2015</ref>), (iii) statistical inference methods for generating repertoires (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Murugan et al., 2012</ref>), (iv) addition of insertions and deletions to the set of SHMs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Klien et al., 1998</ref>) and (v) biases in N addition such as the GC preference (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Briney et al., 2012</ref>).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Bioinformatics, 31(19), 2015, 3213–3215doi:10.</head><figDesc>1093/bioinformatics/btv326 Advance Access Publication Date: 25 May 2015 Applications Note</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Y.Safonova et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors thank Dr. Pavel A. Pevzner and SPAdes team (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bankevich et al., 2012</ref>) for productive collaboration, helpful comments and feedback on using our software.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SPAdes: A new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Bankevich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="455" to="477" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunoglobulin classification using the colored antibody graph</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Bonissone</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Pevzner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Research in Computational Molecular Biology (RECOMB)</title>
		<editor>Przytycka,T.M.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="59" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measurement and clinical monitoring of human lymphocyte clonality by massively parallel VDJ pyrosequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Boyd</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Transl. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Frequency and genetic characterization of v(dd)j recombinants in the human peripheral blood antibody repertoire</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Briney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IMGT/V-QUEST: the highly customized and integrated system for IG and TR standardized V-J and V-D-J sequence analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Brochet</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="503" to="508" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ART: a next-generation sequencing read simulator</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="593" to="594" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Somatic hypermutation in normal and transformed human B cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<surname>Klien</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">162</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="261" to="280" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Janeway&apos;s immunobiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Murphy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>8th. edn. Garland Science</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical inference of the generation probability of T-cell receptors from sequence repertoires</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Murugan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page">161616</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Somatic hypermutagenesis in immunoglobulin genes. II. influence of neighbouring base sequences on mutagenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Rogozin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Kolchanov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1171" to="1182" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards error-free profiling of immune repertoires</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Shugay</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="653" to="655" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-throughput sequencing of the zebrafish antibody repertoire</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Weinstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">324</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="807" to="810" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IgSimulator</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>