
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:52+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies Impact of ontology evolution on functional analyses</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">20 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anika</forename>
								<surname>Groß</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O.Box 100920</postBox>
									<postCode>04009</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<surname>Hartung</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O.Box 100920</postBox>
									<postCode>04009</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kay</forename>
								<surname>Prü Fer</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Evolutionary Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max-Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Deutscher Platz 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>04103</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Janet</forename>
								<surname>Kelso</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Evolutionary Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max-Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Deutscher Platz 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>04103</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Erhard</forename>
								<surname>Rahm</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O.Box 100920</postBox>
									<postCode>04009</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies Impact of ontology evolution on functional analyses</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2671" to="2677"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">20 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts498</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 10, 2012; revised on July 3, 2012; accepted on August 8, 2012</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Supplementary information: Supplementary Data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Ontologies are used in the annotation and analysis of biological data. As knowledge accumulates, ontologies and annotation undergo constant modifications to reflect this new knowledge. These modifications may influence the results of statistical applications such as functional enrichment analyses that describe experimental data in terms of ontological groupings. Here, we investigate to what degree modifications of the Gene Ontology (GO) impact these statistical analyses for both experimental and simulated data. The analysis is based on new measures for the stability of result sets and considers different ontology and annotation changes. Results: Our results show that past changes in the GO are non-uniformly distributed over different branches of the ontology. Considering the semantic relatedness of significant categories in analysis results allows a more realistic stability assessment for functional enrichment studies. We observe that the results of term-enrichment analyses tend to be surprisingly stable despite changes in ontology and annotation. Contact:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Ontologies are increasingly used in the life sciences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bodenreider and Stevens, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Lambrix et al., 2007</ref>). They provide a uniform vocabulary to describe and structure a domain of interest. As a prime example, the Gene Ontology (GO)<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Consortium (2008)</ref>contains knowledge about biological processes (BPs), molecular functions (MFs) and cellular components (CCs). The categories of GO are presented as a directed acyclic graph (DAG), with the edges representing relationships between the categories. Higher-level categories represent more abstract descriptions and encompass all-child categories. These categories are used to semantically describe genes and gene products (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Thomas et al. 2007</ref>). Genes are therefore described by the particular category to which they are annotated and, by extension, by all-parent categories that give a more abstract description. Applications that perform functional enrichment analysis of gene sets take advantage of this property to identify more general categories that contain significantly more signal than expected at random (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Tilford and Siemers, 2009</ref>). Ongoing scientific research provides new domain knowledge that needs to be incorporated into ontologies and annotations. In the case of GO, these changes are incorporated on a regular basis with regular public releases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Gene Ontology Consortium, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Leonelli et al., 2011</ref>). This ontology evolution has been previously analyzed (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hartung et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Park et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Pesquita and Couto, 2011</ref>) and yielded insights into the differences between ontology versions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Noy and Musen, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hartung et al., 2012b</ref>). Typical ontology changes include the addition of new categories and relationships as well as the revision of the existing structure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hartung et al., 2012b</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hartung et al., , 2008</ref>). These ontological modifications can trigger changes in the annotation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Gross et al., 2009</ref>), e.g. when a category is removed, the annotations need to be moved or deleted. Further, annotations may be edited to reflect new knowledge or to eliminate inconsistencies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Dolan et al. 2005</ref>). The GO has evolved substantially since its inception in 2000. Its three sub-ontologies evolved at different rates and in different ways. Between 2007 and 2010, BP increased by about 70%, compared with CC (%40%) and MF (%20%) (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). Applying the method described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hartung et al. (2010)</ref>, we can identify how much different parts of GO have evolved by aggregating the change intensity in subtrees.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>illustrates that different subsections of the GO-MF evolve differently. The non-uniform distribution of changes may have an effect on functional enrichment analyses. The aforementioned studies only considered changes in the ontology while neglecting the potential effects on downstream analyses; for example, how these changes may lead to different results in functional enrichment analyses. While it is rather obvious that the high degree of occurred changes in GO and its annotations will impact analysis results, it is still unknown whether earlier findings are significantly affected or even invalidated. The impact of ontology changes on functional enrichment analyses may depend on where the changes are located in the ontology and what kind of changes dominate. For example, additions of categories at the leaf level might be less critical than structural revisions within the ontology. We provide a method to test to what degree changes of GO and GO annotations (GOAs) may affect functional enrichment analyses. We demonstrate the applicability and usefulness of our approach by analyzing two real-world experimental datasets as well as 50 random datasets. For the experimental datasets, we provide an in-depth study of the underlying changes and their impact on the analysis results. The presented analysis is informative for both ontology curators and users of functional enrichment methods. *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Ontology and annotation model</head><p>For our study, we use the GO, which is represented as a DAG, in which categories are linked by directed edges representing the relationships. Each category c has a unique identifier (e.g. 'blood coagulation' has the identifier GO:0007596). Various annotation sets A are associated with the GO. We use the GOA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Barrell et al., 2009</ref>). Annotations to one category (A(c)) include annotations to c and to all its descendant categories (subgraph of c). The evidence supporting the annotation of a gene to a category is represented as an evidence code, which can be used to assess the origin and likely the quality of an annotation, e.g. experimentally verified or automatically generated. Our evaluation requires consideration of multiple versions of ontologies and annotation sets. New versions always supersede the information of older versions. Furthermore, an annotation set is always associated with a particular ontology version. We denote an ontology version as O v and an annotation version as A v , where v stands for the date of release.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Ontology change detection</head><p>To understand the evolution of ontologies, we use a previously published diff algorithm (available in the CODEX web tool (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Hartung et al., 2012a</ref>)) to identify the changes that occurred between two versions of an ontology. The algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hartung et al., 2012b</ref>) uses a set of rules to first identify basic changes (insert/update/delete) that are then aggregated into a smaller set of more complex (semantic) changes, such as merge, split or changes of entire subgraphs. The following ontology changes are relevant for our study: addC – addition of a category toObsolete – mark a category as obsolete merge – merge of two or more categories into one category split – split one category into two or more categories substitute – substitute one category by another addR/delR – addition/deletion of a relationship between two categories move – move a category from one parent to another parent category.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Term enrichment using FUNC</head><p>We use the program FUNC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Pru¨ferPru¨fer et al., 2007</ref>) to carry out the functional enrichment analysis. FUNC tests each category of the input ontology for significance and then carries out randomizations to correct for multiple testing. For our further analysis, we consider the family-wise error rate corrected P-values associated with each category.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Stability measures</head><p>We propose two kinds of stability measures to assess the impact of ontology and annotation changes on the experimental results set of a functional enrichment analysis. For this purpose, we consider a fixed set of genes, and we compute experimental result set (ER) for different points in time with freely chosen ontology and annotation versions. We will use the example result sets displayed in<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>to illustrate our stability measures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.1">Basic stability measure</head><p>For our measures, we use the following cardinalities for result sets ER i and ER j produced with different ontology or annotation versions: ER i j j, ER j – number of categories in ER i and ER j ER i \ ER j – number of overlapping categories between ER i and ER j ER i n ER j – number of categories only in ER i but not in ER j ER j n ER i – number of categories only in ER j but not in ER i :</p><p>Note that categories are different if their unique identifier (accession) differs. For determining the overlap, we count categories with identical accessions in both ER i and ER j : The key idea for assessing the basic stability of a result set is the following. A result set is considered stable in comparison with an older set if both sets share all categories and no set has unique categories. With fewer categories shared, the measure decreases to indicate instability. Based on the common set similarity measure dice, we can compute the basic result set stability as follows:</p><p>RSstab basic ðER i , ER j Þ ¼ 2 Á ER i \ ER j ER i j jþ ER j :The stability returns a value between 0 and 1, whereby 0 denotes complete instability between the two result sets (no overlapping categories). A stability of 1 means that two considered result sets completely overlap. For instance, the example shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>results in a stability of 0.57 since ER i (ER j ) contains eight (six) categories of which four overlap. We use an analogous measure to determine the stability between annotation versions (Astab). For this, we consider the whole annotation set A or annotations to a specific category A(c). We calculate the set of annotations that are identical between the two versions. This value is then normalized by the total number of annotations. The calculation of the stability measure for A (and analogous for A(c)) is thus identical to the stability between result sets:</p><formula>AstabðA i , A j Þ ¼ 2 Á A i \ A j A i j j þ A j :</formula><p>While there are alternative set similarity measures, such as Cosine or Jaccard, we consider dice as a suitable approach. It corresponds to the harmonic mean, and we compare sets of similar size. According to<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Manning et al. (1999)</ref>, the Jaccard and Cosine measures produce slightly different values than dice, especially in case of low set overlap.<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lin (1998)</ref>proposes a more general measure based on information theory, taking probabilities instead of set overlap into account. This approach is particularly suited for the evaluation of term-enrichment tools, and we consider this a topic for future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.2">Region stability measure The basic stability measure</head><p>evaluates the overlap of categories in the result sets without considering the semantic relatedness of the categories, i.e. it treats them as independent from each other. This may result in an apparent instability even when differing categories are semantically related. We therefore generalize our model to include structural similarity. We first enhance the result sets by grouping together semantically related categories within so-called category regions (CRs). We then define the stability with respect to the CRs of the result sets. The basic model without grouping remains valid as a special case of the region-based approach. Semantic grouping of ER categories: We base the semantic grouping of categories in the experimental result sets on the distance within the ontology. This takes advantage of the fact that related categories tend to be in close proximity, i.e. they are either directly connected by an ontology relationship or only a few relationship 'edges' apart. We control the grouping by a distance parameter d; the base case without grouping corresponds to d ¼ 0. For d40, we recursively group together all categories that are connected by d edges (see Supplementary Algorithm 1). For the example shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, we obtain for d ¼ 1 three regions in ER i and four regions in ER j , e.g. in ER j , we group c 6 and c 13 into one region. For d ¼ 2, the number of regions is reduced to two in ER i and three in ER j , e.g. c 14 and c 17 are grouped together with c 6 and c 13 in ER j :</p><p>Alternative methods exist to group categories in the result sets by applying different semantic similarity measures (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Pesquita et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wang et al. 2007</ref>) or classification algorithms (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Pandey et al. 2009</ref>). Our approach makes use of semantic similarity based on ontology structure and is simple to apply. The approach is also in agreement with term-enrichment approaches such as FUNC that determine the significance of categories based on the ontological structure that try to restrict significant categories to few areas within an ontology. Determining region stability: The semantic grouping of categories allows us to determine the stability of results sets based on their CRs and to assume stability as long as the same or at least overlapping regions are retained in the result sets. We therefore determine the number of regions in ER i having an overlap with regions in ER j and vice versa (see Supplementary Algorithm 3). We consider two regions as overlapping if they share at least one category. We denote the overlapping regions in ER i with CR o i and in ER j with CR o j , respectively. We can now use the information about overlapping regions to compute the region stability as follows:</p><formula>RSstab region ðCR i , CR j Þ ¼ CR o i þ CR o j CR i j jþ CR j :</formula><p>The stability values are, as before, distributed between 0 and 1; for d ¼ 0 (no grouping), the region stability equals the basic stability. In<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, the region stability is 0.57 for d ¼ 0, 0.71 for d ¼ 1 and even 0.8 for d ¼ 2. Increasing the distance leads to fewer but larger regions that more likely overlap with the regions of updated result sets. Non-overlapping regions indicate the addition or removal of larger areas in the ontology and, thus, more significant changes than individual category changes quantified with the basic stability measure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Datasets</head><p>We re-analyzed two datasets that were first tested in 2007 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kosiol et al., 2008</ref>). The authors performed functional enrichment analyses of genes that show signals of positive selection in primates and rodents. We repeat the analyses using newer versions of ontology and annotation. We consider yearly versions between 2003 and 2010, i.e. eight GOA versions<ref type="bibr">(8,</ref><ref type="bibr">17,</ref><ref type="bibr">27,</ref><ref type="bibr">38,</ref><ref type="bibr">47,</ref><ref type="bibr">59,</ref><ref type="bibr">70,</ref><ref type="bibr">81</ref>) and the corresponding GO versions (<ref type="bibr">01-2003, 02-2004, 01-2005, 01-2006, 01-2007, 01-2008, 02-2009, 01-2010</ref>). All newer and older versions are compared with the version used in the original publication (GOA 47 and GO 01À2007 ). For testing, we used the Wilcoxon rank test with 10 000 random sets and a cutoff of at least 20 genes per category. A significant category has to have a P-value that does not exceed a value of 0.05. To test whether the observations from the real datasets apply generally, we generated 50 datasets, randomly seeding significant categories. For this, a set of categories is chosen using a fixed first ontology version and marked as significant by choosing a higher ratio of genes that are<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. Stability measures. Colored nodes denote significant result set categories. We consider two versions i and j of the result set ER (for clarity with stable ontology structure). Yellow categories are significant in both result sets ER i and ER j , red (green) categories are only significant in ER i (ER j ). Stability is computed for CRs grouped using distance d ¼ 0.. .2. For d ¼ 0, each concept is considered as a region (yellow concepts overlap). For d ¼ 1 (d ¼ 2), overlapping CRs are connected by a dashed black (continuous grey) line marked as significant. Then, this simulated dataset can be tested using a different GO version. We generate datasets with the GO versions from 2007 and 2010. We then test the 2007 dataset with the 2010 version (Task A) and vice versa (Task B).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>Between 2003 and 2010, GO grew by a factor of 2.4. Similarly, the number of input annotations increased by factor 2.7 for mouse and human (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table S2</ref>). However, some annotations were also removed. A comparison of whole annotation sets of 2007 and 2010 shows substantial instabilities<ref type="bibr">[AstabðA 2007</ref>, A 2010 Þ ¼ 0:7], i.e. every third annotation was affected by a change. To understand the impact of ontology and annotation evolution on term-enrichment results, we measure the stability for two real-world datasets (primate and rodent dataset) at different time points. We quantify changes in result sets using our basic stability measure and analyze causes for changes using Astab and diff. To identify crucial changes in the results, we applied our region-stability measure. We analyzed 50 random datasets to test whether our observations are generalizable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Primate and rodent datasets</head><p>3.1.1 Basic stability We computed result sets for yearly versions between 2003 and 2010 for the primate (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3a</ref>) and rodent datasets (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3b</ref>). We compared the result sets of each version (ER comp ) against the reference version ER ref (from 2007) by computing the overlap and difference of significant categories. The primate result set (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3a</ref>) contains 19 significant categories in 2007. In general, ontology versions that are closer in time tend to share a higher fraction of significant categories. Since 2008, the results are more stable. A substantial fraction of significant categories are detected in 2007 and 2010, as evidenced by a stability measure (RSstab basic ) of 0.81. The rodent result set (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3b</ref>) contains 23 significant categories in 2007. The preceding (2006) and successive (2008) version overlap by only 8 and 15 categories, respectively. Using the 2010 version, only eight categories of the reference result set remained, and no new categories were detected as significant. Overall, the results set stability (0.52) is lower compared with the primate dataset.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3c</ref>shows a comparison of the result set stability RSstab basic between 2007 and 2010 for both the datasets. To identify the main cause for the changes observed between significant categories found in different years, we tested the results changing ontology and annotation independently. Changing only the ontology affected both datasets (rodents 0.84, primates 0.7). Changing the annotation version (A w ) but fixing the ontology only marginally affected the primate result set (0.97) while it substantially reduced the stability of the rodent result set (0.5). This shows that both ontology and annotation evolution have an impact on the results of term-enrichment analyses. We explore the causes for the differences in significant categories between 2007 and 2010 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 4</ref>). We used diff to identify ontology changes that have caused changes in ER. Moreover, we analyzed the annotation stability (Astab) of all significant result categories c to see whether changes in annotations predominate in some cases. First, there were three new significant categories for primates in 2010. Two categories ('molecular transducer activity' GO:0060089, 'system process' GO:0003008) were added between 2007 and 2010 such that they were additionally detected in the functional enrichment analysis. Another category ('cognition' GO:0050890) has been included in the result set since it received additional annotation. On the other hand, no new categories were detected as significant in rodents. Several categories were no longer significant in both rodent and primate datasets. Three of the 15 non-significant categories in the rodent dataset are directly affected by an ontology evolution operation (merge) while most other categories that became non-significant show a strongly reduced annotation stability of less than 0.7. For instance, for 'regulation of immune system process' ('GO:0002682') only 22 out of 143 annotations in 2010 overlap to the annotation set of 2007 (Astab 0:3). This is in contrast to the primate dataset, where three of the categories were affected by ontology evolution operations (merge, substitute, toObsolete) while only one category shows a large change in annotation. We further observed strong structural changes in the direct semantic context of significant categories: addR j j¼31ð48Þ, delR j j¼10ð11Þ, move j j¼102ð57Þ for primates (rodents) (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S5</ref>). Such structuralmodifications may influence annotation propagation. Adding or deleting relationships to an upper category c leads to a changed annotation set A(c) and, thus, to a reduced annotation stability Astab and possibly to a changed significance of c. Overall, most unaffected significant categories showed a higher annotation stability than categories that gained or lost significance. Electronic annotation that is based on automated methods to infer the function of genes may produce less reliable annotations than manually curated entries. To test this hypothesis, we repeated our analysis of the rodent and primate datasets using only manually curated annotation. However, because as much as 60% of the annotation is derived from automated approaches, the dataset is too small to draw reliable conclusions (primates ER 2007 j j¼ 4, rodents ER 2007 j j¼ 9; see Supplementary Figs S6 and S7 for details).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">Region stability</head><p>Applying the CR stability measure (distance d ¼ 1) summarizes significant categories into semantically related regions (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 5</ref>). For primates, we identify four CRs. All four regions overlap, and the contents of the regions changed only slightly from 2007 to 2010. Considering regions instead of single categories, we obtain perfect stability (RSstab region ¼ 1 instead of RSstab basic ¼ 0:81). For rodents, there were four significant CRs in 2007 (CR 1 , CR 2 , CR 3 , CR 4 ) and 2010 (CR 2 , CR 3 , CR 4a , CR 4b ) but only three of them overlapped. One region (CR 1 'catabolism') lost significance, due to strong annotation evolution (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 4</ref>). Moreover, there was one very large region (CR 4 'response to stimulus'), where 13 categories were no longer significant in 2010. Six remaining categories were split into two regions (CR 4 a 'response to stress', CR 4 b 'immune system process'). The rodent dataset has a CR stability of RSstab region ¼ ð3 þ 4Þ=ð4 þ 4Þ ¼ 0:875 (instead of RSstab basic ¼ 0:52). Comparing CRs incorporates semantic information, which leads to higher stability values since larger regions are considered. If the CR stability is reduced, we argue that there is a meaningful difference in results. With the datasets analyzed here, we see that ontology evolution operations and annotation changes can have effects on term-enrichment analyses. There is a substantial variability between the primate and rodent datasets. While the primate results proved to be relatively stable, we see meaningful changes for the rodent data. The primate dataset was more influenced by ontology changes while annotation changes had a higher impact on the rodent dataset. Term-enrichment analysis will often yield semantically related categories reducing the influence of changes in semantically related categories. The majority of changes have no effect on the semantic interpretation of functional enrichment analysis, although we found some instances in which the interpretation may change. We conclude that term-enrichment results are relatively robust to ontology and annotation evolution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Simulated datasets</head><p>We observe that several categories in the real datasets are affected by evolution of ontology and annotation, and that these changes lead to differences in the enrichment analysis results. To test whether the patterns we observe are generalizable, we generated 50 datasets, randomly seeding significant categories. Repeating this generation of datasets for two versions of the<ref type="bibr">GO (2007</ref><ref type="bibr">GO ( , 2010</ref>) enables us to test to what extent differences between these two ontology versions influence enrichment results. To distinguish semantically related categories that are likely equally affected by changes, from semantically distinct categories, we apply the CR stability measure with distance d ¼ 1.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>shows average values over all 50 random experiments (details in Supplementary Tables S4 and S5). Note that the. All other categories are present in both version sets. The lower boxes highlight evolution operations that happened to categories (dotted boxinformation reducing/revising, striped box-added information). Result categories (including GO accessions) for both species and years are shown in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref>random datasets are larger and thus cover larger ontology parts, possibly leading to a generally lower stability. When testing changes from 2007 to 2010 (Task A), we observe on an average nineBecause we define categories as significant based on a fixed P-value cutoff, some of the categories that lose or gain significance may do so due to small fluctuations in P-value. To test for the relative contribution of this effect to the observed changes, we computed the differences of P-values between 2007 and 2010 for each significant category.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref>shows the distribution of P-value differences for lost and gained significant categories. Most of the categories reveal only a relatively small change in P-value (50:1), showing that most category gains and losses are driven by small fluctuations in significance. However, some categories show substantial P-value differences, suggesting that real structural changes in the ontology or annotation are the basis for the change in P-value.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Enrichment analyses use ontology and annotation to detect significantly enriched categories of genes. We studied the impact of ontology and annotation evolution on term-enrichment analyses by comparing term-enrichment results over different ontology and annotation versions. We proposed different measures to assess the stability of result sets and applied them to analyze the impact of evolution for two real-world and 50 random datasets. The GO undergoes continuous changes in its structure and the annotation due to the ongoing incorporation of new knowledge. These changes are unequally distributed and can cluster in regions representing specific topics. At the level of individual categories, the results of term-enrichment analyses can be significantly affected by ontology and annotation evolution. However, these changes do not necessarily change the interpretation of the result since these terms are often semantically related. This effect is captured by our CR stability measure. The experimental evaluation showed that term-enrichment analyses are generally robust to ontology and annotation evolution. Using our measures, users can identify categories that tend to change their level of significance due to structural ontology changes or heavily changed annotation sets. The two following audiences can benefit from our methods and results:Average number of significant result categories ( ER j j) and more compact CRs ( CR j j) only in 2007 (missing), only in 2010 (new), avgðRSstab basic Þ – average of basic stability, avgðRSstab region Þ – average of CR stability.(i) Ontology curators: For these users, it is important to determine whether planned changes in the ontology or the annotations result in a semantic change. We show here that structural ontology changes do not necessarily imply a semantic change of the results, and we provide stability measures that allow testing of proposed changes in the GO and the implications for functional enrichment analyses.</p><p>(ii) Biologists using the GO for functional enrichment analyses: For these users, it is interesting to know that enrichment results may change over time due to changes in the ontology and annotations and that interpretation of their own results should be made with this in mind.</p><p>We already provide a tool for ontology evolution evaluation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Hartung et al. 2012a</ref>). We plan to extend this tool to detect annotation evolution and to incorporate the here-presented stability measures. The tool may be of particular interest for curators of ontologies to judge the potential impact of changes for users.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Evolution of slim terms in GO molecular functions between 2007 and 2010 (only partially shown, see Supplementary Figures 1–3 for BP, CC and MF visualization). We computed evolution intensities for slim terms by propagating changes from slim-term subtrees (Hartung et al. 2010). Colors denote evolution intensities of the slim terms. Non-slim term categories on the path to the root are coloured white. The graphic was produced using the visualization tool of Amigo (Carbon et al., 2009)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Evolution of ERs between 2003 and 2010 for primates (a) and rodents (b). We compared the ERs for each version ER comp against the reference version ER ref from 2007: overlapping categories (black bar), categories in ER comp but not in ER ref (light gray bar), categories in ER ref but not in ER comp (dark grey bar). (c) Basic result set stability RSstab basic between 2007 and 2010. Different input versions: evolution of ontology and annotation versions (change O v and A w ), only changing the ontology version (change O v ) and only changing the annotation version (change A w )</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Annotation stability for result set categories in ER 2007 and ER 2010 for (a) primates and (b) rodents. The diagrams show all significant categories computed in 2007 and/or 2010 (x-axis). For each category, the overlap of annotations between both versions ( A 2007 ðcÞ \ A 2010 ðcÞ , black bars, y-axis), the number of annotations in 2007 (|A 2007 (c)|, light gray bars, y-axis) and 2010 (|A 2010 (c)|, dark gray bars, y-axis) as well as the resulting annotation stability Atab(A 2007 (c),A 2010 (c)) (black curve, z-axis) are shown. Categories in the dotted (striped) areas were only present in the analysis result of 2007 (2010). All other categories are present in both version sets. The lower boxes highlight evolution operations that happened to categories (dotted boxinformation reducing/revising, striped box-added information). Result categories (including GO accessions) for both species and years are shown in Supplementary Figure 4</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. Category regions for primate and rodent dataset, d ¼ 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.6.</head><figDesc>Fig. 6. Average number of changed categories grouped by absolute P-value difference ( Pvalue 2007 À Pvalue 2010 j j ) for tasks A and B</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: This work was supported by the German Research Foundation, grant RA 497/18-1 ('Evolution of Ontologies and Mappings') and the Max Planck Society. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Average results over 50 random experiments for tasks A and B</figDesc><table>Task A 
Task B 

avgð ER only2007 



Þ 
129.3 
62.6 
avgð CR only2007 



Þ 
8.9 
4.2 

avgð ER only2010 



Þ 
440.7 
856.8 
avgð CR only2010 



Þ 
18.9 
21.4 

avgðRSstab basic Þ 
0.625 
0.519 
avgðRSstab region Þ 
0.719 
0.707 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">A.Groß et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Impact of evolution at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Amigo: online access to ontology and annotation data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Carbon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ireland</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Mungall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Shu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Marshall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Lewis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="288" to="289" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The GOA database in 2009–an integrated gene ontology annotation resource</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Barrell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="396" to="403" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bio-ontologies: current trends and future directions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Bodenreider</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Stevens</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="256" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A procedure for assessing go annotation consistency</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Dolan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The gene ontology project in</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Gene</forename>
				<surname>Ontology</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Consortium</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res.Database Issue)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="440" to="444" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the quality of ontology-based annotations by considering evolutionary changes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Gross</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 6th Int. Workshop on Data Integration in the Life Sciences</title>
		<meeting>the 6th Int. Workshop on Data Integration in the Life Sciences<address><addrLine>Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="87" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing the evolution of life science ontologies and mappings</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hartung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 5th Int. Workshop on Data Integration in the Life Sciences</title>
		<meeting>the 5th Int. Workshop on Data Integration in the Life Sciences<address><addrLine>Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="27" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovering evolving regions in life science ontologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hartung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 7th Int. Conference on Data Integration in the Life Sciences</title>
		<meeting>the 7th Int. Conference on Data Integration in the Life Sciences<address><addrLine>Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="34" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CODEX: exploration of semantic changes between ontology versions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hartung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="895" to="896" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conto–diff: generation of complex evolution mappings for life science ontologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hartung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biomed. Informat</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in. press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patterns of positive selection in six mammalian genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Kosiol</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Biological ontologies. Semantic Web</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Lambrix</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="99" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How the gene ontology evolves</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Leonelli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An information-theoretic definition of similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 15th international conference on Machine Learning, ICML &apos;98</title>
		<meeting>the 15th international conference on Machine Learning, ICML &apos;98<address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="296" to="304" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Foundations of Statistical Natural Language Processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Manning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Promptdiff: a fixed-point algorithm for comparing ontology versions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Noy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Musen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the National Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the National Conference on Artificial Intelligence<address><addrLine>Menlo Park, CA; Cambridge, MA ; London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>AAAI Press MIT Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="744" to="750" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incorporating functional inter-relationships into protein function prediction algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Pandey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monitoring the evolutionary aspect of the gene ontology to enhance predictability and usability</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Park</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 3</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Where GO is going and what it means for ontology extension</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Pesquita</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Couto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Biomedical Ontology CEURWorkshop Proceedings</title>
		<meeting>the 2nd International Conference on Biomedical Ontology CEURWorkshop Proceedings<address><addrLine>Buffalo, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="9" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semantic similarity in biomedical ontologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Pesquita</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000443</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FUNC: a package for detecting significant associations between gene sets and ontological annotations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Pru¨ferpru¨fer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ontology annotation: mapping genomic regions to biological function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Thomas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene set enrichment analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Tilford</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Siemers</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">563</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new method to measure the semantic similarity of go terms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1274" to="1281" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>