
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:47+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Improving protein fold recognition with hybrid profiles combining sequence and structure evolution</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yassine</forename>
								<surname>Ghouzam</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Inserm U1134</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR_S 1134</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Paris Diderot</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Sorbonne Paris Cité</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Institut National de la Transfusion Sanguine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Excellence GR-Ex</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Guillaume</forename>
								<surname>Postic</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Inserm U1134</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR_S 1134</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Paris Diderot</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Sorbonne Paris Cité</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Institut National de la Transfusion Sanguine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Excellence GR-Ex</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alexandre</forename>
								<forename type="middle">G</forename>
								<surname>De Brevern</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Inserm U1134</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR_S 1134</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Paris Diderot</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Sorbonne Paris Cité</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Institut National de la Transfusion Sanguine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Excellence GR-Ex</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jean-Christophe</forename>
								<surname>Gelly</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Inserm U1134</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR_S 1134</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Paris Diderot</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Sorbonne Paris Cité</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Institut National de la Transfusion Sanguine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Excellence GR-Ex</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Improving protein fold recognition with hybrid profiles combining sequence and structure evolution</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv462</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 4, 2015; revised on July 24, 2015; accepted on August 2, 2015</note>
					<note>Structural bioinformatics *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Template-based modeling, the most successful approach for predicting protein 3D structure, often requires detecting distant evolutionary relationships between the target sequence and proteins of known structure. Developed for this purpose, fold recognition methods use elaborate strategies to exploit evolutionary information, mainly by encoding amino acid sequence into profiles. Since protein structure is more conserved than sequence, the inclusion of structural information can improve the detection of remote homology. Results: Here, we present ORION, a new fold recognition method based on the pairwise comparison of hybrid profiles that contain evolutionary information from both protein sequence and structure. Our method uses the 16-state structural alphabet Protein Blocks, which provides an accurate 1D description of protein structure local conformations. ORION systematically outperforms PSI-BLAST and HHsearch on several benchmarks, including target sequences from the modeling competitions CASP8, 9 and 10, and detects $10% more templates at fold and superfamily SCOP levels. Availability: Software freely available for download at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Understanding how proteins adopt their 3D structure remains one of the most challenging questions in science (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Kennedy and Norman, 2005</ref>). The resolution of this problem would have a great impact on various fields of biology and medicine, allowing, for example, the rational design of new protein functions and drug molecules. Despite the progress made over the last decades, our biochemical knowledge and computational power are still insufficient to accurately predict protein structure solely from the amino acid sequence. Nevertheless, on the basis of the evolutionary relationship that many proteins share, it is possible to model the structure of a target protein using, as a template, a related protein of known structure. This approach, called comparative modeling, is currently the most successful in constructing theoretical models of protein structures. Since the quality of the resulting structure prediction largely depends on the template protein selected, the initial step of homology detection is crucial in comparative modeling. When proteins share &gt;30% sequence identity, evolutionary relationships can be found using simple pairwise sequence comparison methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Brenner et al., 1998</ref>): heuristic such as BLAST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Altschul et al., 1990</ref>) or optimal such as SSEARCH (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Pearson, 1991</ref>). However, in the case of non-obvious relationships below the 'twilight zone' of 20À35% sequence identity between the target and the template (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Rost, 1999</ref>), fold recognition methods have been proposed to find related proteins for template-based modeling. Early methods of remote homology detection were based on profile-to-sequence comparison (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Gribskov et al., 1987</ref>). A profile canbe represented as a position-specific scoring matrix (PSSM) encoded from multiple sequence alignment (MSA) of related proteins and, therefore, contains evolutionary information specific to a protein family and defined by the levels of residue conservation at each sequence position. The first profile-to-sequence algorithm proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Henikoff and Henikoff (1994)</ref>, and the widely used PSI-BLAST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Altschul et al., 1997</ref>), were followed by methods derived from the probabilistic interpretation of profiles using hidden Markov models (profile HMMs) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Krogh et al., 1994</ref>), like SAM-T98 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Karplus et al., 1998</ref>) or HMMER (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Eddy, 1998</ref>), which improved both the alignment quality and the sensitivity/specificity of detection. Compared with sequence-to-sequence alignment, profiles and profile HMMs greatly improved identification of distantly related proteins and, consequently, comparative modeling (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Mü ller et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Park et al., 1998</ref>). Fold recognition was later taken to a new level with the FFAS method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Rychlewski et al., 2000</ref>), which was based on profile–profile alignment. By using profiles for both target and template, such methods fully exploit the transitivity of sequence homology, making them more sensitive and specific than profile-tosequence comparisons (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Ohlson et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Panchenko, 2003</ref>). Finally, the pairwise profile HMM comparison introduced with the HHsearch algorithm (Sö ding, 2005) has further pushed the boundaries of remote homology detection and provided one of the current best approach for protein fold recognition. Besides these methods solely based on sequence, some authors have proposed structure-based fold recognition methods called 'threading' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bowie et al., 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Jones et al., 1992</ref>). The principle of threading is to assess the compatibility between the target sequence (1D) and different solved protein structures (3D) by using knowledge-based scoring functions. Thus, comparative modeling may still be achieved by using templates sharing no detectable homology with the target sequence, since proteins may be structurally similar, even without detectable evolutionary relationship between their sequences. Despite interesting success, these 1D–3D methods are limited by the quality of the sequence-to-structure alignment and do not reach the accuracy of the most advanced purely sequence-based methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">McGuffin, 2008</ref>). Following the success of both sequence-and structure-based fold recognition methods, combined approaches have emerged. Indeed, structural information from solvent accessibility, secondary structure or backbone torsion angle can be used to improve sequencebased fold recognition. Such structural features have the advantage of being predictable, which addresses the absence of experimental model for the target protein. Thus, several methods combining discrete structural descriptors with amino acid sequence information have been proposed (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kelley et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Shi et al., 2001</ref>). Given that structural cores change less rapidly, between 3 and 10 times slower than sequences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Illergård et al., 2009</ref>), one can imagine the advantage of using 'structural profiles' that would be generated from 1D descriptions of protein structures, in the same way that sequence profiles are generated from amino acid sequences. Indeed, protein structure being more conserved than sequence through evolution, these structural profiles would be more conserved and richer in evolutionary information than sequence profiles and, therefore, better at detecting distant homologies. In this article, we present ORION, a new method for fold recognition using evolutionary information from both amino acid sequence and protein structure, and encoded as combined sequence/ structure profiles. Our method uses the accurate sequential description of protein local conformations provided by the 16-state structural alphabet protein blocks (PB) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">de Brevern et al., 2000</ref>), instead of the conventional three-state secondary structure, which has important drawbacks, especially for describing the loops which constitutes $45% of the local structure of the proteins. The relevance of PB structural information has previously been demonstrated through numerous applications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Joseph et al., 2010</ref>), such as structural alignment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Gelly et al., 2011</ref>) and local structure prediction (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Rangwala et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Zimmermann and Hansmann, 2008</ref>). The novelty of our method also lies in the use of a combination of sequence and structural profiles for both target and template. The structural profiles used for the template were derived from structural alignments of the HOMSTRAD database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mizuguchi et al., 1998</ref>). For distantly related proteins, structural alignments have been shown to be more relevant than sequence alignments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Elofsson, 2002</ref>). Thus, using as a benchmark the 1032 structural families from HOMSTRAD and 150 targets from the eighth, ninth and tenth editions of the Critical Assessment of Structure Prediction (CASP) experiments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Moult et al., 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Moult et al., , 2011</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Moult et al., , 2014</ref>), we show that ORION outperforms the HHsearch algorithm in recognizing proteins with same or similar folds. Our detailed analysis further indicates that this accurate homology detection can be attributed to the inclusion of the PB structural descriptors into profile–profile alignments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Materials and methods</head><p>ORION is a fold recognition method based on the pairwise comparison of profiles combining sequence and structural information. The three major steps of ORION algorithm are presented in the following sections and illustrated in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. The first step is the generation of the template profile library. Sequence profiles are obtained from MSAs of HOMSTRAD families and represent the 20 amino acid scores for each position of the MSA. Structural profiles represent the 16 PB scores for each position of the MSA. The MSAs of templates, derived from structure alignments, were translated into PB MSAs using the atomic coordinates of the protein structures to generate template PB profiles. Amino acid and PB profiles are joinedto form 'AAPB profiles' containing both sequence and structural evolutionary information. From the query sequence, the second step consists in generating a query profile. The query sequence profile is obtained after three iterations of PSI-BLAST and is used to predict the query PB profile. The third and last step is the search for related proteins in the template profile library. The construction of the AAPB profiles library is described in details in the Section 2.1 and 2.2; the benchmark datasets are detailed in the Section 2.8. ORION performs a global/local alignment by a dynamic programming approach: implementation of dynamic programming, profile scoring function and evaluation of statistical significance of score alignments are described in Sections 2.4–2.7.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Fold library</head><p>The profile library was constructed from HOMSTRAD structural alignments. This database regroups protein families through structural alignments, with 3454 protein structures regrouped into 1032 families. Each family corresponds to a domain identified in the SCOP database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Murzin et al., 1995</ref>). The four major SCOP classes, a, b, a/b and a þ b, represent 20, 19, 25 and 22% of the database, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">AAPB profile library</head><p>Amino acid profiles were generated from the MSA of family members for each family. MSAs families were enriched with homologous sequences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mizuguchi et al., 1998</ref>) and sequences with more than 90% identity were filtered out. The weight of each sequence in the profile depends on its relative diversity (i.e. compared with all the other sequences in the MSA) and is calculated using the Henikoff– Henikoff position-based sequence weights (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Henikoff and Henikoff, 1994</ref>). Profiles are then weighted using 'pseudo-counts' described in the Henikoff–Henikoff weighting scheme (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Henikoff and Henikoff, 1996</ref>). To avoid non-significant columns in the profile, positions with more than 70% gaps were discarded. The PB profiles were obtained by translating the HOMSTRAD structural MSAs into PB MSAs using the atomic coordinates of the protein structures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">de Brevern et al., 2000</ref>). PB profiles are weighted in the same way as for AA profiles. Such profiles based on structural alphabet provide structural evolutionary information, which is expected to improve the detection of remote homologies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Generating query AAPB profiles</head><p>MSAs were obtained by three iterations of PSI-BLAST on Uniref90 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Suzek et al., 2007</ref>) (a subset of the UniProt database containing no pair of sequences with &gt;90% identity) with an E-value threshold of 10 À4. At most 1000 alignments were saved at each round. Each profile was built from the last round of PSI-BLAST. MSAs were purged by removing sequences with more than 70% identity. PB profiles are generated using the LOCUSTRA program (<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Zimmermann and Hansmann, 2008</ref>), which predicts a sequence of PB from a PSI-BLAST MSA, using a two-layer support vector machine (SVM) approach. The input is a PSSM matrix of the 20 residue types extracted from the checkpoint file generated by PSI-BLAST. We modified LOCUSTRA to obtain a PB profile of 16 columns corresponding to the SVM multiclass posterior probabilities for the 16 letters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Profile–profile scoring function</head><p>The PICASSO scoring function introduced by Heger and Holm (2001) has been shown to be one of the most efficient scoring functions for comparing two amino acid profiles.<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Mittelman et al. (2003)</ref>modified it into several variants. The one we chose here is PICASSO3Q (1), which uses only the query and template frequencies Qi and Qj, from query position i and template position j of the profiles in symmetric Equations (2, 3):where Qaa and Qpb are the amino acid and PB frequencies, respectively. p aax is the background frequency of the amino acid x and p pby the background frequency of PB letter y. S(i,j) is the sum of S AA (i,j) and S PB (i,j), which are the PICASSO3Q scores over the amino acid and structural alphabet profiles, respectively. The PICASSO3Q method was applied in the same way for PB and amino acid profiles. S(i,j) is normalized by the median score pair sp and the SD r(sp) of S(i,j) over all column pair (i.e. profile–profile) scores in the database. The median value appears to be preferable to the mean when there are a lot of extreme pair scores (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Gonzales and Ottenbacher, 2001</ref>). In PICASSO3Q, the natural logarithm ln is used instead of log 2 , but we found that the latter performed slightly better (5% higher sensitity at 10% specificity, data not shown). A shift of 0.1 is added to the score to make average scores negative and consequently avoid the alignment of unrelated residues in local regions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Dynamic programming</head><p>ORION carries out global/local dynamic programming to obtain the optimum global/local alignment. This variant of the Smith and Waterman's (1981) local/local and Needleman and Wunsch's (1970) global/global algorithm locally aligns the query against the whole template. We consider that query sequences may be composed of multiple domains that require to be locally aligned, while template family sequences are generally composed of a unique and well-delimited domain that must be globally aligned. It also established that global–local algorithm performs better for fold recognition (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Fischer et al., 1996</ref>). The optimal gap opening penalty go and the optimal gap extension penalty ge were determined by an iterative grid approach on a non-redundant subset of 402 sequences (i.e. the sequences having &lt;30% sequence identity with their family members). Pairwise alignments were performed and all alignments obtained were compared with their respective structural alignments. The pair of values (go, ge) maximizing the percentage of correctly aligned positions was chosen as the optimal values. These optimal values (go ¼ 2 and ge ¼ 0.2) were set as default parameters. We have tested different subsets of HOMSTRAD and have observed that theses values are stable and do not depend of the subset composition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">Metafold: a supplementary level for remote protein structure similarities</head><p>The concept of metafold was introduced to characterize fold similarities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Day et al., 2003</ref>). For example, authors clustered the TIM barrels and the beta propellers into the same fold family (Sö ding and<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Remmert, 2011</ref>), while these structures are classified in two different folds in SCOP. Metafold classification is obtained by a consensus of fold classifications in SCOP, CATH and Dali databases, and thus provides a more unified view of fold space. Here, we propose to use the metafold as an additional hierarchical level above the fold level of SCOP database. There are 422 metafolds groups in the HOMSTRAD database. As expected, immunoglobulin-like and Rossmann fold groups are the most populous ones.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7">Statistical significance of score alignments</head><p>The raw alignment score depends on the composition of the two profiles compared but also on the alignment length. For each family template, a score distribution has been precalculated. For a given family, the template family profile was aligned to a set of 422 profiles of unrelated proteins. Proteins used to obtain score distributions of unrelated targets must be structurally independent. Therefore, scores from protein pairs belonging to the same SCOP fold level or within the same metafold class were removed. Scores of amino acid sequence alignments usually follow an extreme value distribution, a Gumbel law in most cases. Here, score distributions show a good fitness to the Weibull distribution law (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). In fact, the addition of structural information into profiles modifies the score distributions that are close to distributions of threading scores (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Fayyaz Movaghar et al., 2011</ref>). ORION computes a P value from the raw score and the Weibull law parameters that are specific to the template family.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.8">Benchmark datasets</head><p>ORION was compared with different programs to evaluate the distant homology detection rate. Therefore, a query test set has been constituted from the 1032 HOMSTRAD families. For each family, the representative sequence is selected based on the sequence identity between the family members, knowing that the representative sequence share the highest average sequence identity with the rest of the family. The SCOP annotation is hierarchical with the higher levels (family and superfamily levels) describing near evolutionary relationships; the fold level describes distant relationships and/or structural similarities. The metafold level is a consensus level that describes very distant protein similarities. To assess the programs for different degrees of protein relationship, three query datasets have been constituted, one for each level (superfamily, fold and metafold) by selecting sequences having at least one structure in HOMSTRAD with the same SCOP level. This selection resulted in 484, 413 and 434 sequences for the superfamily, fold and metafold levels, respectively. All the sets are non-redundant since 95% of sequences pairs have less than 18, 17 and 16% sequence identity (superfamily, fold and metafold level, respectively). The methods were independently tested for these different levels. HHsearch and PSI-BLAST were tested in the same way as for ORION. For HHsearch, we generated 'hhm' profiles for the queries and the database from MSAs of PSI-BLAST and HOMSTRAD famillies, respectively, using the hhmake program available in the HH-suite package (ftp://toolkit.genzentrum.lmu.de/pub/HH-suite/). The database of hhm profiles has been generated following the HH-suite user guide. HHsearch was run using the query hhm as input file and the HOMSTRAD database of hhm profiles as the input database. For PSI-BLAST, a three-iteration search was run in the HOMSTRAD enriched sequence database with the default E-value threshold for inclusion (0.002). For each query, the methods give a ranked list of proteins from the database. Proteins are ranked by E-value for PSIBLAST, probability for HHsearch and raw score for ORION. The true positives (TPs) and false positives (FPs) were counted considering the classification level of interest. A TP was denoted when the two proteins compared (which define a 'hit') belong to the same class level (e.g. b.1.18.2 and b.1.10.1 at fold SCOP level) and a FP is counted for hits within different class levels (e.g. b.1.18.2 and b.2.6.1 at fold SCOP level). The hits with the same superior class levels were ignored (e.g. b.1.18.11 and b.1.18.2 at fold SCOP level). Each protein is then labeled as TP or FP in the ranked list. Similar benchmark procedures are employed by authors for assessing the template detection performance of their methods (Sö ding, 2005; Sö ding and<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Remmert, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Xu et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Yang et al., 2011</ref>). Some SCOP classes in query test sets and template database may be overrepresented, and the results could suffer from this compositional bias. For example, the immunoglobulin fold and the Rossmann fold are the most represented in the HOMSTRAD database, which could bias the results for these families. To prevent these compositional biases from dominating the benchmarks, each template and query is weighted with the number of member belonging to the same level. Recently,<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Remmert et al. (2012)</ref>used a similar approach to weigh the folds that constitute their dataset.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results and discussion</head><p>The distant homology detection rate of ORION has been assessed and compared with those of the widely used PSI-BLAST and the state-of-the-art method HHsearch. The results are described in the<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>by receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves, which illustrate the performance of a binary classifier, here, the evolution of the true positive rate (TPR) in function of the false positive rate (FPR) ranging from 0 to 10%. As expected, a basic profile–profile method like ORION without PB outperforms a profile-sequence method like PSI-BLAST, with a TPR &gt; 10% higher for 10% FPR. Not surprising either is the fact that the HMM-HMM profile alignments of HHsearch demonstrate higher performance than our amino acid profile–profile method (2.7% higher TPR for 10% FPR). However, the inclusion of PBs into ORION profiles leads to a significant increase of the homology detection rate, with 2.1 times more TP detected for 10% FPR, and makes our method outperform HHsearch and PSI-BLAST. Indeed, for 10% FPR, ORION is 1.8 times (0.55/0.30) and 3.6 times (0.55/0.15) more sensitive thanImproving protein fold recognitionHHsearch and PSI-BLAST, respectively. Thus, the structural features encoded into PBs improve particularly fold recognition and remote homology detection. These results could be explained by the fact that the 16 structural patterns catch almost every local conformation. Additionally, using structural information in the form of structural profiles, which take into account the frequency of each state at each position, gives to our fold recognition method a significant advantage.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>shows the proportion of proteins for which at least one correct template is found among the first five (Top 5) and first ten (Top 10) results, for proteins belonging to the same superfamily, fold and metafold levels. This kind of benchmark is particularly relevant for the evaluation of template selection for comparative modeling. ORION detects on average 17.3 and 10.3% more correct templates than PSI-BLAST and HHsearch respectively, in the top 1, 5 and 10. ORION is very efficient for detecting distant protein relationships (fold and metafold levels), with 20.4% and 13.7% more templates detected than PSI-BLAST and HHsearch, respectively. At superfamily level, HHsearch performs slightly (2.1%) better than ORION. Proteins within the same superfamily but in different families share a probable common evolutionary origin (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Murzin et al., 1995</ref>) with a higher sequence similarity than at fold level. Therefore, the sensibility of sequence methods is still sufficient to detect a relationship between two homolog proteins at this level of divergence. Similar results are observed with the ROC curves at superfamily, fold and metafold levels (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>). At superfamily level, HHsearch performs slightly better than ORION for very low FPR (0–1%), but for higher FPR (1–10%) ORION clearly outperforms HHsearch. As for top ranking, ORION outperforms HHsearch and PSI-BLAST at fold and metafold levels and the difference becomes greater with the inclusion of more templates. All methods have the lowest performances at metafold level, since this level is based on a higher structural diversity among metafold classes, resulting in harder detection. These results suggest that ORION is effective for very remote homolog detection with a high success rate. At fold and metafold levels, true hits (i.e. correct detection of two related proteins) are very distant, with &lt;15% sequence identity and, hence, cannot be easily identified solely from their amino acid sequences. Therefore, methods including additional structural information, such as ORION, allow better detection at these levels. The CASP targets dataset was constituted by selecting the targets of CASP8, 9 and 10 belonging to the 'Template-based modeling' category. We kept targets with at least one template in the HOMSTRAD database within the same fold level. Thus, our CASP dataset contains 150 targets: 49 (out of 120) from CASP8, 72 (out of 111) from CASP9 and 29 (out of 67) from CASP10. This dataset is composed of 'Hard' difficulty targets, since 95% of the pairs share &lt;15% sequence identity and the true positive pair maximum sequence identity is 21.1%. The related ROC curves (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 4</ref>) show that ORION performs better than PSI-BLAST and HHsearch at detecting template structures. For 10% FPR, ORION detects 2.1 times more related proteins than HHsearch and 2.5 times more than PSIBLAST. This holds true for the top ranking comparisons (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>), with 8.6 and 22.9% more homologs detected at the top 10, compared with HHsearch and PSI-BLAST, respectively. Results of ROC curves and top rankings on CASP dataset are similar to those obtained from the HOMSTRAD dataset, except that lower performances are observed due to the overall difficulty of the CASP targets. Six examples of CASP11 targets are presented to underline the importance of the template selection in the protein structure prediction (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>). Models were generated with MODELLER (Eswar<ref type="bibr">et al., 2006</ref>) based on templates and alignments provided by ORION and HHsearch and were evaluated by the GDT-HA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Read and Chavali, 2007</ref>), GDT_TS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Zemla et al., 1999</ref>) and TM-scores (<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Zhang and Skolnick, 2004</ref>). The results show that the templates selected by ORION and HHsearch are different. Indeed, ORION selects better templates than HHsearch, which significantly increases the GDT_TS (improvement ranging from 0.7% for T0829-D1 up to 18.7% for T0855-D1). Thus, ORION provides better templates for generating models that are closer to the target structure. For T0784D1 and T0847-D1 models, ORION and HHsearch converged to identical templates (PDB codes 1byrA and 2lrgA) but the additional templates selected by ORION lead to better models than those obtained from HHsearch (4.4 and 2.6% of GDT_TS increases). The prediction of the 'Easy' target T0773-D1, based on the three templates found by ORION (PDB codes 1mlaA, 2jsxA and 1in0A), is close to the target structure, with the same orientation of beta sheets and alpha helices (<ref type="figure">Fig. 5A</ref>). For the 'Medium' T0829-D1 and 'Hard' T0855-D1 targets, the prediction of a helices positioning is more difficult but the pattern of beta strands is correct (<ref type="figure">Fig. 5B</ref>and C).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusion</head><p>We have developed ORION, a profile–profile alignment method for fold recognition based on a structural alphabet that improves remote homology detection. ORION is able to detect between 2 and 10% more homologs than the state-of-the-art method HHsearch on a balanced test set derived from the HOMSTRAD database. On another test set of target sequences from CASP8, 9 and 10, ORION systematically outperforms HHsearch and PSI-BLAST, detecting, respectively, 4.6 and 16.0% more templates at fold level (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>, mean difference in success rate for top 1, 5 and 10). Our method works particularly well for distantly related proteins due to the addition of accurate predictions of local structural information in the form of PBs. A possible improvement of ORION would be to incorporate other accurately predicted structural features, such as solvent accessibility. The combination of such structural descriptors with the PBs should provide a good approximation of the environmentORION, ORION with PBs profiles; HHsearch, HHsearch with predicted secondary structure information.<ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>. Examples of protein structure predictions based on templates detected by ORION. The structural models were obtained with MODELLER, using ORION sequence alignments. CASP targets (on the right) are colored in grey and models are on the left. Target and model structures were aligned with the TM-align program (<ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Zhang and Skolnick, 2005</ref>). The three CASP11 targets are T0773-D1 (A), T0829-D1 (B) and T0855-D1 (C)Improving protein fold recognitionpreferences for each amino acid of the target protein sequence. This information is helpful to predict structural core positions and, therefore, identify more remote homologs. For example, a series of central buried alpha helices could be identified from the target sequence with a combination of the predicted PBs and solvent accessibility descriptors, these latter restricting the number of possible template hits. Another possible improvement would touch on the weights of the different terms in the scoring function. Optimal weights were obtained from an evaluation of the successful detection rate on a balanced HOMSTRAD test set. This assessment indicates that the sequence and structural scoring terms should be equally weighted for the highest success rate (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S2</ref>). However, the weights could be dynamically adjusted according to the target sequence. Thus, while close homologs detection is based on the sequence, very remote homologs detection requires using more structural information, since the structure is more conserved than the sequence throughout the evolution. To address the issue of the weighting of the scoring terms, ORION may evaluate the difficulty of the detection in the initial search and then adjust the different parameters and perform another search in the template library. Finally, ORION and HHsearch show significant differences in template detection suggesting that they are complementary. Thus, ORION would also contribute to the improvement of the quality of metaservers and other consensus-based prediction algorithms.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Flow chart of ORION algorithm. Template library profile is generated using structural alignments of HOMSTRAD families (Step A). Query profile is obtained from PSI-BLAST and LOCUSTRA (Step B). ORION is then used to search for related proteins in the template library (Step C)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Performance of ORION, HHsearch and PSI-BLAST at detecting related proteins within the same scop level (family, superfamily and fold levels are combined), for all pairs of the HOMSTRAD dataset. Performances of ORION and HHsearch without structural information ('ORION no PB' and 'HHsearch no SS', respectively) are also shown</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Performance of ORION, HHsearch and PSI-BLAST at detecting related proteins within the same superfamily, fold and metafold levels for all pairs of the HOMSTRAD dataset</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Performance of ORION, HHsearch and PSI-BLAST at detecting related proteins within the same fold, for all pairs of the CASP dataset</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 3782 Bioinformatics, 31(23), 2015, 3782–3789 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv462 Advance Access Publication Date: 7 August 2015 Original Paper</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Success rate (%) of ORION, HHsearch and PSI-BLAST at recognizing HOMSTRAD proteins within the same superfamily, fold or metafold levels</figDesc><table>Method 
Superfamily only 
Fold only 
Metafold only 

1st 
T5 
T10 1st T5 
T10 1st 
T5 
T10 

ORION 
31.1 48.4 56.6 21.8 47.8 60.2 18.2 50.1 62.6 
HHsearch 33.2 51.6 58.2 11.4 29.5 37.0 12.5 36.7 51.3 
PSI-BLAST 13.5 22.2 37.6 
4.1 12.7 28.2 10.9 29.8 52.0 

ORION, ORION with PBs profiles; HHsearch, HHsearch with predicted 
secondary structure information. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. Success rate (%) of ORION, HHsearch and PSI-BLAST at recognizing proteins from the CASP dataset within the same fold level</figDesc><table>Method 
Fold only 

First 
Top 5 
Top 10 

ORION 
10.1 
26.2 
40.3 
HHsearch 
7.6 
23.5 
31.7 
PSI-BLAST 
2.8 
8.3 
17.4 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 3. Structural alignment scores of six targets from CASP11 with models generated from the templates ('Templ.') found by ORION and HHsearch ORION HHsearch</figDesc><table>Target 
Templ. 
GDT-TS 
GDT-HA 
TM-score 
Templ. 
GDT-TS 
GDT-HA 
TM-score 

T0829 
3f5rA 
49.63 
35.45 
0.46 
4ifsA, 4khbD3k8rA 
48.88 
33.79 
0.45 
T0855 
2vt8A 
40.22 
23.91 
0.46 
1cv8A3bbzA2ipqX 
21.52 
16.55 
0.30 
T0784 
2lrgA 3u6gA 
91.60 
78.00 
0.93 
2lrgA 4hzuS 
87.20 
69.00 
0.90 
T0769 
3e8oA1n5sA 
71.91 
51.29 
0.75 
3udcA1xhjA 
60.83 
38.92 
0.67 
T0773 
1mlaA2jsxA 1in0A 
72.39 
51.49 
0.73 
2k49A2inpL 3hluA 
66.79 
47.02 
0.64 
T0847 
1byrA 1bysA2f5tx 
73.52 
55.77 
0.80 
1byrA 4gelA 4ggiA 
70.86 
52.52 
0.78 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Y.Ghouzam et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgement</head><p>We thank Dr Olav Zimmermann and Dr Ulrich H.E. Hansmann for providing the LOCUSTRA software.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by grants from INSERM, Paris Diderot University, Sorbonne Paris Cité, Institut National de la Transfusion Sanguine and Laboratory of Excellence GR-Ex. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basic local alignment search tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">215</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="410" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3389" to="3402" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A method to identify protein sequences that fold into a known three-dimensional structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">U</forename>
				<surname>Bowie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">253</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="164" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Assessing sequence comparison methods with reliable structurally identified distant evolutionary relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Brenner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<publisher>PNAS</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6073" to="6078" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian probabilistic approach for predicting backbone structures in terms of protein blocks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>De Brevern</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="287" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A consensus view of fold space: combining SCOP, CATH, and the Dali domain dictionary</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Day</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2150" to="2160" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Profile hidden Markov models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Eddy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="755" to="763" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study on protein sequence alignment quality</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Elofsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="330" to="339" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative protein structure modeling using Modeller</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Eswar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Protoc Bioinformatics. Chapter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Unit. 5.6</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical significance of threading scores</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Fayyaz</forename>
				<surname>Movaghar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing the performance of fold recognition methods by means of a comprehensive benchmark</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Fischer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pac. Symp. Biocomput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="300" to="318" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">iPBA: a tool for protein structure comparison using sequence alignment strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J.-C</forename>
				<surname>Gelly &apos;</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measures of central tendency in rehabilitation research: what do they mean?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Gonzales</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Ottenbacher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Phys. Med. Rehabil</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Profile analysis: detection of distantly related proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Gribskov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4355" to="4358" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PICASSO: generating a covering set of protein family profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Heger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Holm</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="272" to="279" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using substitution probabilities to improve position-specific scoring matrices</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Henikoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Henikoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Appl. Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Position-based sequence weights</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Henikoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Henikoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">243</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="574" to="578" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure is three to ten times more conserved than sequence—a study of structural response in protein cores</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Illergård</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="508" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new approach to protein fold recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">358</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="89" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A short survey on protein blocks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Joseph</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hidden Markov models for detecting remote protein homologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Karplus</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="846" to="856" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhanced genome annotation using structural profiles in the program 3D-PSSM1</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Kelley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">299</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="501" to="522" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What don&apos;t we know? Science, 309, 75 Hidden Markov models in computational biology: applications to protein modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Kennedy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Norman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Krogh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">235</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1501" to="1531" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Protein fold recognition and threading (eds) Computational Structural Biology: Methods and Applications 1st Edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Mcguffin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Schwede,T. and Peitsch,M.C.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>World Scientific Publishing Co Pte Ltd</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="60" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic scoring measures for profile–profile comparison yield more accurate short seed alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Mittelman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1531" to="1539" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HOMSTRAD: a database of protein structure alignments for homologous families</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Mizuguchi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2469" to="2471" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Critical assessment of methods of protein structure prediction Round VIII</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Moult</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Critical assessment of methods of protein structure prediction (CASP)—round IX</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Moult</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Critical assessment of methods of protein structure prediction (CASP) — round x</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Moult</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Benchmarking PSI-BLAST in genome annotation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Mü Ller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">293</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1257" to="1271" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SCOP: a structural classification of proteins database for the investigation of sequences and structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Murzin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">247</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="536" to="540" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Profile–profile methods provide improved fold-recognition: a study of different profile–profile alignment methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Ohlson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="188" to="197" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding weak similarities between proteins by sequence profile comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Panchenko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="683" to="689" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequence comparisons using multiple sequences detect three times as many remote homologues as pairwise methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Park</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1201" to="1210" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Searching protein sequence libraries: comparison of the sensitivity and selectivity of the Smith-Waterman and FASTA algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Pearson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="635" to="650" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">svmPRAT: SVM-based protein residue annotation toolkit</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Rangwala</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">439</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessment of CASP7 predictions in the high accuracy template-based modeling category</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Read</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Chavali</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 8</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HHblits: lightning-fast iterative protein sequence searching by HMM-HMM alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Remmert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Twilight zone of protein sequence alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Rost</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of sequence profiles. Strategies for structural predictions using sequence information</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Rychlewski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="241" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FUGUE: sequence-structure homology recognition using environment-specific substitution tables and structure-dependent gap penalties1</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Shi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">310</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="243" to="257" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein homology detection by HMM–HMM comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Sö Ding</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="951" to="960" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein sequence comparison and fold recognition: progress and good-practice benchmarking</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Sö Ding</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Remmert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="404" to="411" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UniRef: comprehensive and non-redundant UniProt reference clusters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Suzek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1282" to="1288" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FFAS-3D: improving fold recognition by including optimized structural features and template re-ranking</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Xu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="660" to="667" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving protein fold recognition and template-based modeling by employing probabilistic-based matching between predicted one-dimensional structural properties of the query and corresponding native properties of templates</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2076" to="2082" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Processing and analysis of CASP3 protein structure predictions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Zemla</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scoring function for automated assessment of protein structure template quality</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Skolnick</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="702" to="710" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TM-align: a protein structure alignment algorithm based on the TM-score</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Skolnick</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2302" to="2309" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LOCUSTRA: accurate prediction of local protein structure using a two-layer support vector machine approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Zimmermann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H E</forename>
				<surname>Hansmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1903" to="1908" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Improving protein fold recognition</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>