
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:30+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Inferring the perturbation time from biological time course data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jing</forename>
								<surname>Yang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Manchester</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christopher</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Penfold</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Warwick Systems Biology Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Warwick</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Coventry</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Murray</forename>
								<forename type="middle">R</forename>
								<surname>Grant</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Biosciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Exeter</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Exeter</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Magnus</forename>
								<surname>Rattray</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Manchester</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Inferring the perturbation time from biological time course data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw329</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 11, 2015; revised on March 16, 2016; accepted on May 23, 2016</note>
					<note>Systems biology *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Alfonso Valencia Availability and Implementation: An R package, DEtime, implementing the method is available at https://github.com/ManchesterBioinference/DEtime along with the data and code required to repro-duce all the results. Contact: Jing.Yang@manchester.ac.uk or Magnus.Rattray@manchester.ac.uk Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Time course data are often used to study the changes to a biological process after perturbation. Statistical methods have been developed to determine whether such a perturbation induces changes over time, e.g. comparing a perturbed and unperturbed time course dataset to uncover differences. However, existing methods do not provide a principled statistical approach to identify the specific time when the two time course datasets first begin to diverge after a perturbation ; we call this the perturbation time. Estimation of the perturbation time for different variables in a biological process allows us to identify the sequence of events following a perturbation and therefore provides valuable insights into likely causal relationships. Results: We propose a Bayesian method to infer the perturbation time given time course data from a wild-type and perturbed system. We use a non-parametric approach based on Gaussian Process regression. We derive a probabilistic model of noise-corrupted and replicated time course data coming from the same profile before the perturbation time and diverging after the perturbation time. The likelihood function can be worked out exactly for this model and the posterior distribution of the perturbation time is obtained by a simple histogram approach, without recourse to complex approximate inference algorithms. We validate the method on simulated data and apply it to study the transcriptional change occurring in Arabidopsis following inoculation with Pseudomonas syrin-gae pv. tomato DC3000 versus the disarmed strain DC3000hrpA.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Gene expression time profiles can reveal important information about cellular function and gene regulation (see, e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bar-Joseph, 2004</ref>). A common experimental design is to perturb a biological system either before or during a time course experiment. In this case, a fundamental problem is to identify the precise perturbation time when a gene's time profile is first altered. In this paper we present an exactly tractable Bayesian inference procedure to infer the perturbation time by comparing perturbed and wild-type gene expression profiles. Ordering genes by their perturbation time gives valuable insight into the likely causal sequence of events following a perturbation. We demonstrate the applicability of our method by studying the timing of transcriptional changes in Arabidopsis thaliana leaves following inoculation with the V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. hemibiotrophic bacteria Pseudomonas syringae pv. tomato DC3000 versus the disarmed strain DC3000hrpA. Most methods for the analysis of differentially expressed genes are based upon snapshots of gene expression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Dudoit et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kerr et al., 2000</ref>) and there are many well-established software packages for that purpose targeted at microarray and RNA-Seq data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Anders and Huber, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hardcastle and Kelly, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Robinson et al., 2010</ref>). However, most of these methods cannot easily be extended to time course gene expression data and ignoring the temporal nature of the data is statistically inefficient. Methods have therefore been developed specifically for time-series applications. In the case of gene expression profiles under a single condition, onesample methods have been developed to discriminate differentially expressed genes from constitutively expressed genes. For example, probabilistic models have been designed for this purpose which use a likelihood-ratio test to rank genes based on a comparison between a dynamic and a constant profile (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Angelini et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kalaitzis and Lawrence, 2011</ref>). When expression profiles are available from two or more conditions then a two-sample test is more appropriate (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Conesa et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Kim et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Stegle et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Storey et al., 2005</ref>).<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Storey et al. (2005)</ref>apply a polynomial regression model to simulate the temporal behaviour of genes and a statistical test to identify differentially expressed genes.<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Conesa et al. (2006)</ref>adopt a two-step regression model in analyzing temporal profiles of genes with time treated as an extra experimental factor.<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Kim et al. (2013)</ref>apply Fourier analysis to time course gene expression data and identify differentially expressed genes in the Fourier domain.<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Stegle et al. (2010)</ref>apply a model based on Gaussian Process (GP) regression which is closely related to our proposed approach. In this model, when two time series are the same they are represented by a shared GP function but where they differ they are better represented by two independent GP functions. Binary latent variables are used to model whether a particular time interval is better represented by two independent GPs or one combined GP. More recently, the GP regression framework has been refined through use of a non-stationary covariance function and a simplified scoring approach to detect time periods of differential gene expression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Heinonen et al., 2014</ref>). Similar to the work of<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Stegle et al. (2010)</ref>, a log-likelihood ratio is used to identify time periods of differential expression. In order to better adapt to the case where unevenly or sparsely distributed times are used, they introduce a non-stationary covariance function and proposed two novel likelihood ratio tests to evaluate the likelihood at arbitrary time points. All these approaches can be used to find differentially expressed genes and some can be used to identify temporal domains where there is support for profiles being different. However, these methods do not directly score the probability of the perturbation time where two profiles first diverge, which is the aim of our approach. Although the methods of<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Stegle et al. (2010) and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Heinonen et al. (2014)</ref>can be adapted to provide an estimate of the perturbation time, e.g. by applying a thresholding procedure to their differential expression scores, we show here that direct inference of the perturbation time is a more powerful approach when that is the object of interest. In this paper, we propose a method to identify the perturbation point given data from two time course experiments. We use a nonparametric GP to describe the joint posterior distribution of two time profiles which are equal up to a proposed perturbation time. The perturbation time is then a model parameter which can be inferred. We derive the covariance function of the GP model and show that the likelihood function is exactly tractable. The posterior distribution of the perturbation time can be computed through a simple one-dimensional histogram approach, with no assumptions over the shape of the posterior distribution and no need to resort to complex approximate inference schemes. This differs from<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Stegle et al. (2010) and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Heinonen et al. (2014)</ref>in that we focus specifically on inferring the perturbation time and derive an exact approach to this problem.<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Stegle et al. (2010)</ref>creates a mixed model in prespecified time intervals with the transition between independent GPs and shared GPs. The likelihood in that case must be approximated using Expectation Propagation (EP) due to its non-Gaussian nature.<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Heinonen et al. (2014)</ref>provide a simpler approach by adopting the expected marginal log-likelihood ratio or the noisy posterior concentration ratio to construct a smooth curve indicating time periods of differential expression. However, their approach does not allow direct inference of the perturbation time. The paper is organized as follows. In Section 2, we present background on GP regression and derive the covariance function, likelihood function and posterior inference procedure for our new model. In Section 3, the algorithm is demonstrated on simulated data and subsequently applied to identify the perturbation times for Arabidopsis genes in a microarray time series dataset detailing the transcriptional changes that occur in Arabidopsis following inoculation with DC3000 versus the disarmed strain DC3000hrpA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Lewis et al., 2015</ref>) and with a brief conclusion presented in Section 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Gaussian process regression</head><p>Gaussian Processes (GPs) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Rasmussen and Williams, 2006</ref>) extend multivariate Gaussian distributions to infinite dimensionality and can be used as probabilistic models that specify a distribution over functions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Lawrence, 2005</ref>). GPs have been used in a range of gene expression applications, e.g. to model the dynamics of transcriptional regulation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Gao et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Honkela et al., 2010</ref>) and in temporal differential expression scoring (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Heinonen et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kalaitzis and Lawrence, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Stegle et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Yuan, 2006</ref>). We have a dataset D with N inputs X ¼ fx n g N n¼1 and corresponding real valued targets Y ¼ fy n g N n¼1. In the case of time course data the data are ordered such that x n ! x nÀ1 but there is no restriction on the spacing since GPs operate over a continuous domain. We allow the case x n ¼ x nÀ1 since that provides a simple way to incorporate replicates. We assume that measurement noise in Y, denoted by , is i.i.d Gaussian distributed $ N ð0; r 2 IÞ and the underlying model for Y as a function of X is f ðÁÞ, so that Y ¼ f ðXÞ þ ; and f ðXÞ represents the mean of the data generating process. Our prior modelling assumption is that the function f is drawn from a GP prior with mean function lðXÞ, covariance function KðX; XÞ and hyperparameters h.where KðX; XÞ is the N Â N covariance matrix with elements Kðx n ; x m Þ. The covariance function describes typical properties of the function f, e.g. whether it is rough or smooth, stationary or nonstationary etc. We choose the squared exponential function,</p><formula>Kðx n ; x m Þ ¼ a exp À ðx n À x m Þ 2 2l 2 ! ; (1)</formula><p>with hyper-parameters h ¼ ða; lÞ specifying the amplitude and lengthscale of samples drawn from the prior. This choice corresponds to a prior assumption of smooth and stationary functions. However, our model can be applied with any other choice of covariance function, e.g. the non-stationary covariance introduced by<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Heinonen et al. (2014)</ref>. The hyper-parameters can be estimated from the data by maximum likelihood or through a Bayesian procedure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Rasmussen and Williams, 2006</ref>). We can also consider the noise variance, r 2 , as an additional hyper-parameter to be estimated similarly. A typical regression analysis will be focused on a new input x Ã and its prediction f Ã. Based upon Gaussian properties (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Rasmussen and Williams, 2006</ref>) the posterior distribution of f Ã given data Y is pðf Ã jYÞ $ N ðl Ã ; C Ã Þ withWe see then that the posterior distribution is also a GP but it is adapted to the data. The mean prediction is a weighted sum over data with weights larger for nearby points in a manner determined by the covariance function. The posterior covariance captures our uncertainty in the inference of f Ã and will typically be reduced as we incorporate more data. A special case of GP regression, which is useful in deriving our model below, is the case where ðX; YÞ is a single point ðx p ; uÞ measured with zero noise. In this case the GP regression of all new points X given ðx p ; uÞ is then pðf ðXÞjYÞ $ N ðlðXÞ; CðX; XÞÞ;</p><formula>(2)</formula><p>with2.2 Joint distribution of two functions constrained to cross at one point</p><p>Consider the case where two time profiles, f ðXÞ and gðZÞ, evaluated at specified sets of time points X and Z, respectively, cross at the point x p with f ðx p Þ ¼ gðx p Þ ¼ u at the crossing point. Before considering the constraint we use the same GP prior for each function with hyperparameters h, f ðXÞ $ GPðlðXÞ; KðX; XÞÞ; gðZÞ $ GPðlðZÞ; KðZ; ZÞÞ:</p><p>Imposing the constraint that the functions cross at x p is equivalent to observing a data point ðx p ; uÞ with zero noise. Then pðf jX; uÞ and pðgjZ; uÞ are as in Eq. (2),</p><formula>pðf ðXÞjuÞ $ N ðl X ; C X Þ; pðgðZÞjuÞ $ N ðl Z ; C Z Þ; with l X ¼ KðX; x p Þu Kðx p ; x p Þ ; C X ¼ KðX; XÞ À KðX; x p ÞKðX; x p Þ &gt; Kðx p ; x p Þ ; l Z ¼ KðZ; x p Þu Kðx p ; x p Þ ; C Z ¼ KðZ; ZÞ À KðZ; x p ÞKðZ; x p Þ &gt; Kðx p ; x p Þ ;</formula><p>In practice, the time profiles f ðXÞ and gðZÞ are typically measured at the same time points, so that Z can be replaced by X. The value of the functions at the crossing point, u, is not known and we marginalize it out using the prior Gaussian distribution u $ N ð0; Kðx p ; x p ÞÞ. The joint probably distribution of f and g is then given by Eq. (5) below, p fðXÞ; gðXÞ ð Þ¼ ð pðf jX; uÞpðgjX; uÞpðuÞdu;</p><formula>/ exp À 1 2 f g ð ÞR À1 f g ð Þ &gt; ;</formula><formula>(5)</formula><p>so that the two functions are jointly Gaussian distributed as N ð0; RÞ with covariance given by,</p><formula>R ¼ K ff K fg K gf K gg ! ¼ K X k X k &gt; X k xp k X k &gt; X k xp K X ; 0 B B B B @ 1 C C C C A ; (6)</formula><p>where K X ; k xp and k X are abbreviations for KðX; XÞ; Kðx p ; x p Þ and KðX; x p Þ, respectively. We show an example of this covariance function in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 1</ref>(upper panel) for X in the range<ref type="bibr">[0,</ref><ref type="bibr">100]</ref>and x p ¼ 40. The detailed derivations of Eqs. (5) and</p><p>(6) are illustrated in the Supplementary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">The data likelihood under the model</head><p>We define the perturbation time x p as the point where two time profiles first begin to diverge. If the time profiles are measured without noise then it would be trivial to identify this point. However, biological time course data from high-throughput experiments are often corrupted by significant biological and technical sources of noise and our task is to infer the perturbation time given noisy time course data. In order to do that we must first derive the likelihood function under the new model. Let two sets of gene expression time course data, y c ðXÞ and y p ðXÞ, represent noisy measurements with i.i.d Gaussian measurement noise, N ð0; r 2 IÞ, from the control condition and perturbed condition, respectively. A GP prior is placed on the mean functions<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 1</ref>. Illustration of the covariance matrix, R, for two functions f and g evaluated at points evenly distributed in<ref type="bibr">[0,</ref><ref type="bibr">100]</ref>and crossing at x p ¼ 40 (upper) and the resulting data covariance matrix, b R, for time course data y c and y p from a wild-type and perturbed system respectively (lower)</p><p>Inferring the perturbation timeunderlying y c and y p and a time point x p is defined as the perturbation time point. The data model is defined as: 1. The two datasets y c and y p before x p are noise-corrupted versions of the same underlying mean function f which has a GP prior, y c ðx n Þ $ N ðf ðx n Þ; r 2 Þ; y p ðx n Þ $ N ðf ðx n Þ; r 2 Þ for x n x p :</p><p>2. The mean function for y c stays intact after x p while the mean function for y p changes to follow g, y c ðx n Þ $ N ðf ðx n Þ; r 2 Þ;</p><formula>y p ðx n Þ $ N ðgðx n Þ; r 2 Þ for x n &gt; x p ;</formula><p>where f and g are constrained to cross at x p and follow the GP described in Eq. (5). The joint distribution of y c and y p is then</p><formula>p y c ðXÞ; y p ðXÞjx p À Á ¼ exp À 1 2 y c y p ! &gt; b R À1 y c y p ! ! ; (7)</formula><p>where the covariance matrix b R can be worked out in terms of the covariance matrix R for the joint distribution of f and g defined by Eq.</p><formula>(6), b R ¼ b K y c y c b K y c y p b K y p y c b K y p y p 0 @ 1 A ; (8) with b K y c ðX1Þy c ðX2Þ ¼ K f ðX1Þf ðX2Þ þ r 2 I X 1 2 X; X 2 2 X b K y c ðX1Þy p ðX2Þ ¼ ( K f ðX1Þf ðX2Þ K f ðX1ÞgðX2Þ X 1 2 X; X 2 x p X 1 2 X; X 2 &gt; x p b K y p ðX1Þy c ðX2Þ ¼ ( K f ðX1Þf ðX2Þ K gðX1Þf ðX2Þ X 1 x p ; X 2 2 X X 1 &gt; x p ; X 2 2 X b K y p ðX1Þy p ðX2Þ ¼ K f ðX1Þf ðX2Þ þ r 2 I K gðX1Þf ðX2Þ K f ðX1ÞgðX2Þ K gðX1ÞgðX2Þ þ r 2 I X 1 x p ; X 2 x p X 1 &gt; x p ; X 2 x p X 2 &gt; x p ; X 1 x p X 1 &gt; x p ; X 2 &gt; x p 8 &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; :</formula><p>The lower panel in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 1</ref>shows the data covariance matrix b R for X evenly spread in the range ½0; 100 and with a perturbation occurring at x p ¼ 40.Since we have a simple histogram representation for the posterior distribution of the perturbation time point x p then we can easily estimate the mean, median or mode (MAP) of the posterior distribution to provide a point estimate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Posterior distribution of the perturbation point</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Pre-filtering to remove non-DE genes</head><p>In many applications a large number of genes will show no strong evidence for DE at any time or will have a low signal-to-noise due to being weakly expressed. We therefore filter genes prior to using our model. A DE gene will be better represented by two independent GPs rather than a shared GP under control and perturbed conditions. We therefore filter genes using the log-likelihood ratio r between the independent GP model (equivalent to x p approaching À1 in the perturbation model) and the integrated GP (with x p approaching þ1):We note that it is difficult to distinguish genes with a late perturbation time from those that are non-DE and our filtering approach may remove some genuine late perturbation genes. In many applications we are primarily interested on relatively early perturbations (e.g. in the application considered here) in which case this will not significantly impact the results. In the Supplementary we consider an alternative filtering approach which is based on detecting genes with time-varying profile in either the control or perturbed condition and is therefore less likely to filter out late x p genes. The method has been implemented in the DEtime R-package (github.com/ManchesterBioinference/DEtime) and also as the DEtime kernel in the GPy Python package (github.com/ SheffieldML/GPy). The running time for the whole genome (32 578 genes) for the example in Section 3.3 on a Intel(R) Core(TM) i73770 CPU of 3.40 GHz is around 11 h using the DEtime R-package.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results and discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Generating simulated data</head><p>We generated data under a range of different scenarios to explore performance and robustness to deviations from the model. We generated expression profiles from three different covariance models, one matching the one used for inference and the other two generating rougher profiles. We then add noise using three different noise models, one matching the Gaussian model used for inference and two from heavier-tailed distributions.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 2</ref>(a) shows an example of simulated data (using the profile 1 þN ð1:5Þ scenario) with two replicates and a perturbation at 4 h. The estimated posterior distribution of x p is shown in the upper panel and in the lower panel we show the GP regression function after fixing x p at the MAP value. In this case the MAP estimate for x p is very close to the ground truth. The mean, mode and median of the posterior distribution of x p for 19 simulated datasets are illustrated in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 2</ref>(b) together with the 5–95 percentile coverage of the posterior distribution. It is clear that the posterior distributions of the perturbation time cover the actual perturbation time to a great extent and that the three different point estimates are typically close to the ground truth values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">profile</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Comparison with a thresholding approach</head><p>Related methods have been introduced to identify regions of differential expression from time course data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Heinonen et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Stegle et al., 2010</ref>). Such methods can in principle also be used to identify the perturbation time by locating the first time point where the DE score passes some threshold value. Here we compare our approach to the most recently published package of this type, developed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Heinonen et al. (2014)</ref>implemented in the nsgp R-package. The nsgp package infers the differentially expressed time periods and uses four likelihood ratios: marginal log-likelihood ratio (MLL), expected marginal log-likelihood ratio (EMLL), the posterior concentration (PC) and the noisy posterior concentration (NPC) to quantify these regions. We adopt thresholds of 0.5 and 1.0 to define the initial perturbation points, respectively. The mean, median and mode of the posterior distribution of the inferred perturbation points from our method are also computed. The performance of ranking x p using each method is measured by Spearman's rank correlation coefficient with the known ground truth and the mean and standard deviation of the rank correlation coefficients across 100 dataset are illustrated in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. From the table, it is clear that the mean, median and MAP estimates from the DEtime package provide better ranking performance. The results from the nsgp package vary significantly through different ratios and thresholds, among which, EMLL with threshold 1.0 performs the best in this task, giving rank correlation coefficient of 0.67 6 0.16 when tested on the simulated profile 1 contaminated with Gaussian noise N ð1:5Þ, which is still considerably lower than the rank correlation coefficients from mean, median or mode of the DEtime package. In order to compare the performance of the algorithm on data with varied signal-to-noise ratios, we adjusted the signal amplitude hyperparameter a and compared the results from DEtime and nsgp with a ¼ 1:5; 10:0; 20:0; 30:0. Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>illustrates the results which shows the robustness of the proposed model. Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure S1</ref>shows the errorbar of the mean, median, mode from DEtime package and EMLL with thresholds of 0.5 and 1.0 from nsgp package across 100 replicates along all perturbation times for all simulated datasets. We observe that the DEtime package provides reasonable estimation of the initial perturbation time under various noise distributions whereas the performance of the EMLL ratio from nsgp package varies substantially and its performance seems to be deteriorating with later initial perturbations. We note that methods in the nsgp package are not designed specifically for the task of inferring the initial perturbation point as they were proposed for the more general problem of identifying DE regions. Nevertheless, a common application of time-series DE studies is to distinguish early and late DE events. We have demonstrated that one can obtain greater accuracy by focusing on this specific task rather than adapting a more general DE method.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Bacterial infection response in A. thaliana</head><p>To determine the biological utility of estimating perturbation times, we re-examined a large dataset recently published by<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Lewis et al. (2015)</ref>that captures the transcriptional reprogramming associated with defence and disease development in A. thaliana leaves inoculated with P. syringae pv. tomato DC3000 and the non-pathogenic DC3000hrpA mutant strain. The differences in gene expression between these two challenges is a result of the action of virulence factors delivered by the DC3000 strain into the plant cell, in this case predominately the collaborative activities of 28 bacterial effector proteins.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 3</ref>shows examples of an early and late perturbed gene identified by our method. A preliminary investigation of the perturbation times of differentially expressed genes revealed two peak times (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. S2</ref>), allowing genes to be assigned to one of three groups: early, intermediate and late perturbed genes. This initial characterization was consistent with major phase changes in the infection process, and the onset of effector mediated transcriptional reprogramming: effectors are not delivered into plant cells until 90–120 min post inoculation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Grant et al., 2000</ref>), and do not promote bacterial growth until $8 hpi, when they have effectively disabled host defence processes. This general progression is reflected in GO and pathway analysis outlined in Supplementary Section 4. The recent study by<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Lewis et al. (2015)</ref>provided a comprehensive overview of the transition from defence to disease. Thus we investigated if the calculation of perturbation times providedInferring the perturbation timesupporting evidence and additional novel insights not highlighted by<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Lewis et al. (2015)</ref>. To do so, genes were first grouped according to their GO or AraCyc Pathway annotation, and the cumulative perturbation time for each term calculated. The time at which more than 50% of the genes associated with a particular term were perturbed could then be used to rank terms, allowing a high resolution understanding of the infection process. Heat maps showing the cumulative density function (CDF) of perturbation times for each term are shown in Supplementary Figures S4–S10. For clarity, we chose to focus predominately on the earliest processes perturbed by bacterial effectors as these are predicted to be processes integral to the suppression of innate immunity. As an initial proof of concept we focussed on the perturbation of hormone pathways, as modulation of these pathways are well known to be integral to pathogen virulence strategies (<ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>). First we looked at abscisic acid (ABA) pathways, as it has previously been shown that DC3000 rapidly induces de novo ABA biosynthesis and hijacks ABA signalling pathways to promote virulence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">de Torres-Zabala et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">de Torres Zabala et al., 2009</ref>).<ref type="figure">Figure 4A</ref>shows a strong link between various GOs associated with ABA processes and early perturbation, which is what is predicted in the literature and demonstrated by<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Lewis et al. (2015)</ref>. Amongst these early ABA signalling components induced were the classic ABA responsive TFs, RD26 and both ATAIB and AFP2 were induced around 2 hpi. This prediction suggests that effectors are targeting ABA signaling very early in the infection process. Furthermore &gt; 50% of genes annotated with 'regulation of abscisic acid biosynthetic process' were perturbed by 2.3 hpi, consistent with measurable increased in de novo ABA biosynthesis 6 hpi, (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">de Torres-Zabala et al., 2007</ref>), with subsequent perturbation of 'cellular response to abscisic acid stimulus' occurring by 3.5 hpi. Two genes showing perturbation at 4.1 hpi and annotated as ABA responsive, BLHL1 and TCP14, are predicted to be targeted by the DC3000 effector AvrPto in yeast two hybrid protein–protein interaction studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Mukhtar et al., 2011</ref>). Moreover a knockout of TCP14 results in enhanced disease resistance to DC3000, consistent with TCP14 being a virulence target of effectors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Weßling et al., 2014</ref>). Subsequently, a number of ABA related pathways appear to be further targeted later in the infection. Interestingly 'negative regulation of abscisic acid-activated signaling pathway' was perturbed at 4.4 hpi suggesting this is an example of a failed host response<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Lewis et al. (2015)</ref>. Other notable perturbed ABA related ontologies included 'abscisic acid transport' (4.9 hpi), 'abscisic acid catabolic process' (5.1 hpi), 'abscisic acid binding' (5.1 hpi), 'abscisic acidactivated signaling pathway' (6.3 hpi), 'abscisic acid biosynthetic process' (7.2 hpi) and 'positive regulation of abscisic acid-activated signaling pathway' (7.2 hpi). Thus we can validate the importance of ABA in the infection process but, moreover, using our estimation of perturbation process we can see fine resolution of the increased impact of ABA biosynthesis and signaling on the infection process not evidenced by the previous analyses (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Lewis et al., 2015</ref>) as illustrated in<ref type="figure">Figure 4A</ref>. As expected, we also identified strong early perturbations in salicylic acid (<ref type="figure">Fig. 4B</ref>) related ontologies, as these are key targets for effector mediated suppression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">DebRoy et al., 2004</ref>). For further validation, we looked at ontologies associated with the hormone jasmonic acid (<ref type="figure">Fig. 4C</ref>). The JA ontologies show more delayed perturbation than ABA, particularly notably the ontologies associated with 'response to jasmonic acid' (2.3 hpi), 'jasmonic biosynthetic processes' (3.7 hpi) and 'regulation of jasmonic acid mediate signaling pathways' (3.8 hpi). This is consistent with the recent study byusing a specific targeted analysis of the samedataset which demonstrated that the JA contribution to DC3000 pathogenesis was preceded by a stronger ABA component. Thus both the ABA and JA analyses provide two examples that validate the utility of the perturbation estimation approach. Two other hormone signalling pathways, gibberellic acid (<ref type="figure">Fig. 4D</ref>) and ethylene (<ref type="figure">Fig. 4E</ref>), are predicted to play a minor role in establishment of virulence, with their contributions only occurring late in the infection process. We next identified two signalling and two primary metabolism pathways that are predicted to be important in the early conflict between plant defence and pathogen virulence: MAP kinase kinase (MAPKK) activity, regulation of protein kinase activity, NAD biosynthesis process and methionine biosynthesis (<ref type="figure">Fig. 4F</ref>/G). MAMP signaling activates an early kinase phosphorylation cascade that initiates transcriptional activation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Zipfel, 2014</ref>), however little is known about the transcriptional activation or kinases. Remarkably, 8 out of the 10 MAPKKs encoded by the Arabidopsis genome were perturbed early. Given that these MAPKKs are responsible for phosphorylation of the 20 downstream MAPKs their respective roles are naturally extensive. However, MAPKKs are strongly implicated in biotic stress. Most notably, the DC3000 effector HopF2 can interact with Arabidopsis MKK5 and most likely other MAPKKs to inhibit MAPKs and PAMP-triggered immunity. This is probably through MAPKK inhibition via ADP-ribosylation as HopF2 delivery inhibited PAMP-induced MPK phosphorylation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Wang et al., 2010</ref>). Functional evidence for a positive role of MKKs in defence comes from work in tobacco, where transient expression of AtMKK7/AtMKK9 and AtMKK4/AtMKK5 caused a hypersensitive response (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Zhang et al., 2008</ref>). However, the roles of MKKs are likely to be multifunctional and may be manipulated by effectors to promote virulence. The MAPKK, MKK1 was shown to negatively regulate immunity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Kong et al., 2012</ref>). This may be through a dual role in activating ABA signalling as AtMKK1 as well as AtMKK2 and AtMKK3, could activate the ABA responsive RD29A promoter and MKK8 could activate the RD29B promoter (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">HUA et al., 2006</ref>). Concomitant with perturbation of the MKK pathway was a significant early perturbation of a sets of genes associated with regulation of protein kinase activity. Strikingly, these genes belong to a class of evolutionarily conserved kinases functioning as metabolic sensors and are activated in response to declining energy levels. Their co-regulation is probably because they typically function as a heterotrimeric complex comprising two regulatory subunits, b and c and an a-catalytic subunit. Intriguingly, a recent study predicted that the two clade A type 2C protein phosphatases that are negative regulators of ABA signalling, ABI1 and PP2CA, negatively regulate the Snf1-related protein kinase1 and that PP2C inhibition by ABA results in SnRK1 activation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rodrigues et al., 2013</ref>). Moreover, SnRK1 and ABA were shown to induce largely overlapping transcriptional responses, thus these data reveal a previously unknown link between ABA and energy signalling during DC3000 infection. A pathway intimately linked to energy signalling and redox reactions is NAD biosynthesis, one of the most significantly perturbed pathways following effector delivery (<ref type="figure">Fig. 4G</ref>). Although powdery mildew infection of barley leaves was reported to be associated with increased NAD content more than 40 years ago (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Ryrie and Scott, 1969</ref>) and recently the identification of the fin4 (flagellin insensitive 4) mutant as aspartate oxidase (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Macho et al., 2012</ref>), a precursor of the NANP biosynthetic pathway, the role of pyridines in plant defence has received little attention. NAD and NADP play crucial roles in pro-oxidant and antioxidant metabolism and have been linked to biotic stress responses, including production of nitric oxide and metabolism of reactive lipid derivatives (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Crawford and Guo, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Mano et al., 2005</ref>). We highlight two possible, and contrasting, roles for rapid induction of NAD biosynthesis components by effectors. First, it has recently been shown that chloroplast ROS production is influenced by NADP:NADPH ratios and bacteria effector delivery rapidly suppresses a MAMP triggered chloroplast burst of hydrogen peroxide in an ABA dependent manner (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">de Torres Zabala et al., 2015</ref>). Second, poly(ADP-Ribose) polymerases (PARPs) is emerging as a key regulator of defence responses. PARPs are important NADþ consuming enzymes induced by biotic stress, polymerizing long poly(ADP-ribose) chains on target proteins including histones. Adams<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Phillips et al. (2010)</ref>reported a 40–50% decrease in NADþ 12 hpi of DC3000 challenged leaves compared to a mock<ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>. The CDF of inferred perturbation times of gene sets associated with hormone, signalling and metabolism related gene ontology terms. Abbreviations: reg., regulation; biosynth., biosynthesis; SP, signalling pathway; resp., response; act., activity; gibb., gibberellin; phos., phosphorylation; dephosph., dephosphorylation; GTASE, glucosyltransferase</p><p>Inferring the perturbation timecontrol and $50% increase in total cellular and nuclear poly(ADPRib) polymers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Adams-Phillips et al., 2010</ref>). Consistent with these results, a knockout of PARP2, which is induced by MAMPs, restricts DC3000 growth (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Song et al., 2015</ref>) demonstrating that loss of poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation activity affects the capacity of Arabidopsis to limit DC3000 growth. The second primary metabolism example we choose to highlight is the very rapid induction methionine biosynthesis pathway (<ref type="figure">Fig.  4G</ref>). Methionine is a sulphur amino acid involved in multiple cellular processes from being a protein constituent, to initiation of mRNA translation as well as functioning as a regulatory molecule in the form of S-adenosylmethionine (SAM). There are 13 unique genes associated with this ontology, and while it is outside the scope of this manuscript to explore these in detail it is worth noting that this includes DMR1 (Downy Mildew Resistance 1) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">van Damme et al., 2009</ref>), encoding homoserine kinase, which produces O-phospho-Lhomoserine, a compound at the branching point of methionine and threonine biosynthesis. Mutations in dmr1 lead to elevated foliar homoserine and resistance to the biotrophic pathogens Hyaloperonospora arabidopsidis, Oidium neolycopersici, F. culmorum and F. graminearum, although the mechanism has yet to be identified (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Brewer et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Huibers et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">van Damme et al., 2009</ref>). Thus in summary, we have validated perturbation times against previous analyses, and provide four new examples derived from examining early perturbation times of biological pathways to identify novel signalling and, particularly, primary metabolic pathways that are implicated in the transition from defence to disease following infection with DC3000. These examples provide compelling leads for further investigation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusion</head><p>We have introduced a fully Bayesian approach to infer the initial point where two gene expression time profiles diverge using a novel GP regression approach. We model the data as noise-corrupted samples coming from a shared function prior to some 'perturbation time' after which it splits into two conditionally independent functions. The full posterior distribution of the perturbation point is obtained through a simple histogram approach, providing a straightforward method to infer the divergence time between two gene expression time profiles under different conditions. The proposed method is applied to a study of the timing of transcriptional changes in A. thaliana under a bacterial challenge with a wild-type and disarmed strain. Analysis of differences in the gene expression profiles between strains is shown to be informative about the immune response. Many transcriptional perturbation experiments are focused on a single perturbation. However, multiple perturbations occurring at different times or a single perturbation targeting many conditions will be needed to unmask complex gene regulatory strategies. An interesting future line of research would be the development of GP covariance structures to uncover the ordering of events under these more general scenarios.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>We write, f ðXÞ $ GPðlðXÞ; KðX; XÞÞ; and the likelihood of Y becomes pðYjX; hÞ $ N ðlðXÞ; KðX; XÞ þ r 2 IÞ;</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>According to Bayes' rule the posterior distribution of x p is, pðx p jy c ðXÞ; y p ðXÞÞ ¼ pðy c ðXÞ; y p ðXÞjx p Þpðx p Þ ð pðy c ðXÞ; y p ðXÞjx p Þpðx p Þdx p : We assume a uniform prior on x p within the range ½x min ; x max  of the observed data. We use a simple discretization x p 2 ½x min ; x min þd; x min þ 2d;. .. ; x max  in this range. Then the posterior can be approximated as a simple summation over this grid, pðx p jy c ðXÞ; y p ðXÞÞ ' pðy c ðXÞ; y p ðXÞjx p Þ X x¼xmax x¼xmin pðy c ðXÞ; y p ðXÞjxÞ ; only requiring that we evaluate the likelihood at each grid point. There are hyper-parameters h also involved in the posterior distribution of x p which would potentially complicate matters. We choose to estimate these hyper-parameters prior to inferring x p. To do this we use maximum likelihood optimization for the case where x p approaches-1 which corresponds to the two GPs for the control and perturbed conditions being independent,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>r</head><figDesc>¼ logLðy c ðXÞ; y p ðXÞjx p ! À1Þ À logLðy c ðXÞ; y p ðXÞjx p ! þ1Þ</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>1</head><figDesc>: simulated noise-free profile generated from the model G P h ð0; b R h Þ with b R h given in Eq. (8) assuming a squared exponential covariance function (recall Eq. (1)) with the hyperparameters h ¼ fa ¼ 30:0; l ¼ 2:0g. 2. profile 2 : simulated noise-free profile generated from above model with the covariance function in the form of a matern32 covariance function (see Rasmussen and Williams, 2006) with the same hyperparameters as above. 3. profile 3 : simulated noise-free profile generated from above model with the covariance function in the form of a matern12 covariance function (an Ornstein-Uhlenbeck (OU) process) with the same hyperparameters as above. Nine simulated dataset are induced with different kinds of i.i.d noise on top of profile 1 , profile 2 and profile 3 , respectively: Gaussian N ð1:5Þ, Student-t distributed with 3 ðTð3ÞÞ and 6 ðTð6ÞÞ degrees of freedom. The simulated data are sampled every hour from 0 h until 18 h. We simulate data with a range of perturbation times x p 2 f0; 1 ;. .. ; 17; 18g and 100 different sets of data are produced for each x p value.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. (a) The shaded area in the lower panel represents the 95% credible region of the GP regression result. In the top panel we show the inferred posterior distribution for the perturbation time x p. (b) The mean, mode and median of the posterior distribution of x p with the 5-95 percentile coverage of the posterior distribution for 19 simulated dataset at different perturbation time points (dashed line shows the ground truth)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Examples of fitting the DEtime model to an early-perturbed (left) and late-perturbed gene from an experiment comparing arabadopsis leaves collected from plants infected with DC3000 (condition 1) and the mutant DC3000hrpA (condition 2). The shaded area represents the 95% credible region of the GP and the dashed line is the estimated mean of the model</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Funding</head><figDesc>M.R. and J.Y. were supported by the EU FP7 project RADIANT (Grant 305626 to M.R.) and MRC award MR/N00017X/1, M.R.G. and C.A.P. by the BBSRC [BB/F005806/1 to M.R.G. and C.A.P.] and EPSRC [EP/I036575/1 to C.A.P.] UK research councils. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1. Comparison of the means and stds of the Spearman's rank correlation coefficients of the mean, median and MAP estimation of the perturbation times from our DEtime package and different likelihood ratios with various thresholds from the nsgp package. M</figDesc><table>n represents the M ratio with a threshold of n. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">J.Yang et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disruption of poly (adp-ribosyl) ation mechanisms alters responses of arabidopsis to biotic stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Adams-Phillips</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="280" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Anders</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Huber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bats: a Bayesian user-friendly software for analyzing time series microarray experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Angelini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">415</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing time series gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Bar-Joseph</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2493" to="2503" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutations in the arabidopsis homoserine kinase gene dmr1 confer enhanced resistance to F. culmorum and F. graminearum</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Brewer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Plant Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">317</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">masigpro: a method to identify significantly differential expression profiles in time-course microarray experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Conesa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1096" to="1102" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New insights into nitric oxide metabolism and regulatory functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Crawford</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Q</forename>
				<surname>Guo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Plant Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel JAZ co-operativity and unexpected ja dynamics underpin Arabidopsis defence responses to Pseudomonas syringae infection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>De Torres</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New Phytol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">209</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1120" to="1134" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pseudomonas syringae pv. tomato hijacks the Arabidopsis abscisic acid signalling pathway to cause disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>De Torres-Zabala</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1434" to="1443" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antagonism between salicylic and abscisic acid reflects early host–pathogen conflict and moulds plant defence responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>De Torres Zabala</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="375" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chloroplasts play a central role in plant defence and are targeted by pathogen effectors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>De Torres Zabala</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Plants</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15074</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A family of conserved bacterial effectors inhibits salicylic acid-mediated basal immunity and promotes disease necrosis in plants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Debroy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9927" to="9932" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical methods for identifying differentially expressed genes in replicated cDNA microarray experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Dudoit</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Sin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gaussian process modelling of latent chemical species: applications to inferring transcription factor activities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Gao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The RPM1 plant disease resistance gene facilitates a rapid and sustained increase in cytosolic calcium that is necessary for the oxidative burst and hypersensitive cell death</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Grant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="450" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">bayseq: empirical Bayesian methods for identifying differential expression in sequence count data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Hardcastle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Kelly</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">422</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting time periods of differential gene expression using Gaussian processes: an application to endothelial cells exposed to radiotherapy dose fraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Heinonen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model-based method for transcription factor target identification with limited data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Honkela</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7793" to="7798" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Activation of the nacl-and drought-induced RD29A and RD29B promoters by constitutively active Arabidopsis MAPKK or MAPK proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Hua</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant, Cell Environ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1761" to="1770" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Powdery mildew resistance in tomato by impairment of SlPMR4 and SlDMR1</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Huibers</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">67467</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple approach to ranking differentially expressed gene expression time courses through Gaussian process regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Kalaitzis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Lawrence</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">180</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of variance for gene expression microarray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Kerr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="819" to="837" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A method to identify differential expression profiles of time-course gene data with Fourier transformation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">310</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The MEKK1-MKK1/MKK2-MPK4 kinase cascade negatively regulates immunity mediated by a mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase kinase in Arabidopsis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Kong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2225" to="2236" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic non-linear principal component analysis with Gaussian process latent variable models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Lawrence</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mach. Learn. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1783" to="1816" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptional dynamics driving MAMP-triggered immunity and pathogen effector-mediated immunosuppression in Arabidopsis leaves following infection with Pseudomonas syringae pv tomato dc3000</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Lewis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3038" to="3064" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aspartate oxidase plays an important role in Arabidopsis stomatal immunity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Macho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1845" to="1856" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protection against photooxidative injury of tobacco leaves by 2-alkenal reductase. Detoxication of lipid peroxide-derived reactive carbonyls</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Mano</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1773" to="1783" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Independently evolved virulence effectors converge onto hubs in a plant immune system network</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Mukhtar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">333</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="596" to="601" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Rasmussen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Williams</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">) Gaussian Processes for Machine Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>The MIT Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">edger: a bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ABI1 and PP2CA phosphatases are negative regulators of snf1-related protein kinase1 signaling in Arabidopsis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Rodrigues</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3871" to="3884" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nicotinate, quinolinate and nicotinamide as precursors in the biosynthesis of nicotinamide-adenine dinucleotide in barley</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Ryrie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Scott</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="679" to="685" />
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PARP2 is the predominant poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase in Arabidopsis DNA damage and immune responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Song</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A robust Bayesian two-sample test for detecting intervals of differential gene expression in microarray time series</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Stegle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="367" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Significance analysis of time course microarray experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Storey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12837" to="12842" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Downy mildew resistance in arabidopsis by mutation of homoserine kinase</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Van Damme</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2179" to="2189" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Pseudomonas syringae ADP-ribosyltransferase inhibits Arabidopsis mitogen-activated protein kinase kinases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2033" to="2044" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convergent targeting of a common host proteinnetwork by pathogen effectors from three kingdoms of life</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Weßling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Host Microbe</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="375" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flexible temporal expression profile modelling using the Gaussian process</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Yuan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Stat. Data Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1754" to="1764" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The arabidopsis map kinase kinase 7: a crosstalk point between auxin signaling and defense responses? Plant Signal</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="272" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plant pattern-recognition receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Zipfel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Inferring the perturbation time</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>