
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:53+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Isaac: ultra-fast whole-genome secondary analysis on Illumina sequencing platforms</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Come</forename>
								<surname>Raczy</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Chesterford Research Park</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina United Kingdom</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Little Chesterford</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Nr Saffron Walden</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1XL</postCode>
									<settlement>Essex</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Roman</forename>
								<surname>Petrovski</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Chesterford Research Park</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina United Kingdom</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Little Chesterford</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Nr Saffron Walden</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1XL</postCode>
									<settlement>Essex</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christopher</forename>
								<forename type="middle">T</forename>
								<surname>Saunders</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5200 Illumina Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>92122</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ilya</forename>
								<surname>Chorny</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5200 Illumina Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>92122</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Semyon</forename>
								<surname>Kruglyak</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5200 Illumina Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>92122</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Elliott</forename>
								<forename type="middle">H</forename>
								<surname>Margulies</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Chesterford Research Park</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina United Kingdom</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Little Chesterford</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Nr Saffron Walden</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1XL</postCode>
									<settlement>Essex</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Han-Yu</forename>
								<surname>Chuang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5200 Illumina Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>92122</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Morten</forename>
								<surname>Kä Llberg</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5200 Illumina Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>92122</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Swathi</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Kumar</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5200 Illumina Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>92122</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Arnold</forename>
								<surname>Liao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5200 Illumina Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>92122</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kristina</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Little</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5200 Illumina Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>92122</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Strö Mberg</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5200 Illumina Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>92122</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Stephen</forename>
								<forename type="middle">W</forename>
								<surname>Tanner</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Illumina, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5200 Illumina Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>92122</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Isaac: ultra-fast whole-genome secondary analysis on Illumina sequencing platforms</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2041" to="2043"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt314</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on December 20, 2012; revised on May 9, 2013; accepted on May 27, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Martin Bishop Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>An ultrafast DNA sequence aligner (Isaac Genome Alignment Software) that takes advantage of high-memory hardware (448 GB) and variant caller (Isaac Variant Caller) have been developed. We demonstrate that our combined pipeline (Isaac) is four to five times faster than BWA þ GATK on equivalent hardware, with comparable accuracy as measured by trio conflict rates and sensitivity. We further show that Isaac is effective in the detection of disease-causing variants and can easily/economically be run on commodity hardware. Availability: Isaac has an open source license and can be obtained at https://</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Motivated by a growing need for faster turnaround times for whole-genome sequencing (WGS) data analysis, we present here a novel alignment and variant calling pipeline that is able to rapidly align WGS data and deliver high-quality variant calls on a single server node. The aligner, Isaac Genome Alignment Software, is designed to align next-generation sequencing data with low-error rates (single or paired-ends). Speed improvements come from the fact that the Isaac aligner has been designed to take full advantage of all the computational power available on a single server node. As a result, the Isaac aligner scales well over a broad range of hardware architectures, and alignment performance improves with hardware capabilities (i.e. clock speed, number of cores, IO bandwidth and memory). The typical endto-end time to align a $30–40Â human dataset from BCL or FASTQ files to a sorted and duplicate-marked BAM file is $4 h on an Amazon High-Memory Quadruple Extra Large Instance and can be as fast as 2 h on an optimized high end server (see Supplementary Material for specs). Beyond speed and scalability, the Isaac aligner also delivers ease-of-use, flexibility and robustness. The creation of sorted, duplicate-marked BAM files from BCL or FASTQ files is done in a single operation, alleviating the need to rewrite large BAM files multiple times in a typical workflow. Additional command-line options are available to the expert user to finely control the algorithm's inputs, outputs and computational performance (Supplementary Section S1 describes the details of the Isaac aligner algorithm and its implementation). The Isaac Variant Caller calls SNPs and small indels using a Bayesian framework to compute probabilities over diploid genotype states. The Isaac Variant Caller uses an internal read realignment routine to improve variant call accuracy near indels and includes a site-specific error dependency term (Supplementary Section S2 provides a detailed explanation of the Isaac Variant Caller algorithm and implementation). The Isaac Variant Caller is designed to efficiently genotype and provide output for all variant and non-variant genomic loci as Genome VCF files (gVCF;<ref type="bibr">Saunders et al.</ref>, manuscript in preparation; https://sites.google.com/site/gvcftools/), a convention for efficiently representing whole-genome output in VCF format (http://www.1000genomes.org/node/101). To demonstrate the performance of the Isaac aligner and variant caller pipeline (Isaac), we compare the quality of the variant calls and the time-to-answer of this pipeline with the community standard combination of Burrows–Wheeler Alignment (BWA) (<ref type="bibr">Durbin, 2009, 2010</ref>) and the Genome Analysis Tool Kit (GATK) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">DePristo et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">McKenna et al., 2010</ref>). We also demonstrate that Isaac can successfully detect a clinically deleterious variant in a neonatal sample (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Saunders et al., 2012</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Software</head><p>BWA can be obtained from http://bio-bwa.sourceforge.net/. GATK can be obtained from http://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/. Isaac can be obtained from https://github.com/sequencing and is subject to the Illumina open source license.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Alignment and variant calling</head><p>The details of the alignment and variant calling pipelines are discussed in Supplementary Section S3. Briefly, the aligner/variant caller *To whom correspondence should be addressed. combinations are Isaac and BWA þ GATK. For Isaac, indel realignment is performed by the Isaac aligner, whereas for BWA þ GATK, indel realignment is performed post-alignment using GATK. For the GATK variant calling, the GATK best practices is used, which involves variant calling using the Unified Genotyper followed by filtering with the variant quality score recalibration (VQSR) protocol (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">McKenna et al., 2010</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Datasets</head><p>Two datasets were used for the analysis. The first dataset, used for the comparison of Isaac and BWA þ GATK, is a human family trio selected from the 1000 Genomes project (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Genomes Project, 2010</ref>). The trio consists of CEPH family members NA12878 (child), NA12891 (father) and NA12892 (mother). This dataset was used to evaluate the variant call quality by assessing the number of Mendelian SNP conflicts, the SNP conflict rate and the sensitivity (% callable bases) of each pipeline. The second dataset is a neonatal sample (UDT173) used for genetic disease diagnosis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Saunders et al., 2012</ref>). This dataset was used to demonstrate that Isaac can be effectively used to isolate clinically relevant variants. In addition to evaluating the quality of the variant calls, the performance in wall clock time of each pipeline on equivalent computer hardware architectures is reported. The CEPH DNA was obtained from Coriell Institute and sequenced internally on a HiSeq 2000. The neonatal sample was sequenced on a HiSeq 2500. Polymerase chain reaction-free sequencing methods were used for all the samples analyzed (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Saunders et al., 2012</ref>).<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>depicts the wall clock time for each of the pipelines. Isaac took $7–8 h as compared with 43–46 h for BWA þ GATK, demonstrating a significant performance enhancement on equivalent computer hardware. One source of this improved performance is that Isaac does not require generation of FASTQ files before alignment. In general, the generation of FASTQ files adds an additional 2–3 h to the BWA þ GATK workflow.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>compares the quality of the resulting variant calls and the sensitivity of the two pipelines. The number of conflicts was slightly larger for Isaac with a slight reduction in sensitivity. Additional alignment and variant metrics are shown in the Supplementary Section S4. To demonstrate Isaac's clinical use, we analyzed a genome with a previously confirmed novel disease-causing mutation in ATP7A, causing Menkes Disease (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Saunders et al., 2012</ref>). To show that the results of Isaac are capable of being equivalently filtered to identify the correct disease-causing mutation, we generated small variants from the same genome sequence data using Isaac. The variants went through an annotation pipeline<ref type="bibr">[</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Genomes Project, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">McLaren et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Stenson et al., 2003</ref>) and produced results that also identified the correct disease-causing variant (see<ref type="figure">Table 3</ref>Note: Filters are applied consecutively. Variants altering the protein coding sequence are those that are non-synonymous, frame shirt, stop gain/loss or splice site; medically relevant genes are those genes with variants in HGMD; variants predicted to be deleterious are determined by its polyphen score (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ramensky et al., 2002</ref>) and/or SIFT score (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Ng and Henikoff, 2003</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Hardware specifications</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Alignment and variant calling was performed on commodity hardware comprising a single computer node having 65 GB of random access memory (RAM) and containing two 8 core Intel Õ Xeon Õ CPU E5-2650 @ 2.00 GHz processors. Hyper threading was activated resulting in 32 virtual cores. To run the Isaac aligner, a minimum of 48 GB of RAM is required, whereas BWA requires a minimum of 3 GB of RAM.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Variant Effect Predictor (VEP), 1000 genomes, Human Gene Mutation Database (HGMD)] (</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>). ACKNOWLEDGEMENT I.C. wrote the manuscript and performed the analysis. C.R. and R.P. developed the Isaac aligner. C.T.S. developed the Isaac variant caller. Additional authors contributed to the data analysis. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 3. Variant filtering results with Isaac</figDesc><table>Isaac 
Applied filter 

13 212 
Transcripts with variants 
1136 
Transcripts containing two or more autosomal variants, or 
one variant on chrX or chrY; 55% allele frequency 
147 
Variants altering the protein-coding sequence 
16 
Variants overlapping a medically relevant gene 
6 
Variants predicted to be deleterious 
5 
Variants excluding splice site variants 
3 
Evolutionarily conserved variants 
1 
Homozygous/hemizygous variants (disease-causing variant) 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Wall clock times in hours for alignment, Indel realignment and variant calling for Isaac and BWA þ GATK</figDesc><table>Sample 
Yield (Gb) 
Alignment 
Indel 
realignment 

Variant 
calling 

Isaac 
NA12878 
120 
4.46 
N/A 
1.51 
NA12891 
119 
5.66 
N/A 
1.50 
NA12892 
129 
5.68 
N/A 
1.58 

BWA þ GATK 
NA12878 
120 
32.22 
3.55 
8.37 
NA12891 
119 
31.33 
3.60 
8.12 
NA12892 
129 
34.55 
3.76 
8.61 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2.</figDesc><table>Total number of SNP conflicts, SNP conflict rate and sensitivity 
(% of non-N reference sites called) of Isaac and BWA þ GATK 

Conflicts 
Conflict rate (%) 
Sensitivity (%) 

Isaac 
6318 
0.139 
94.5 
BWA þ GATK 
5315 
0.126 
95.8 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">C.Raczy et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Isaac at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framework for variation discovery and genotyping using next-generation DNA sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Depristo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="491" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A map of human genome variation from populationscale sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Genomes</forename>
				<surname>Project</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">467</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1061" to="1073" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast and accurate short read alignment with BurrowsWheeler transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Durbin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1754" to="1760" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast and accurate long-read alignment with BurrowsWheeler transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Durbin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="589" to="595" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genome analysis toolkit: a mapreduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Mckenna</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1297" to="1303" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deriving the consequences of genomic variants with the Ensembl API and SNP Effect Predictor</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Mclaren</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2069" to="2070" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SIFT: predicting amino acid changes that affect protein function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Ng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Henikoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3812" to="3814" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human non-synonymous SNPs: server and survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Ramensky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3894" to="3900" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid whole-genome sequencing for genetic disease diagnosis in neonatal intensive care units</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Saunders</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Transl. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="135" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human gene mutation database (HGMD): 2003 update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Stenson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mutat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="577" to="581" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>