
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining IsoCor: correcting MS data in isotope labeling experiments</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pierre</forename>
								<surname>Millard</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université de Toulouse</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INSA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">UPS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">INP; LISBP</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>135 Avenue de Rangueil</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-31077</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR792</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">INRA</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ingénierie des Systèmes Biologiques et des Procédés</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-31400</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR5504</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-31400</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Fabien</forename>
								<surname>Letisse</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université de Toulouse</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INSA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">UPS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">INP; LISBP</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>135 Avenue de Rangueil</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-31077</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR792</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">INRA</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ingénierie des Systèmes Biologiques et des Procédés</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-31400</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR5504</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-31400</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Serguei</forename>
								<surname>Sokol</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université de Toulouse</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INSA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">UPS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">INP; LISBP</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>135 Avenue de Rangueil</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-31077</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR792</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">INRA</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ingénierie des Systèmes Biologiques et des Procédés</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-31400</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR5504</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-31400</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jean-Charles</forename>
								<surname>Portais</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université de Toulouse</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INSA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">UPS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">INP; LISBP</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>135 Avenue de Rangueil</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-31077</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR792</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">INRA</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ingénierie des Systèmes Biologiques et des Procédés</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-31400</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR5504</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-31400</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining IsoCor: correcting MS data in isotope labeling experiments</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1294" to="1296"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts127</idno>
					<note>MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [13:02 9/4/2012 Bioinformatics-bts127.tex] Page: 1294 1294–1296 Associate Editor: John Quackenbush</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Mass spectrometry (MS) is widely used for isotopic labeling studies of metabolism and other biological processes. Quantitative applications—e.g. metabolic flux analysis—require tools to correct the raw MS data for the contribution of all naturally abundant isotopes. IsoCor is a software that allows such correction to be applied to any chemical species. Hence it can be used to exploit any isotopic tracer, from well-known (13 C, 15 N, 18 O, etc) to unusual (57 Fe, 77 Se, etc) isotopes. It also provides new features—e.g. correction for the isotopic purity of the tracer—to improve the accuracy of quantitative isotopic studies, and implements an efficient algorithm to process large datasets. Its user-friendly interface makes isotope labeling experiments more accessible to a wider biological community. Availability: IsoCor is distributed under OpenSource license at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
				<date type="submission" when="2011-11-23" />
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Mass spectrometry (MS) is extensively used for stable isotopic studies of metabolism. During the last decade, quantitative approaches—such as 13 C metabolic flux analysis—have been increasingly used in the fields of systems biology and biotechnology to provide novel biological insights and improve industrial processes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Nicolas et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Sauer, 2006</ref>). In such experiments, the different labeled forms—or isotopologues—of metabolites are quantified by the fine exploitation of isotopic clusters in MS spectra (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Kiefer et al., 2007</ref>). These clusters also contain information on all other isotopes that occur naturally in the molecules. To extract meaningful labeling information—i.e. isotopologue distribution—the contribution of naturally occurring isotopes first has to be subtracted. This can be achieved using publicly available software such as MSCorr (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wahl et al., 2004</ref>) developed under MATLAB or the algorithm developed in Perl by (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Moseley, 2010</ref>). However, the former software is only applicable to 13 C-labeling experiments and the latter is restricted to the correction of ultra-high resolution MS data for natural abundance of 13 C or 15 N. Here, we present a novel software to correct MS data, IsoCor, which includes the following features:<ref type="bibr">, 1999</ref>). For molecules containing a high number of atoms, the number of possible combinations to be calculated is high which can cause a bottleneck in the correction process. In probability theory, the probability distribution of the sum of independent variables is the convolution of their individual distributions. Therefore, the calculation can be performed faster by iteratively convolving the isotopic vectors v A = [p(A(1)),…,p(A(x)</p><p>)] of all the atoms—except those of the label tracer—where p(A(x)) denotes the natural abundance of the x-th isotope of the atom A. Finally, the contribution of the tracer is added by convolving the previous isotopic cluster i-1 times by the purity vector of the tracer (e.g. [0.01, 0.99] for a purity of 99%), and n-i times by its natural abundance (e.g. [0.9893, 0.0107] in a 13 C-labeling experiment) when it has to be corrected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Optimization algorithm</head><p>Because the measurement of isotopic clusters contains noise, Equation (1) has to be solved using a least squares method. This process can result in biases, such as the calculation of negative isotopic fractions sometimes observed with MSCorr. Because negative fractions cannot exist, they are just flattened to 0 in (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Moseley, 2010</ref>), which can lead to errors in the estimated parameters and in their interpretation. To avoid such biases, the optimization method used in IsoCor includes constraints on the isotopic fraction values. We applied the L–BFGS–B algorithm described in (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Byrd et al., 1995</ref>) and implemented in the optimize.l_bfgs_g() function of the SciPy module. The cost function of the minimization process is defined as the sum of the squared weighted errors. The lower boundary of corrected isotopic fractions is constrained to 0, and the stopping criterion is fixed to 10 −10 of relative reduction in cost value. The fitted isotopologue distribution is normalized to 1. The residuum vector may be used for an independent quality control (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Moseley, 2010</ref>). The calculation speed and correction accuracy of IsoCor were evaluated by processing several sets of simulated isotopologues with varying numbers of tracer atoms (up to 100 to stress the algorithm) and levels of labeling. The correction was performed after addition of the theoretical contributions of other naturally abundant elements to these isotopologues, with or without addition of measurement noise. The implementation was quite robust and highly accurate in both cases (see the IsoCor tutorial), showing that IsoCor provides high calculation speed together with high precision. Hence IsoCor is capable to efficiently process the large datasets that can now be acquired with modern, high-throughput MS technologies. This is critical for highthroughput metabolomics and even more for high-throughput fluxomics, which is a current major challenge for many biological applications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">USAGE</head><p>IsoCor is provided with plain text files that contain the information required to perform the correction. The file Isotopes.dat contains the values of the natural abundances of isotopes commonly found in biological compounds (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Rosman and Taylor, 1998</ref>). The files Metabolites.dat and Derivatives.dat contain the elemental formula of most common metabolites and derivative residues, respectively. These files can be easily edited and implemented according to the user's needs. Complete usage of IsoCor is detailed in the tutorial provided with the software.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>shows its graphic user interface. Briefly, the user can load datasets containing one or more isotopic clusters to be corrected (Panel C). These data files should be generated according to the format described in the tutorial. The options— i.e. selection of the isotopic tracer, correction for the isotopic purity of the label input, correction for unlabeled positions in the label input and calculation of mean enrichment—of the correction process have to be selected (Panel B) before running the calculation. When correction is applied to single isotopic clusters, the calculated</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Screenshot of IsoCor after correction of a single isotopic cluster. (A) List of metabolites; (B) correction parameters panel; (C) selection of experimental data files; and (D) calculation results.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. • Correction for any chemical element, thereby extending the range of isotopic tracers—from well-known ( 13 C, 15 N) to unusual ( 57 Fe, 77 Se, etc) isotopes—and chemical species that can be investigated. Tracer elements with more than two isotopes (e.g. 16 O, 17 O, 18 O) can be considered. • When metabolite derivatization is required for analytical purposes [e.g. derivatization of amino acids for GC-MS analysis (Wittmann, 2007)], IsoCor performs appropriate correction by taking into account the contribution of naturally occurring isotopes brought by the derivatization reagent. • IsoCor provides two options that allow flexible correction of isotopic clusters to account for (or not) the composition of the label input including: (i) correction for the isotopic purity of the label input and (ii) correction for the occurrence of unlabeled positions in the label input. These options are of particular value for specific applications (RodriguezCastrillon et al., 2008; Wittmann and Heinzle, 1999). • IsoCor calculates the mean isotopic enrichment of molecules, which refers to the molecular content in the isotope. This information is particularly useful for targeted metabolic investigations, such as the quantification of split ratios between two metabolic pathways. • IsoCor can be applied to large datasets and can deal with the increasing number of data that are generated with modern methods in a single experiment.</note>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors are thankful to the members of the MetaSys team (LISBP, Toulouse, France) for fruitful discussions and to Daphne Goodfellow for careful reading of the manuscript.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A limited memory algorithm for bound constrained optimization. Siam</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Byrd</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Sci. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1190" to="1208" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mass isotopomer distribution analysis at eight years: theoretical, analytic, and experimental considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Hellerstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Neese</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">276</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1146" to="1170" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determination of carbon labeling distribution of intracellular metabolites from single fragment ions by ion chromatography tandem mass spectrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Kiefer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">360</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correcting for the effects of natural abundance in stable isotope resolved metabolomics experiments involving ultra-high resolution mass spectrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Moseley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">139</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Response of the central metabolism of Escherichia coli to modified expression of the gene encoding the glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Nicolas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEBS Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">581</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3771" to="3776" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isotope pattern deconvolution as a tool to study iron metabolism in plants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Rodriguez-Castrillon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Bioanal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">390</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="579" to="590" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bioinformatics-bts127.tex] Page</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1296" to="1294" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Millard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isotopic compositions of the elements 1997</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J R</forename>
				<surname>Rosman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D P</forename>
				<surname>Taylor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pure Appl. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolic networks in motion: 13C-based flux analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<surname>Sauer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">62</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correcting mass isotopomer distributions for naturally occurring isotopes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Van Winden</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnol. Bioeng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="477" to="479" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New tools for mass isotopomer data evaluation in (13)C flux analysis: mass isotope correction, data consistency checking, and precursor relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Wahl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Dauner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Wiechert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnol. Bioeng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fluxome analysis using GC-MS. Microb</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Wittmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Fact</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mass spectrometry for metabolic flux analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Wittmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Heinzle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnol. Bioeng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="739" to="750" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>