
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:41+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">IsoMIF Finder: online detection of binding site molecular interaction field similarities</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matthieu</forename>
								<surname>Chartier</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Sherbrooke</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>J1H 5N4</postCode>
									<settlement>Sherbrooke</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>59650</postCode>
									<settlement>Villeneuve-d&apos;Ascq</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Etienne</forename>
								<surname>Adriansen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Telecommunication and computer network engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Télé com Lille</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lille</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rafael</forename>
								<surname>Najmanovich</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Sherbrooke</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>J1H 5N4</postCode>
									<settlement>Sherbrooke</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>59650</postCode>
									<settlement>Villeneuve-d&apos;Ascq</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">IsoMIF Finder: online detection of binding site molecular interaction field similarities</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv616</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 11, 2015; revised on September 24, 2015; accepted on October 17, 2015</note>
					<note>Structural bioinformatics *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Contact: Rafael.Najmanovich@Usherbrooke.ca Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>IsoMIF Finder is an online server for the identification of molecular interaction field (MIF) similarities. User defined binding site MIFs can be compared to datasets of pre-calculated MIFs or against a user-defined list of PDB entries. The interface can be used for the prediction of function, identification of potential cross-reactivity or polypharmacological targets and drug repurposing. Detected similarities can be viewed in a browser or within a PyMOL session. Availability and Implementation: IsoMIF Finder uses JSMOL (no java plugin required), is cross-browser and freely available at bcb.med.usherbrooke.ca/imfi.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Background</head><p>Binding site similarities capture local physico-chemical correspondences between two protein structures, in particular cavities, based on functional pseudocenters (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Shulman-Peleg et al., 2005</ref>), all surface atoms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Najmanovich et al., 2008</ref>), electrostatic surfaces (<ref type="bibr">Kinoshita et al., 2007</ref>) or molecular interaction fields (MIFs) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chartier and Najmanovich, 2015</ref>) among others. Applications include, the prediction of molecular function, detection of cross-reactivity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Weber et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Xie et al., 2009</ref>) and polypharmacological targets (<ref type="bibr">Kalliokoski and Vulpetti, 2011</ref>), druggability analyses (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Campagna-Slater et al., 2011</ref>), prediction of fragments or bioisosteric replacements (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Tang and Altman, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wood et al., 2012</ref>), drug repurposing and classification (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Allali-Hassani et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Najmanovich et al., 2007</ref>), etc. We present IsoMIF Finder, a versatile web-server for the detection of MIF similarities with IsoMIF (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chartier and Najmanovich, 2015</ref>). IsoMIF uses 6 probes (hydrophobic, aromatic, H-bond donor/acceptor and positive/negative charge) and a coarse-grained force field to define MIFs measured in cavities and a graph matching procedure to detect MIF similarities. Web-servers exist for some other methods e.g. SuMo (<ref type="bibr">Jambon et al., 2005</ref>), pdbFun (<ref type="bibr">Ausiello et al., 2005</ref>), eF-seek (<ref type="bibr">Kinoshita et al., 2007</ref>), SiteEngine (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Shulman-Peleg et al., 2005</ref>), ProBiS server (<ref type="bibr">Konc and Janežič, 2014</ref>) and IsoCleft Finder (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kurbatova et al., 2013</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Submitting a job</head><p>The query MIFs are calculated in cavities of a PDB structure. The user first provides a PDB (<ref type="bibr">Berman et al., 2007</ref>) structure by entering a 4 letter-code or uploads its own. The user then chooses to find the top N largest cavities in the PDB or to find the cavity where a specified ligand is bound. Cavities are identified with the Get_Cleft algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Gaudreault et al., 2015</ref>), our in-house implementation of Surfnet (<ref type="bibr">Laskowski, 1995</ref>). The user then selects the comparison set, either one of four pre-calculated MIF datasets or a user defined PDB structure list. The four datasets are the human purinome with 2643 MIFs calculated around purine containing ligands bound to human proteins, the scPDB with 8077 MIFs calculated in ligand binding sites (<ref type="bibr">Desaphy et al., 2015</ref>), a non-redundant PDB pisces dataset (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Wang and Dunbrack, 2003</ref>) with 14 082 entries and a dataset of 412 entries of structures of drugs bound to their primary targets (or homologue) taken from the PDB website. As mentioned, the user can alternatively provide a list of PDB structures and for each V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>621</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.specify the top N largest cavities to find or one with a specified bound ligand. The MIFs of the comparison set will be calculated in these cavities. Finally, several parameters can be defined and optimal values for each are chosen by default. We refer the readers to the original IsoMIF publication for an explanation of these parameters and other methodological details (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chartier and Najmanovich, 2015</ref>) and to the online help guide.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Cropping the cavities</head><p>The cavities identified can sometimes be very large and include nondruggable cavities. By cropping the cavities, the user ensures the query MIFs are calculated in regions of interest. For this, a 3D molecule viewer for each query cavity (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S1</ref>) shows cavity lining residues that can be unchecked, cropping the cavity volume within 3 A ˚ radius of their atoms. If the user provided a list of PDB entries for the comparison set, a table lists the cavities found with corresponding information like chains in contact, bound molecules and number of residues in contact (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>). Each cavity can be visualized within the protein structure (GIF and PNG) and the user can select only the cavities of interest for the comparison.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Results page</head><p>A results table for each query cavity lists the top hits found (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>) and can be downloaded in CSV format. The top hits can be sorted by Tanimoto similarity or number of nodes (similar probes detected). Additional data provided includes Z-score, the search space (number of grid points sampled), the crystalized ligand around which the hit MIF is calculated (for purinome, scPDB and drug-target datasets only), the PFAM family, Uniprot and protein name. A snapshot of the detected similarities can be visualized in the browser with a GIF or PNG image. Downloadable PyMOL sessions show the query (green) and target hit (cyan) structures with bound molecules and MIF similarities, all superimposed using the transformation matrix that optimally minimizes the pairwise distance between matched probes. The similar probes are shown using spheres coloured by interaction type: hydrophobic (cyan), aromatic (orange), H-bond donor (blue), acceptor (red), positive (green) and negative (magenta) charge. Bigger spheres represent probes from the query protein and smaller spheres from the comparison set protein. Semi-transparent spheres represent the initial MIFs of each protein. The matched probes and the initial MIFs for each probe have individual selections in PyMOL making it easy to analyse the different objects individually (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S4</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Example application</head><p>High level of binding site MIF similarity suggests the cavities might share similar molecular functions. In other words, a drug bound in a one could bind the other. Experimental evidence suggests that carbonic anhydrases can be cross-reactivity targets of celecoxib, a COX-2 specific inhibitor and that this approved drug could be repurposed to treat glaucoma (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Weber et al., 2004</ref>). When using the celecoxib binding site of COX-2 (PDB 6COX) as query, carbonic anhydrase XIV (PDB 1RJ6) is found within the top hits of the drug-target dataset (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>; created using the PyMOL session of the MIF similarities). Both ligands have a sulfonamide group surrounded by histidines in both proteins causing the negative charge similarities (magenta spheres). In 6COX, HIS90 could interact with the sulfonamide via hydrogen bonding while in 1RJ6 the interaction would be mediated by a Zn 2þ atom (small grey sphere) coordinated by HIS94 119 and 96. Hydrogen bond donor and acceptor similarities were also found near the sulfonamide (not shown for clarity). The hydroxyl of THR199 in 1RJ6 creates a region favorable for H-bond acceptor probes, similarly to the amine of GLN192 in 6COX. The same detailed analysis could be done for other probes. This example highlights how the results of IsoMIF Finder can be used to analyse binding site similarities, the underlying structural determinants in a context of drug repurposing and analysis of cross-reactivity.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Bioinformatics, 32(4), 2016, 621–623doi:10.</head><figDesc>1093/bioinformatics/btv616 Advance Access Publication Date: 25 October 2015 Applications Note</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Negatively charged probe similarities between celecoxib binding site of PDB 6COX and acetazolamide binding site of 1RJ6</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.Chartier et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural and chemical profiling of the human cytosolic sulfotransferases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Allali-Hassani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">97</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural chemistry of the histone methyltransferases cofactor binding site</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Campagna-Slater</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="612" to="623" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of binding site molecular interaction field similarities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Chartier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Najmanovich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1600" to="1615" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NRGsuite: a PyMOL plugin to perform docking simulations in real time using FlexAID</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Gaudreault</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">458</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">IsoCleft Finder—a web-based tool for the detection and analysis of protein binding-site geometric and chemical similarities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Kurbatova</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of 3D atomic similarities and their use in the discrimination of small molecule protein-binding sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Najmanovich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of binding site similarity, smallmolecule similarity and experimental binding profiles in the human cytosolic sulfotransferase family</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Najmanovich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="104" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SiteEngines: recognition and comparison of binding sites and protein-protein interfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Shulman-Peleg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="341" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge-based fragment binding prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Tang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Altman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003589</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PISCES: a protein sequence culling server</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Dunbrack</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1589" to="1591" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unexpected nanomolar inhibition of carbonic anhydrase by COX-2-selective celecoxib: new pharmacological opportunities due to related binding site recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Weber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="550" to="557" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pharmacophore fingerprint-based approach to binding site subpocket similarity and its application to bioisostere replacement</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Wood</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2031" to="2043" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug discovery using chemical systems biology: identification of the protein-ligand binding network to explain the side effects of CETP inhibitors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Xie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000387</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IsoMIF Finder</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>