
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:54+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology JEPETTO: a Cytoscape plugin for gene set enrichment and topological analysis based on interaction networks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">7 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Charles</forename>
								<surname>Winterhalter</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Systems &amp; Synthetic Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Evry Val-d&apos;Essonne</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91000</postCode>
									<settlement>Evry</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pawel</forename>
								<surname>Widera</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Systems &amp; Synthetic Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Evry Val-d&apos;Essonne</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91000</postCode>
									<settlement>Evry</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Natalio</forename>
								<surname>Krasnogor</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Systems &amp; Synthetic Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Evry Val-d&apos;Essonne</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91000</postCode>
									<settlement>Evry</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computing Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Newcastle University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>NE1 7RU</postCode>
									<settlement>Newcastle</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology JEPETTO: a Cytoscape plugin for gene set enrichment and topological analysis based on interaction networks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1029" to="1030"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">7 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt732</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 30, 2013; revised on November 25, 2013; accepted on December 13, 2013</note>
					<note>Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>JEPETTO (Java Enrichment of Pathways Extended To TOpology) is a Cytoscape 3.x plugin performing integrative human gene set analysis. It identifies functional associations between genes and known cellular pathways, and processes using protein interaction networks and topological analysis. The plugin integrates information from three separate web servers we published previously, specializing in enrichment analysis, pathways expansion and topological matching. This integration substantially simplifies the analysis of user gene sets and the interpretation of the results. We demonstrate the utility of the JEPETTO plugin on a set of misregulated genes associated with Alzheimer&apos;s disease. Availability: Source code and binaries are freely available for down-load at http://apps.cytoscape.org/apps/jepetto, implemented in Java and multi-platform. Installable directly via Cytoscape plugin manager. Released under the GNU General Public Licence.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The integration of heterogeneous data derived from functional genomics experiments is an essential step in providing insights into biological systems behaviour, especially disease-related processes. Nowadays this integration is becoming easier, thanks to extendable network analysis platforms such as Cytoscape (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Shannon et al., 2003</ref>). Although several existing Cytoscape plugins do functional analysis, not many go beyond performing a 'term-based' search or link ontology. In contrast, JEPETTO integrates gene sets with pathways and the molecular interaction networks they are embedded in. It uses information from three different web servers to perform network enrichment, pathways expansion and topological analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">IMPLEMENTATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Input</head><p>Our plugin operates on target gene set provided by a user. The list of gene names can be given directly or imported from an existing network created in Cytoscape (many gene identifier formats are accepted, e.g. Ensembl, HGNC, Entrez, UniProt). The other main parameters are the reference annotation database (KEGG, BioCarta, GO, InterPro, etc.) and the molecular interaction network (STRING or a user-defined network).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Processing</head><p>There are two types of analysis available in JEPETTO based on: (1) enrichment or (2) topology. For the enrichment analysis, EnrichNet and PathExpand web servers are used and the topological analysis is performed with TopoGSA. The plugin communicates with the web servers as shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 1A</ref>, and integrates the results within the Cytoscape environment. This single-point integration eliminates the need to use the web servers individually and simplifies repeated analysis on previously obtained results. EnrichNet (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Glaab et al., 2012</ref>) maps the input gene set onto a molecular interaction network and, using a random walk, scores distances between the genes and pathways/processes in a reference database. This network-based association score (XD-score) is relative to the average distance to all pathways and represents a deviation (positive or negative) from the average distance. As an option, EnrichNet provides XD-scores for 60 human tissues, derived from tissue-specific gene expression data. PathExpand (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Glaab et al., 2010a</ref>) maps the input pathway/process onto the human protein–protein interaction network and extends it with proteins that (1) are strongly associated with the pathway nodes; and (2) increase the pathway compactness by connecting its disconnected members. The exact expansion acceptance criteria can be modified in the plugin advanced options. TopoGSA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Glaab et al., 2010b</ref>) maps the input gene set on an interaction network, computes its topological signature and compares it against signatures of pathways/processes in a reference database. The topological signature is built from five distinct *To whom correspondence should be addressed.properties, among others: network density, centrality of nodes in the network or their tendency to form clusters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Output</head><p>The enrichment analysis finds pathways significantly associated with the input gene set (in terms of XD-score). When a pathway is selected, its expansion is constructed and a network of interactions between the gene set, pathway and expansion is generated (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>). The topology analysis finds pathways with a pattern of interactions most similar to those in the input gene set and visually compares their topological properties (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CASE STUDY</head><p>We have retrieved the Alzheimer's disease-related set of genes from Phenopedia (http://www.hugenavigator.net). The enrichment analysis of this set assigned the highest XD-score (1.94) to the Alzheimer's disease pathway. The pathway was expanded and the disease environmental network (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>) was generated. The following genes were added as the expansion: TMED10, METTL2B, APH1B, MMP17 and PITX3. The first three of these genes have been experimentally characterized as direct Alzheimer's cofactors (additional details in Supplementary Information). MMP17 protein family was found to play a role in-amyloid proteins degradation related to the increase of mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK), the main trigger of the Alzheimer's disease (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Yoshiyama et al., 2000</ref>). PITX3 is involved in transcription of a micro-RNA that is known to have reduced expression levels in Parkinson's diseased brains and may also contribute to the Alzheimer's pathology development (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Shioya et al., 2010</ref>). The topological analysis of the largest connected component of the Alzheimer's disease environmental network confirmed the previous findings. Among the most topologically similar pathways were Wnt signalling pathway related to MMP17 and Parkinson's disease pathway related to PITX3. It also highlighted similarity to sclerosis and diabetes and several environmental information processing pathways (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>and Supplementary Information).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">SUMMARY</head><p>JEPETTO integrates three different network-centric human gene set analysis methods under a single interface of the Cytoscape 3.x environment. It performs enrichment and topological analysis based on the interaction networks. It displays the target gene set within its interaction environment and identifies possible gene cofactors and topologically related pathways and processes that are unlikely to be detected using traditional term-based analysis. In the case study of the Alzheimer's disease-associated genes, JEPETTO was able to identify a number of known disease cofactors and suggested directions for further investigation.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council [EP/J004111/1]. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Target gene set within Alzheimer's disease environmental network. Grey nodes represent the input set, green the pathway and blue the overlap between them. Orange nodes represent the expansion. Interactions between the input set and added nodes are highlighted: edges to pathway nodes are green and edges to expansion nodes are orange</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Comparative analysis of topological properties. The red square next to the Wnt signalling pathway represents the target network</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">C.Winterhalter et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extending pathways and processes using molecular interaction networks to analyse cancer genome data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Glaab</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">597</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TopoGSA: network topological gene set analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Glaab</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1271" to="1272" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EnrichNet: network-based gene set enrichment analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Glaab</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="451" to="457" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Shannon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2498" to="2504" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aberrant microRNA expression in the brains of neurodegenerative diseases: miR-29a decreased in Alzheimer disease brains targets neurone navigator 3</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Shioya</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuropath. Appl. Neuro</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">320</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selective distribution of matrix metalloproteinase-3 (MMP-3) in Alzheimer&apos;s disease brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Yoshiyama</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Neuropathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>