
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:37+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">JSpeciesWS: a web server for prokaryotic species circumscription based on pairwise genome comparison</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<surname>Richter</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Ribocon GmbH</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Fahrenheitstraße. 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>28359</postCode>
									<settlement>Bremen, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ramon</forename>
								<surname>Rossell O-M Ora</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Marine Microbiology Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Mediterranean Institute for Advanced Studies</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>C/ Miquel Marqué s, 21</addrLine>
									<postCode>07190</postCode>
									<settlement>Esporles</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Frank</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Oliver</forename>
								<surname>Glö Ckner</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Microbial Genomics and Bioinformatics Research Group</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Celsiusstraße 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>28359</postCode>
									<settlement>Bremen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Life Sciences and Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jacobs University gGmbH Bremen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Ring 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>28759</postCode>
									<settlement>Bremen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jö</forename>
								<surname>Rg Peplies</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Ribocon GmbH</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Fahrenheitstraße. 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>28359</postCode>
									<settlement>Bremen, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">JSpeciesWS: a web server for prokaryotic species circumscription based on pairwise genome comparison</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv681</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on September 10, 2015; revised on October 29, 2015; accepted on November 12, 2015</note>
					<note>Genome analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: John Hancock Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online. Contact: mrichter@ribocon.com</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>JSpecies Web Server (JSpeciesWS) is a user-friendly online service for in silico calculating the extent of identity between two genomes, a parameter routinely used in the process of poly-phasic microbial species circumscription. The service measures the average nucleotide identity (ANI) based on BLASTþ (ANIb) and MUMmer (ANIm), as well as correlation indexes of tetra-nucleotide signatures (Tetra). In addition, it provides a Tetra Correlation Search function, which allows to rapidly compare selected genomes against a continuously updated reference database with currently about 32 000 published whole and draft genome sequences. For comparison, own genomes can be uploaded and references can be selected from the JSpeciesWS reference database. The service indicates whether two genomes share genomic identities above or below the species embracing thresholds, and serves as a fast way to allocate unknown genomes in the frame of the hitherto sequenced species. Availability and implementation: JSpeciesWS is available at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>DNA-DNA-hybridization (DDH) measures the degree of genomic similarity between two pools of DNA molecules. Despite that distinct DDH determination methods frequently lead to different results, since nearly 50 years it is considered as the gold standard for species delineation (Rossell o-M ora and<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Amann, 2015</ref>). In times of cost-efficient sequencing with scientists having easy access to thousands of publicly available genome sequences, the species delineation based on user friendly computational pairwise genome comparisons to determine overall genome relatedness indices<ref type="bibr">[OGRI, (Chun and Rainey, 2014</ref>)] has emerged. This approach has already been widely accepted by the scientific community (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Colston et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Li et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Lugli et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Oren and Garrity, 2014</ref>) and specialized tools like the stand-alone software JSpecies (Richter and Rossell o-M ora, 2009) or similar solutions (<ref type="bibr">MeierKolthoff et al., 2013</ref>) have proven to provide valuable OGRI results. Here we present the JSpecies Web Server (JSpeciesWS) a webbased implementation of the core features of the original JSpecies software for easy user-access and extended functionality. It represents the latest development of JSpecies in terms of usability,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>929</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</p><p>Bioinformatics,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>JSpeciesWS has been implemented with the Google Web Toolkit (http://www.gwtproject.org/) version 2.7.0 and uses a TwitterBootstrap clone (https://github.com/gwtbootstrap3/gwtbootstrap3) for the user interface elements. Imported sequences get validated by using the FastaValidator version 1 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Waldmann et al., 2014</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Average nucleotide identity based on BLAST1</head><p>The average nucleotide identity based on BLAST þ (ANIb) calculation is implemented as described by Goris et al. (2007). In contrast to the original JSpecies stand-alone implementation, the web server uses BLAST version 2.2.29 þ (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Camacho et al., 2009</ref>) instead of BLAST version 2.2.26 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Altschul et al., 1997</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Average nucleotide identity based on MUMmer</head><p>For average nucleotide identity based on MUMmer (ANIm) calculation, the dnadiff script of the MUMmer tool version 3.0 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kurtz et al., 2004</ref>) is used instead of a self-written parser used by the original JSpecies stand-alone implementation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Tetra-nucleotide signature correlation index</head><p>Tetra is an alignment-free parameter correlating with ANI, and implemented in the same way as the original JSpecies stand-alone (Richter and Rossell o-M ora, 2009).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Tetra Correlation Search</head><p>TCS is a new feature of JSpeciesWS that allows rapid comparisons against the JSpeciesWS reference database, providing a list of the most similar genomes based on their resulting Tetra-nucleotide signature correlation index.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Genomes reference database</head><p>The internal JSpeciesWS genome database resembles NCBI's genomic sequence data taken from ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genomes/ genbank and includes all primary submissions of assembled genome sequences and their associated annotation data. Currently, more than 32 000 prokaryotic genomes at different stages of finishing are included. For each entry, taxonomic information is provided for the field's domain, phylum, class, order, family, genus and species. Further contextual data extracted from the original entry (if available) include genome size, guanine-cytosine content, Gram staining, shape, arrangement, endospores formation, motility, salinity, oxygen, habitat and temperature range.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Usage</head><p>JSpeciesWS does not require user registration. By visiting the website, a session is generated linked to a dedicated genome cart. The genome cart can be filled with own genome uploads and/or genomes can be added from the JSpeciesWS reference database. The cart (session) expires automatically after a period of 14 days of inactivity (no revisit based on session code provided) and all data will be deleted. The limit of genomes per cart is currently set to 15. Pairwise ANIb, ANIm or Tetra calculations can be performed between all genomes in the cart (all vs all) or, alternatively, only one genome of the cart can be selected for comparison against all other genomes in the cart to reduce calculation time. In addition, a TCS can be performed for each genome in the cart against the complete JSpeciesWS reference database of all published whole and draft genomes. After starting an analysis, the status field is regularly updated and the user is finally informed about a finished calculation by a pop-up message. In addition, the user can provide an e-mail address to become informed about the completion of the calculations. A all versus all comparison of 15 genomes (210 calculations) takes on the current system about 2 h based on ANIb, 30 min based on ANIm and 10 min based on Tetra. All results can be revisited, exported for further processing and shared among users.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusion</head><p>Recent studies have shown that electronic (in silico) pairwise OGRI can replace standard laboratory-based DDH in order to simplify, and at the same time substantiate, this central aspect of prokaryotic species delineation. In addition, OGRI allows taxonomists to quickly verify the species affiliation of any public genome sequence and to identify wrongly annotated submissions. JSpeciesWS will help to further propagate this approach by providing fast and easy access to the corresponding analyses and a comprehensive genomes reference database.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This research leading to these results has received funding from the European Community's Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013) under grant agreement no 311975. This publication reflects the views only of the author, and the European Union cannot be held responsible for any use which may be made of the information contained therein. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>32(6), 2016, 929–931 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv681 Advance Access Publication Date: 16 November 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table>flexibility, and efficiency. An online reference database of all pub-
lished whole and draft genomes (about 32 000) with pre-calculated 
OGRI results has been added and can be searched in seconds based 
on genome comparison using the new Tetra Correlation Search 
(TCS) function. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.Richter et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3389" to="3402" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BLASTþ: architecture and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Camacho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">421</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating genomics into the taxonomy and systematics of the Bacteria and Archaea</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Chun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Rainey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="316" to="324" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Bioinformatic genome comparisons for taxonomic and phylogenetic assignments using aeromonas as a test case</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Colston</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page">2136</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA–DNA hybridization values and their relationship to whole-genome sequence similarities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Goris</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Versatile and open software for comparing large genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kurtz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship of the whole genome sequence identity to DNA hybridization varies between genera of prokaryotes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigation of the evolutionary development of the genus bifidobacterium by comparative genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Lugli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6383" to="6394" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome sequence-based species delimitation with confidence intervals and improved distance functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Meier-Kolthoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">60</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Then and now: a systematic review of the systematics of prokaryotes in the last 80 years</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Oren</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Garrity</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shifting the genomic gold standard for the prokaryotic species definition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Richter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Rossell O-M Ora</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19126" to="19131" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Past and future species definitions for Bacteria and Archaea</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Rossell O-M Ora</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Amann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Appl. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FastaValidator: an open-source Java library to parse and validate FASTA formatted sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Waldmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Res. Notes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">365</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>