
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:49+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis KalignP: Improved multiple sequence alignments using position specific gap penalties in Kalign2</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nanjiang</forename>
								<surname>Shu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biochemistry and Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Stockholm Bioinformatics Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Center for Biomembrane Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep4">Swedish e-science Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stockholm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>106 91</postCode>
									<settlement>Stockholm</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Arne</forename>
								<surname>Elofsson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biochemistry and Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Stockholm Bioinformatics Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Center for Biomembrane Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep4">Swedish e-science Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stockholm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>106 91</postCode>
									<settlement>Stockholm</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis KalignP: Improved multiple sequence alignments using position specific gap penalties in Kalign2</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1702" to="1703"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr235</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 2, 2011; revised on March 25, 2011; accepted on April 8, 2011</note>
					<note>[13:38 14/5/2011 Bioinformatics-btr235.tex] Page: 1702 1702–1703 Associate Editor: Martin Bishop of KalignP is available under the GNU General Public License, Version 2 or later from the same website. Contact: arne@bioinfo.se Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Kalign2 is one of the fastest and most accurate methods for multiple alignments. However, in contrast to other methods Kalign2 does not allow externally supplied position specific gap penalties. Here, we present a modification to Kalign2, KalignP, so that it accepts such penalties. Further, we show that KalignP using position specific gap penalties obtained from predicted secondary structures makes steady improvement over Kalign2 when tested on Balibase 3.0 as well as on a dataset derived from Pfam-A seed alignments. Availability and Implementation: KalignP is freely available at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The alignment of multiple sequences is essential for many tasks in sequence analysis, e.g. protein structure and function prediction, similarity search and phylogenetic analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Pei, 2008</ref>). Due to the importance of multiple sequence alignment (MSA) in a variety of biological applications, a number of programs have been developed. Three aspects are usually considered when developing an MSA program, the alignment accuracy, the computational speed and the memory usage. Kalign2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Lassmann et al., 2009</ref>) is one of the fastest MSA methods, and still the alignment accuracy is comparable to many of the slower methods. Moreover, it produces high quality alignments consistently when aligning large number of sequences, i.e. Kalign2 is well suited for MSA tasks in large-scale genome analysis. However, in contrast to other methods such as ClustalW (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Thompson et al., 1994</ref>), Kalign2 does not allow externally supplied position specific gap penalties (ESPSGP).<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Thompson et al. (1994)</ref>showed that gaps occur far more often between major secondary structure elements than within. Also gaps are much more frequent in disordered regions of proteins. For integral transmembrane (TM) proteins, residues are more conserved at TM regions and few gaps are allowed within (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Kauko et al., 2008</ref>). * To whom correspondence should be addressed. Further, the inclusion of ESPSGP allows some inclusion of expertise knowledge into the alignment procedure. Here, we introduce KalignP as a modified version of Kalign2 that accepts ESPSGP. Unlike ClustalW, where ESPSGP is only applicable to profile alignments, KalignP incorporates ESPSGP into sequences and forward them to the full progressive alignment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Implementation of KalignP</head><p>KalignP inherits the syntax of Kalign2 but extends its functionality for protein sequence alignment. The ESPSGP can be supplied in the Enhanced Fasta format (see Supplementary Material) so that gap penalties are set individually for each position. The default gap penalties will be replaced by ESPSGP when aligning two single sequences. Gap penalties of profiles (consensus of sequences) are calculated in the same way as Kalign2 but ESPSGP will be used instead of the constant gap penalty. KalignP also inherits one of the best merits of Kalign2: low memory consumption. Since KalignP uses the same progressive method as Kalign2, it consumes almost the same amount of memory as Kalign2. KalignP takes about 50% more CPU time than Kalign2 for the alignment itself. The KalignP package, including automatic secondary structure prediction and ESPSGP calculation from secondary structures predicted by PSIPRED_single (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Jones, 1999</ref>) (version 3.2), is about 15 times slower than Kalign2, but this speed is still comparable to many other MSA programs such as ClustalW and Muscle (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Edgar, 2004</ref>), see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>and Supplementary Material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Estimation of ESPSGP from predicted secondary structure</head><p>The principle to estimate ESPSGP from the predicted secondary structure is simple: increase the gap penalty at helices and sheets while lowering the gap penalty at coils. ESPSGP for position i is set as</p><formula>ESPSGP(i) = GP default * 1.0+m(i) (1)</formula><p>where m(i) is a variable to adjust the gap penalty at residue i based on the predicted structural information, see Supplementary Material for details.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>We benchmarked KalignP using gap penalties from predicted secondary structure with other methods on Balibase 3.0. KalignP outperformed Kalign2 on all five reference-sets (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). The results were evaluated by SP (Sum-of-Pairs) score and TC (Total Columns) score (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Thompson et al., 2005</ref>). SP score is the sum of scores of the projected pairwise alignments and TC score is the sum of scores of each column for a multiple alignment. The4.51e-5 and 0.0167 for SP and TC scores, respectively, with the alternative hypothesis that true difference in the means of Kalign2 and KalignP is less than 0. The paired t-test was performed by R. Here, KalignP were optimized on Balibase 3.0 using a 3-fold crossvalidation (see Supplementary Material). The largest improvement was made on RV50 (for proteins with insertions) where KalignP made a 2.0% improvement for SP score and 2.4% for TC score (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). Only two methods in the benchmark outperformed KalignP, T_coffee (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Notredame et al., 2000</ref>) and Probcons (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Do et al., 2005</ref>) but these methods are much slower. Note that the speed of KalignP for alignment alone is comparable to Kalign2. However, including the time for secondary structure prediction and ESPSGP calculation it is slower but still comparable to<ref type="bibr">ClustalW and Muscle (Edgar, 2004</ref>). KalignP made a steady improvement on the alignment of TM proteins as well. As shown in the benchmark on ref7 (for TM proteins) of Balibase 3.0, KalignP outperformed Kalign2 by 1.6% for SP score and 1.8% for TC score (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). However, the significance of the improvement as shown by the t-test is not strong (P-values are 0.0623 and 0.278 for SP and TC scores, respectively). This is most likely because the sample size is too small. The Balibase 3.0 ref7 contains only eight alignments and the results for KalignP were obtained by optimizing parameters on all these alignments. Therefore, over-training might be an issue here. To test the robustness of KalignP on the alignment of TM proteins, we created another reference dataset PfamA-mem which was derived from Pfam-A (version 24.0) seed alignments and filtered by matching the key word 'transmembrane' in the 'DE' record. The same parameters optimized from ref7 were used to test these 51 alignments in PfamA-mem (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S3</ref>for a list of these 51 Pfam-A alignments). A similar improvement of KalignP over Kalign2 was obtained (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). The P-values for paired t-test are 2.75e-4 and 3.85e-3 for SP and TC scores, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Here, we present KalignP, a method that allows externally supplied position specific gap penalty, and maintains the high speed and accuracy of Kalign2. Using gap-penalties from predicted secondary structures a steady improvement is seen. Further, KalignP is more flexible than Kalign2, as researchers can modify the behavior of alignment using other knowledge.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: Swedish Research Council (VR-NT 2009-5072, VR-M 2007-3065); SSF (the Foundation for Strategic Research); the EU 7'th Framework Program by support to the EDICT project (contract No: FP7-HEALTH-F4-2007-201924). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>P-values of paired t-test of all 386 alignments in Balibase 3.0 are</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1.</figDesc><table>Performance of multiple sequence alignment methods on 
Balibase 3.0 (using core blocks) in SP score. All SP scores are multiplied 
with 100 for easy reading 

Method CPU a (s) 
RV11 b RV12 c RV20 d RV30 e RV40 f RV50 g All 

Kalign2 
57 
64.4 91.3 91.9 82.5 88.4 81.9 83.6 
KalignP 
95 (974 h ) 65.6 91.8 92.4 83.4 89.8 83.9 84.6 
Mafft 
223 
56.0 89.6 91.1 84.0 87.8 84.9 81.8 
ClustalW 1281 
58.2 88.4 88.8 77.1 78.9 76.9 78.6 
Muscle 
1281 
65.7 92.3 91.5 84.2 86.5 85.3 84.4 
T_coffee 25 293 
73.0 94.4 93.4 87.1 89.2 90.2 87.8 
Probcons 26 085 
74.0 94.6 93.7 87.5 90.3 90.1 88.3 

a The CPU time refers to single threaded process running on a Linux box with Intel 

quad-core 2.50 GHz CPU and 4 GB memory. 
b Reference 1: equi-distant sequences with &lt;20% identity. 
c Reference 1: equi-distant sequences with 20–40% identity. 
d Reference 2: families aligned with highly divergent 'orphan' sequences. 
e Reference 3: subgroups with &lt;25% residue identity between groups. 
f Reference 4: sequences with N/C-terminal extensions. 
g Reference 5: sequences with internal insertions. 
h KalignP running time including secondary structure prediction and ESPSGP 

calculation. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2.</figDesc><table>Benchmark on ref7 (transmembrane proteins) of Balibase 3.0 (left) 
and PfamA-mem using 51 alignments of transmembrane proteins derived 
from Pfam-A seed alignments (right) 

Method 
CPU a (s) 
SP 
TC 
CPU a (s) 
SP 
TC 

Kalign2 
5 
89.2 
43.6 
3 
84.6 
59.3 
KalignP 
9 (64 b ) 90.8 
45.4 
4 (88 b ) 86.2 
62.6 
Mafft 
12 
87.0 
35.0 
20 
83.6 
56.6 
ClustalW 
155 
79.2 
40.4 
81 
84.0 
59.3 
Muscle 
93 
88.7 
43.1 
59 
85.7 
61.3 
T_coffee 2946 
90.8 
50.2 
3093 
88.4 
66.8 
Probcons 3217 
92.4 
53.0 
1441 
88.6 
67.1 

a The CPU time refers to single threaded process running on a Linux box with Intel 

quad-core 2.50 GHz CPU and 4 GB memory. 
b KalignP running time including secondary structure prediction and ESPSGP 

calculation. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1703"> at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ProbCons: probabilistic consistency-based multiple sequence alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Do</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="330" to="340" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Edgar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1792" to="1797" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein secondary structure prediction based on position-specific scoring matrices</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">292</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coils in the membrane core are conserved and functionally important</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Kauko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">380</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="170" to="180" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kalign2: high-performance multiple alignment of protein and nucleotide sequences allowing external features</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Lassmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="858" to="865" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">T-Coffee: a novel method for fast and accurate multiple sequence alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Notredame</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">302</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="217" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple protein sequence alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Pei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="382" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CLUSTAL w: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Thompson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4673" to="4680" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BAliBASE 3.0: latest developments of the multiple sequence alignment benchmark</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Thompson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>