
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:53+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Bioinformatics-btr041.tex] Gene expression LSPR: an integrated periodicity detection algorithm for unevenly sampled temporal microarray data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rendong</forename>
								<surname>Yang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory of Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">China Agricultural University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100193</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chen</forename>
								<surname>Zhang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Applied Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">China Agricultural University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100083</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zhen</forename>
								<surname>Su</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory of Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">China Agricultural University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100193</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Bioinformatics-btr041.tex] Gene expression LSPR: an integrated periodicity detection algorithm for unevenly sampled temporal microarray data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1023" to="1025"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr041</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on November 5, 2010; revised on December 25, 2010; accepted on January 15, 2011</note>
					<note>Page: 1023 1023–1025 Associate Editor: Trey Ideker Availability: LSPR algorithm is implemented as MATLAB software and is available at http://bioinformatics.cau.edu.cn/LSPR Contact: zhensu@cau.edu.cn Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We propose a three-step periodicity detection algorithm named LSPR. Our method first preprocesses the raw time-series by removing the linear trend and filtering noise. In the second step, LSPR employs a Lomb–Scargle periodogram to estimate the periodicity in the time-series. Finally, harmonic regression is applied to model the cyclic components. Inferred periodic transcripts are selected by a false discovery rate procedure. We have applied LSPR to unevenly sampled synthetic data and two Arabidopsis diurnal expression datasets, and compared its performance with the existing well-established algorithms. Results show that LSPR is capable of identifying periodic transcripts more accurately than existing algorithms.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Most algorithms for analyzing cell cycle or circadian rhythm temporal expression data require that the input signals are equally sampled. For irregularly sampled time-series, the Lomb–Scargle periodogram has been proposed to analyze time-course gene expression data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Glynn et al., 2006</ref>). A comparison study of periodicity detection methods for irregularly sampled data concluded that the Lomb–Scargle method performed better than most existing methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Zhao et al., 2008</ref>). However, this method is subject to noise and is not powerful for short time-series. In this study, we propose a new periodicity identification algorithm based on the Lomb–Scargle periodogram and harmonic regression method for unevenly sampled time-series. Our algorithm, named LSPR, has a similar procedure to that of the ARSER algorithm, which was proposed to analyze evenly sampled temporal expression profiles (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Yang and Su, 2010</ref>). The main difference is that LSPR uses spectrum analysis for unevenly sampled data introduced by Lomb and additionally elaborated by Scargle, while ARSER employs autoregressive spectral estimation, which can only analyze evenly sampled data. For a given irregularly sampled time-series, LSPR first estimates the period by the Lomb–Scargle periodogram in the frequency domain, and then models the periodic signals by the harmonic regression method in the time domain. Such a joint strategy overcomes the limitations of the Lomb–Scargle periodogram and gives better descriptions of periodic patterns. By applying LSPR to the analysis of synthetic data and Arabidopsis diurnal expression data, we found our method was more powerful in detecting periodic transcripts compared with two well-established periodicity detection algorithms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Overview</head><p>Broadly, LSPR is a three-step integrated algorithm, including data preprocessing, spectral analysis and harmonic regression. Data preprocessing entails detrending and smoothing procedures. Detrending removes the linear trend in the raw time-series using ordinary least squares (OLS) regression. This process can remove the effects of accumulating data from a trend, to show only the absolute changes in values and to allow potential cyclical patterns to be identified. The detrended time-series are input into a spectral analysis and harmonic regression procedure. Including noise may influence the ability of the spectral analysis to predict the exact periods, so a fourth degree Savitzky–Golay filter (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Savitzky and Golay, 1964</ref>) is used to smooth the detrended time-series, before the spectral analysis is used as another input to evaluate periods. In the spectral analysis step, LSPR estimates the spectrum by the Lomb–Scargle periodogram (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Lomb, 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Scargle, 1982</ref>), which enables the extraction of periodic components from unevenly sampled timeseries. Finally, to validate the statistical significance of identified periodicity from the spectral analysis, LSPR employs harmonic regression to model the cyclical components. The harmonic regression model fits the detrended timeseries with sinusoids and gives predictions for amplitude, phase, mean value and P-value. The P-values calculated for each time-series are adjusted for multiple testing corrections under two alternative false discovery rate (FDR) procedures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995</ref>; Storey and<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Tibshirani, 2003</ref>) (see Supplementary Material for details).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Procedure of the LSPR algorithm</head><p>LSPR identifies periodicity using the following step-by-step procedures for an input time-series {x i }:</p><p>(1) Remove the linear trend in the time-series {x i }, denoting the detrended time-series as {˙ x i }.Page: 1024 1023–1025</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>R.Yang et al.</head><p>(2) Smooth {˙ x i } by a fourth-order Savitzky–Golay algorithm. The smoothed time-series is denoted as {¨x{¨x i }.</p><p>((5) The periods { ˙ T j } and { ¨ T j } are chosen as input for the harmonic regression for {˙ x i } (Supplementary Equation 3).</p><p>(6) Use Akaike's information criterion (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Akaike, 1974</ref>) to determine the best harmonic regression model among the models generated in Step (5) and give outputs of period, amplitude, phase and P-value for {x i }. Users can use P-values to identify periodic patterns.</p><p>(7) For large-scale time-course data, FDR values are used to determine periodicity. In this study, genes with FDR values &lt;0.05 are considered as periodic genes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Detecting periodicity in synthetic data</head><p>To test the LSPR algorithm and compare its performance with prior methods, we prepared comprehensive datasets containing periodic and non-periodic samples (see Supplementary Material). The periodic samples were generated by two models. One is the stationary periodic model defined by a cosine curve with constant amplitude and mean value. The stationary model was widely used to generate synthetic data in previous studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Liew et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Ptitsyn et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Wichert et al., 2004</ref>). Considering the dampening effect of the circadian rhythm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Westermark et al., 2009</ref>), the periodic data were also generated by another non-stationary model defined by a cosine curve with exponentially damped amplitude and mean value. Compared with the stationary model, the non-stationary model is more likely to approximate the natural biological rhythm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Refinetti, 2004</ref>). The non-periodic data in the synthetic datasets were generated by two random processes. One was white noise following a standard normal distribution. Another widely accepted stochastic process in time-series is the autoregressive model considering the general correlation between successive measurements. Here, we used an autoregressive process of order one (AR(1)) to generate the random time-series. In our synthetic datasets, the periodic signals include 10 000 stationary and 10 000 non-stationary samples with varied period, phase and signal-to-noise ratio (SNR). The non-periodic signals include 10 000 white noise signals and 10 000 AR(1) signals. Each time-series possessed 20 unevenly sampled time-points over the course of 2 days. This sampling design is consistent with the method adopted by<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Smith et al. (2004)</ref>. Four datasets were constructed by combining the periodic and non-periodic signals. We applied LSPR, the Lomb–Scargle periodogram and COSOPT to analyze these four datasets. Since the task is to separate periodic signals from non-periodic signals, we can treat it as a binary classification problem. This allows receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analysis to be conducted.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>shows the ROC analysis for the three algorithms according to their determination thresholds (FDR q-value for LSPR andLomb–Scargle, pMMC-β for COSOPT). We found LSPR performed the best of the three algorithms in all the cases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Application of LSPR in Arabidopsis diurnal expression data</head><p>Here, we applied LSPR to analyze two independent datasets from the studies of the diurnal gene expression of a model plant, Arabidopsis. These datasets were named after their respective first author: Smith data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Smith et al., 2004</ref>) and Blasing data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Blasing et al., 2005</ref>). Smith data were unevenly sampled at 11 time-points with 2 biological replicates for each. Blasing data were evenly sampled at six time-points with 4 h intervals and three biological replicates. We also applied the Lomb–Scargle periodogram and COSOPT, a widely used algorithm for analyzing circadian or diurnal expression data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Straume, 2004</ref>) to analyze the same datasets as those processed with LSPR. We found the Lomb–Scargle method identified zero transcripts as rhythmic in both Smith and Blasing data at an FDR cutoff of 0.05. Thus, we studied the results given by COSOPT and LSPR. Of all the 22 810 Arabidopsis genes, we found LSPR identified 7851 transcripts (35% of the complete Arabidopsis genome) as rhythmic genes in the Blasing data and 6709 transcripts (30% of the complete Arabidopsis genome) in the Smith data with an FDR cutoff of 0.05 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2A</ref>). These fractions of clock-regulated genes were consistent with an estimate of between 31% and 41% of expressed genes being circadian regulated reported by a recent study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Covington et al., 2008</ref>). The overlap of identified rhythmically expressed genes between the Smith and Blasing data is 19% of all expressed genes, which is larger than the 13% obtained by COSOPT (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2A</ref>). Moreover, we found the set of 3602 genes present in Blasing but absent in Smith, according to LSPR, has significant overlap with the set of 2832 genes present in Blasing but absent in Page: 1025 1023–1025 LSPRSmith according to COSOPT (55% overlap, 2284 genes in common). Similarly, the set of identified genes present in Smith but absent in Blasing as found by LSPR also has significant overlap with the set of identified genes present in Smith but absent in Blasing as found by COSOPT (54% overlap, 1676 genes in common).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2B</ref>shows LSPR identified 99% and 97% of the rhythmic genes identified by COSOPT in the Blasing and Smith data, respectively. In addition, LSPR newly identified 9% and 7% of the complete genome transcripts as rhythmic genes in the Blasing and Smith data, respectively. Also, results can be compared with a benchmark set of 28 known clock-regulated genes reported in previous studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Dodd et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Pruneda-Paz, 2009</ref>). Two of these genes were found among the newly identified genes found by LSPR in the Blasing data. One is ZEITLUPE (ZTL), which encodes clock-associated PAS protein (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Somers et al., 2000</ref>). The other is PHYTOCHROME B (PHYB), an element in the input of the cytokinin signal to the circadian phase (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hanano et al., 2006</ref>).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>[13:</head><figDesc>08 17/3/2011 Bioinformatics-btr041.tex]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. ROC analysis of LSPR, COSOPT and the Lomb–Scargle periodogram. Testing datasets contains: (A) 10 000 stationary periodic signals and 10 000 white noise, (B) 10 000 non-stationary periodic signals and 10 000 white noise, (C) 10 000 stationary periodic signals and 10 000 AR(1)-based signals and (D) 10 000 non-stationary periodic signals and 10 000 AR(1)-based signals. A greater area under the ROC curve means more accuracy for prediction. LSPR gives the best performance of all the three algorithms.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Comparisons of periodicity detecting algorithms applied to two Arabidopsis datasets. (A) Overlap of periodic transcripts identified by LSPR (left) and COSOPT (right) for the Blasing and Smith data. (B) Overlap of periodic transcripts in the Blasing data (left) and Smith data (right), identified by LSPR and COSOPT.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>3) Calculate the Lomb–Scargle periodogram of {¨x{¨x i } (Supplementary Equation 1). Then select all periods { ¨ T j }∈[T start ,T end ] that show peaks in the spectrum. T start and T end are the start and end of the selected period range. (4) Calculate the Lomb–Scargle periodogram of detrended time-series {˙ x i } (Supplementary Equation 1), and select all periods { ˙ T j }∈ [T start ,T end ] that show peaks in the spectrum.</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank Daofeng Li for web server assistance, and Wenying Xu and Yi Ling for helpful advice and discussions.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new look at the statistical model identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Akaike</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="723" />
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controlling the false discovery rate-a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Benjamini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Hochberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B Methodol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sugars and circadian regulation make major contributions to the global regulation of diurnal gene expression in Arabidopsis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Blasing</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3257" to="3281" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global transcriptome analysis reveals circadian regulation of key pathways in plant growth and development</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Covington</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">130</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Arabidopsis circadian clock incorporates a cADPR-based feedback loop</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Dodd</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">318</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1789" to="1792" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting periodic patterns in unevenly spaced gene expression time series using Lomb-Scargle periodograms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Glynn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="310" to="316" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple phytohormones influence distinct parameters of the plant circadian clock</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hanano</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Cells</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1381" to="1392" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spectral estimation in unevenly sampled space of periodically expressed microarray time series data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Liew</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">137</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Least-squares frequency-analysis of unequally spaced data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Lomb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysics Space Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="447" to="462" />
			<date type="published" when="1976" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A functional genomics approach reveals CHE as a component of the Arabidopsis circadian clock</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Pruneda-Paz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">323</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1481" to="1485" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Permutation test for periodicity in short time series data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Ptitsyn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-stationary time series and the robustness of circadian rhythms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Refinetti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">227</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="571" to="581" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smoothing and differentiation of data by simplified least squares procedures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Savitzky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Golay</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1627" to="1639" />
			<date type="published" when="1964" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Studies in astronomical time-series analysis. 2. Statistical aspects of spectral-analysis of unevenly spaced data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Scargle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">263</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="835" to="853" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diurnal changes in the transcriptome encoding enzymes of starch metabolism provide evidence for both transcriptional and posttranscriptional regulation of starch metabolism in Arabidopsis leaves</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2687" to="2699" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ZEITLUPE encodes a novel clock-associated PAS protein from Arabidopsis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Somers</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="329" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical significance for genomewide studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Storey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Tibshirani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9440" to="9445" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA microarray time series analysis: automated statistical assessment of circadian rhythms in gene expression patterning</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Straume</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Enzymol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">383</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantification of circadian rhythms in single cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Westermark</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000580</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying periodically expressed transcripts in microarray time series data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Wichert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing circadian expression data by harmonic regression based on autoregressive spectral estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Su</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="168" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting periodic genes from irregularly sampled gene expressions: a comparison study</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Zhao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EURASIP J. Bioinform. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">769293</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>