
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:31+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis mapDamage2.0: fast approximate Bayesian estimates of ancient DNA damage parameters</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Há</forename>
								<surname>Kon</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jó</forename>
								<surname>Nsson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for GeoGenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Natural History Museum of Denmark</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1350 København K</addrLine>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<surname>Auré Lien Ginolhac</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for GeoGenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Natural History Museum of Denmark</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1350 København K</addrLine>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mikkel</forename>
								<surname>Schubert</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for GeoGenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Natural History Museum of Denmark</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1350 København K</addrLine>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Philip</forename>
								<forename type="middle">L F</forename>
								<surname>Johnson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Emory University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30322</postCode>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>GA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ludovic</forename>
								<surname>Orlando</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for GeoGenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Natural History Museum of Denmark</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1350 København K</addrLine>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis mapDamage2.0: fast approximate Bayesian estimates of ancient DNA damage parameters</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1682" to="1684"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt193</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 13, 2013; revised on April 16, 2013; accepted on April 18, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Michael Brudno Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Ancient DNA (aDNA) molecules in fossilized bones and teeth, coprolites, sediments, mummified specimens and museum collections represent fantastic sources of information for evolutionary biologists, revealing the agents of past epidemics and the dynamics of past populations. However, the analysis of aDNA generally faces two major issues. Firstly, sequences consist of a mixture of endogen-ous and various exogenous backgrounds, mostly microbial. Secondly, high nucleotide misincorporation rates can be observed as a result of severe post-mortem DNA damage. Such misincorporation patterns are instrumental to authenticate ancient sequences versus modern contaminants. We recently developed the user-friendly mapDamage package that identifies such patterns from next-generation sequen-cing (NGS) sequence datasets. The absence of formal statistical mod-eling of the DNA damage process, however, precluded rigorous quantitative comparisons across samples. Results: Here, we describe mapDamage 2.0 that extends the original features of mapDamage by incorporating a statistical model of DNA damage. Assuming that damage events depend only on sequencing position and post-mortem deamination, our Bayesian statistical framework provides estimates of four key features of aDNA molecules: the average length of overhangs (), nick frequency () and cytosine de-amination rates in both double-stranded regions (d) and overhangs (s). Our model enables rescaling base quality scores according to their probability of being damaged. mapDamage 2.0 handles NGS datasets with ease and is compatible with a wide range of DNA library protocols. Availability: mapDamage 2.0 is available at ginolhac.github. io/mapDamage/ as a Python package and documentation is maintained at the Centre for GeoGenetics Web site (geogenetics.ku.dk/ publications/mapdamage2.0/).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>DNA in historical samples is subject to a plethora of environmental conditions and degradation reactions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Sawyer et al., 2012</ref>). Abasic sites, strand breaks, interstrand cross-links and a wide diversity of atypic nucleotidic bases are formed following oxidative and hydrolytic degradation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Lindahl, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Paä¨Paä¨bo et al., 2004</ref>), even in the most favorable preservation conditions. Post-mortem DNA damage limits our ability to access ancient DNA (aDNA) sequences and increases the risk of exogenous modern contamination, as undamaged DNA molecules are more prone to enzymatic manipulation. Nucleotide misincorporation patterns, which are mostly driven by deaminated forms of cytosines (uracils), have been suggested as a powerful approach to authenticate aDNA sequences generated on nextgeneration sequencing (NGS) platforms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Briggs et al., 2007</ref>) and motivated the creation of the mapDamage package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ginolhac et al., 2011</ref>). Such patterns could vary according to the specific molecular approach used for constructing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Meyer et al., 2012</ref>) and/or amplifying (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ginolhac et al., 2011</ref>) second-generation DNA libraries. For instance, for one of the most popular protocols (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Meyer and Kircher, 2010</ref>), we observe inflated cytosine deamination rates at 5 0-overhangs, an increase in C ! T substitution rates toward sequencing starts and complementary increase in G ! A rates toward reads ends (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Briggs et al., 2007</ref>). Conversely, a novel procedure targeting single-stranded templates has shown elevated C ! T substitution rates at both ends (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Meyer et al., 2012</ref>). Statistical modeling of such patterns has been developed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Briggs et al., 2007</ref>with strand break, overhangs and cytosine deamination as key factors. Using read alignment to reference genomes and maximum likelihood optimization, this approach has delivered the first quantitative estimates of damage parameters. However, the likelihood framework originally implemented scales poorly with the size of NGS datasets, and extensive running times have prevented common usage. Here, we present an extension of mapDamage, which implements a fast approximation of the DNA damage model using a Bayesian framework. mapDamage 2.0 opens the possibility of comparing DNA damage levels across temporal and environmental gradients. Posterior distributions of damage parameters also enable penalizing the quality score of likely damaged bases, reducing noise in downstream single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) calling procedures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">APPROACH</head><p>Here we build on the DNA damage model described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Briggs et al., 2007</ref>. We make the simplifying assumption that mutations *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by-nc/3.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com and post-mortem DNA damage are independent within a fragment, with occurrences depending only on the relative position from the sequence ends.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">METHODS</head><p>The general idea is to mutate bases following an Hasegawa, Kishino and Yano (HKY) transition matrix (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Hasegawa et al., 1985</ref>) and then independently add post-mortem damage on top of mutated bases. In this framework, we have multinomial distributions describing the positionspecific substitutions for any given base (S A, i , S C, i , S G, i and S T, i ).</p><formula>S A, i $ Mul D A , 1, 0, 0, 0 ð ÞÁÂð, Þ Á P dam ð d , s , , , iÞ ð Þ</formula><p>Â is the HKY transition matrix, and P dam is defined as the DNA damage transition matrix. We assume post-mortem cytosine deamination is the main driver of nucleotide misincorporations in agreement with experimental evidence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Briggs et al., 2007</ref>), providingWhere the base-specific damage probabilities are defined as</p><formula>p ct ð d , s , , , iÞ ¼ i i s þ d 1 À i ð Þ ð Þ p ga ð d , s , , , iÞ ¼ ð1 À i Þ i s þ d 1 À i ð Þ ð Þ</formula><p>The motivation for the base-specific damage probabilities p dam is best explained by the Markov chain in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>where the first jump decides if the position is before or after a nick; then a C ! T substitution could be observed following deamination in overhang or double-stranded DNA regions. A similar Markov chain could be drawn for G ! A substitutions (Supplementary Section 1). For rescaling base quality scores, we assume that C ! T and G ! A substitutions either originate from true biological differences or from damage driven misincorporations. We can derive an estimate for the probability that a C ! T (similar for G ! A) misincorporation at position i along the reads is due to damage using</p><formula>p dam ðiÞ ¼ Â c, c Á p c, t ðiÞ Â c, c Á p c, t ðiÞ þ Â c, t</formula><p>We can now correct base quality scores provided in alignment BAM files [p err ði, rÞ at position i for read r] using p 0 err ði, rÞ ¼ 1 À ð1 À p err ði, rÞÞð1 À p dam ðiÞÞ</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>We applied mapDamage2.0 on a series of aDNA sequence datasets generated from a range of periods, source materials and environments (Supplementary Section 3). Posterior predictive intervals and empirical frequencies are in general agreement, as shown for the ancient plague dataset (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S2</ref>and Supplementary Figs S4–S9) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Schuenemann et al., 2011</ref>), demonstrating the adequacy of our method. We observed a ratio of cytosine deamination rates for double-and singlestranded regions orders of magnitude greater than estimates based on in vitro experiments in aqueous solution (0.007 in Lindahl, 1993 versus 0.026–0.070 for Schuenemann et al., 2011 in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>). This suggests that tissue-and sample-specific micro-environmental characteristics drive different DNA damage kinetics in situ. We also found a significant rank correlation between the posterior mean for single-stranded cytosine deamination and sample age (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S3</ref>) in agreement with Sawyer et al., 2012. However, remains of similar age and location showed diverse parameter estimates (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S2</ref>), suggesting a prominent role of micro-environmental characteristics over age in diagenesis. We also applied our quality rescaling scheme to the sequence data of an Australian Aboriginal individual who died in 1920s (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Rasmussen et al., 2011</ref>). This increased the overlap of genotype calls to dbSNP v137, suggesting that lower false-positive SNP calls were achieved (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S4</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">CONCLUSION</head><p>We have developed a computational method for inferring aDNA damage parameters from NGS sequence datasets, with minimal changes to the DNA damage model presented by<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Briggs et al., 2007</ref>. Our model is compatible with the specificities of different sequencing and library building protocols. We believe that downscaling quality scores of likely damaged bases is the first from a long list of possible applications for damage parameter posterior distributions, limiting the impact of nucleotide misincorporations in downstream sequence analyses. The knowledge of such distributions could also be instrumental for improving mapping procedures to reference genomes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Schubert et al., 2012</ref>).</p></div>
			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="1683"> mapDamage2.0 at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">H.Jó nsson et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patterns of damage in genomic DNA sequences from a Neandertal</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Briggs</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14616" to="14621" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">mapDamage: testing for damage patterns in ancient DNA sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ginolhac</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2153" to="2155" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dating of the human-ape splitting by a molecular clock of mitochondrial DNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hasegawa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="160" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Instability and decay of the primary structure of DNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Lindahl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">362</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="709" to="715" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Illumina sequencing library preparation for highly multiplexed target capture and sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Meyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kircher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cold Spring Harb. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">5448</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A high-coverage genome sequence from an archaic denisovan individual</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Meyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">338</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="222" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic analyses from ancient DNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Paä¨paä¨bo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="645" to="679" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An aboriginal Australian genome reveals separate human dispersals into Asia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Rasmussen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">334</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="94" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal patterns of nucleotide misincorporations and DNA fragmentation in ancient DNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Sawyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">34131</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving ancient DNA read mapping against modern reference genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Schubert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">178</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Targeted enrichment of ancient pathogens yielding the pPCP1 plasmid of Yersinia pestis from victims of the Black Death</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Schuenemann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="746" to="752" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>