
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:54+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">markophylo: Markov chain analysis on phylogenetic trees</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Utkarsh</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Dang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">McMaster University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>L8S 4K1</postCode>
									<settlement>Hamilton</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">G</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Brian</forename>
								<surname>Golding</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">McMaster University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>L8S 4K1</postCode>
									<settlement>Hamilton</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">markophylo: Markov chain analysis on phylogenetic trees</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv541</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 29, 2015; revised on September 2, 2015; accepted on September 8, 2015</note>
					<note>Genome analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: David Posada Contact: udang@mcmaster.ca Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Continuous-time Markov chain models with finite state space are routinely used for analysis of discrete character data on phylogenetic trees. Examples of such discrete character data include restriction sites, gene family presence/absence, intron presence/absence and gene family size data. While models with constrained substitution rate matrices have been used to good effect, more biologically realistic models have been increasingly implemented in the recent literature combining, e.g., site rate variation, site partitioning, branch-specific rates, allowing for non-stationary prior root probabilities, correcting for sampling bias, etc. to name a few. Here, a flexible and fast R package is introduced that infers evolutionary rates of discrete characters on a tree within a probabilistic framework. The package, markophylo, fits maximum-likelihood models using Markov chains on phylogenetic trees. The package is efficient, with the workhorse functions written in Cþþ and the interface in user-friendly R. Availability and implementation: markophylo is available as a platform-independent R package from the Comprehensive R Archive Network at https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/marko phylo/. A vignette with numerous examples is also provided with the R package.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>A Markov chain framework is frequently adopted to estimate evolutionary rates of discrete characters on phylogenetic trees. Some examples of previously investigated data using such models include restriction sites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Felsenstein, 1992</ref>), gene family size data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hahn et al., 2005</ref>), gene family presence/absence patterns (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hao and Golding, 2006</ref>), intron presence/absence data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kim and Hao, 2014</ref>), etc. A good introduction to such models can be found in O'Meara (2012) and Yang (2014). It has been noted before that many variants of such models are just restrictions of more general models for investigation of specific hypotheses or different kinds of data (O'<ref type="bibr">Meara, 2012</ref>). Hence, there is a clear need for a flexible and efficient software to provide a unified interface that would allow fitting of varied discrete character datasets. Recently, Kim and Hao (2014) put forward a unified R (R Core<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Team, 2015</ref>) package, namely DiscML, that provided users the option of biologically realistic features like gamma rate variation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Yang, 1994</ref>), estimation of character prior root probabilities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cohen et al., 2008</ref>), correcting for ancient characters being lost from all examined extant taxa (cf.<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Felsenstein, 1992</ref>), etc. As noted in Kim and Hao (2014), while many of these features are found in existing programs like BayesTraits (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Pagel et al., 2004</ref>), CAFE3 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Han et al., 2013</ref>), BadiRate (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Librado et al., 2012</ref>) and GLOOME (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cohen et al., 2010</ref>), the sum total of these above-mentioned desirable features was not available in a single flexible software. However, DiscML is not computationally inexpensive. Moreover, DiscML does not currently allow for partition analyses or for accounting for sampling bias arising due to multiple unobserved phyletic patterns (see Supplementary Material). Here, we present markophylo, an R package that is both fast and flexible. The markophylo package allows for estimating evolutionary rates using a user-specified, i.e. hypothesis driven,substitution rate matrix in a continuous-time Markov chain model on phylogenies. The package is computationally efficient, with the workhorse functions written in Cþþ, using the Rcpp (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Eddelbuettel et al., 2011</ref>) and RcppArmadillo (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Eddelbuettel and Sanderson, 2014</ref>) packages. The package is flexible, capable of modelling a myriad array of processes (described below in Section 2.2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Description</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Input</head><p>A phylogenetic tree with branch lengths in units of expected substitutions per site and a matrix containing phyletic patterns of discrete characters are the primary external inputs needed for markophylo. The tree must be in the phylo format of the APE package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Paradis et al., 2004</ref>), while each row of the matrix represents a phyletic pattern, where the columns denote closely related taxa of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Features</head><p>The following features are available in the primary function markophylo::estimaterates:</p><p>1. Custom substitution rate matrices can be easily specified. These can be as simple as matrices where each non-diagonal entry is hypothesized to be the same (discrete character analogue of<ref type="bibr">Jukes and Cantor, 1969</ref>), or birth-death matrices, or symmetric matrices (where the instantaneous rate of change from character i to j is the same as character j to i), to matrices where each nondiagonal entry is different. 2. A custom character-only or numeric-only alphabet for the discrete characters can be specified with no limit on the number of possible states. 3. Clades or groups of branches hypothesized to follow substitution rates different from other branches can be easily specified. This is often essential when a clade is very diverged from other branches based on evolutionary time. 4. Sites can also be split into different partitions, where each partition of sites is a group of sites following their own rates different from the sites in the other partitions. This is useful, e.g. when different rates are hypothesized for mitochondrial versus nuclear genes (O'<ref type="bibr">Meara, 2012</ref>). 5. Gamma rate variation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Yang, 1994</ref>) can be specified: a common gamma distribution (with a ¼ b, where a and b are the shape and rate parameters, respectively) over all partitions or separate gamma rates within each partition separately. The latter option is useful when the hypothesized evolutionary processes among the different partitions are different enough to warrant separate gamma distributions for each partition. 6. Prior root probabilities for each discrete character can be either user-specified (based on some known constraint at the root), equal for each character state, follow Markov chain stationary probabilities or be estimated in the maximum likelihood framework when it is not reasonable to assume stationarity. 7. Correcting for multiple unobservable phyletic patterns, i.e. sampling (aka acquisition or ascertainment) bias. It is often important to correct for sampling bias. If sampling bias exists during data collection, some phyletic patterns cannot be observed in the data and as a result, not correcting for this in the statistical model can lead to biased estimates. Such a correction has been applied previously. For example, this correction has been used in the analysis of restriction sites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Felsenstein, 1992</ref>), when only variable characters are recorded (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Lewis, 2001</ref>), correcting for unobservable ancient genes that are lost and not observed at the tips (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hao and Golding, 2006</ref>) or because gene families appearing in the COG database cannot occur in less than three genomes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cohen and Pupko, 2010</ref>). DiscML only provides the option of correcting for observations of a zero character for each taxa; however, multiple user-specified phyletic patterns can be easily corrected for in markophylo.</p><p>The package also contains five example (simulated) datasets and a vignette that contains numerous examples. These data illustrate the kinds of models that the package is capable of fitting to discrete character data recorded for multiple taxa (with a user phylogeny).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Output</head><p>The output from the primary function contains parameter estimates for the user-specified substitution rate matrix, standard errors, time taken, a reduced dataset containing unique patterns and their frequencies and model selection criteria values, namely the Akaike information criterion (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Akaike, 1973</ref>) and the Bayesian information criterion (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Schwarz, 1978</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Discussion</head><p>Here, a flexible and efficient R package named markophylo for estimating evolutionary rates of discrete characters is introduced. When compared with existing packages like DiscML, markophylo is at least an order of magnitude faster. Moreover, markophylo implements a wide variety of features increasingly seen in more biologically realistic Markov chain models run on discrete character datasets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>This work was supported by the National Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada [140221-10 to G.B.G]. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 130 Bioinformatics, 32(1), 2016, 130–132 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv541 Advance Access Publication Date: 11 September 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">U.J.Dang and G.B.Golding at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information theory and an extension of the maximum likelihood principle</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Akaike</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceeding of the Second International Symposium on Information Theory. Akademiai Kiad</title>
		<editor>Petrov,B.N. and Caski,F.</editor>
		<meeting>eeding of the Second International Symposium on Information Theory. Akademiai Kiad<address><addrLine>Budapest</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="281" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inference and characterization of horizontally transferred gene families using stochastic mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Cohen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Pupko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="703" to="713" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A likelihood framework to analyse phyletic patterns</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Cohen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">363</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3903" to="3911" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GLOOME: gain loss mapping engine</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Cohen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2914" to="2915" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RcppArmadillo: accelerating R with high-performance Cþþ linear algebra</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Eddelbuettel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Sanderson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Stat. Data Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1054" to="1063" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rcpp: seamless R and Cþþ integration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Eddelbuettel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stat. Softw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenies from restriction sites: a maximum-likelihood approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Felsenstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the tempo and mode of gene family evolution from comparative genomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Hahn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1153" to="1160" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating gene gain and loss rates in the presence of error in genome assembly and annotation using CAFE 3</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Han</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1987" to="1997" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The fate of laterally transferred genes: life in the fast lane to adaptation or death</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Hao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Golding</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="636" to="643" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Evolution of protein molecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Cantor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Munro,H.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
			<publisher>Mammalian Protein Metabolism. Academic Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="281" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DiscML: an R package for estimating evolutionary rates of discrete characters using maximum likelihood</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Hao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">320</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A likelihood approach to estimating phylogeny from discrete morphological character data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Lewis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="913" to="925" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BadiRate: estimating family turnover rates by likelihood-based methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Librado</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="281" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolutionary inferences from phylogenies: a review of methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Meara</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Ecol. Evol., Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian estimation of ancestral character states on phylogenies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Pagel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="673" to="684" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">APE: analyses of phylogenetics and evolution in R language</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Paradis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>R. Package version 3.2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R Core</forename>
				<surname>Team</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<pubPlace>Vienna, Austria</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the dimension of a model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Schwarz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="461" to="464" />
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximum likelihood phylogenetic estimation from DNA sequences with variable rates over sites: approximate methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="306" to="314" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Molecular Evolution A Statistical Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford, UK.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>