
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:37+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">MDWeb and MDMoby: an integrated web-based platform for molecular dynamics simulations</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Adam</forename>
								<surname>Hospital</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Research in Biomedicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Barcelona Supercomputing Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Joint IRB-BSC Program on Computational Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Barcelona Science Park, Josep Samitier 1-5</addrLine>
									<postCode>08028, 08034</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona, Jordi Girona 31, Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Structural Bioinformatics Node</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Josep Samitier 1-5</addrLine>
									<postCode>08028</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pau</forename>
								<surname>Andrio</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Research in Biomedicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Barcelona Supercomputing Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Joint IRB-BSC Program on Computational Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Barcelona Science Park, Josep Samitier 1-5</addrLine>
									<postCode>08028, 08034</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona, Jordi Girona 31, Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Computatinal Bioinformatics Node</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Jordi Girona 31</addrLine>
									<postCode>08034</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Carles</forename>
								<surname>Fenollosa</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Research in Biomedicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Barcelona Supercomputing Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Joint IRB-BSC Program on Computational Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Barcelona Science Park, Josep Samitier 1-5</addrLine>
									<postCode>08028, 08034</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona, Jordi Girona 31, Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Computatinal Bioinformatics Node</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Jordi Girona 31</addrLine>
									<postCode>08034</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Damjan</forename>
								<surname>Cicin-Sain</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Research in Biomedicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Barcelona Supercomputing Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Joint IRB-BSC Program on Computational Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Barcelona Science Park, Josep Samitier 1-5</addrLine>
									<postCode>08028, 08034</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona, Jordi Girona 31, Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Structural Bioinformatics Node</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Josep Samitier 1-5</addrLine>
									<postCode>08028</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Modesto</forename>
								<surname>Orozco</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>modesto.orozco@irbbarcelona.org</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Research in Biomedicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Barcelona Supercomputing Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Joint IRB-BSC Program on Computational Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Barcelona Science Park, Josep Samitier 1-5</addrLine>
									<postCode>08028, 08034</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona, Jordi Girona 31, Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Structural Bioinformatics Node</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Josep Samitier 1-5</addrLine>
									<postCode>08028</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Barcelona</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Av. Diagonal 643</addrLine>
									<postCode>08028</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Josep</forename>
								<surname>Lluís Gelpí</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Research in Biomedicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Barcelona Supercomputing Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Joint IRB-BSC Program on Computational Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Barcelona Science Park, Josep Samitier 1-5</addrLine>
									<postCode>08028, 08034</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona, Jordi Girona 31, Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Computatinal Bioinformatics Node</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Jordi Girona 31</addrLine>
									<postCode>08034</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Barcelona</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Av. Diagonal 643</addrLine>
									<postCode>08028</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">MDWeb and MDMoby: an integrated web-based platform for molecular dynamics simulations</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1278" to="1279"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts139</idno>
					<note type="submission">Structural bioinformatics Advance Access publication March 21, 2012 Received on December 19, 2011; revised on February 27, 2012; accepted on March 18, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [12:55 9/4/2012 Bioinformatics-bts139.tex] Page: 1278 1278–1279 Spain Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>MDWeb and MDMoby constitute a web-based platform to help access to molecular dynamics (MD) in the standard and high-throughput regime. The platform provides tools to prepare systems from PDB structures mimicking the procedures followed by human experts. It provides inputs and can send simulations for three of the most popular MD packages (Amber, NAMD and Gromacs). Tools for analysis of trajectories, either provided by the user or retrieved from our MoDEL database (http://mmb.pcb.ub.es/MoDEL) are also incorporated. The platform has two ways of access, a set of web-services based on the BioMoby framework (MDMoby), programmatically accessible and a web portal (MDWeb). Availability: http://mmb.irbbarcelona.org/MDWeb; additional information and methodology details can be found at the web site</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Molecular dynamics (MD) has experienced a long evolution since its origins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">McCammon et al., 1977</ref>), being now a mature technique that allows to obtain accurate pictures of the dynamics of proteins and nucleic acids. Unfortunately, the practical use of MD is limited by three factors: (i) force-fields uncertainties; (ii) the need of large computational resources; and (iii) the high-level expertise needed to use efficiently the technique. Indeed, setting up a system for simulation requires a large series of operations, and a number of decisions that demand a significant degree of expertise and large amounts of human time, in most cases similar to that of computing the trajectory. The end result is that newcomers to the field face a stiff learning curve. These problems reach a maximum in highthroughput projects (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Meyer et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Rueda et al., 2007</ref>; Van * To whom correspondence should be addressed. der<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kamp et al., 2010</ref>), where thousands of trajectories need to be launched and supercomputer resources are required. We present here a tool designed to help naïve users to completely prepare systems for simulation, and that allows expert users to use MD in the high-throughput regime. The tool is presented in two different versions: a web-services-oriented software platform (MDMoby), and a web portal MDWeb. The technology has been adapted to be accessed as web-services following BioMoby (www.biomoby.org;<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">BioMoby Consortium, 2008</ref>). MDMoby can be run with usual web-services clients and also programmatically through suitable APIs (http://inb.bsc.es). In turn, the web portal MDWeb provides a friendly environment to setup new systems, run test simulations and perform analysis within a guided interface. Setup files can be prepared, at present time, for Amber (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Case et al., 2010</ref>), NAMD (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Phillips et al., 2005</ref>) and Gromacs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Hess et al., 2008</ref>), and analyses can be carried out from trajectories written in the most usual formats. Additionally, the platform is interfaced to our flexibility analysis software FlexServ, so providing coarsegrained simulation, and advanced analysis tools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Camps et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Emperador et al., 2008</ref>), and also with our MoDEL database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Meyer et al., 2010</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">IMPLEMENTATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">MDMoby</head><p>MDMoby services have been developed under the BioMoby framework (www.biomoby.org;<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">BioMoby Consortium, 2008</ref>). To this end, a complete new set of data types was designed (see MDWeb help section for a detailed information about MDMoby ontology). Among them, the most relevant are MD_Topology, MD_Structure and MD_Trajectory, that contain information on topologies, structures and trajectory files, respectively. Those data types have been defined in an abstract form, and specialized in the inherited objects. Hence, data formats are inferred from object name and handled without user intervention. Setup services cover operations like structure repair, titration of ionizable residues and relevant water molecules, neutralization of the system, addition of salt and solvent, energy minimization, thermalization and system equilibration. A limited set of parameterized ligands are available to</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MDWeb and MDMoby</head><p>be included in the setup process. Full automatic setup procedures in standard conditions for the software packages covered are offered as pre-packed workflows. Underlying software is based in the Ambertools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Case et al. 2010</ref>) and VMD (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Humphrey et al. 1996</ref>) packages, combined with in-house and publicly available programs (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>). The tool allows launching test simulations in our servers, and provides the necessary scripts for running production simulations at the user side. Scripts provided contain the necessary instructions to be customized to match the users' configuration. Basic analysis results are provided from Ambertools and Gromacs tools, complemented with in-house software. Tools for conversion between trajectory formats are available to facilitate trajectory sharing, extension and analysis. Supplementary Tables S2 and S3, and MDWeb site's help show the full offer of web-services and operations available. MDMoby is accessible through Perl and Java APIs provided by the Spanish National Institute of Bioinformatics (http://inb.bsc.es), and, in a limited extent, using clients like Taverna (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hull et al., 2006</ref>) or Jorca (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Martín-Requena et al., 2010</ref>). Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S1</ref>shows a sample Perl script to prepare of a protein system using MDMoby.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">MDWeb</head><p>MDWeb is a web portal implemented in PHP and MySQL that provides a GUI to MDMoby. It provides users with a personal workspace where intermediate data, trajectories and analysis results can be stored. Registration is free but necessary to maintain a permanent workspace. The primary entry is a structure (uploaded or obtained from PDB) for setup or a trajectory for analysis. The input structure or trajectory acts as the root of a tree (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S2</ref>for some screenshots) to that new sets of data are added according to the operations performed. Every new component of the tree is identified by its BioMoby's datatype, and can be visualized (with JMol, http://www.jmol.org), or downloaded. For every component the appropriate choice of operations is presented. To guide the non-experts, pre-packed workflows including recommended options are also available. However, all web-services in MDMoby are available separately, allowing more experienced users to finely tune the procedures. Results of trajectory analysis are presented through alphanumerical values, 2D plots or Jmol-based 3D visualizations, as appropriate. Analysis results can also be downloaded for further processing. Trajectories from the MoDEL library (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Meyer et al., 2010</ref>) can also be loaded in MDWeb and analyzed. MDWeb handles efficiently potentially slow operations, which are derived to a batch queue to be executed. Results become available in the workspace as soon as calculations are finished and can be recovered at a later time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>The software platform formed by MDMoby and its portal MDWeb provides a step forward in the current offer of software to help in the use of MD. It is a consequence of the automation required to develop the MoDEL project and integrates the expertise accumulated over the years on massive setup of systems and analysis of MD trajectories. The modular nature of the web-service paradigm in which the platform is created assures that the system can grow to incorporate new operations without a significant change of the interface or even to incorporate MDMoby services to user's codes. The platform provides non-experts users of pre-packed tools allowing to do complete MD analysis without a deep knowledge of the details involved. At the same time, the platform is flexible enough as to allow expert users to perform finely tuned simulations. The platform is not tied to a specific software package, therefore increasing the number of potential users and helping them in code-migration and re-use of trajectories. MDMoby and MDWeb constitute a growing platform where eventually new operations and scenarios will be included in the future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head><p>We are indebted all the beta-testers of the platform.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [12:55 9/4/2012 Bioinformatics-bts139.tex] Page: 1279 1278–1279</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: Spanish Ministry of Education and Science [grant numbers: BIO2006-01602, CTQ2005-09365, CONSOLIDER E-Science Project in Supercomputation]; The EU Commission [contract INFSO-RI-261523, ScalaLife project]; the Instituto de Salud Carlos III [National Institute of Bioinformatics and the COMBIOMED network]; the ERC for an Advanced Grant to M.O., and the Fundación Marcelino Botín. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interoperability with Moby 1.0 – It&apos;s better than sharing your toothbrush</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Biomoby</forename>
				<surname>Consortium</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FlexServ: an integrated tool for the analysis of protein flexibility</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Camps</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1709" to="1710" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Case</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the suitability of coarse-grained techniques for the representation of protein dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Emperador</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2127" to="2138" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GROMACS 4: algorithms for highly efficient, load-balanced, and scalable molecular simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Hess</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Theory Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="447" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Taverna: a tool for building and running workflows of services</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Hull</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="729" to="732" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Web. Server Issue</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">VMD: visual molecular dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Humphrey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">jORCA: easily integrating bioinformatics Web Services</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Martín-Requena</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="553" to="559" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamics of folded proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Mccammon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">267</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="585" to="590" />
			<date type="published" when="1977" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MoDEL (Molecular Dynamics Extended Library): a database of atomistic molecular dynamics trajectories</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Meyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structure</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1399" to="1409" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scalable molecular dynamics with NAMD</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Phillips</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comp. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1781" to="1802" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A consensous view to protein dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Rueda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="796" to="801" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynameomics: a comprehensive database of protein dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Van Der Kamp</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structure</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="435" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>