
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:48+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">MemGen: a general web server for the setup of lipid membrane simulation systems</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christopher</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Knight</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Microbiology and Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georg-August-University Gö ttingen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>37077 Gö ttingen</addrLine>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jochen</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Hub</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Microbiology and Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georg-August-University Gö ttingen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>37077 Gö ttingen</addrLine>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">MemGen: a general web server for the setup of lipid membrane simulation systems</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv292</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 4, 2015; revised on April 28, 2015; accepted on May 2, 2015</note>
					<note>Structural bioinformatics *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Molecular dynamics simulations provide atomic insight into the physicochemical characteristics of lipid membranes and hence, a wide range of force field families capable of modelling various lipid types have been developed in recent years. To model membranes in a biologically realistic lipid composition, simulation systems containing multiple different lipids must be assembled. Results: We present a new web service called MemGen that is capable of setting up simulation systems of heterogenous lipid membranes. MemGen is not restricted to certain lipid force fields or lipid types, but instead builds membranes from uploaded structure files which may contain any kind of amphiphilic molecule. MemGen works with any all-atom or united-atom lipid representation. Availability and implementation: MemGen is freely available without registration at http://memgen.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations of lipid membranes have come of age. Since the first simulation of a bilayer membrane more than 30 years ago (Van der<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Ploeg and Berendsen, 1982</ref>), MD simulations have been used to study various processes at atomic or nearatomic resolutions such as lipid diffusion, solute permeation, electroporation, undulation and phase transition. In addition, they are required to provide a realistic environment for simulations of membrane proteins. To this end, a range of lipid force fields have been developed which reproduce membrane parameters such as the area per lipid, order parameters and X-ray scattering factors. Atomistic lipid force fields can be separated into united-atom (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Berger et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Chiu et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Piggot et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Ulmschneider and Ulmschneider, 2009</ref>) and all-atom force fields (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Dickson et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Jämbeck and Lyubartsev, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Maciejewski et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Pastor and</ref>Following an alternative approach, we present the new web server MemGen that automatically sets up lipid membrane simulation systems. The server is not restricted to certain force fields, lipid types, or specific MD simulation software. The user uploads one or more lipid structure files (http://memgen.uni-goettingen.de). Alternatively, any amphiphilic molecule such as an alcohol or detergent may be uploaded. Subsequently, the server generates a compact representation of each lipid that is aligned along the z-axis (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1A</ref>), to avoid atomic overlaps in the assembled membrane. After building the membrane with the requested molar fractions of each lipid, the server hydrates the membrane with a requested number of water molecules per lipid. Eventually, counter ions and, optionally, sodium chloride is added (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1B</ref>). The final structure is provided for download in PDB format, which can be processed by any MD software.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>In order to generate a compact representation of an uploaded lipid, a force field topology of the lipids is required. To this end, MemGen builds a GAFF topology of each lipid using ACPYPE, which builds upon the Antechamber software (da<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Silva and Vranken, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Wang et al., 2004</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Wang et al., , 2006</ref>). Because GAFF requires an all-atom representation, hydrogen atoms are added with Open Babel if the user uploads a united-atom lipid (O'<ref type="bibr">Boyle et al., 2011</ref>). By analysing the bond structure of the lipid, MemGen detects the terminal atoms of the lipid tails, as well as a central head group atom. Subsequently, using the Gromacs simulation software and applying a combination of simulated annealing, constant-force pulling on the head group and tail atoms, as well as position-restraining potentials, a highly compact representation of the lipid is created (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1A</ref>) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Pronk et al., 2013</ref>). Hydrogen atoms added by Open Babel are removed. A lipid monolayer is generated by placing the compact representations of the lipids on a square grid, and two such monolayers are assembled to build the bilayer (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1B</ref>). To release some strain from the highly ordered lipids, a 1.2-picosecond simulation is conducted at 300 Kelvin with position-restraining potentials on the terminal tail atoms. The requested number of water molecules per lipid are added. The charge of the lipid is determined by counting the number of amine, phosphate and carboxyl groups. Accordingly, counter ions are added to neutralize the simulation cell. If requested, additional salt is added.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Discussion</head><p>We tested MemGen using lipids from a wide range of all-atom and united-atom force fields, including various sterol, detergent and alcohol molecules (see Supporting Discussion). Tested lipids contained between one and six lipid tails and different head group types. The energy minization and equilibration of the systems were numerically stable. An example is shown in supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure S1</ref>in the supporting material. It is important to note that MemGen provides a highly ordered and hence, unphysical initial configuration, which requires careful equilibration for at least 10 nanoseconds. MemGen does not provide or maintain lipid force field files. These must be taken from the force field developers' web sites, or from repositories such as LipidBook (Doman´skiDoman´<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Doman´ski et al., 2010</ref>). By design, MemGen does not generate asymmetric bilayers with differing compositions of the two monolayers. Because the areas per lipid are not additive in lipid mixtures, it is difficult to predict the equilibrated membrane area of some lipid mixtures. However, since membranes are nearly incompressible, any area mismatch between the two monolayers results in large lateral pressures. To set up such asymmetric membranes, the user may first equilibrate two symmetric systems, removing an appropriate number of lipids manually to achieve the same equilibrium area, and subsequently merge one leaflet from each simulation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Gurtovenko and Vattulainen, 2008</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This project was supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (HU 1971/1-1). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Setup of a membrane simulation system by MemGen. (A) A compact representation of the lipids is created, allowing the setup of a membrane without atomic overlaps. (B) Membrane simulation system containing cardiolipin (dark blue), POPE (light blue) and water (red/white). Top: top view; bottom: side view. (C) Screenshot of MemGen</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">MacKerell, Jr., 2011), which differ in the modelling of apolar hydrogen atoms. Hence, force field development is an active field of research, and more force field families covering a wider range of lipid types are expected to be published in the near future. More recently, because biological membranes contain thousands of different lipid types, the interest in simulations of heterogenous membranes has increased (Ró g et al., 2009; Zocher et al., 2013). Setting up such heterogenous membranes can be tedious. Upon building such membranes, atomic overlaps between neighbouring lipids must be strictly avoided. Otherwise, minimizing the energy of the sytem fails, leading to numerical instabilities in the first simulation steps. To our knowledge, two web services have so far been developed to facilitate the setup of membrane simulation systems, namely CHARMM-GUI and Membuilder (Ghahremanpour et al., 2014; Jo et al., 2009). These services allow the user to choose from a list of lipid types and force fields, which are kept on their respective servers. Hence, these services require frequent maintenance upon publication of new lipid types and force fields. In addition, they do not allow the insertion of molecules that are not available server-side. V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 2897 Bioinformatics, 31(17), 2015, 2897–2899 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv292 Advance Access Publication Date: 7 May 2015 Applications Note at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">C.J.Knight and J.S.Hub at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular dynamics simulations of a fluid bilayer of dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine at full hydration, constant pressure, and constant temperature</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Berger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2002" to="2013" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An improved united atom force field for simulation of mixed lipid bilayers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S.-W</forename>
				<surname>Chiu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2748" to="2763" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ACPYPE-Antechamber python parser interface</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W S</forename>
				<surname>Da Silva</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Vranken</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Res. Notes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">367</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GAFFlipid: a General Amber Force Field for the accurate molecular dynamics simulation of phospholipid</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Dickson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soft Matter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9617" to="9627" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lipidbook: a public repository for force-field parameters used in membrane simulations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Doman´skidoman´doman´ski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Membr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">236</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MemBuilder: a web-based graphical interface to build heterogeneously mixed membrane bilayers for the GROMACS biomolecular simulation program</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Ghahremanpour</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="441" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Membrane potential and electrostatics of phospholipid bilayers with asymmetric transmembrane distribution of anionic lipids</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Gurtovenko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Vattulainen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4629" to="4634" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Derivation and systematic validation of a refined all-atom force field for phosphatidylcholine lipids</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Jämbeck</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Lyubartsev</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3164" to="3179" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CHARMM-GUI membrane builder for mixed bilayers and its application to yeast membranes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Jo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Refined OPLS all-atom force field for saturated phosphatidylcholine bilayers at full hydration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Maciejewski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4571" to="4581" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open Babel: An open chemical toolbox</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Boyle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cheminf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">33</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development of the CHARMM force field for lipids</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Pastor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Mackerell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Jr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1526" to="1532" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Electroporation of the E. coli and S. aureus membranes: molecular dynamics simulations of complex bacterial membranes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Piggot</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13381" to="13388" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GROMACS 4.5: a high-throughput and highly parallel open source molecular simulation toolkit</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Pronk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="845" to="854" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ordering effects of cholesterol and its analogues</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Ró G</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="1788" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">United atom lipid parameters for combination with the optimized potentials for liquid simulations all-atom force field</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Ulmschneider</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Ulmschneider</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Theory Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1803" to="1813" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular dynamics simulation of a bilayer membrane</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Van Der Ploeg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Berendsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3271" to="3276" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development and testing of a general amber force field</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1157" to="1174" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic atom type and bond type perception in molecular mechanical calculations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Graphics Modell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">247260</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Local micro-partition coefficients govern solute permeability of cholesterol-containing membranes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Zocher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2760" to="2770" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>