
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">MetaCycle: an integrated R package to evaluate periodicity in large scale data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gang</forename>
								<surname>Wu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Systems Pharmacology and Translational Therapeutics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute for Translational Medicine and Therapeutics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ron</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Anafi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Sleep Medicine</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Sleep and Circadian Neurobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>19104</postCode>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Hughes</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Missouri–St. Louis, St. Louis</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63121</postCode>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Karl</forename>
								<surname>Kornacker</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Emeritus Professor of Sensory Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ohio State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>43210</postCode>
									<settlement>Columbus</settlement>
									<region>OH</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<forename type="middle">B</forename>
								<surname>Hogenesch</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Systems Pharmacology and Translational Therapeutics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute for Translational Medicine and Therapeutics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Systems Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">MetaCycle: an integrated R package to evaluate periodicity in large scale data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw405</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 26, 2016; revised on June 16, 2016; accepted on June 20, 2016</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Detecting periodicity in large scale data remains a challenge. While efforts have been made to identify best of breed algorithms, relatively little research has gone into integrating these methods in a generalizable method. Here, we present MetaCycle, an R package that incorporates ARSER, JTK_CYCLE and Lomb-Scargle to conveniently evaluate periodicity in time-series data. MetaCycle has two functions, meta2d and meta3d, designed to analyze two-dimensional and three-dimensional time-series datasets, respectively. Meta2d implements N-version programming concepts using a suite of algorithms and integrating their results. Availability and implementation: MetaCycle package is available on the CRAN repository (https:// cran.r-project.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Identifying periodic signals in time-series data is important in studying oscillatory systems, such as the circadian clock or cell cycle. Researchers have devised and evaluated many methods (see a short list in<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Doherty and Kay, 2010</ref>), each with strengths and weaknesses (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Deckard et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Wu et al., 2014</ref>). For example, LombScargle (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Glynn et al., 2006</ref>) and JTK_CYCLE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hughes et al., 2010</ref>) can differentiate between periodic and non-periodic profiles for cosine curves with high noise or low sampling rate (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Deckard et al., 2013</ref>). On the other hand, some popular methods, including Fisher's G Test (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Fisher, 1929;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wichert et al., 2004</ref>) and ARSER (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Yang and Su, 2010</ref>), fail without complete, evenly sampled time series data. To avoid such 'mode failure' and capture the most value from data, one could choose the best algorithm for each experiment. However, for any single experiment the choice of optimal algorithm is often unclear and may depend on unknown features of the data, such as the shape of the oscillatory patterns or the nature of the noise. Alternatively, a fault-tolerant method that avoids mode failure would have wider applicability, insulating the user from tricky decisions. Here, we present MetaCycle, an N-version programming (NVP) method to explore periodic data. NVP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Avizienis and Chen, 1977</ref>) is a concept from the aeronautics industry. Aircraft guidance systems employ multiple independent algorithms and a voting scheme to integrate their results. A method that performs poorly in a particular condition will be outvoted by other methods that better accommodate that condition. NVP has three elements: (i) an initial specification that addresses the problem to be solved, data formats, and methods of integrating specified variables from N-version programs, (ii) two or more independent algorithmic approaches (N-version software, or NVS) to solve the problem and (iii) an execution environment (N-version executive, or NVX) that runs NVS and provides decision algorithms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Avizienis, 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chen and Avizienis, 1978</ref>). MetaCycle incorporates these concepts into its meta2d mode, which analyzes data from a single time series. Using the same input file, MetaCycle::meta2d implements ARSER (ARS), JTK_CYCLE (JTK) and Lomb-Scargle (LS), from dramatically different disciplines, computer science, statistics and physics, respectively. After running these algorithms, meta2d integrates their results in a common output file in the (R) environment. We show that MetaCycle::meta2d avoids mode failure while providing robust power in rhythm detection and accurate phase estimations. Further, researchers often want to integrate results from multiple individuals, preserving individual contributions to an overall result. For analyzing data from multiple time series (e.g. several individuals), MetaCycle provides another mode, MetaCycle::meta3d, a convenient and efficient tool to integrate multiple large-scale time series datasets from individual subjects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>Our functional requirement, the initial specification step of NVP, is identifying periodic signals from time-series datasets. At this step, we also specify input data formats, comparison vectors (c-vectors; including P-values, period length and phase), the decision algorithm, and where it will be applied (cc-points). A detailed description of the decision algorithm is in the vignette. In brief, as default, Fisher's method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Fisher, 1925</ref>) is used to integrate P-values. Arithmetic and circular means are applied in period and phase integration, respectively. The c-vectors do not include amplitude, which is re-calculated with the ordinary least squares method by constructing a general periodic model. Three independent algorithms (ARS, JTK and LS) were then selected from best of breed methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Deckard et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Wu et al., 2014</ref>) and developed into NVS. At the third step, we used the R language as the N-version execution environment (NVX). R assures input consistency for each version, local supervision, and implementation of the decision algorithm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results and discussion</head><p>In model organism experiments, genetically similar animals are typically used, making the identification of each individual sample unimportant. Indeed, in the vast majority of such experiments, only one sample is used from any individual. With human research, though, individual subjects are usually recruited, with samples (e.g. blood, skin) collected from the same person over time. Unless samples are pooled, this generates multiple time series datasets. We classify single time-series datasets from one individual or pools as 2D, while multiple time series datasets are designated 3D (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>). Two functions-meta2d and meta3d in MetaCycle are designed to analyze time-series datasets in these categories. MetaCycle allows users to select one or more cycling detection algorithms from ARS, JTK and LS to analyze their datasets. Using the same input data format, analyzing different kinds of timeseries datasets (evenly or unevenly sampled, with or without replicates or missing values) becomes much easier. Additionally, MetaCycle reports integrated results when analyzing single timeseries datasets with two or three algorithms or when analyzing multiple time series with the same algorithm. Using simulated data generated from several different oscillatory reference waves and adding normally distributed noise, we show that NVP generally performs better than using single algorithm in reporting cycling (Supplementary Figs S2 and S3) or phase values (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S4</ref>). In some cases, NVP may not give better results than the single most suitable method, but it will rarely give the worst results. For example, in analyzing time-series datasets with high temporal resolution (every 1 h over 2 days; Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig.  S3</ref>), NVP does better than ARS but not as well as LS or JTK (Under these conditions, all three methods do relatively well but have similar mode failure, while ARS has relatively more false positive observations.). We also applied the NVP method on experimental timeseries data studying mammalian circadian rhythms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Hughes et al., 2009</ref>) and the yeast cell cycle (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Orlando et al., 2008</ref>). In addition to finding the majority of cycling transcripts in the original paper (90. 9, 83.8 and 55.6% of 24, 12 and 8 h cycling transcripts from mouse liver at FDR &lt; 0.01; Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>), there are 1223 (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S5</ref>), 46 (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6</ref>) and 13 (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S7</ref>) of 24, 12 and 8 h cycling transcripts specially identified by the NVP method. In addition, in yeast cell cycle dataset, the NVP method specifically identified 377 periodic genes that were not listed in the original analyses (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S8</ref>). With more and different large-scale time-series datasets being produced (e.g. ChIP-seq, proteomics, metabolite profiling), tools for better handling these data are needed. Selecting the best algorithm for each dataset can be tricky, as experimental designs and biological unknowns can interact to produce a myriad of complications. Further, algorithms often require different input formats and runtime parameters and sometimes are implemented in different languages (e.g. in R, Python, or MATLAB). To address these problems, we have developed an NVP method using three popular methods— ARS, JTK and LS—in the MetaCycle package in R. To facilitate its use and further development (e.g. new periodicity detection or integration algorithms), we have made the source code available via Github and the program available through CRAN.</p></div>
			<note place="foot" n="1"> Bioinformatics, 2016, 1–3 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw405 Advance Access Publication Date: 4 July 2016 Applications Note Bioinformatics Advance Access published July 19, 2016 at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors thank Dr. Rendong Yang for his input on applying ARSER, Siqi Liu and Dr. Ben Voight for helpful discussions about Fisher's method for integrating P-values, Dr. Yihui Xie for helpful advice about implementing a web application of MetaCycle and Dr. Steve Haase for information on his yeast dataset. We also thank members of the Hogenesch lab for valuable discussion and advice on this project.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the Implementation of N-version Programming for Software Fault Tolerance during Execution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Avizienis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of COMPSAC 77 (First IEEE-CS International Computer Software and Application Conference)</title>
		<meeting>COMPSAC 77 (First IEEE-CS International Computer Software and Application Conference)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1977" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="155" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Methodology of N-Version Programming, Software Fault Tolerance</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Avizienis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="46" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">N-version programming: a fault-tolerance approach to reliability of software operation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Avizienis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Digest of 8th FTCS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="9" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design and analysis of large-scale biological rhythm studies: a comparison of algorithms for detecting periodic signals in biological data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Deckard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3174" to="3180" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circadian control of global gene expression patterns</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Doherty</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Kay</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="444" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Statistical Methods for Research Workers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Fisher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1925" />
			<publisher>Oliver and Boyd</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tests of significance in harmonic analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Fisher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. R. Soc. A</title>
		<meeting>. R. Soc. A</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1929" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="59" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting periodic patterns in unevenly spaced gene expression time series using Lomb–Scargle periodograms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Glynn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="310" to="316" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Harmonics of circadian gene transcription in mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Hughes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000442</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">JTK_CYCLE: an efficient nonparametric algorithm for detecting rhythmic components in genome-scale data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Hughes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Rhythms</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="372" to="380" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global control of cell-cycle transcription by coupled CDK and network oscillators</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Orlando</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">453</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="944" to="947" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying periodically expressed transcripts in microarray time series data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Wichert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of five methods for genome-wide circadian gene identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Rhythms</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing circadian expression data by harmonic regression based on autoregressive spectral estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Su</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="168" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>