
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:54+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology MiRror: a combinatorial analysis web tool for ensembles of microRNAs and their targets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yitzhak</forename>
								<surname>Friedman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biological Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Sudarsky Center for Computational Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Guy</forename>
								<surname>Naamati</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hebrew University of Jerusalem</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91904</postCode>
									<country key="IL">Israel</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michal</forename>
								<surname>Linial</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biological Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Sudarsky Center for Computational Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology MiRror: a combinatorial analysis web tool for ensembles of microRNAs and their targets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1920" to="1921"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq298</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 11, 2010; revised on June 2, 2010; accepted on June 3, 2010</note>
					<note>[16:52 30/6/2010 Bioinformatics-btq298.tex] Page: 1920 1920–1921 Associate Editor: Ivo Hofacker</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The miRror application provides insights on microRNA (miRNA) regulation. It is based on the notion of a combinatorial regulation by an ensemble of miRNAs or genes. miRror integrates predictions from a dozen of miRNA resources that are based on complementary algorithms into a unified statistical framework. For miRNAs set as input, the online tool provides a ranked list of targets, based on set of resources selected by the user, according to their significance of being coordinately regulated. Symmetrically, a set of genes can be used as input to suggest a set of miRNAs. The user can restrict the analysis for the preferred tissue or cell line. miRror is suitable for analyzing results from miRNAs profiling, proteomics and gene expression arrays.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Recent miRNA discovery techniques confirmed the presence of hundreds of miRNAs in healthy and diseased tissues. Currently, approximately 900 miRNAs are reported in human and approximately 600 in mouse. It was shown that miRNA binding sites are not confined solely to 3-untranslated regions (UTRs), but also are found in coding regions and introns (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Kim, 2005</ref>). Furthermore, multiple features were shown to be imperative in regulation by miRNAs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Sethupathy et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Nielsen et al., 2007</ref>). This led to a growing number of resources and algorithms that predict the pairing of miRNAs and their targets (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Mendes et al., 2009</ref>). Currently, mirBase (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Griffiths-Jones et al., 2008</ref>) is the most exhaustive collection of miRNAs with over approximately 15 000 mature miRNA sequences. miRBase collection (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Enright et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Griffiths-Jones et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">John et al., 2004</ref>) is based on MicroCosm algorithm. Additional exhaustive miRNA targets predictors include TargetScan (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Lewis et al., 2003</ref>) and PicTar (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Krek et al., 2005</ref>). Other large-scale resources for microRNA–target pairing includes PITA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kertesz et al., 2007</ref>), microRNA.org that is based on miRanda algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Betel et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Enright et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">John et al., 2004</ref>), DIANA-microT 3.0 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Maragkakis et al., 2009</ref>), miRDB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Wang, 2008</ref>) and ElMMO-MirZ (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Hausser et al., 2009</ref>). For * To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First authors. a subset of miRNAs–target pairs, in vivo experimental validation is available in TarBase database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Papadopoulos et al., 2009</ref>). We have developed miRror, an interactive tool for analyzing experimental results under the notion of coordination in miRNAs regulation. A coordinated regulation by several miRNAs was proposed [see discussion (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Ivanovska and Cleary, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Krek et al., 2005)]</ref>. For a set of miRNAs, miRror outputs a ranked list of gene targets according to their likelihood to be targeted by the miRNA ensemble and vice versa for a set of regulated genes. miRror converts all predictor resources results into a unified platform by incorporating a statistical measure according to the hypergeometrical distribution. For example, in miRNAs overexpressing experiments in human cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Lim et al., 2005</ref>), 174 genes (miR-124) and 65 genes (miR-1) were downregulated and were used as input for miRror. The original miRNAs were identified as the top candidates with a P-value &lt;3e-11 and with 91–93% of the genes marked as targets for the relevant miRNA. Similar results were obtained by using only 50% of the gene lists, supporting the robustness of the miRror platform.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">SYSTEM OVERVIEW</head><p>miRror is a platform by which an experimentalist can gain biological insights on sets of molecular entities. Such sets are the product of large-scale experiments such as miRNA profiling, mass spectrometry proteomics and gene expression data. miRror operates at a dual mode where ensemble of (i) miRNAs and (ii) gene targets/proteins are used as the input.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Prediction tools resources integration</head><p>Database files from multiple miRNA–target prediction resources were separated to human, mouse and fly. The resources used include TargetScan, MicroCosm implemented in miRBase, PicTar, DIANAMicroT, PITA, ElMMO-MirZ, miRanda-based microRNA.org, TargetRank, miRDB and TarBase. miRror combines the resources following a conversion of the miRNAs and gene targets identifiers. RefSeq and UniProtKB identifiers are indicated as the primary entries. TarBase used as a validation resource rather then a prediction database.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">miRtegrate analysis</head><p>miRtegrate protocol is the core of miRror (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). It calculates the probability of matches between miRNAs in the user list and the best set of targets derived from miRNA–target predictions as reported by each of the selected resources. For each gene, we<ref type="bibr">Page: 1921</ref><ref type="bibr">Page: 1920</ref><ref type="bibr">Page: –1921</ref>take into account the list of miRNAs that were associated with it. We calculated the probability of the gene's interaction with the collection of miRNAs in the user set as opposed to the rest of the miRNAs in that database. The miRNA–targets coverage associated with each of the prediction resources is used for the calculation of a statistical significant threshold. We applied a default value of 0.05 as a threshold and calculated the P-value by considering all probabilities that are more significant that the threshold. P-value for miRNAs as input was performed according to the hypergeometric distribution with a correction for multiple testing. The same principle is applied with genes as input. For more details see the 'Help' section of the website.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>microRNAs and their targets</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Advanced options and filtration</head><p>The miRror results are a ranked list of best predicted molecules (miRNAs or genes,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). A refinement of the results is based on several advanced options. Several background distributions such as different tissues and cell lines can be applied for the miRtegrate calculations. Tissues are annotated by the gene expression data from FlyAtlas (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Chintapalli et al., 2007</ref>) and GNF atlas (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Su et al., 2004</ref>). Using these optional backgrounds, new calculation for the P-value is activated to account for the apparent difference in coverage. The user can also select any subset of prediction resources to be used. A default parameter requires that a target will be selected by at least two databases. However, an intuitive option for changing the number of the miRror results is provided to the user by modifying all parameters (P-value threshold, minimal number of miRNAs that bind to each of the targets and minimal number of miRNA–target databases). The web tool provides multiple sorting options, optional filtration thresholds and downloading options. Furthermore, results that are experimentally validated in TarBase are highlighted. The user can forward the results to a set of analysis tools to represent enriched pathways, networks and functional annotations (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We present miRror as a novel integration scheme for a dozen of miRNA–target prediction resources. miRror provides a double-sided view for ensembles of miRNAs or genes. Based on the notion of combinatorial regulation adopted by miRror, the reported list of targets for a miRNAs ensemble is a small subset of the inclusive list that is produced by the summation of predictors. As some miRNAs are predicted to pair with hundreds of targets, a reduction to a small but significant set of targets is valuable for the experimentalist. miRror application towards a set of genes as input is powerful in proposing potential miRNAs ensemble. Thus, the online tool can be used to generate hypotheses on the role of a specific genes or specific minimal set of miRNAs in any cellular settings.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>[16:52 30/6/2010 Bioinformatics-btq298.tex]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. A schematic view of the miRror platform. miRror supports experimental results of miRNAs (m) or genes set (g) as input. The predictor resources (a to x) are unified by miRtegrate into a statistical framework. Biological knowledge is further extracted by applying external tools.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank the ProtoNet team and Solange Karsenty for design and operation of the miRror website.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The microRNA.org resource: targets and expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Betel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="153" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using FlyAtlas to identify better Drosophila melanogaster models of human disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Chintapalli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="715" to="720" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MicroRNA targets in Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Enright</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">miRBase: tools for microRNA genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MirZ: an integrated microRNA expression atlas and target prediction resource</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Hausser</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="272" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combinatorial microRNAs working together to make a difference</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Ivanovska</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Cleary</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Cycle</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3137" to="3142" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human microRNA targets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>John</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">363</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of site accessibility in microRNA target recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kertesz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1278" to="1284" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MicroRNA biogenesis: coordinated cropping and dicing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="376" to="385" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combinatorial microRNA target predictions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Krek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="495" to="500" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of mammalian microRNA targets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Lewis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="787" to="798" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microarray analysis shows that some microRNAs downregulate large numbers of target mRNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Lim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">433</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="769" to="773" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate microRNA target prediction correlates with protein repression levels</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Maragkakis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">295</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Current tools for the identification of miRNA genes and their targets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Mendes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2419" to="2433" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determinants of targeting by endogenous and exogenous microRNAs and siRNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Nielsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RNA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1894" to="1910" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The database of experimentally supported targets: a functional update of TarBase</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Papadopoulos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A guide through present computational approaches for the identification of mammalian microRNA targets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Sethupathy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="881" to="886" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A gene atlas of the mouse and human protein-encoding transcriptomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Su</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6062" to="6067" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">miRDB: a microRNA target prediction and functional annotation database with a wiki interface</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RNA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1012" to="1017" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>