
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:43+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis MMuFLR: missense mutation and frameshift location reporter</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">18 2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Susan</forename>
								<forename type="middle">K</forename>
								<surname>Rathe</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Masonic Cancer Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">James</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Johnson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Supercomputing Institute for Advanced Computation Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kevin</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A T</forename>
								<surname>Silverstein</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Supercomputing Institute for Advanced Computation Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jesse</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Erdmann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Supercomputing Institute for Advanced Computation Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Adrienne</forename>
								<forename type="middle">L</forename>
								<surname>Watson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Masonic Cancer Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Cell Biology and Development</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Brain Tumor Program</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Flavia</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Popescu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Minnesota</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>55455</postCode>
									<settlement>Minneapolis</settlement>
									<region>MN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<forename type="middle">R</forename>
								<surname>Ohlfest</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Minnesota</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>55455</postCode>
									<settlement>Minneapolis</settlement>
									<region>MN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Largaespada</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Masonic Cancer Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Cell Biology and Development</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Minnesota</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>55455</postCode>
									<settlement>Minneapolis</settlement>
									<region>MN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis MMuFLR: missense mutation and frameshift location reporter</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2353" to="2354"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">18 2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt385</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 12, 2013; revised on June 14, 2013; accepted on July 1, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Inanc Birol Availability: http://toolshed.g2.bx.psu.edu/ Contact: rath0096@umn.edu or johns198@umn.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Cancer researchers seeking immunotherapy targets in cancer cells need tools to locate highly expressed proteins unique to cancer cells. Missense mutation and frameshift location reporter (MMuFLR), a Galaxy-based workflow, analyzes next-generation sequencing paired read RNA-seq output to reliably identify small frameshift mutations and missense mutations in highly expressed protein coding genes. MMuFLR ignores known SNPs, low quality reads and poly-A/T sequences. For each frameshift and missense mutation identified, MMuFLR provides the location and sequence of the amino acid substitutions in the novel protein candidates for direct input into epitope evaluation tools.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Next-generation sequencing (NGS) holds promise for individualized targeted treatment, particularly in the realm of cancer immunotherapy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Meinke et al., 2005</ref>). Identifying aberrant transcripts from a patient's tumor cells may provide candidate target epitopes, which can be used to generate patient-specific vaccines. Given the quantity of data generated by NGS, it is important to have an efficient and repeatable process to deconstruct the data and present the most relevant vaccine targets, which includes missense and small frameshift mutations located in proteincoding regions of highly expressed genes. We offer missense mutation and frameshift location reporter (MMuFLR) as a process to analyze NGS RNA-seq paired read output to identify a limited set of peptides that may be targets for immunotherapy. MMuFLR is implemented as a workflow in Galaxy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Blankenberg et al., 2010</ref>). Galaxy is a server-based workflow system designed to run a series of applications, presented to the user as tools, in an easy-to-use repeatable manner. MMuFLR uses a few custom-developed Galaxy tools and those in the standard distribution of Galaxy. In this pilot project, MMuFLR's ability to identify potential vaccine targets was tested in RNA-seq datasets derived from two benign human meningiomas. However, the use of MMuFLR is not limited to cancer immunotherapy. It can also be used to locate prominent mutations responsible for cancer development and for other maladies, such as genetic diseases, developmental defects and drug resistance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">WORKFLOW</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Map read sequences to reference genome</head><p>MMuFLR starts with the NGS RNA-seq paired read output in the form of two fastq-formatted files. Each read pair is individually mapped to the reference genome using TopHat (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Langmead et al., 2009</ref>), resulting in a bam formatted file. The standard Galaxy distribution includes TopHat in its toolset. The custom Galaxy tool 'Filter SAM or BAM' invokes the SAMtools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Li et al., 2009</ref>) view command to filter TopHat bam output by the MAPQ score.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Refine the mapping</head><p>TopHat, as is typical with short read mappers, may find multiple mappings for individual read pairs, which are equally valid. The mapped reads can be analyzed in aggregate to improve upon the initial mapping of individual reads. The MMuFLR workflow uses software from the genome analysis toolkit (GATK) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">DePristo et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">McKenna et al., 2010</ref>) along with Picard-tools (http://picard.sourceforge.net) to perform this collective analysis and realign the individual reads. GATK requires bam input to be labeled with read group information and be sorted in reference order. Several Picard-tools ('Add or Replace Groups', 'Paired Read Mate Fixer', 'Mark Duplicate Reads' and 'Reorder SAM/BAM') add the read groups, filter out unmapped pairs, remove exact duplicate reads and sort the resulting bam output into reference order. Two GATK tools, 'Realigner Target Creator' and 'Indel Realigner', realign the reads based on aggregate information from all reads. Duplicate reads are again identified and removed with 'Mark Duplicate Reads'.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Multiple alignment</head><p>The realigned reads are then assembled into a multiple alignment using the Galaxy tool 'MPileup', which invokes SAMtools MPileup. The custom Galaxy tool, 'Pileup to VCF', filters the pileup results and converts them to the standard variant call format (VCF). Filter parameters to the 'Pileup to VCF' tool *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com include minimum base quality, minimum coverage depth and minimum frequency of a specific allele.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Eliminate common variants</head><p>The resulting VCF file will likely contain many commonly known variants, which would not be useful in determining candidate targets. MMuFLR uses the 'annotate' command of SnpSift (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cingolani et al., 2012</ref>) to merge variants from the samples being evaluated with known variants from the dbSNP database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Sherry et al., 2001</ref>), as well as a user-provided list. Then the 'filter' command of SnpSift is used to eliminate those annotated variant entries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Determine variant effects</head><p>MMuFLR next categorizes the effect of each variant using SnpEff (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cingolani et al., 2012</ref>). The 'filter' command of SnpSift is used to separate the missense and frameshift variants into individual files for reporting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">Report variants</head><p>Finally, a new Galaxy tool, 'SnpEff Ensembl CDS', inserts the variants into transcripts retrieved from Ensembl (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Flicek et al., 2013</ref>) and reports the amino acid sequence of the abnormal peptides. Included in the report are the sequencing depth of reads at the mutation site and the prevalence of the mutation. A parameter can be set to ignore poly-A/T sequences of specified lengths.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>MMuFLR was executed for two human meningioma RNA-seq datasets, MG1 and MG2. MMuFLR settings restricted the selection of candidate genes with minimum coverage of five reads, with a prevalence 40.32 and a Phred quality score of 20 or more. MMuFLR also ignored poly A/T mononucleotide sequences of 5. MMuFLR identified 16 frameshifts and 576 missense mutations in the MG1 sample, and 10 frameshifts and 509 missense mutations in the MG2 sample. The candidates were evaluated for their presence in other samples. Sanger sequencing of nine prominent candidates, not found in other cancer samples, verified the existence of the mutations within the tumor samples, with the MMuFLR prevalence accurately reflecting the relative abundance of the mutation within the total transcripts present (<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>). Because there were no normal samples available for comparison, these mutations may represent rare germline variants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>One challenge for developing patient-specific cancer vaccines is identifying novel peptides specific to the tumor cells. MMuFLR is an innovative Galaxy-based software tool designed to locate highly abundant transcripts with frameshift or missense mutations within protein-coding sequences. MMuFLR ignores potentially false candidates such as frameshifts located within poly A/T sequences of mononucleotides, which is believed to result from a loss of fidelity during replication due to dissociation within the reverse transcriptase binding site in a phenomenon referred to as 'stuttering'. Because there is always a lag between the identification of SNPs and their incorporation into the dbSNP database, MMuFLR provides the ability to establish a supplementary SNP table in which the researcher can record and thereby ignore SNPs identified during their research efforts. MMuFLR has been successfully tested with both human and mouse samples, but should be easily adaptable to other organisms.Note: Included in the table are the location of the variant, the reference sequence being replaced, the fraction of reads with the mutation (prevalence) and the number of reads (depth).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Frameshift and missense mutations identified by MMuFLR and verified using Sanger sequencing</figDesc><table>Sample 
Gene 
Variant 
position 

Reference Variant Prevalence Depth 

Frameshift mutations 
MG1 ZNF812 
chr19:9800968 
CT 
T 
0.50 
20 
MG2 CPNE1 
chr20:34215234 
G 
TG 
0.45 
98 
MRPL16 chr11:59577372 
C 
GC 
0.37 
27 
ZP3 
chr7:76071183 
T 
TG 
0.50 
14 
DNAJB7 chr22:41257834 
A 
TA 
1.00 
6 

Missense mutations 
MG1 COL6A2 
chr21:47545737 
A 
G 
0.50 
899 
MG2 APP 
chr21:27484329 
T 
A 
0.46 
432 
FRMPD2 chr10:49389016 
A 
G 
0.48 
227 
CCDC74A chr2:132288362 
T 
C 
0.97 
29 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">S.K.Rathe et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank the BioMedical Genomics Center for providing RNA sequencing, oligo preparation and Sanger sequencing, and the Minnesota Supercomputing Institute, which maintains the Galaxy software, and provides data management services and training.Conflict of Interest: Dr. Largaespada is co-owner and advisor to NeoClone Biotechnology, Inc. and Discovery Genomics, Inc. No resources or personnel from either company were involved in this research in any way.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Galaxy: a web-based genome analysis tool for experimentalists</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Blankenberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Protoc. Mol. Biol., Chapter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1910</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using Drosophila melanogaster as a model for genotoxic chemical mutational studies with a new program</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Cingolani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SnpSift. Front. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framework for variation discovery and genotyping using next-generation DNA sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Depristo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="491" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Flicek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Langmead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The sequence alignment/Map format and SAMtools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2078" to="2079" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genome analysis toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Mckenna</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1297" to="1303" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antigenome technology: a novel approach for the selection of bacterial vaccine candidate antigens</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Meinke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vaccine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2035" to="2041" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">dbSNP: the NCBI database of genetic variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Sherry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="308" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>