
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:58+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining ModuLand plug-in for Cytoscape: determination of hierarchical layers of overlapping network modules and community centrality</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Máté</forename>
								<surname>Szalay-Bek</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Semmelweis University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1444</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Robin</forename>
								<surname>Palotai</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Semmelweis University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1444</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Balázs</forename>
								<surname>Szappanos</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Biological Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>6726</postCode>
									<settlement>Szeged</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">István</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Kovács</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Semmelweis University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1444</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Loránd Eötvös University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute for Solid State Physics and Optics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Wigner Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1525</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Balázs</forename>
								<surname>Papp</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Biological Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>6726</postCode>
									<settlement>Szeged</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Péter</forename>
								<surname>Csermely</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Semmelweis University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1444</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mario</forename>
								<surname>Albrecht</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining ModuLand plug-in for Cytoscape: determination of hierarchical layers of overlapping network modules and community centrality</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2202" to="2204"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts352</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on November 21, 2011; revised on June 13, 2012; accepted on June 14, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [19:06 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts352.tex] Page: 2202 2202–2204 Associate Editor: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Contact: csermely</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The ModuLand plug-in provides Cytoscape users an algorithm for determining extensively overlapping network modules. Moreover, it identifies several hierarchical layers of modules, where meta-nodes of the higher hierarchical layer represent modules of the lower layer. The tool assigns module cores, which predict the function of the whole module, and determines key nodes bridging two or multiple modules. The plug-in has a detailed JAVA-based graphical interface with various colouring options. The ModuLand tool can run on Windows, Linux or Mac OS. We demonstrate its use on protein structure and metabolic networks. Availability: The plug-in and its user guide can be downloaded freely from: http://www.linkgroup.hu/modules.php.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Nodes of biological networks often belong to multiple network communities. Recently, a number of methods were published to determine tightly or extensively overlapping network modules (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Adamcsek et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ahn et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Fortunato, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kovács et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Mihalik and Csermely, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Palla et al., 2005</ref>). Our ModuLand framework (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kovács et al., 2010</ref>) introduced community landscapes. The x–y plane of a community landscape is a conventional 2D visualization of the network, whereas the z-axis represents community centrality. Community centrality of a given edge (or node) was defined as the sum of local influence zones of all network edges (or nodes) including the given edge (or node; Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S1</ref>). Thus community centrality represents an integrated measure of the whole network's influence to one of its edges or nodes. Hills of the community landscape correspond to network modules (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S1</ref>) yielding extensive overlaps. This concept led to the development of the ModuLand family of network modularization methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kovács et al., 2010</ref>). * To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as the joint first Authors.</p><p>The widely used Cytoscape program (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Shannon et al., 2003</ref>) has several very useful clustering plug-ins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bader and Houge, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Morris et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Rhrissorrakrai and Gunsalus, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Rivera et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Su et al., 2010</ref>). However, these methods do not focus on extensive modular overlaps, and do not build a modular hierarchy, where meta-nodes of the higher level represent modules of the lower level. Moreover, existing plug-ins do not provide measures identifying the centre of the module, as well as key nodes bridging two or multiple modules (see Supplementary Table S9, and Supplementary Discussion). Here, we introduce the Cytoscape plug-in of the most widely applicable version of the ModuLand method family (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kovács et al., 2010</ref>). We demonstrate its ability to determine biologically relevant, extensively overlapping network modules, hierarchical layers of modules, module cores and key inter-modular nodes using protein structure and metabolic networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">SOFTWARE OVERVIEW</head><p>The ModuLand Cytoscape plug-in uses the LinkLand influence zone determination method and the ProportionalHill module assignment method of our formerly published ModuLand network module determination method family (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kovács et al., 2010</ref>). These two methods provide a good trade-off between the fast (but rather inaccurate), and accurate (but rather slow) other ModuLand methods. The installation of the ModuLand plug-in follows Cytoscape procedures. This is much easier than the setup required for the earlier version (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kovács et al., 2010</ref>). The program can be distributed as a single .jar file. Moreover, the current implementation works on Linux, Windows and Mac OS, thereby extending the options of the former version. The plug-in determines extensively overlapping modules using any undirected network type and weight description of Cytoscape. Moreover, the plug-in calculates a set of hierarchical modules. In the modular hierarchy, modules of the lower level become metanodes of the upper level, and modular overlaps of the lower level become weights of the meta-edges at the upper level. The plug-in creates, automatically re-loads and visualizes the higher and higher level hierarchies (with lower and lower number of meta-nodes and meta-edges, see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>), until the whole network coalesces into a single meta-node.The lower number of modules at higher hierarchical levels may be visualized either using the meta-nodes of the higher hierarchical level itself, or projecting this higher level modular structure to the nodes of the original network. On any level of module hierarchy, nodes or meta-nodes can be visualized assigning them the colour of the module they mostly belong to. This shows a non-overlapping assignment of nodes to modules. Nodes can also be marked by blending the colours of the modules proportional to the overlapping module assignment of the given node. Edges may be optionally visualized as a mix of the colour of their two nodes. The plugin sets meta-node labels on the higher hierarchical level based on the modules of one level below in the hierarchy. The metanode on the higher hierarchical level representing the module has the name of the node having the highest modular assignment value for the corresponding module at one level below in the hierarchy. Node colours can also visualize several node (or metanode) measures including weighted degree, betweenness centrality, community centrality, overlap and bridgeness (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>). The plug-in has an option to merge highly similar module pairs containing roughly the same nodes or meta-nodes with the same intensity. For merging of modules the plug-in offers a correlation histogram, and allows the user to select an appropriate correlation threshold. The runtime complexity of the plug-in version remained ∼ O(n 3 ), as defined earlier (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kovács et al., 2010</ref>). To enhance the performance of the plug-in for calculating the higher hierarchical layers further, we introduced a user-selected optimization. This results in the disappearance of meta-edges with very small weights at the higher hierarchical levels. These low intensity meta-edges are derived from the minor overlaps of distant modules of the lower level. This optimization allowed a speedup in running time by a factor of 7 for larger networks (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_0">Table S10</ref>). The plug-in is capable to generate overview reports for each hierarchical level. These reports list the number of the nodes (metanodes), edges (meta-edges) and modules, the effective number of modules (see<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kovács et al., 2010</ref>) and the size of each module. The overview also contains the list of the 10 nodes of each module having maximal module assignment value to the respective module (called as the module core). Data related to the module assignment and the calculated measures of nodes (and meta-nodes of higher hierarchical levels) can be exported in a csv or txt format. The plug-in contains a Help function, and a detailed step-by-step User Guide can also be downloaded from the plug-in webpage: www.linkgroup.hu/modules.php.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ModuLand plug-in for Cytoscape</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS AND CONCLUSION</head><p>ModuLand-derived communities of various yeast protein–protein interaction networks gave a functionally meaningful description of the yeast interactome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kovács et al., 2010</ref>). Function of module core proteins proved to be good indicator of the function of the whole</p><p>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE<ref type="bibr">[19:06 19</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>M.Szalay-Bek ˝ o et al.</head><p>module (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Mihalik and Csermely, 2011</ref>). Here, we demonstrate the use of the ModuLand Cytoscape plug-in on the protein structure network of Escherichia coli Met-tRNA synthase, since an elegant study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Ghosh and Vishveshwara, 2007</ref>) showed the existence of four alternative communication paths in this enzyme. The five major sub-domains of Met-tRNA synthase were well reflected by the five modules obtained at the second hierarchical level of the protein structure network (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>; Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S3</ref>). Key amino acids of the most frequently used communication path (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Ghosh and Vishveshwara, 2007</ref>) either belonged to the module cores of the three modules involved in transmission of conformational changes, or were inter-modular nodes between these modules (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S4</ref>). These observations were in agreement with earlier findings (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Ghosh and Vishveshwara, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Sethi et al., 2009</ref>). We further demonstrated the use of the ModuLand plug-in by comparing the modular structures of the metabolic networks of the free-living bacterium E.coli and the endosymbiont Buchnera aphidicola (<ref type="bibr">Pál et al., 2006</ref>). E.coli metabolic module cores had a significant overlap (Fisher's exact test P = 1.4×10 −7 ; see Supplementary Information for more details) with the modules determined earlier by<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Guimera and Amaral (2005)</ref>. Both visual inspection (see Supplementary Figs S4–S7) and numerical values (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S7</ref>) suggested a more differentiated modular structure of the E.coli metabolic network than that of B.aphidicola. This finding is in agreement with earlier findings (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Kreimer et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Mihalik and Csermely, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Parter et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Samal et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Tamames et al., 2007</ref>). The difference in modular structure was not likely to be caused by the difference in the size of the E.coli and B.aphidicola networks (see Supplementary Figs S8 and S9, and Supplementary Tables S7 and S8). E.coli module cores corresponded to significantly less metabolic functions than those of B.aphidicola (0.53 versus 0.67 functions per module core reactions, respectively; bootstrap method P = 0.0392). This difference remained even when we used an ensemble of 1000 randomly selected sub-networks of the E.coli metabolic network having the same number of nodes or edges as found in the smaller B.aphidicola network (see Supplementary Material for more details). Moreover, additional tests suggested that the large twinmodules forming the centre of the B.aphidicola network were not responsible for the differences observed in the number of metabolic functions (see Supplementary Material). These results indicated that modules of the metabolic network of an organism from a variable environment (E.coli) are more specialized than metabolic network modules of a symbiont having a constant environment (B.aphidicola). It is noteworthy that our result is in agreement with earlier findings using non-overlapping modularization (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Parter et al., 2007</ref>), which is a further indication that the module cores of the plug-in capture well the biologically relevant function of modules. In conclusion, the ModuLand Cytoscape plug-in provides a userfriendly and efficient method to identify and visualize a hierarchy of extensively overlapping modules, and determines key network positions (like module cores and bridges). As shown by several case studies, modules identified by the plug-in correspond to biologically meaningful groups, module cores help the identification of biological functions and inter-modular nodes have a key role in a variety of biological networks.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [19:06 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts352.tex] Page: 2203 2202–2204</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The hierarchical modular structure determined by the ModuLand Cytoscape plug-in. The left side shows the protein structure network of E.coli Met-tRNA synthase and its three hierarchical levels as determined by the plug-in. Each meta-node of a higher hierarchical level represents a module of the level right below. All networks are coloured according to the five modules identified on hierarchical level 1. This colouring option can be performed by the two clicks of the plug-in main dialog box shown on the right</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank the Editor and the anonymous Reviewers for their comments and suggestions, Amit Ghosh (Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, CA, USA) and Saraswathi Vishveshwara (Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, India) for the 3D coordinates of E.coli Met-tRNA-synthase, and members of the LINK-Group (www.linkgroup.hu) for their discussions and help.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CFinder: Locating cliques and overlapping modules in biological networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Adamcsek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1021" to="1023" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Link communities reveal multiscale complexity in networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Ahn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">466</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="761" to="764" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An automated method for finding molecular complexes in large protein interaction networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Bader</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W V</forename>
				<surname>Houge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Community detection in graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Fortunato</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">486</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study of communication pathways in methionyl-tRNA synthetase by molecular dynamics simulations and structure network analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ghosh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Vishveshwara</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15711" to="15716" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variations in clique and community patterns in protein structures during allosteric communication: investigation of dynamically equilibrated structures of methyionyl tRNA synthetase complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ghosh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Vishveshwara</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11398" to="11407" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional cartography of complex metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Guimera</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Amaral</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">422</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="895" to="900" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Community landscapes: a novel, integrative approach for the determination of overlapping network modules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Kovács</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12528</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of modularity in bacterial metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Kreimer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6796" to="6981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heat shock partially dissociates the overlapping modules of the yeast protein-protein interaction network: a systems level model of adaptation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Á</forename>
				<surname>Mihalik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Csermely</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002187</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">clusterMaker: a multi-algorithm clustering plugin for Cytoscape</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Morris</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J H</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">436</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chance and necessity in the evolution of minimal metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Pál</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">440</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="667" to="670" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uncovering the overlapping community structure of complex networks in nature and society</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Palla</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">435</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="814" to="818" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental variability and modularity of bacterial metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Parter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">169</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MINE: module identification in networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Rhrissorrakrai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Gunsalus</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="0192" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NeMo: Network Module identification in Cytoscape</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Rivera</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental versatility promotes modularity in genome-scale metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Samal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">135</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamical networks in tRNA:protein complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Sethi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6620" to="6625" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Shannon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2498" to="2504" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GLay: community structure analysis of biological networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Su</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3135" to="3137" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modular organization in the reductive evolution of proteinprotein interaction networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Tamames</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">94</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>