
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:29+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">More challenges for machine-learning protein interactions</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Tobias</forename>
								<surname>Hamp</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Informatics, Bioinformatics and Computational Biology I12</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Technische Universität Mü nchen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>85748</postCode>
									<settlement>Garching/Munich</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Burkhard</forename>
								<surname>Rost</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Informatics, Bioinformatics and Computational Biology I12</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Technische Universität Mü nchen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>85748</postCode>
									<settlement>Garching/Munich</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">More challenges for machine-learning protein interactions</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu857</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on September 9, 2014; revised on December 6, 2014; accepted on December 23, 2014</note>
					<note>Sequence analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Alfonso Valencia Availability and implementation: Datasets used in our analyses are available at https://rostlab.org/ owiki/index.php/PPI_challenges Contact: rost@in.tum.de Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Machine learning may be the most popular computational tool in molecular biology. Providing sustained performance estimates is challenging. The standard cross-validation protocols usually fail in biology. Park and Marcotte found that even refined protocols fail for protein–protein interactions (PPIs). Results: Here, we sketch additional problems for the prediction of PPIs from sequence alone. First, it not only matters whether proteins A or B of a target interaction A–B are similar to proteins of training interactions (positives), but also whether A or B are similar to proteins of non-interactions (negatives). Second, training on multiple interaction partners per protein did not improve performance for new proteins (not used to train). In contrary, a strictly non-redundant training that ignored good data slightly improved the prediction of difficult cases. Third, which prediction method appears to be best crucially depends on the sequence similarity between the test and the training set, how many true interactions should be found and the expected ratio of negatives to positives. The correct assessment of performance is the most complicated task in the development of prediction methods. Our analyses suggest that PPIs square the challenge for this task.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Prediction is the acid test for understanding</head><p>Machine learning appears to be easily applicable through tools such as Weka (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Hall et al., 2009</ref>). As opposed to standard statistical analyses, its ability to predict allows distinguishing 'true understanding' from 'rationalization given the fact'. However, if we choose more free parameters than supported by the evidence, we easily over-train or over-optimize, i.e. predictions drop to the descriptive level of statistics, instead of being the acid test for understanding. Crossvalidation (CV) and testing on new data are supposed to prevent such a failure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Refined CV</head><p>Standard CV proceeds as follows. Given a set of observations S to machine learn: split S into two sets S train (to optimize parameters) and S test (to assess performance). Even better: split S into m different sets and use one for testing and the other m À 1 for training, essentially creating m different solutions to the problem. Many refined versions of the above protocol have been implemented (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Kohavi, 1995</ref>). However, after several decades of applying machine learning to computational biology, we observe that the above procedures do not suffice to generate sustained performance estimates. Several refinement steps are needed. First, we need to reduce the redundancybetween S train and S test. What exactly constitutes redundancy is not trivial to define, but if we can infer that test protein A has feature X only because it is sequence similar to a training protein A' with feature X (homology-based inference), redundancy is too high (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Rost, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Rost and Sander, 1993</ref>). In this case, even simple statistics can mislead (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Rost, 2002</ref>). Second, we need to split S into three, not two types of sets: training, cross-training and testing (also termed training, testing, hold-out). The cross-training set will be used to decide which method to choose in the end: if you developed two methods m 1 and m 2 and could only publish one, you cannot use the test set for both, optimizing the choice 'm 1 versus m 2 ' and estimating performance. Data used for method optimization no longer provides independent performance estimates. For this, you need the crosstraining complication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3">Refined CV fails for machine-learning PPIs</head><p>Park &amp; Marcotte have demonstrated that the above refined CV still fails for the prediction of protein–protein interactions (PPIs) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Park and Marcotte, 2012</ref>). For each test interaction A–B between proteins A and B they distinguished three cases: C1 if both A and B, but not the interaction A–B, were used for training, C2 if this was the case for either A or B and C3 if neither A nor B were used for training. By a great margin, all methods performed best for C1 and worst for C3, i.e. for the prediction of proteins without any experimental annotation. Arguably, such new proteins are most interesting to predict. Here, we present findings that expand on this theme that machine-learning PPIs requires much more careful data set preparations than other applications. Ultimately, PPIs appear to square the noise and the complexity of reducing it, similar to the effect overrepresented protein families had on the prediction of protein function (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Rost, 2002</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.1">Human PPIs</head><p>The Hippie database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Schaefer et al., 2012</ref>) collects human PPIs with experimental annotations. A reliability score grades each interaction according to the trust in the annotation. We followed the Hippie procedure and reduced version 1.2 (<ref type="bibr">Aug 2011</ref>) to the top 10% highest scoring interactions to obtain a high-quality subset (HumanHQ). It contained 7237 PPIs from 3915 unique proteins. We applied the same procedure to Hippie version 1.6 (<ref type="bibr">Nov 2013</ref>) and used the difference between both sets to test (HumanHQ_new; 7201 new PPIs in 3877 proteins; 1561 of these 3877 proteins were new).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2">Yeast PPIs</head><p>Reliable, manually curated yeast PPIs were in the core data set of the Database of Interacting Proteins<ref type="bibr">[YeastHQ;</ref><ref type="bibr">Apr 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Salwinski et al., 2004)]</ref>. It contains 4796 PPIs among 6434 proteins. Due to slow growth, we could not compile a large enough 'new' test data set.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.3">Redundancy reduction</head><p>We reduced redundancy of both, HumanHQ and YeastHQ, by excluding sequence-similar interactions as follows. We considered proteins X to be sequence similar to X 0 if their HSSP value (HVAL) was greater than 20 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Mika and Rost, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Rost, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Sander and Schneider, 1991</ref>). This corresponds to $40% pairwise sequence identity for 250 aligned residues. When we included an interaction A–B in the non-redundant set, we excluded all interactions A 0 –C and B 0 –D (A 0 similar to A; B 0 similar to B). Put differently: A and B were sequence dissimilar to any other protein in the data set. We refer to both sets as HumanHQ_nr (842 PPIs) and YeastHQ_nr (746 PPIs).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.4">CV and testing (C1, C2, C3)</head><p>Here, we introduce 'generalized' Park-Marcotte classes C1–C3. Proteins of a test interaction only need to be similar (HVAL(X,X 0 ) &gt; 20), not identical, to proteins of the training set to be in class C1 or C2. We randomly split each non-redundant set of PPIs (HumanHQ, YeastHQ) into 10 partitions, using nine to train and one to test. All test cases belonged to class C3, because neither A nor B of a test interaction A–B had HVAL &gt; 20 to any protein in the training set. The non-redundant C2 test set first contained each PPI A–B of the full PPI set (HumanHQ or YeastHQ) if exactly one protein (A or B) had HVAL &gt; 20 to any protein in the training set. We redundancy reduced this C2 test set internally in the same way as the full HQ sets before. The C1 test set was created in analogy to C2, except that both proteins A and B needed to have HVAL &gt; 20 to proteins in the training set. We repeated this 10 times so that each of the 10 partitions was the test set exactly once. Classes C1, C2 and C3 contained 1825, 2046 and 842 PPIs for human and 1636, 1663 and 746 for yeast. We applied the same procedure to the time difference test, with the full redundancy reduced HumanHQ as the training set and test sets C1–C3 created from HumanHQ_new (C1: 392, C2: 580 and C3: 218 PPIs).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.5">Negative interactions</head><p>Given a positive training set (known PPIs), our definitions of C1–C3 classified each protein pair AB in an organism (none (C3), one (C2) or both (C1) of the proteins A and B have HVAL &gt; 20 to proteins in the training set). Hence, we sampled negatives (non-interactions) randomly for each class C1–C3 from all protein pairs in that class. For example, all the C1 negatives of one training test set combination were sampled from all pairs that were classified as C1 with respect to this particular training set (See Supplementary Material S1.1). All proteins of an organism were given by the EBI Reference Proteomes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Dessimoz et al., 2012</ref>) and filtered so that no protein was shorter than 50 or longer than 5000 residues. The number of negatives was set to be 10 times higher than the number of positives in each training and test set. We always removed negatives listed as positive in the full Hippie 1.2 database, i.e. including low-quality experimental evidence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.6">Data set modifications</head><p>The setup described so far was the default for training and comparing different PPI prediction methods. In the following, we describe modifications. Modification 1: No sequence similarity between negative training and testing. We tested the effect on performance in class C3 when sequence-similar negatives were removed between training and test sets. To this end, we sampled negatives as before from all C3 pairs in an organism, but made sure that no protein of a negative training interaction had HVAL &gt; 20 to a protein of a negative test interaction. Modification 2: Bringing redundancy back. PPIs can be redundant on the level of interaction partners and on the level of sequences. We explored the impact of both types in the training set (keeping test and negative training sets the same; see Supplementary Material S1.2). Redundant interactions were added from the full HQ data set (HumanHQ or YeastHQ). For redundancy on the level of interaction partners, we took the proteins of all positive PPIs in a redundancy-reduced training set and added all PPIs between them (2.5 6 0.1x more PPIs for human, 3.1 6 0.1x for yeast). Sequence redundancy was added by including all PPIs in the training set that did not violate the sequence similarity constraints to the respective test sets C1–C3 (4.9 6 0.2x more PPIs for human, 4.3 6 0.1x for yeast). We obtained similar results for both types of redundancy. For simplicity, we only show those for interaction partner redundancy in the main text (See Supplementary Material S4.2 for others).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.7">Evaluation</head><p>All prediction methods that we assessed can be retrained with custom PPIs and provide a score for each test PPI. We could therefore calculate standard recall-precision curves. To minimize sampling noise, we repeated every experiment above ten times from the beginning (e.g. we performed ten times 10-fold CVs) and averaged over 10 curves. The curves in the Results correspond to the difference between two such average curves, because we measured the change in precision when applying the modifications described before. They were calculated by subtracting the precision values of one curve from those of another curve.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.8">Prediction methods</head><p>Park and Marcotte (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Park and Marcotte, 2012</ref>) established PIPE2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Pitre et al., 2008</ref>) and SigProd (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Martin et al., 2005</ref>) as the top two methods that predict PPIs from sequence alone and that have already been published. We used those two along with the lower performing but methodologically distinct AutoCorrelation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Guo et al., 2008</ref>) and a new in-house method named PPI-PK (Protein-Protein Interaction Profile Kernel; unpublished). The latter encodes a PPI as pairs of k-mers that are conserved in the evolutionary profiles of the two sequences and then uses SVMs for prediction. PIPE2 was the only method that did not use negative PPIs during training. The other details did not matter with respect to the results we report, because we confirmed similar findings for several, very different methods developed in-house over the last years (data not shown).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results and Discussion</head><p>Sequence similarity has not played a crucial role in the evaluation of PPIs predictions. One reason may be that homology-based inference of PPIs works reliably only for high levels of similarity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Mika and Rost, 2006</ref>). Park and Marcotte discovered that the accuracy of predicting a new target interaction between proteins A and B depends crucially on whether both A and B (C1), any of the two (C2) or neither (C3) have been used for training (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Park and Marcotte, 2012</ref>). Here, we have investigated three important questions that arose from this discovery. Firstly, can we improve methods by using noninteracting pairs (negative PPIs) that are sequence-similar between training and testing? Secondly, how does data redundancy in the training set affect the three classes (C1–C3)? Thirdly, which prediction method is best and can we actually determine real-world prediction accuracy?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Sampling of negatives crucial for optimal performance</head><p>The work by Park and Marcotte suggests that higher sequence similarity between training and test sets improves performance. This might also pertain to negatives (non-interacting protein pairs), which have exclusively been sampled from proteins of the positive training interactions in (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Park and Marcotte, 2012</ref>). We increased similarity by sampling negative PPIs separately for each class C1–C3 from all the respective class-specific protein pairs in an organism (See Section 2). This procedure made negative test PPIs highly sequence-similar to negative training PPIs and sampled all negatives from the same population (See Supplementary Material S1.1). We measured the effect of this increased sequence similarity with high-quality data sets and several prediction methods. We trained and evaluated models twice: First, all negatives were chosen randomly from all C3 pairs of an organism. Then we did the same, but proteins had to be sequence-dissimilar between training and test sets (See Section 2;<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). For all data sets, sequence similarity between negative PPIs yielded higher performance for three of the four methods tested (human CV:<ref type="figure">Fig. 2A</ref>, other results and details in Supplementary Material S4.1). PIPE2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Pitre et al., 2008</ref>) was the exception as it did not use negatives for training. Its differences resulted from a different protein background population from which negative PPIs were sampled. This might indicate that the test set was more difficult, thus emphasizing the performance gain of the other methods. The same conclusions hold for yeast and new human PPIs, but the effect of the background population was weaker. AutoCorrelation performed only slightly better than random in C3, so that the differences were not as pronounced as for the other methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Challenging predictions not improved by sampling many PPIs per protein</head><p>In machine learning, good training data is equally important to choosing the right learning method. One frequent problem is redundancy. It may carry important signals, but also 'mislead the learner' to focus on less relevant aspects. PPI data sets can have two types of redundancy: overrepresented protein families and overrepresented interaction partners. For example even if all proteins are pairwise dissimilar, one protein may still have many more interaction partners than others. On the other hand, proteins may still be sequence similar even if every protein has only one interaction partner. Most developers have not redundancy reduced PPI data sets at all; very, we created two data sets (Variant 1 and Variant 2) which differ from a third Baseline data set in terms of redundancy amongst positive training PPIs and sequence similarity between negative training and test PPIs. We compared the PPI prediction performance achieved with each variant to the performance of the baseline (<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>)</p><p>few did it on the level of sequences. Supposedly, interaction modes are so diverse that additional PPIs always add knowledge. Also, different proteins can use the same mechanism of interaction (e.g. SH2/ 3 domains). Thus, more PPIs should also help predicting interactions between so far unseen proteins. We put this hypothesis to the test. First, we performed CVs with the non-redundant data sets used before. We considered test classes C1–C3. Then we compared these results to those obtained after adding all interactions back to the training sets and repeating the experiments (See Section 2;<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). For both yeast and human, we found significant differences in performance for classes C1 and C2 in 15 out of 16 experiments, but virtually no difference for C3 (<ref type="figure">Fig. 2B</ref>for human CV; others in Supplementary Material S4.2). For the lowest levels of recall, the non-redundant training sets even performed slightly better. Adding even more redundancy strengthened the trends (Supplementary Material S4.2). Our observations were puzzling. A PPI may be more likely to be predicted if similar proteins in the training data have many interaction partners. This would explain some of the difference that we observed in C1–C2. However, it does not explain how a fraction of the input data can achieve the same or even better performance than the full data. We additionally suspect a distinction between signals that act on the level of particular family pairs (interologs) and those that are universally valid among all proteins. For C1 and C2, a new PPI can use the signals specific for at least one of its families, which may be learned if multiple interaction partners for each protein are allowed. For C3 pairs, neither protein can 'hook' to a family and universally valid motifs might dominate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Best method lies in the eye of the beholder</head><p>If we zoom into the comparison of two methods, e.g. PIPE2 and SigProd, we see that test classes C1–C3 impact the methods differently and even change which method is perceived as better (Supplementary Material S4.3). For human C1, e.g. PIPE2 outperforms SigProd up to $51% recall and becomes worse than SigProd for higher recalls. The latter regime is relevant for finding many interactions with as few wet-lab experiments as possible. The precision of PIPE2 in C2 was reduced and lower than SigProd starting at much lower recall levels than in C1. In C3, SigProd consistently outperformed PIPE2. This was the same for all data sets (HumanHQ, YeastHQ and HumanHQ_new). What is considered the best method to predict PPIs from sequence depends on the sequence similarity between training and test sets, on how many true PPIs should be found (recall) and hence also on the ratio of positives to negatives. The latter has been estimated for human and yeast several times, but keeps changing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Rajagopala et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Sambourg and Thierry-Mieg, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Stumpf et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Venkatesan et al., 2009</ref>). Its effect on precision can be estimated quite precisely (Supplementary Material S2), but classes C1–C3 further complicate matters. For C1, e.g. the ratio might be much lower than for C3 as we may have already found many PPIs experimentally (Supplementary Material S3). In practice, this could turn the intuition that C1 is 'easier' than C2 or C3 on its head. The best C1 predictions may actually contain fewer true interactions than the best C2 or C3 predictions. One may also challenge the biological relevance of the remaining C1 interactions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusions</head><p>Our results prove that the determination of performance of PPI prediction methods is even more complicated than anticipated. They also stress the importance of data preparation when machinelearning PPIs. Just as the choice of the method, the best preparation depends on the objective. The latter is largely defined by the sequence similarity between targets and templates (class C1 or C3?). The levels of similarity that are important depend on many parameters, including model organism and amount of experimental data. This is different for cross-and interspecies predictions. For optimal performance, we may also need to trade-off data quality with proteome coverage. Lastly, the sequence similarity threshold that defined classes C1–C3 was arbitrary (HVAL &gt; 20). All trends that we observed here will most likely be reinforced when pushing it to the upper or lower limits. Clearly, much remains to be improved for sequence-based PPI predictions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by a grant from the Alexander von Humboldt foundation through the German Ministry for Research and Education (BMBF: Bundesministerium fuer Bildung und Forschung). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig1.</head><figDesc>Fig 1. Flow chart of data preparation. Starting with all redundant positive PPIs (upper left), we created two data sets (Variant 1 and Variant 2) which differ from a third Baseline data set in terms of redundancy amongst positive training PPIs and sequence similarity between negative training and test PPIs. We compared the PPI prediction performance achieved with each variant to the performance of the baseline (Fig. 2)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 1521 Bioinformatics, 31(10), 2015, 1521–1525 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btu857 Advance Access Publication Date: 12 January 2015 Discovery Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">T.Hamp and B.Rost at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">More challenges for machine-learning PPIs</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank Yung Ki Park (HJKRI) and Shawn Martin (Sandia) for method implementations and very helpful hints; to Tim Karl (TUM) for invaluable help with hardware and software; to Marlena Drabik (TUM) for administrative support. Thanks also to Miguel Andrade (MDC Berlin) and the whole Hippie team for providing such an excellent resource. Last, not least, thanks to Rolf Apweiler (UniProt, EBI, Hinxton), Amos Bairoch (CALIPHO, SIB, Geneva), Ioannis Xenarios (Swiss-Prot, SIB, Geneva), and their crews for maintaining excellent databases and to all experimentalists who enabled this analysis by making their data publicly available.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward community standards in the quest for orthologs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Dessimoz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="900" to="904" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using support vector machine combined with auto covariance to predict protein-protein interactions from protein sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Guo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3025" to="3030" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The WEKA data mining software: an update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIGKDD Explor. Newsl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study of cross-validation and bootstrap for accuracy estimation and model selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Kohavi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IJCAI&apos;95 Proceedings</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Montreal, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1137" to="1143" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting protein-protein interactions using signature products</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Martin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="218" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UniqueProt: creating representative protein sequence sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Mika</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Rost</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3789" to="3791" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein–protein interactions more conserved within species than across species</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Mika</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Rost</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flaws in evaluation schemes for pair-input computational predictions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Park</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Marcotte</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1134" to="1136" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global investigation of protein-protein interactions in yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae using re-occurring short polypeptide sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Pitre</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4286" to="4294" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The binary protein-protein interaction landscape of Escherichia coli</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Rajagopala</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Twilight zone of protein sequence alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Rost</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enzyme function less conserved than anticipated</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Rost</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">318</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="595" to="608" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of protein secondary structure at better than 70% accuracy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Rost</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Sander</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">232</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="584" to="599" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The database of interacting proteins: 2004 update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Salwinski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New insights into protein-protein interaction data lead to increased estimates of the S. cerevisiae interactome size</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Sambourg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Thierry-Mieg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">605</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Database of homology-derived structures and the structural meaning of sequence alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Sander</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Schneider</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HIPPIE: Integrating protein interaction networks with experiment based quality scores</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Schaefer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31826</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Estimating the size of the human interactome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Stumpf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>PNAS</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6959" to="6964" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An empirical framework for binary interactome mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Venkatesan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="90" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>