
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:46+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">ms-data-core-api: an open-source, metadata-oriented library for computational proteomics</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yasset</forename>
								<surname>Perez-Riverol</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">European Molecular Biology Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1SD</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Julian</forename>
								<surname>Uszkoreit</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Medical Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Ruhr-Universitä t Bochum</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Medizinisches Proteom-Zenter</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>ZKF, E.142, Universitä tsstr. 150</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-44801</postCode>
									<settlement>Bochum</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Aniel</forename>
								<surname>Sanchez</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Proteomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ciudad de la Habana</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CU">Cuba</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Tobias</forename>
								<surname>Ternent</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">European Molecular Biology Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1SD</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Noemi</forename>
								<surname>Del Toro</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">European Molecular Biology Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1SD</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Henning</forename>
								<surname>Hermjakob</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">European Molecular Biology Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1SD</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Juan</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Antonio</forename>
								<surname>Vizcaíno</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">European Molecular Biology Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1SD</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rui</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">European Molecular Biology Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1SD</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">ms-data-core-api: an open-source, metadata-oriented library for computational proteomics</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv250</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 17, 2015; revised on April 14, 2015; accepted on April 20, 2015</note>
					<note>Systems biology *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Availability and implementation: The software is freely available at https://github.com/PRIDE-Utilities/ms-data-core-api. Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online Contact: juan@ebi.ac.uk</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The ms-data-core-api is a free, open-source library for developing computational prote-omics tools and pipelines. The Application Programming Interface, written in Java, enables rapid tool creation by providing a robust, pluggable programming interface and common data model. The data model is based on controlled vocabularies/ontologies and captures the whole range of data types included in common proteomics experimental workflows, going from spectra to pep-tide/protein identifications to quantitative results. The library contains readers for three of the most used Proteomics Standards Initiative standard file formats: mzML, mzIdentML, and mzTab. In addition to mzML, it also supports other common mass spectra data formats: dta, ms2, mgf, pkl, apl (text-based), mzXML and mzData (XML-based). Also, it can be used to read PRIDE XML, the original format used by the PRIDE database, one of the world-leading proteomics resources. Finally, we present a set of algorithms and tools whose implementation illustrates the simplicity of developing applications using the library.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The Proteomics Standards Initiative (PSI) has developed and actively promotes the use of open standard data formats to represent the data produced in mass spectrometry (MS) based proteomics experiments (including technical and biological metadata). Three of the most broadly used formats are: mzML (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Martens et al., 2011</ref>) to capture the 'primary' data (the spectra and chromatograms), mzIdentML (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Jones et al., 2012</ref>) to report peptide identifications as well as the inferred protein identifications, and the tab-delimited mzTab format (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Griss et al., 2014</ref>) that can represent both identification and quantification results. There is increasing interest in new software tools and libraries that can work with these standards. As a result, a set of software libraries in different programming languages has been created (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Perez-Riverol et al., 2014</ref>). However, having these independent libraries for different formats can complicate the development of new software. Developers typically have to invest V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2903</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bioinformatics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Design and implementation</head><p>The ms-data-core-api library provides a unified access interface to different proteomics MS-derived data types, independent of the format-specific details (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). This interface provides methods to access and retrieve information on metadata, chromatograms, spectra, peptide spectrum matches (PSMs), peptides, proteins, protein modifications including post-translational modifications (PTMs) and quantitative results (Supplementary information, section S1.2). The biggest advantage of using the library is that any application based on it is largely file format agnostic. Following a modular design, many independent libraries were grouped at the same dependency level (Supplementary information,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). The developed data model provides adapters that can translate the input data from the different source files into the core data structures, enabling the support of widely used formats (Supplementary information,<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>). Crucially, the output from some of the most used analysis software in the field supports or can be converted to these highly popular formats, and then supported by the library (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). The API is composed of four functional components: (i) the data models incorporating all data structures (chromatograms, spectra, peptide/protein identifications, and quantitative information; Supplementary information, section S1.2.2); (ii) the transformers between the native file data representation and the data model; (iii) the cache system warranting fast and efficient access to the data (Supplementary information 1, section S1.2.3); and (iv) the data access controllers that can interface with external tools and libraries. Metadata-driven design: The data model has three major components: proteomics data, features and properties and metadata (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). The proteomics data comprise the spectra related information (intensities and masses), peptide/protein identifications mzML(sequences, protein identifiers) and quantitation information. Also, the proteomics data model encodes the associated features (e.g. scores, thresholds, etc) as cvParams, which refer to either a controlled vocabulary (CV) or an ontology (e.g. the PSI-MS CV), and userParams, which are user-defined parameters to represent information not yet included in CVs and ontologies. The API also contains general metadata on the experimental set-up. For example, metadata on the protein identification protocol such as software, enzyme and search database are part of the ProteinDetectionProtocol class. Cache design and PRIDE utilities: The design of the ms-datacore-api aims to achieve an optimal balance between memory consumption and access performance to the data by using a custom caching implementation (Supplementary information,<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>). Most of the data structures in the API are cached as key-value entries depending on access patterns. Data objects are cached as a whole if they are requested frequently, whereas objects requested less often are cached as mappings to their locations within the source file for fast random access. Also, new refinements were introduced in the file format native readers (Supplementary information, Section S1.2. 2). The independent PRIDE Utilities module (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>) provides a cvParam mapper that enables ms-data-core-api to homogenize terms across different file formats. It also includes functions to predict isoelectric point (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Perez-Riverol et al., 2012</ref>), monoisotopic mass, and the GRAVY index (Supplementary information, Section S1.2.4). As shown in the code snippet below, the calculation of these properties for all the supported formats takes minimum effort:Exporting to mzTab: The library includes a range of options to export the core data models and the processed results to mzTab files. The current version enables the conversion from mzIdentML and PRIDE XML to mzTab files including a set of filters to select only the high-quality peptide and protein identifications (Supplementary information, Section S1.2.4). As shown in the code snippet below, the conversion of mzIdentML to mzTab takes minimum effort:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Spectra</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Tools and future directions</head><p>Various algorithms, tools and pipelines have already been developed using the ms-data-core-api including PRIDE Inspector, the PRIDE internal submission pipeline, HI-bone and the PIA protein inference algorithm, among others (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Perez-Riverol et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Vizcaino et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Wang et al., 2012</ref>; Supplementary information, Section S3). The widespread use of the library ensures its stability, continued development, and community support. The ms-data-core-api library is freely available, and is released under the Apache 2.0 license at https://github.com/PRIDE-Utilities/ms-data-core-api.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Overview of the design of the ms-data-core-api</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>MzIdentMLControllerImpl controller ¼ new MzIdentMLControllerImpl(new File( " file.mzid " )); Collection&lt;Comparable&gt; proteins ¼ controller.get ProteinIds(); for(Comparable id: proteins) for(Comparable pepId: controller.getPeptideIds(id)) double pI¼ IsoelectricPointUtils.calculate(controller.get PeptideSequence(id,pepId)));</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Funding</head><figDesc>Y.P-R. is supported by the BBSRC 'PROCESS' grant [BB/K01997X/1]; R.W. by the BBSRC 'Quantitative Proteomics' grant [BB/I00095X/1]; T.T. by the BBSRC 'Proteogenomics' grant [BB/L024225/1]; J.A.V. and N.d.T. by the Wellcome Trust [grant number WT101477MA] and J. U. by PURE (Protein Unit for Research in Europe), a project of North Rhine-Westphalia, Germany. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>, 31(17), 2015, 2903–2905 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv250 Advance Access Publication Date: 24 April 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from considerable time and effort in basic functionality such as converting data structures between formats, shifting their focus away from the novel aspects of their software. In parallel, the volume of MS proteomics data available in the public domain keeps growing. This presents immense potential for quality assessment and data reanalysis (Perez-Riverol et al., 2015). A large proportion of the public data is in standard formats, which are heavily promoted by the resources part of ProteomeXchange (Vizcaino et al., 2014). Here we present the ms-data-core-api, an open-source Java Application Programming Interface (API) to efficiently handle the main data types in MS proteomics workflows, ranging from spectra to peptide/protein identifications to quantitative results. The current version supports three major PSI data standards (mzML, mzIdentML and mzTab) and the majority of mass spectra file formats (mzXML, mzData, mgf, pkl, dta, ms2, apl). This makes ms-data-core-api the first open-source API supporting both identification and quantitation PSI file formats. In addition, as a key feature, it fully supports access to data stored in the PRIDE database (Vizcaino et al., 2013) by also supporting the PRIDE XML format, providing access to all the projects available in this older format. We also introduce a rapidly growing set of algorithms and tools whose implementation helps to illustrate the simplicity of developing applications based on ms-data-core-api.</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mzTab data exchange format: communicating massspectrometry-based proteomics and metabolomics experimental results to a wider audience</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Griss</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecular &amp; cellular proteomics: MCP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2765" to="2775" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mzIdentML data standard for mass spectrometrybased proteomics results</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecular &amp; cellular proteomics: MCP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="014381" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">mzML—a community standard for mass spectrometry data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Martens</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Proteomics MCP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="000133" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Making proteomics data accessible and reusable: current state of proteomics databases and repositories</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Perez-Riverol</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="930" to="950" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isoelectric point optimization using peptide descriptors and support vector machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Perez-Riverol</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2269" to="2274" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HI-bone: a scoring system for identifying phenylisothiocyanate-derivatized peptides based on precursor mass and high intensity fragment ions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Perez-Riverol</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3515" to="3520" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open source libraries and frameworks for mass spectrometry based proteomics: a developer&apos;s perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Perez-Riverol</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1844</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The PRoteomics IDEntifications (PRIDE) database and associated tools: status in 2013</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Vizcaino</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1063" to="1069" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ProteomeXchange provides globally coordinated proteomics data submission and dissemination</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Vizcaino</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PRIDE Inspector: a tool to visualize and validate MS proteomics data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>