
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:34+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis NetComm: a network analysis tool based on communicability</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ian</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Campbell</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular and Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>77054</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Regis</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>James</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular and Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>77054</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Edward</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Chen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular and Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>77054</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chad</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Shaw</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular and Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>77054</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<surname>Hancock</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular and Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>77054</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis NetComm: a network analysis tool based on communicability</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="3387" to="3389"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu536</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 10, 2014; revised on July 11, 2014; accepted on August 2, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Contact: cashaw@bcm.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Set-based network similarity metrics are increasingly used to productively analyze genome-wide data. Conventional approaches, such as mean shortest path and clique-based metrics, have been useful but are not well suited to all applications. Computational scientists in other disciplines have developed commu-nicability as a complementary metric. Network communicability considers all paths of all lengths between two network members. Given the success of previous network analyses of protein–protein interactions , we applied the concepts of network communicability to this problem. Here we show that our communicability implementation has advantages over traditional approaches. Overall, analyses suggest network communicability has considerable utility in analysis of large-scale biological networks. Availability and implementation: We provide our method as an R package for use in both human protein–protein interaction network analyses and analyses of arbitrary networks along with a tutorial at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Many types of biological data, for example protein–protein interactions, coexpression data and biomedical research literature naturally lend themselves to formation of interconnected networks. While finding meaningful connections between network members (i.e. nodes, proteins or genes) can be challenging, networks provide an opportunity to contextualize results at the system level. Standard analyses rely on relationships between individual pairs of nodes and can be vulnerable to stochasticity and technical errors. Identifying sets of relationships between individual nodes and groups of others is one strategy for a more robust metric of connectedness. The challenge remains to retain topological information while simplifying network interactions into univariate representations for statistical analysis and comparison with other data types. A number of metrics have been successfully applied to the analysis of biological networks previously (<ref type="bibr">Broh ee et al., 2008</ref>). Shortest path analysis assesses the fewest connections (i.e. edges) required to connect a query node to one or more targets. However, nodes which themselves have many connections (i.e. high degree) are on average closer to all nodes. Therefore, identifying meaningful relationships by shortest path often requires some form of degree correction. Another weakness of shortest path analysis is that two or more paths of the same length are equivalent to a single path of that length. Thus, information regarding connectedness is lost. Jaccard similarity between two nodes is the quotient of the intersection and the union of their kth degree interactors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Jaccard, 1912</ref>). This metric is useful for testing connections to 'near by' nodes, but performs poorly for nodes that are far apart. The method of random walk mean first passage assesses how soon a random walk leaving a node takes to reach a given target (<ref type="bibr">Noh and Rieger, 2003</ref>). This metric may also require degree correction. Researchers in physics have proposed communicability as a metric of connectedness (<ref type="bibr">Estrada and Hatano, 2008</ref>). We previously used communicability to identify proteins connected in the human PPI network to a set of epilepsy proteins to aid identification of novel epilepsy genes (<ref type="bibr">Campbell et al., 2013</ref>). Communicability considers paths of all lengths between two nodes scaled by the factorial of path length (<ref type="bibr">Estrada and Hatano, 2008</ref>), retaining more information about connectedness compared with shortest path metrics. It remains useful across greater path lengths compared with Jaccard similarity and avoids algorithmic stochasticity. Communicability is still influenced by degree and is challenged by large networks such as the human protein–protein interaction network. Here, we propose a degree-normalized network connectedness metric inspired by network communicability and suitable for analysis of large complex networks. We provide an implementation for the human PPI network, as well as tools for arbitrary networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>Finite network communicability Communicability C i,j between two nodes i and j counts paths of all lengths between them. Contributions are scaled so that longer paths contribute less than shorter ones (<ref type="bibr">Estrada and Hatano, 2008</ref>). Using the adjacency matrix A, where the i,j entry is 1 if nodes are connected and 0 otherwise, communicability is defined:</p><formula>C i;j = X 1 k=1 ðA k Þ i;j k! =ðe A Þ i;j F i;j = X l k=1 ðA k Þ i;j k! ð1Þ</formula><p>Evaluating e A for large networks is possible (<ref type="bibr">Estrada and Hatano, 2008</ref>). However, when we investigated use of conventional network communicability in genome-wide networks, we found size and interconnectedness resulted in large values and loss of variability between nodes. Thus, we investigated a metric we deem finite network communicability F i,j considering finite path lengths from 1 to l (Equation 1). Preliminary analysis revealed our metric was vulnerable to node degree. Thus, we *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>y</head><p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. normalized by subtracting the mean and dividing by the standard deviation in that row:</p><formula>F i;j = X l k=1 ðA k Þ i;j ÀðA k Þ i i;k k! F i;T = X l k=1 ðA k Þ i;T ÀðA k Þ i i;k k! ð2Þ</formula><p>where i,k is the standard deviation of the i-th row of the k-th power of the adjacency matrix. To compute the metric F i,T to a set of target nodes T, we computed the mean across the set of nodes for each power (Equation 2). Other metrics of center and scale such as median and interquartile range can also be used.</p><p>Human disease network and genome-wide association studies (GWAS)catalog Phenotypic classes for Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man (OMIM) disease genes were extracted computationally from the Supplementary Tables from Goh et al. (2007). Genes assigned to multiple classes because different mutations of the same gene cause different phenotypes (allelic heterogeneity) were allowed; however, each gene could contribute to the same class only once. For shortest path analysis, we computed the mean shortest path for each node to each disease class and centered and scaled in a manner analogous to network communicability. Gene–disease associations from GWAS were downloaded from the National Human Genome Research Institute Catalogue of Published GWAS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Welter et al., 2014</ref>). Diseases 'type 1 diabetes', 'type 2 diabetes', 'breast cancer', 'age-related macular degeneration' and 'coronary heart disease' were selected because of a large quantity of associations and diverse etiologies. Associations met a significance of 5 Â 10 –8 and corresponded to a single gene.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>We assessed connectedness of 3724 proteins causative of Mendelian diseases that have been previously classified to 18 phenotypic classes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Goh et al., 2007</ref>). We used the InWeb (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Lage et al., 2007</ref>) network to calculate mean communicabilities of proteins causing neurological and cardiovascular disease to those of other classes. Our metric identified increased connectedness among proteins within classes than between classes and outperformed shortest path (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1A</ref>, Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). Our method similarly identified interactions among gene products associated with type 1 diabetes (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1B</ref>).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Finite network communicability performance. Same class disease proteins are more connected within than to proteins in other classes. (A) Connectedness among proteins causing neurologic phenotypes does not appear greater than to proteins in other classes by shortest path; however, on average, these same proteins are more connected to each other than to other class proteins by finite network communicability. Interestingly, proteins of the psychiatric class form the second strongest connections. (B) Protein products of genes with significant associations to type 1 diabetes are more connected than to proteins associated with other diseases. P-values are Bonferroni corrected Wilcox post hoc tests following a significant Kruskal–Wallis test. T1D, type 1 diabetes; T2D, type 2 diabetes; AMD, age-related macular degeneration; CHD, coronary heart disease</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> CONCLUSIONS Network communicability provides advantages over alternative metrics because it retains topology information, lends itself to set-based analysis and is easy to represent with univariate scores. It outperforms shortest path in a variety of situations. Overall, our metric may prove useful in the analysis of a variety of biological networks, and our package provides a straightforward approach to computation even on large networks.</note>

			<note place="foot">I.M.Campbell et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">NetComm at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank the Lupski laboratory at BCM for valuable feedback.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human disease network</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K.-I</forename>
				<surname>Goh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8685" to="8690" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The distribution of the flora in the alpine zone</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Jaccard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New Phytol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="1912" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A human phenome-interactome network of protein complexes implicated in genetic disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Lage</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="316" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Random walks on complex networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Noh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Rieger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The NHGRI GWAS Catalog, a curated resource of SNP-trait associations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Welter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1001" to="1006" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>