
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-11T00:00+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Network-guided sparse regression modeling for detection of gene-by-gene interactions</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">10 2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chen</forename>
								<surname>Lu</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jeanne</forename>
								<surname>Latourelle</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pulmonary Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Boston University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">The NHLBI&apos;s Framingham Heart Study</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Framingham</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">George</forename>
								<forename type="middle">T</forename>
								<surname>O &apos;connor</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">José</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Dupuis</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pulmonary Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">The NHLBI&apos;s Framingham Heart Study</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Framingham</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Bioinformatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eric</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Kolaczyk</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">The NHLBI&apos;s Framingham Heart Study</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Framingham</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Program in Bioinformatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics and Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Boston University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mario</forename>
								<surname>Albrecht</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Boston University School of Public Health</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Network-guided sparse regression modeling for detection of gene-by-gene interactions</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1241" to="1249"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">10 2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt139</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 4, 2012; revised on March 1, 2013; accepted on March 21, 2013</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Contact: chenlu@bu.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Genetic variants identified by genome-wide association studies to date explain only a small fraction of total heritability. Gene-by-gene interaction is one important potential source of unexplained total heritability. We propose a novel approach to detect such interactions that uses penalized regression and sparse estimation principles, and incorporates outside biological knowledge through a network-based penalty. Results: We tested our new method on simulated and real data. Simulation showed that with reasonable outside biological knowledge, our method performs noticeably better than stage-wise strategies (i.e. selecting main effects first, and interactions second, from those main effects selected) in finding true interactions, especially when the marginal strength of main effects is weak. We applied our method to Framingham Heart Study data on total plasma immunoglobulin E (IgE) concentrations and found a number of interactions among different classes of human leukocyte antigen genes that may interact to influence the risk of developing IgE dysregulation and allergy. Availability: The proposed method is implemented in R and available at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Unlike Mendelian diseases, in which disease phenotypes are largely driven by mutation in a single gene locus, complex disease and traits are associated with a number of factors, both genetic and environmental, as well as lifestyle. In addition, while most Mendelian diseases are rare, many complex diseases are frightfully common, from asthma to heart disease, hypertension to Alzheimer's and Parkinson's to various forms of cancer. Arguably motivated by classical successes with Mendelian diseases and traits, the study of complex diseases and traits in the modern genomics era has focused largely on the identification of individually important genes. Genome-wide association studies (GWAS), the current state of the art, have been central to the discovery of many genes in various diseases (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hindorff et al., 2010</ref>). However, unfortunately, the vast majority of genetic variants associated with complex traits identified to date explain only a small amount of the overall variance of the trait in the underlying population (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Manolio et al., 2009</ref>). As a result, most GWAS findings thus far have had little clinical impact. Currently, most GWAS are carried out one single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) at a time. Typically, for each SNP, a model is specified, relating disease status or disease trait to the SNP plus other potentially relevant covariates. The statistical significance of each SNP is quantified through the P-value of an appropriate test. Finally, a multiple-testing correction is applied to correct the collection of P-values across SNPs. The end result is a list of SNPs declared to be significantly associated with the status or trait of interest, which in turn can be mapped to their closest genes, although some associations have been found in 'gene deserts' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hindorff et al., 2010</ref>). The single-SNP approach has the important attribute that it is (relatively) computationally efficient. However, it can be severely under-powered because of the small effect size of most genetic variants identified to date (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hindorff et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Manolio et al., 2009</ref>). Additionally, this approach does not adjust for correlation among SNPs, nor does it extend in a natural manner to search for interactions between markers. In contrast, multiple regression (i.e. where multiple SNPs are modeled simultaneously) is a natural alternative. However, naive implementation (i.e. incorporating all SNPs of interest) is both infeasible and undesirable. This is due to various reasons, including the sheer number of SNPs typically available (e.g. hundreds of thousands to millions), the comparatively small number of SNPs likely to be associated and 'small n, large p' problems. Recently, however, computationally efficient multiple regression strategies for GWAS have begun to emerge that use various methods of high-dimensional variable selection (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ayers and Cordell, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Logsdon et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Ma et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Szymczak et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wu et al., 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Wu et al., , 2010</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Zhou et al. 2010</ref>). Compared with traditional single-SNP methods, penalized regression methods have been found to yield fewer correlated SNPs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ayers and Cordell, 2010</ref>) and to be capable of producing substantially more power while having a lower false-discovery *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>y</head><p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the last two authors should be regarded as joint Last Authors. rate (FDR;<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">He and Lin, 2011</ref>). Furthermore, and most relevant to the current article, regression methods can include SNP by SNP interactions in a natural manner. However, to date, this typically has been done in a greedy stage-wise manner, by fitting main-effect models first and then restricting attention to interactions among those effects found significant (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wu et al., 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Wu et al., , 2010</ref>). In addition, the above work makes limited or no use of supplementary biological information on, for example, biological pathways and gene function. We propose a novel network-guided statistical methodology to facilitate the discovery of gene-by-gene (G Â G) interactions associated with complex quantitative traits related to human disease, one which addresses both of the shortcomings cited above. Main effects and interaction effects in our model are chosen simultaneously, thus allowing for the possibility of detecting genes for which the marginal main effect is weak. Variable selection is done through penalized regression using sparse estimation principles. The penalty allows for the incorporation of information on biological pathways and gene function into the analysis of continuous traits related to human disease. In doing so, this penalty acts as an informal prior distribution on the set of possible G Â G interactions, which in practice allows the investigator to reduce the number of interactions examined for the model from the nominal and computationally prohibitive O((number of SNPs) 2 ) to a more manageable, say, O(number of SNPs). Simulations indicate that, given relevant pathway information, our approach performs well in finding true interactions without losing the ability of detecting main effects, and can noticeably outperform existing stage-wise methods. In addition, application of our proposed methodology to a study of plasma total immunoglobulin E (IgE) concentrations for participants in the Framingham Heart Study (FHS) illustrates the substantial promise of the method. The rest of this article is organized as follows: in Section 2, we describe our statistical approach. We introduce the model and our proposed penalty, describe how biological information is incorporated into the penalty and explain the optimization algorithm used for model fitting and a strategy for choosing tuning parameters. The design and results of an extensive simulation study are presented in Section 3, in which we examine models with varying degrees of interactions and penalties reflecting different extents of biological knowledge. Our analysis of the IgE concentration data is provided in Section 4. Some additional discussion may be found in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Modeling G Â G interaction</head><p>Let Y be a quantitative trait of interest, and let fX j g p j¼1 be p predictors representing SNPs. To include interactions, we are interested in a model of the form</p><formula>Y ¼ 0 þ X p j¼1 j X j þ X k4j jk X jk þ ð1Þ</formula><p>where X jk ¼ X j X k. We expect that both the j s and the jk s are sparse, as it is unlikely that there is more than a small fraction of SNPs affecting the phenotype Y, either as main effects or as interactors. In practice, p will range from hundreds to millions. Our goal is to fit the high-dimensional model (1) to data. When p is large but only a small percentage of predictors and interactions are present in the true model, a general approach is to minimize a penalized regression criterion. Accordingly, we propose to estimate the coefficients ¼ ðf j g, f jk gÞ T in our model using a penalized least-squares criterion. Let Y ¼ ðY 1 ,. .. , Y n Þ T , X j ¼ ðX 1j ,. .. , X nj Þ T and X jk ¼ ðX 1j X 1k ,. .. , X nj X nk Þ T represent our variables Y, X j and X jk collected over n samples. Our criterion is then written as follows:Penalized linear regression has been found to be a powerful tool for fitting high-dimensional models, particularly in situations where the nominal number of variables is large relative to the number of observations (e.g. Bu¨hlmannBu¨hlmann and Van De Geer, 2011). In the context of GWAS, typically p ) n. Hence, it is impossible to fit a model with the full set of Oðp 2 Þ nominal interactions among all p SNPs. However, the coefficient vector is expected to be sparse. Therefore, a penalty function that enforces sparseness can be helpful here, by encouraging the optimization in (2) to find solutions in which a large percentage of the main effects and their interactions are zero, thus dropping the corresponding terms from the model. Following standard practice, we wish to include interactions only if their corresponding main effects are also included in the model. The construction of the sparseness penalty P W , therefore, must be handled with some care, so as to enforce the resulting hierarchical constraint among coefficients. In addition, we would like our penalty to allow for the use of biological knowledge (e.g. biological pathways, gene functional classes, etc.) in fitting the model. We address these two goals by defining a penalty of the form<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">ð3Þ</ref>where the w jk ! 0 are non-negative weights provided by the investigator, and W ¼ ½w jk  is used to denote the matrix of weights over all SNP pairs i, j. The values 1 , 2 40 are tuning parameters. Our penalty is a generalization of that proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Radchenko and James (2010)</ref>for the purpose of fitting general types of interaction models (in<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Radchenko and James (2010)</ref>, w jk 1 for all j, k). Note that, following those authors, we express the penalty in un-normalized form (standard lasso algorithms, for example, without interactions, assume jjX j jj ¼ 1 and hence jjX j j jj 2 ¼ 2 j ). It can be shown that the penalty automatically enforces the hierarchical constraint (i.e. inclusion of main effects before interactions). Main effects and interactions can be treated differently by varying 2 with respect to 1. The elements of the matrix W are generic and allow for the possibility of including biological information a priori into the model selection process. We next describe a manner for doing so, in which network principles are used in a natural way.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">A network-based penalty</head><p>Here we describe how we construct the matrix W, using information on biological pathways. Similar constructions may be had generally using other common resources (e.g., databases of genes and their biological function, such as Gene Ontology). Note that W acts as a dissimilarity matrix in P W. Under our construction, W is defined in association with a graph showing relationships among SNPs, which in turn derives from a bipartite graph relating SNPs to pathways. The intuition underlying our construction is to (i) allow interactions only among SNPs corresponding to genes that are common to at least one pathway, and (ii) to encourage interactions more among those SNP pairs that are common to more pathways. Let S 1 ,. .. , S p denote our p SNPs, and P 1 ,. .. , P m , our m pathways. We define G to be a bipartite graph, with one set of nodes representing SNPs, and the other, pathways. An edge in G connects an SNP S i to a pathway P ' if that SNP maps sufficiently close to a gene found in the pathway. We then define G SNP to be the one-mode projection of G onto the set of SNPs.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figures 1</ref>and 2 show three toy examples of graphs G and G SNP , for p ¼ 3 SNPs and m ¼ 2 pathways. An equivalent representation of the relationship between SNPs and pathways in the network G SNP is a p Â m incidence matrix M, describing which SNPs are linked to which pathways. For the three examples in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 1</ref>, the corresponding incidence matrices are</p><formula>M 1 ¼ 1 0 1 1 0 1 2 4 3 5 M 2 ¼ 1 0 1 1 1 1 2 4 3 5 M 3 ¼ 1 0 0 1 0 1 2 4 3 5 ð4Þ</formula><p>Similarly, the analogous m Â m (weighted) adjacency matrix is the standard representation of the one-mode projection G SNP. Calling this matrix A, it is related to the incidence matrix M of the original graph G through the expression A ¼ MM T. For the three examples shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 1</ref>and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2</ref>, the adjacency matrices areFinally, we define the dissimilarity matrix W element-wise by setting w jk ¼ 1=a jk. In the case where a jk ¼ 0, we set w jk ¼ 1 by convention. Note that the resulting implication for the optimization in (2) is that jk is set to zero, i.e. the term X jk cannot enter the model. Hence, only those pairs of SNPs j, k that share at least one pathway (i.e. w jk 51) may potentially enter the model. As a result, it is possible to substantially reduce the number of interaction terms considered for entry into the model, thus making the simultaneous search for main effects and interactions easier to perform. For example, in the application presented in Section 4, 17 025 SNPs were used, nominally corresponding to $145 million interactions. However, in using the 186 pathways from the Kyoto Encyclopeida of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database to construct our matrix W, this number was reduced to less than 480 000 potential interactions. We note that there are certainly other ways of constructing the matrix W. For example, a variation on the procedure described above would be to define w jk ¼ 1 if a jk 40, and infinity otherwise. This is equivalent to equipping the graph G SNP with a binary adjacency matrix and letting w jk ¼ 1=a jk as before, and results in the equal treatment of all interactions that are allowed to enter the model, regardless of how many pathways are shared by pairs j, k. In addition, of course, other types of outside information—if judged relevant—can be used in place of pathways, as mentioned above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Model selection and fitting</head><p>To perform the optimization in (2), we use cyclic coordinate descent, a now-standard choice for problems such as ours (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Friedman et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Wu and Lange, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wu et al., 2009</ref>). As the name indicates, the cyclic coordinate descent algorithm updates one element of at a time using coordinate descent principles, while holding all others fixed, and cycles through all elements until convergence. In our context, the details of the resulting algorithm parallel those of Radchenko and James (2010). We, therefore, present only a sketch of the algorithm and relevant formulas here. Detailed derivation can be found in Supplementary Material, Section 1. Consider the estimation of j. We note that, with respect to this parameter, the objective function in (2) can be written as</p><formula>1 2 ~ Y j À X j j À Á T ~ Y j À X j j À Á þ 1 w 2 jj jjX j j jj 2 þ X k6 ¼j w 2 jk jjX jk jk jj 2 ! 1=2 þC j ð6Þ where ~ Y j ¼ Y À P '6 ¼j X ' ~ ' À P p '¼1 P k4' X 'k ~ 'k .</formula><p>Here ~ ' is the current value of ' at this stage of our iterative algorithm, and similarly for ~ 'k , while C j is all of the rest of the penalty term P W ðÞ that does not involve j. The updates to the estimates ~ j of the main effects j take the form of a shrinkage estimate,</p><formula>~ j ¼ j ^ j , for j 2 ½0, 1. Here ^ j ¼ X T j ~ Y j</formula><p>is the solution to the problem of fitting a regression-through-the-origin for ~ Y j on X j , and the shrinkage parameter j is the solution to the equation</p><formula>j 1 þ 1 w 2 jj ðw 2 jj X T j X j 2 j ^ 2 j þ c j Þ 1=2 ! ¼ 1 ð7Þ</formula><p>where c j ¼ P k6 ¼j w 2 jk jjX jk jk jj 2. The value j can be obtained using the Newton–Raphson method. In the special case where c j ¼ 0, which must be the case when w jk ¼ 0 for all k 6 ¼ j (i.e. SNP j is not allowed to participate in any interactions), Equation (7) can be solved in closed form, yielding j ¼ ð1 À 1 w jj =½ðX T j X j Þ 1=2 j ^ j jÞ þ. Now consider the estimation of jk. Similar arguments show that the iterations in the cyclic coordinate descent algorithm involve updates of the form ~ jk ¼ jk ^ jk , for jk 2 ½0, 1. Here ^ jk ¼ X T jk ~ Y jk =X T jk X jk is the solution to the problem of fitting a regression-through-the-origin for ~ Y jk on X jk , where</p><formula>~ Y jk ¼ Y À X p '¼1 X ' ~ ' À X m4' X ð', mÞ6 ¼ðj, kÞ X 'm ~ 'm</formula><p>The shrinkage parameter jk for interaction terms is the solution to the equationis achieved. Following standard practice, on termination of our cyclic coordinate descent algorithm, we generate a final estimate of coefficients for those variables X j and X jk that were allowed to enter the model, using ordinary least squares. All corresponding effect-size estimates and P-values produced by our methodology result from this final step. For datasets with a small number of predictors fX j g, the algorithm can be easily fit as described. However, for larger numbers of predictors, we use a 'swindle', in analogy to that proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wu et al. (2009)</ref>and implemented in MENDEL (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Lange et al., 2001</ref>). The basic idea is to apply the algorithm to a much smaller number, say k, of pre-screened predictors, and to choose the smoothing parameter(s) such that only a desired number, say s5k, of predictors X j enters the model. The Karush– Kuhn–Tucker (KKT) conditions for our optimization problem are then checked for the estimate ~ resulting from our algorithm (augmented with zeros for coefficients of all predictors eliminated at the pre-screening stage). If the KKT conditions are satisfied, we are done; if not, we double k and repeat the process. Following<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wu et al. (2009)</ref>, we let our initial choice of k be a multiple of s, i.e. k ¼ 10 Â s in the applications we show. Pre-screening consists of sorting the t statistics of fitting ordinary least-square regression of Y on each predictor X j separately (i.e. traditional GWAS) and extracting those predictors with the k largest t statistics. Details can be found in Supplementary Material, Section 2.</p><formula>jk ^ jk 1 þ 1 w 2 jk 1 ðw 2 jk X T jk X jk 2 jk ^ 2 jk þ c jk 1 Þ 1=2 " ( þ 1 ðw 2 kj X T kj X kj 2 jk ^ 2 jk þ c jk 2 Þ 1=2 #) ¼ signð ^ jk Þ j ^ jk j À 2 w jk ðX T jk X jk Þ À1=2 h i þ ð8Þ where c jk 1 ¼ w 2 jj X T j X j 2 j þ X n6 ¼j, k w 2 jn X T jn X jn 2 jn and c jk 2 ¼ w 2 kk X T k X k 2 k þ X n6 ¼k, j w 2 kn X T</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Choice of tuning parameters</head><p>In the penalty function P W defined in (3), the tuning parameters 1 , 2 directly influence the number of variables that enter the final model. In principle, these two parameters may be allowed to vary freely and a cross-validation strategy used to select the best values. However, this strategy is unrealistic for GWAS, where the number of SNPs may range into millions. Instead, we use a strategy that allows investigators some control in dictating how many variables enter the model, and thereby specify the tuning parameters implicitly. First, we impose a linear relation between the two tuning parameters, i.e. 2 ¼ c 1. Because 2 is directly involved only in the selection of interaction terms, specifying the constant c may be interpreted as 'tuning' the number of interactions relative to main effects. The tuning parameter 1 is responsible for the number of main effects in the model. Because 1 is essentially a decreasing function of the number of main effects entered in the model and often investigators have at least some rough expectation of how many SNPs they feel are likely to be associated with their phenotype, we set 1 by pre-specifying the number of main effects to include in the final model (i.e. denoted s above). Second, calculations show that the relation c % ffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi</p><formula>jk p r holds, where 2 j ¼ 2p j ð1 À p j Þ</formula><p>is the variance of SNP j coded as the number of minor alleles under the assumption of Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium; the variance is defined here in terms of the minor allele frequency (MAF) p j , and r is the ratio of the thresholds for main effects and interactions to enter the model within the cyclic coordinate descent algorithm. See Supplementary Material, Section 3, for details. We recommend that c be chosen by the user through (i) specifying a desired ratio r and (ii) knowledge of the distribution of SNP MAFs. By setting the desired number of main effects and the value c, we implicitly specify the values of the tuning parameters 1 , 2. A smaller value of c (corresponding to a larger value of r) means more interactions may enter the model, for a fixed number of main effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">SIMULATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Simulation study design</head><p>We carried out a simulation study to assess (i) the performance of our method under various interaction scenarios and (ii) the effect of different choices of the W matrix in our penalty on our ability to detect interaction. We also compared our method with the stage-wise selection method proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wu et al. (2009)</ref>, which restricts interaction search to SNPs first declared to have main effects. In each simulated dataset, there are 1000 subjects and 1000 SNPs as predictors. The SNPs are coded additively (0, 1, 2), simulated with a MAF of 50%, and drawn from a binomial distribution with two trials. Lower MAFs were also investigated (MAF ! 10%, see Supplementary Material, Section 4.5). The quantitative trait Y is then simulated using the effect SNPs and interactions specified under assumed models. The effect sizes are set for 80% power under standard single-SNP additive models. Among the 1000 SNPs, 20 (SNPs 1–20) have true main effects on the simulated trait, and the remaining 980 SNPs have no effect. To test our method in various interaction situations, we evaluate three different models:Model 1 has no interactions involved. Models 2 and 3 both have 10 interaction terms involved, and the interactions are all among true main effects. However, in Model 2, there is one cluster with 5 interacting SNPs, while in Model 3 there are 10 clusters, each with two interacting SNPs. In addition, we explore six different ways to construct the W matrix used in the penalty. In each case, we allow all SNPs to be evaluated as possible main effects, by having all ones down the diagonal of W. For the possible interaction terms, coded by the off-diagonal elements of W, we consider the following additions:in a manner aimed at mimicking the interaction structure corresponding to the KEGG database, only some subset of which will likely be relevant to any given study (and the rest, 'noise'). Specifically, an additional set of 'pathways' (i.e. gene sets) were defined, in addition to those defined by the models themselves, until 20 pathways were formed. To these 20, we then randomly allocated 160 additional SNPs so that the average number of SNPs per pathway roughly mimicked what is observed in KEGG. W 5 represents a single pathway of SNPs 1–40, similar to W 2 but with more SNPs (20 non-active SNPs) involved. W 6 then represents two pathways with each having 10 active and 10 non-active SNPs. It is similar to W 5 in the sense that the allowed interactions involve SNPs 1–40, but W 6 has smaller amount of non-active interactions. We chose 1 by setting the desired number of main effects selected as 25, the value of 1 is automatically determined by our program once the value 25 is provided. This is a natural choice because there are 1000 SNPs in our data and 20 true main effects in the models. This choice will affect type I error because at least 5 of the 25 predictors selected as main effects will be false, but this number is modest compared with the total of 1000 SNPs and can be easily adjusted by resetting 1 according to investigator preference. The parameter c is set to 0.5 (i.e. r ¼ 1:0 under our model). The selected predictors are then ranked by their absolute t-values resulting from the ordinary least-square fit on the selected predictors for the final model. By setting a threshold on the rank, we choose the number of interactions to be reported and compare the performance of interaction selection under various W matrix specifications across a range of thresholds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Simulation results</head><p>In<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 3</ref>, we compare the results under various W matrix specifications, for Models 2 and 3. We assess the ability to find true interactions by computing the average FDR of interactions over 100 trials and plotting 1 À FDR against the rank threshold for selected interactions. As the threshold increases, more interactions get selected, and thus FDR increases and the curves have a downward trend. Examining the results, we see that W 1 clearly has the best performance, as it reflects the truth about the interactions in the model; all false interactions are excluded a priori, and thus the 1 À FDR curve for W 1 is a straight line at 1. Recall that W 3 is equivalent to W 1 plus random 'noise'. Importantly, therefore, we note that pure 'noise' among non-active SNPs does not appear to impact much the selection of true interactions, as W 3 has the second best performance after W 1. This conclusion is reinforced by the results for W 2 and W 4 , where the 1 À FDR curves are nearly identical. In contrast, the results in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 3</ref>also suggest that selection of interactions is to some extent adversely affected when allowing 'noise' interactions among active SNPs, as W 6 has better performance than W 2 and W 5 , while W 2 and W 5 have similar performance. In comparing our method with that of<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wu et al. (2009)</ref>, as implemented in Mendel, we can see in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 3</ref>that our method outperforms stage-wise selection for all choices considered for the matrix W. This observation is significant in showing that using accurate prior information, even with moderate 'noise' (i.e. specifying non-existent interactions), it is possible to outperform the stage-wise approach by over 10–20% on the 1 À FDR scale. Note that we used the default option in Mendel that tests interactions among selected main effects. There are other options in Mendel one can choose that may perform somewhat better. With respect to the detection of main effects, the performance of our methodology is shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref><ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>, we can also see that our method has the same or higher average power for detecting true main effects than the stage-wise approach of<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wu et al. (2009)</ref>, as implemented in Mendel. In both approaches, the non-active SNPs have a small chance of being declared as main effects. We also tested two more cases where main-effect sizes were moderate and weak, corresponding to 50% power and 20% power, respectively, under standard single-SNP additivemodels. To assess the performance of our method in finding interactions under these various strengths of main effects, we reverse the direction of interactions so that there are no marginal SNP effects. The W matrix we used is W 2 , as described before, to make a fair comparison with respect to the inclusion of noise interactions. The results under such models are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 4</ref>. As we can see from the figure, the approach implemented using Mendel could not find true interactions under any of the models [the regular (Mendel), the moderate (Mendel.moderate) and the weak (Mendel.weak) main-effect models], as it only searches for interactions among main effects selected in the first stage. In contrast, our proposed approach is able to find some of the true interactions because it incorporates information from the W matrix, the network of interactions built from outside knowledge. Not surprisingly, the model with stronger main effect (M2W2, M3W2) performs better in finding true interactions than moderate (M2W2.moderate, M3W2.moderate) or weak (M2W2.weak, M3W2.weak) maineffect models. There are a number of other important questions that one can explore in simulations. We further checked four of them and found that (i) our approach outperforms simple association tests; (ii) scaling up data size by adding more 'noise' SNPs makes it harder to find true main effects but does not adversely affect the selection of interactions' (iii) besides the obvious advantage of decreasing computing time, using network information in our penalty yields advantages in detecting interactions beyond that deriving from the hierarchical nature of the penalty; and (iv) our approach is robust to modest linkage disequilibrium among SNPs. A detailed description of these results can be found in Supplementary Material, Section 4.</p><formula>10 20 0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">APPLICATION TO IGE CONCENTRATION</head><p>We applied our algorithm to evaluate G Â G interactions for log plasma IgE concentration, a biomarker that is often elevated in individuals with allergy to environmental allergens. An elevated plasma IgE concentration is associated with allergic diseases, including asthma, allergic rhinoconjunctivitis, atopic dermatitis and food allergy. Although several genes influencing IgE concentrations have been identified to date, the interactions among these genes or others yet to be identified to be important players have not been studied (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Granada et al., 2012</ref>). We sought to investigate G Â G effects on log IgE concentration in the FHS cohorts. Participants from the town of Framingham, Massachusetts, have been recruited in these studies starting in 1948, and have been followed over the years for theMain effects<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Granada et al., 2012</ref>). We are interested in looking at G Â G interactions associated with IgE concentration, as an illustration of our methodology.</p><formula>W 1 W 2 W 3 W 4 W 5 W 6 Model 1 SNPs with interaction — — — — — —</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Preliminaries</head><p>Genotypes were from Affymetrix 500K and MIPS 50K arrays, with imputation performed using HapMap 2 European reference panel (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Li et al., 2010</ref>). Dosage genotypes (expected number of minor alleles) were used in our analysis, although the software implementation of the Wu et al.</p><p>(2009) approach (Mendel) required genotypes to be coded as 0, 1 or 2 and could not handle dosage. Therefore, in our analysis using Mendel, for each individual, we used the genotype with the highest posterior probability at each SNP. We analyze the natural logarithm of plasma total IgE concentrations as our phenotype (i.e. Y), adjusted for smoking status (current, former and amount of life time smoking in terms of pack-years), age, sex and cohort of origin. A total of 6975 participants (3209 men and 3766 women) aged 19 years and older had good-quality genotypes and were included in our analysis. Familial relationship was ignored when applying our algorithm and the<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wu et al. (2009)</ref>approach, but we subsequently applied linear mixed-effect models to account for familial correlation to obtain estimates of effect sizes. Some pre-processing was used to select a set of SNPs to include in our analysis. First, we attempted to map each of the 2 411 590 genotyped and imputed SNPs in the dataset to a reference gene containing it. If no such gene was available, then we mapped the SNP to the closest reference gene within 60 kb of the SNP, if available. Otherwise, the SNP was excluded. After establishing this mapping between genes and SNPs, some genes were found to include multiple SNPs. We kept only one SNP for each gene, selecting in each case that SNP most significantly associated with the phenotype, based on a linear mixed-effect regression. As a result, the SNPs in the final dataset have low linkage disequilibrium (correlation) and a unique SNP-to-gene correspondence (additional analyses suggest that our results, reported below, are fairly robust to modest amounts of disequilibrium in these data. See Supplementary Materials, Section 4.4). The final dataset has 17 025 SNPs/genes. We used the KEGG pathway database to build our W matrix, following the steps described in Section 2. The KEGG pathway database has a total of 72 354 genes and 5268 unique genes, resulting in 479 066 interactions allowed in our W matrix.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Results</head><p>For our analysis on 17 025 SNPs, we chose to look for 10 main effects, although we allowed the algorithm to terminate after selecting 10 AE 1 main effects, resulting in 9 main effects selected in the current analysis. The parameter c was set to 0.1, which, based on an average estimated SNP variance of 0.27 for these data, corresponds to r % 2:7. Nine interactions were found in our approach, yielding a model with 15 ¼ 9 þ 6 variables. To calibrate our results with those from the stage-wise procedure of<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wu et al. (2009)</ref>, as implemented in Mendel, the latter was run to select 9 variables in the first stage (i.e. fitting only main effects), and then 15 variables in the second stage (i.e. fitting both main effects and interactions, selected from among the 9 SNPs resulting from the first stage). This process produced a final model with nine main effects and six interactions. In terms of computing time, our analysis ran in $5 min on our cluster Linga, equipped with two Intel Xeon CPUs E5345 @ 2.33 GHz, withThe results from our proposed method and from the stagewise procedure are shown in the left and right, respectively, of<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>. The estimates of effect size and the ranks are from the linear mixed-effect model for the final model after variable selection procedure, for both methods. Genes previously found in a GWAS of these FHS data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Granada et al., 2012</ref>) are indicated with an asterisk in the table. In our approach, four of the six interaction pairs involved human leukocyte antigen (HLA) genes, which encode antigen-presenting cell-surface proteins that are key regulators of the immune response. The other two interactions identified were among genes both previously associated with log IgE concentrations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Granada et al., 2012</ref>). In contrast, Mendel did not detect any interactions among genes in the HLA regions or among pairs of previously associated genes. From a biological perspective, a number of the interactions discovered by our method are of non-trivial potential interest. The major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class I antigens HLA-A,-B and-C are involved with cell-mediated immunity targeting cells expressing proteins produced intracellularly, for example, by viruses, while the MHC class II antigens HLADP,-DQ and-DR play key roles with humoral immunity, including the production of IgE antibodies directed against environmental allergens (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Klein and Sato, 2000</ref>). HLA-G is a nonclassical MHC class I antigen that may have immunomodulatory effects through actions on natural killer cells, T lymphocytes and antigen-presenting cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Carosella et al., 2008</ref>). Genetic variants in these different classes of HLA genes—each class influencing a different but interconnected aspect of immune function—could well interact to influence the risk of developing IgE dysregulation and allergy. The observed interaction between SNPs in the alpha chain of the high affinity receptor for IgE (FCER1A) and interleukin (IL)-13 genes may reflect a number of mechanisms. For example, a genetic variant causing increased expression of Fc"RI on mast cells would lead to increased antigen-induced activation of these cells, which would consequently produce more IL-13 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Burd et al., 1995</ref>), leading to more class-switch recombination and IgE production. Genetic variation of Fc"RI on classical antigen-presenting cells may also promote Th2 cell activation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Potaczek et al., 2009</ref>) with consequent IL-13 release. Thus, SNPs in these two genes in the same pathway leading to increased IgE production could have synergistic effects. Overall, identification of these interactions may help identify the children at highest risk for developing allergy, possibly helping focus interventions to prevent allergy, and may provide new insights into the genetic basis and mechanisms of allergy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">DISCUSSION</head><p>There are many potential sources of missing hereditability. G Â G interactions is one such source. In turn, there are many types of genetic interactions, including multiplicative and non-multiplicative (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Mukherjee et al. 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Mukherjee et al. , 2012</ref>. In this article, we focus on investigating multiplicative interactions in the form of a product between two variables. Our proposed methodology provides a promising new approach to tapping this source, by exploiting the wealth of biological knowledge accumulated in various pathway databases. The simulations reported here suggest that our approach performs better in finding true interactions with a reasonable prior biological knowledge incorporated, compared with the stagewise regression method that first fits a main-effect model and then searches for interactions among selected main effects. Furthermore, the real-data results are promising in suggesting that better performance likely may be realized in real data as well. Future work to be done on this topic includes extending the computational algorithm to account for linkage disequilibrium among SNPs, and producing a software implementation that uses standard formatted files such as genotype files from the PLINK (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Purcell et al. 2007</ref>) software package.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>kn X kn 2 kn which again can be computed using the Newton–Raphson method. When c jk 1 and c jk 2 are both zero, jk can be solved in closed form, yielding jk ¼ 1 À ½ð2 1 þ 2 Þw jk =½ðX T jk X jk Þ 1=2 j ^ jk j n o þ The shrunken estimates of coefficients of predictors and interactions are updated in the iterative process described above until convergence</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Simple illustration of network representations between SNPs (S1, S2, S3) and pathways (P1, P2)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. One-mode projection of the three examples in Figure 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Model1:</head><figDesc>only 20 main effects with no interaction, Model 2: 20 main effects þ all two way interactions among SNPs 1–5, and Model 3: 20 main effects þ SNP1 Â SNP2 þ SNP3 Â SNP4 þ SNP5 Â SNP6 þ. .. þ SNP19 Â SNP20.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>W1:</head><figDesc>þ true interactions in models, W 2 : þ two-way interactions among all true main effects (SNPs 1–20), W 3 : þ true interactions þ random 'noise' interactions, W 4 : þ two-way interactions among all true main effects þ random 'noise' interactions, W 5 : þ two-way interactions among SNPs 1–40 (all true main effects and 20 non-active SNPs), and W 6 : þ two-way interactions among SNPs 1–10 and 21–30 þ two-way interactions among SNPs 11–20 and 31–40. The matrix W 1 is an ideal case. It only allows true interactions built in the model to enter that model. Note that W 1 is different for each of Models 1, 2 and 3. The matrix W 2 introduces some 'noise' interactions by allowing all interactions among true main effects. It is equivalent to a single pathway of SNPs 1–20 and is the same for all models. The matrix W 3 adds random 'noise' interactions to W 1 , while W 4 adds random 'noise' interactions to W 2. Note that W 3 and W 4 both vary across models. The random 'noise' interactions are introduced</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><figDesc>. The average power of main effects are grouped into three categories: the true SNPs involved in interaction, true SNPs not involved in interaction and the SNPs that have no effect on the simulated trait. Recall that there is no interaction in Model 1, and all true SNPs in Model 3 are involved in interaction, so they have only two relevant groups of SNPs. As we can see from the Model 2 result, SNPs involved in interactions are detected more easily than SNPs not involved in interactions. Comparing Table 1 with</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Interaction results of Model 2 and Model 3 under 6 W matrix specifications and Mendel analysis</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Interaction results of Model 2 and Model 3 without marginal main effect</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: National Institute Health (grants DK078616, ES020827 GM078987, AG028321, N01 HC25195 and P01 AI050516) (in part). A portion of this research used the Linux Cluster for Genetic Analysis (LinGA-II), funded by the Robert Dawson Evans Endowment of the Department of Medicine at Boston University School of Medicine and Boston Medical Center. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>0</figDesc><table>Rank Threshold 

1−FDR 

1−FDR versus Rank Threshold for M2 

M2W1 
M2W2 
M2W3 
M2W4 
M2W5 
M2W6 
Mendel 

10 
20 

0.0 

0.2 

0.4 

0.6 

0.8 

1.0 

Rank Threshold 

1−FDR 

1−FDR versus Rank Threshold for M3 

M3W1 
M3W2 
M3W3 
M3W4 
M3W5 
M3W6 
Mendel 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1. Simulation results for detection of main effects</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2.</figDesc><table>Detection of main effects by stage-wise competitor 

Main effects 
Model 2 
Model 3 

SNPs with interaction 
1.000 
1.000 
SNPs without interaction 
0.557 
— 
Non-active SNPs 
0.012 
0.005 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 3. Results of application to IgE concentration data</figDesc><table>Network-guided sparse regression 
Mendel analysis 

Gene 1 
Gene 2 
t-value 
Found 
Gene 1 
Gene 2 
t-value 
Found 

FCER1A 
À5.6441 

a 

LRP1 
4.7084 
MPP6 
4.4184 
SNF1LK2 
4.3969 
STAT6 
À4.2453 

a 

EMID2 
À4.1795 
IL-13 
4.0073 

a 

RAB3C 
3.8585 
LRP1 
3.7072 
HLA-DQA2 
3.6883 

a 

HLA-DPB1 
HLA-DQA2 
1.6314 
FCER1A 
À2.8098 

a 

FCER1A 
HLA-DQA2 
1.4193 
HLA-DPB1 
2.1346 
HLA-G 
1.3657 

a 

LOC441108 
1.9687 
HLA-DPB1 
1.1655 
LOC441108 
DDX1 
1.7449 
HLA-A 
0.8442 

a 

LRP1 
DDX1 
À1.6417 
FCER1A 
IL-13 
0.6318 
FCER1A 
SNF1LK2 
À1.5967 
HLA-DQA2 
0.4590 

a 

DDX1 
SNF1LK2 
À1.4047 
HLA-A 
HLA-DPB1 
0.4318 
DDX1 
À1.1802 
HLA-G 
HLA-A 
À0.2813 
HLA-DPB1 
EMID2 
0.8505 
HLA-G 
HLA-DQA2 
0.0678 
HLA-DPB1 
LOC441108 
À0.8076 

Note: Terms are ranked based on absolute t-value. a The genes that were found in publication. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">C.Lu et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Sparse regression for G Â G interactions at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SNP selection in genome-wide and candidate gene studies via penalized logistic regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Ayers</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Cordell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="879" to="891" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Statistics for High-Dimensional Data: Methods, Theory and Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Bu¨hlmannbu¨hlmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Van De Geer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York Inc</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Activated mast cells produce interleukin 13</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Burd</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1373" to="1380" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hla-g: from biology to clinical benefits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Carosella</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathwise coordinate optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Friedman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Appl. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="302" to="332" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A genome-wide association study of plasma total ige concentrations in the framingham heart study</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Granada</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Allergy Clin. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="840" to="845" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A variable selection method for genome-wide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A catalog of published genome-wide association studies. National Human Genome Research Institute</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Hindorff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The HLA system. First of two parts. N Eng</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Klein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Sato</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">343</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="702" to="709" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mendel version 4.0: a complete package for the exact genetic analysis of discrete traits in pedigree and population data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Lange</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">504</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mach: using sequence and genotype data to estimate haplotypes and unobserved genotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="816" to="834" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A variational Bayes algorithm for fast and accurate multiple locus genome-wide association analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Logsdon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">58</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of non-Hodgkin&apos;s lymphoma prognosis signatures using the CTGDR method</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Ma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding the missing heritability of complex diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Manolio</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">461</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="747" to="753" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tests for gene-environment interaction from case-control data: a novel study of type i error, power and designs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Mukherjee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="615" to="626" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Lu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Testing gene-environment interaction in large-scale case-control association studies: possible choices and comparisons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Mukherjee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">175</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic variability of the high-affinity ige receptor-subunit (fc&quot;ri)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Potaczek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunol. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plink: a toolset for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Purcell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="559" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variable selection using adaptive nonlinear interaction structures in high dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Radchenko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>James</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1541" to="1553" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Machine learning in genome-wide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Szymczak</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Screen and clean: a tool for identifying interactions in genomewide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coordinate descent algorithms for lasso penalized regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Lange</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="224" to="244" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide association analysis by lasso penalized logistic regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="714" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association screening of common and rare genetic variants by penalized regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Zhou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2375</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sparse. regression for G Â G interactions</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>