
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:59+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics NMRe: a web server for NMR protein structure refinement with high-quality structure validation scores</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hyojung</forename>
								<surname>Ryu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Korean Bioinformation Center (KOBIC)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Research Institute of Bioscience and Biotechnology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-806</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
									<country>the Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Nanobiotechnology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Yuseong-Gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-350</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
									<country>the Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gyutae</forename>
								<surname>Lim</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Korean Bioinformation Center (KOBIC)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Research Institute of Bioscience and Biotechnology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-806</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
									<country>the Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Nanobiotechnology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Yuseong-Gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-350</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
									<country>the Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bong</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Hyun</forename>
								<surname>Sung</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Bioenergy and Biochemical Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Research Institute of Bioscience and Biotechnology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-806</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
									<country>the Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jinhyuk</forename>
								<surname>Lee</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Korean Bioinformation Center (KOBIC)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Research Institute of Bioscience and Biotechnology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-806</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
									<country>the Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Nanobiotechnology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Yuseong-Gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-350</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
									<country>the Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics NMRe: a web server for NMR protein structure refinement with high-quality structure validation scores</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv595</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 9, 2015; revised on September 23, 2015; accepted on October 10, 2015</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Protein structure refinement is a necessary step for the study of protein function. In particular , some nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) structures are of lower quality than X-ray crystallographic structures. Here, we present NMRe, a web-based server for NMR structure refinement. The previously developed knowledge-based energy function STAP (Statistical Torsion Angle Potential) was used for NMRe refinement. With STAP, NMRe provides two refinement protocols using two types of distance restraints. If a user provides NOE (Nuclear Overhauser Effect) data, the refinement is performed with the NOE distance restraints as a conventional NMR structure refinement. Additionally, NMRe generates NOE-like distance restraints based on the inter-hydrogen distances derived from the input structure. The efficiency of NMRe refinement was validated on 20 NMR structures. Most of the quality assessment scores of the refined NMR structures were better than those of the original structures. The refinement results are provided as a three-dimensional structure view, a secondary structure scheme, and numerical and graphical structure validation scores. Availability and implementation: NMRe is available at http://psb.kobic.re.kr/nmre/</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The determination of three-dimensional (3D) protein structures is an important challenge in structural biology because structure is closely related to function. NMR (Nuclear Magnetic Resonance) spectroscopy is one method of protein structure determination, and it also provides information about the dynamics of proteins. However, protein structures determined by NMR spectroscopy are of lower quality than X-ray structures. Thus, refinement is a necessary step in NMR structure study. Three NMR structure refinement databases have been constructed: DRESS (a Database of REfined Solution NMR Structures;<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Nabuurs et al., 2004</ref>), RECOORD (REcalculated COORdinates Database;<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Nederveen et al., 2005</ref>) and STAP (Statistical Torsion Angle Potential;<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Yang et al., 2012</ref>). NMR structure refinement using the NOE (Nuclear Overhauser Effect) distance data obtained by NMR is performed in many refinement studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bertini et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chen et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Mao et al., 2014</ref>). However, NOE distance data exist in various formats, such as CYANA, CNS and XPLOR. Therefore, NOE data manipulation is difficult for general researchers. Another problem in improving NMR structures is the ambiguity and sparseness of NOE data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Nilges, 1997</ref>). The NMRe web server provides simple and fast NMR structure refinement with NOE-like distance data using the</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Materials and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Two developed energy potentials</head><p>The STAP is a grid-type, knowledge-based energy potential that focuses on the torsion angle combinations (u-w, u-v1, w-v1 and v1v2) of high-resolution X-ray structures under 2.0 A ˚ (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Kim et al., 2013</ref>). The efficiency of STAP was demonstrated in earlier studies via NMR structure refinement (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Yang et al., 2012</ref>). Another energy potential is the structure-derived distance potential, which was generated by inter-hydrogen distances below 7 A ˚ obtained from a given NMR structure, and this potential has greatly enhanced NMR structure refinement without experimental information (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Ryu et al., 2014</ref>). The potential functions consisted of two parameters: the equilibrium distance of two interacting hydrogen atoms and widths from 0 to 10 A ˚ at 1 A ˚ intervals. In a previous study, we found that the optimal width parameter is 4 A ˚. The optimal width is the default width for NMRe refinement calculations. This potential function prevents serious deviation from the current state of the original structure during the refinement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Running a refinement</head><p>Whole process of NMRe refinement is shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 1A</ref>. First, NMRe converts the input Protein Data Bank (PDB) file into a CHARMM-readable format and all ensemble structures are separated for simulation. Then, the 'NMRe_dist' is performed with distance restraints obtained from the given input PDB structure. When a user optionally uploads the NOE restraint file, the 'NMRe_noe' is performed with 'NMRe_dist'. In the 'NMRe_noe', the uploaded NOE file is used to generate the restraining potential of CHARMM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Brooks et al., 2009</ref>). The simulated annealing (SA) simulation is conducted with the CHARMM default energy and the EEF1.1 solvation energy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Lazaridis and Karplus, 1999</ref>) using CHARMM (see the Supplementary Information for more information). After refinement, NMRe evaluates structural quality to compare the refined structure and the original structure using structure validation scores.</p><p>The detailed structure validation scores are described in Supplementary Information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>NMRe refinement was tested on 20 structures obtained from PDB that have both NMR and X-ray structures (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>). The X-ray structures were used as a reference for measuring backbone similarity. The structure quality was measured using backbone similarity, NOE violation and structure validation scores (Supplementary Tables S2 and S3 and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>). In the 'NMRe_dist', the TM-score was increased from 0.79 to 0.80, and three energy scores (DOPE, nDOPE and dDFIRE) were stabilized. The clash score was also improved from 53.81 to 0.40. The Ramachandran score and several parameters of the WHAT_CHECK Z-score were significantly improved in the 'NMRe_noe'. In particular, the PROCHECK Ramachandran score was improved from 80.98 to 95.36. In Supplementary Table S3, comprehensive NOE restraint violations were reported. The number of violated NOE, Root Mean Square Deviation (RMSD) and Maximum NOE violation were improved in 'NMRe_noe'. However, 'NMRe_dist' has a slightly increased NOE restraints violation in comparison with original. Because the experimental measurement of NOE distance may have a distance error (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Nilges, 1997</ref>) of 0.5–1.0 A ˚ , these results are not regarded as a serious defect. Additionally, we demonstrated that dihedral angle restraints do not contribute much in this protocol (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S5</ref>). One of example target (2L4S) and comparison of the performance between the NMRe and other known refinement protocols are described in Supplementary Information.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 611 Bioinformatics, 32(4), 2016, 611–613 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv595 Advance Access Publication Date: 26 October 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table>inter-hydrogen distance restraints obtained from a given original 
structure. Conventional refinement is also performed using NOE 
distance data in the XPLOR/CYANA format. For acquiring better 
structure validation scores during the refinement process, a know-
ledge-based energy function (STAP) is added into the target energy 
potential. We expect the NMRe web server will contribute to NMR 
structure studies by providing accurate refinements. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> Web server NMRe uses PDB formats as an input 3D structure, and a NOE restraint is optional. The XPLOR or CYANA format is allowed. NMRe provides outputs in four ways (Fig. 1B and Supplementary Fig. S4) and is presented in the &apos;Analysis&apos; page of the status table. The 3D structure viewer shows structural changes caused by the refinement simulation. The secondary structure scheme presents the creation of the secondary structure, and when a user clicks on the secondary structure shape, it is highlighted in the 3D structure viewer. The &apos;Structural scores&apos; table shows the structure validation scores used to quantify the quality of various protein structure properties. The structure validation scores of the original/refined structures are compared with the normalized structure validation scores of 18 347 X-ray structures in a radar chart (Fig. 1B). The shaded region of the chart indicates greater quality than an average X-ray structure (upper 50% in structure quality). The refined structures can be downloaded through download links. Funding This study was supported by grants from the Korean Research Institute of Bioscience and the Biotechnology Research Initiative Program. The National Research Foundation of Korea funded this work under grant numbers 2012R1A1A2002676, 2012-0006002 and 20120006011. The Pioneer Research Center Program is funded by the Ministry of Science, ICT &amp; Future Planning (2013M3C1A3064780). Conflict of Interest: none declared. Supplementary Data Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online. Fig 1. (A) Flow chart of the NMRe refinement process. (B) Output of a refinement. The output page contains a 3D structure viewer, a secondary structure scheme and numerical/graphical structure validation scores</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A grid-enabled web portal for NMR structure refinement with AMBER</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Bertini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2384" to="2390" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CHARMM: the biomolecular simulation program</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Brooks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1545" to="1614" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Refinement of NMR structures using implicit solvent and advanced sampling techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16038" to="16047" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical torsion angle potential energy functions for protein structure modeling: a bicubic interpolation approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1156" to="1165" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effective energy function for proteins in solution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Lazaridis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Karplus</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="152" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein NMR structures refined with Rosetta have higher accuracy relative to corresponding X-ray crystal structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Mao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1893" to="1906" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DRESS: a database of REfined solution NMR structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Nabuurs</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="483" to="486" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RECOORD: a recalculated coordinate database of 500þ proteins from the PDB using restraints from the BioMagResBank</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Nederveen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="662" to="672" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ambiguous distance data in the calculation of NMR structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nilges</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fold. Des</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein NMR structures refined without NOE data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Ryu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108888</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">STAP refinement of the NMR database: a database of 2405 refined solution NMR structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="525" to="530" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>