
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:48+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies ontoCAT: an R package for ontology traversal and search</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Natalja</forename>
								<surname>Kurbatova</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">EMBL Outstation-Hinxton</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">European Bioinformatics Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Tomasz</forename>
								<surname>Adamusiak</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">EMBL Outstation-Hinxton</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">European Bioinformatics Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pavel</forename>
								<surname>Kurnosov</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">EMBL Outstation-Hinxton</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">European Bioinformatics Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Morris</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Swertz</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">EMBL Outstation-Hinxton</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">European Bioinformatics Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Misha</forename>
								<surname>Kapushesky</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">EMBL Outstation-Hinxton</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">European Bioinformatics Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alex</forename>
								<surname>Bateman</surname>
								<roleName>Associate Editor:</roleName>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Genomics Coordination Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Groningen and University of Groningen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Groningen</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies ontoCAT: an R package for ontology traversal and search</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2468" to="2470"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received on January 13, 2011; revised on June 8, 2011; accepted on June 17, 2011</note>
					<note>[13:03 30/7/2011 Bioinformatics-btr375.tex] Page: 2468 2468–2470</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: There exist few simple and easily accessible methods to integrate ontologies programmatically in the R environment. We present ontoCAT—an R package to access ontologies in widely used standard formats, stored locally in the filesystem or available online. The ontoCAT package supports a number of traversal and search functions on a single ontology, as well as searching for ontology terms across multiple ontologies and in major ontology repositories. Availability: The package and sources are freely available in Bioconductor starting from version 2.8:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The R package ontoCAT was created to support basic operations on ontologies: traversal and search, uniform access to ontologies in OWL (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Lacy, 2005</ref>) and OBO (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Barry et al., 2007</ref>) formats and to provide R access to major ontology repositories OLS and BioPortal. Several hundreds of public ontologies and numerous private ontologies for describing biological data exist today. Using ontologies in R (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Gentleman, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">R Development Core Team, 2006</ref>) is difficult due to the lack of uniform package support. At the same time numerous Java-based ontology projects are available. ontoCAT takes advantage of a standard Java library with the same name 'ontoCAT' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Adamusiak et al., 2010</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Adamusiak et al., , 2011</ref>) to implement its functionality. The ontoCAT package: @BULLET gives unified, format-independent access to ontology terms and the ontology hierarchy represented in OWL and OBO formats;</p><p>@BULLET provides basic methods for ontology traversal, such as searching for terms, listing a specific term's relations, showing paths to the term from the root element of the ontology, showing flattened-tree representations of the ontology hierarchy; and @BULLET supports working with groups of ontologies and with major public ontology repositories: searching for terms across * To whom correspondence should be addressed. ontologies, listing available ontologies and loading ontologies for further analysis as necessary.</p><p>No other package with similar functionality exists at the moment in the R environment. The integration of the above functionality into R allows combining and automating ontology-related tasks. Different examples of ontology-related tasks that can be accomplished with the help of the ontoCAT package are given in the package documentation (http://www.ontocat.org/wiki/OntocatGuide): gene enrichment test and grouping of results, search and re-annotation of free-text to ontology and operations with relationships. ontoCAT has been included into Bioconductor, the main R open source project in bioinformatics. ontoCAT has been downloaded 347 times since its first release in December 2010. There is a large research community already using R to work with Gene Ontology (GO). Working with other ontologies is not as well–developed and ontoCAT helps to fill the gap.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>The ontoCAT R package consists of two main parts, grouping similar methods: @BULLET Single ontology traversal methods. @BULLET Methods to work across multiple ontologies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Single ontology traversal methods</head><p>The ontoCAT package can load an ontology in OWL or OBO format from a local file or on-the-fly from a URI. Reasoning over ontologies and extracting relationships is supported by using HermiT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Motik et al., 2009</ref>) reasoner. OBO ontologies are translated by OWL API (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Horridge and Bechhofer, 2009</ref>) into valid OWL format that can be reasoned over. Ontologies can also be loaded from ontology repositories. Two public repositories are supported: BioPortal for accessing and sharing biomedical ontologies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Noy et al., 2009</ref>), currently hosting 241 ontologies and the Ontology Lookup Service (OLS) for querying multiple ontologies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Cote et al., 2008</ref>), currently hosting 81 ontologies. To load an ontology getOntology(path/accession) method of the Ontology class is available. It takes a single argument, specifying the local filesystem path, the full URI for the ontology file, or its OLS/BioPortal accession. The reference ontology supported by ontoCAT is Experimental Factor Ontology (EFO) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Malone et al., 2010</ref>), developed for applications in functional genomics. The latest version of EFO can be loaded by using the method getEFO(). When an ontology is loaded, other ontoCAT methods become available.<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Cline et al., 2007</ref>). In ontoCAT the subsumption 'subclass/superclass' is supported in a user friendly form of 'child – parent' relationship. No distinction is made between universals (classes) and particulars (instances) as they are both treated as ontology terms with parent–child relationship: class is treated as parent, instances are children of the class. The advantage of using a reasoner in ontoCAT is the ability to work with different relationships in addition to subsumption. However, if reasoning over ontology is not desirable getOntologyNoReasoning method should be used instead of getOntology method described above. An example of relationships that can be retrieved by ontoCAT starting from a particular EFO ontology term 'EFO_0000815' (heart) is given in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>. Below there are several examples of ontoCAT methods: @BULLET searchTerm(Ontology, 'myocardium') returns a list of terms where 'myocardium' is mentioned; @BULLET getTermParentsById(Ontology, 'EFO_0003087') lists parents of the term 'EFO_0003087' (atrial myocardium): 'EFO_0000819' (myocardium) (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>); @BULLET getTermById(Ontology, 'EFO_0000819') returns ontology term by its accession: 'EFO_0000819' (myocardium); @BULLET getTermChildren(Ontology, term) lists children of the term 'EFO_0000819' (myocardium): 'EFO_0003087' (atrial myocardium) and 'EFO_0003088' (ventricular myocardium) (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>); @BULLET showHierarchyDownToTerm(Ontology, 'EFO_0000819') prints out a flattened-tree representation of the ontology from the root term down to 'EFO_0000819'</p><p>(A number of self-descriptive methods like showPathsToTerm(Ontology, term), isRoot(Ontology, term) are also available. The full list of methods together with descriptions is provided in online documentation (http://www.ontocat.org/wiki/r) and is included into the package.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Operations on multiple ontologies</head><p>ontoCAT provides methods to work with groups or 'batches' of ontologies, local or web-based. Users can search for terms across such resources and load specific individual ontologies by accession. To create a local batch of ontologies the getOntologyBatch(path) method of the batch class is provided, taking a single argument: the path to the local directory containing ontology files. By default, a call to getOntologyBatch() without any arguments will load the EFO ontology. Ontologies can be added to an existing batch as needed via the addOntology(The ontoCAT package also provides methods to list ontologies in batches and to list ontologies available in BioPortal and OLS: listLoadedOntologies(batch), listOLSOntologies(batch) and listBioportalOntologies(batch). When the sought terms are found and term-specific operations (parent/child/other relationships retrieval, etc.) are needed, the getOntology(batch,accession) returns the ontology object for the concrete ontology with all single-ontology methods available.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">TECHNICAL DETAILS</head><p>The package is based primarily on the Ontology Common API Tasks Java library, on the OWLAPI and depends on rJava R package. HermiT reasoner is used to support relationships. ontoCAT R package is open-source and is available under the Apache License Version 2.0. We provide two versions of ontoCAT:</p><p>@BULLET Light-weight ontoCAT package version is available in Bioconductor (http://bioconductor.org) starting from release 2.7, and includes all single-ontology functionality except for methods to work with multiple ontologies and search in OLS and BioPortal. @BULLET Full version includes batch methods and due to package size limitations are available only from the project website.</p><p>The package sources and full documentation are available at http://www.ontocat.org/wiki/r.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>The ontoCAT R package consists of convenient methods for working with ontologies in the R environment. The package has been successfully used in a number of</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>projects in the Functional</head><p>Page: 2470 2468–2470</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>N.Kurbatova et al.</head><p>Genomics Group at the European Bioinformatics Institute and this is its first public release. The package provides basic operations on ontologies represented in standard formats and enables searches in online ontology repositories: OLS and BioPortal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. An example of a directed acyclic graph representing all the relationships in an ontology for a particular EFO ontology term 'EFO_0000815' (heart). Edges are labeled according to the relationship. Organism part classes are represented as ellipses and disease classes are shown as rectangles. The ontoCAT package was used to compute the relationships which were later processed in Cytoscape (Cline et al., 2007).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Ontology Common API Tasks development team and the EBI Gene Expression Atlas development team.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: European Community's Seventh Framework Programme projects GEN2PHEN (grant number 200754); SYBARIS (grant number 242220); NWO/Rubicon (grant number 825.09.008). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">OntoCAT – a simpler way to access ontology resources. Nature Precedings, [Epub ahead of print</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Adamusiak</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OntoCAT – simple ontology search and integration in Java, R and REST\JavaScript</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Adamusiak</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">218</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The OBO foundry: coordinated evolution of ontologies to support biomedical data integration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Barry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1251" to="1255" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integration of biological networks and gene expression data using Cytoscape</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Cline</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protocol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2366" to="2382" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ontology lookup service: more data and better tools for controlled vocabulary queries</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Cote</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="372" to="376" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">R Programming for Bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Gentleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>Chapman &amp; Hall\CRC</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The OWL API: a Java API for working with OWL 2 ontologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Horridge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Bechhofer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<pubPlace>Chantilly, Virginia</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>6th. OWL Experienced and Directions Workshop</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">OWL: representing Information Using the Web Ontology Language</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Lacy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>Trafford Publishing</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Victoria, BC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hypertableau reasoning for description logics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Motik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Art. Intell. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioPortal: ontologies and integrated data resources at the click of a mouse</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Noy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="170" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling sample variables with an experimental factor ontology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Malone</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1112" to="1118" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Development</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Core</forename>
				<surname>Team</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<pubPlace>Vienna, Austria</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>