
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-11T00:00+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">OSA: a fast and accurate alignment tool for RNA-Seq</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jun</forename>
								<surname>Hu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Omicsoft Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>164 Quade Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>27513</postCode>
									<settlement>Cary</settlement>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Bioinformatics Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">North Carolina State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ricks Hall, 1 Lampe Dr</addrLine>
									<postCode>27607</postCode>
									<settlement>Raleigh</settlement>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Huanying</forename>
								<surname>Ge</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Genome Analysis Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Amgen Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>One Amgen Center Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>91320</postCode>
									<settlement>Thousand Oaks</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matt</forename>
								<surname>Newman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Omicsoft Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>164 Quade Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>27513</postCode>
									<settlement>Cary</settlement>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kejun</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Omicsoft Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>164 Quade Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>27513</postCode>
									<settlement>Cary</settlement>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">OSA: a fast and accurate alignment tool for RNA-Seq</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1933" to="1934"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts294</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 2, 2012; revised on May 1, 2012; accepted on May 9, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [10:49 18/6/2012 Bioinformatics-bts294.tex] Page: 1933 1933–1934 Sequence analysis Associate Editor: Ivo Hofacker Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Accurately mapping RNA-Seq reads to the reference genome is a critical step for performing downstream analysis such as transcript assembly, isoform detection and quantification. Many tools have been developed; however, given the huge size of the next generation sequencing datasets and the complexity of the transcriptome, RNA-Seq read mapping remains a challenge with the ever-increasing amount of data. We develop Omicsoft sequence aligner (OSA), a fast and accurate alignment tool for RNA-Seq data. Benchmarked with existing methods, OSA improves mapping speed 4–10-fold with better sensitivity and less false positives. Availability: OSA can be downloaded from http://omicsoft.com/osa. It is free to academic users. OSA has been tested extensively on Linux, Mac OS X and Windows platforms. Contact:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>RNA-Seq, a high-throughput sequencing technology used to sequence complementary DNA, has been widely thought of as 'a revolutionary tool for transcriptomics study' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Wang et al., 2009</ref>). Compared with microarray technology, conventional expressed sequence tag (EST) or other tag-based sequencing, it has less sampling bias, higher resolution and much broader expression range coverage (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Marioni et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Ozsolak and Milos, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Wang, et al., 2008</ref>). For human, mouse and other mammalian organisms with a relatively well-annotated genome, mapping short reads from next generation sequencing (NGS) to reference transcriptome/genome is usually the first and essential step for RNA-Seq data analysis. This 'reference-based' approach tends to be more sensitive and computationally efficient than a de novo assembly approach (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Martin and Wang, 2011</ref>). Many tools have been developed in recent years (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Au et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Chen et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Grant et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Huang et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Trapnell et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Wang et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Wu and Nacu, 2010</ref>). TopHat (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Trapnell et al., 2009</ref>) maps the reads to reference genome using bowtie (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Langmead et al., 2009</ref>). The consensus islands are first clustered; the splice junctions are then generated by enumerating the canonical donor and acceptor sites between the neighboring islands for putative introns. RNA-Seq unified mapper (RUM) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Grant et al., 2011</ref>) and RNASeqR (<ref type="bibr">Chen et al., 2011</ref>) align the reads against both * To whom correspondence should be addressed. transcriptome and genome using bowtie. The results are merged and the un-mapped reads are further aligned to genome with blat (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Kent, 2002</ref>). SOAPsplice (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Huang et al., 2011</ref>) first maps reads to reference genome indexed with Burrows Wheeler transformation (BWT), and then unmapped reads are aligned again using two segment strategies. MapSplice (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Wang et al., 2010</ref>) and SpliceMap (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Au et al., 2010</ref>) also use similar break and assemble approach for longer reads. We introduce Omicsoft sequence aligner (OSA), an ultra-fast RNA-Seq aligner/mapper, different from the majority of existing methods relying on Bowtie or BWA, which use a BWT-based index. OSA uses a k-mer indexed genome hash table and avoids breaking down longer reads into sub-reads and merging steps, which becomes increasingly computationally expensive with the longer reads from the newer sequencing machines. OSA is 4–10 times faster than popular RNA-Seq aligners developed and used so far. It works well for both short and long reads and its performance does not deteriorate for high-sequencing error data. OSA also significantly improves the ability to detect both short and long indels as well as exon junctions.OSA implements various optimization strategies at different stages of mapping pipeline to improve alignment speed and accuracy. All the reference and read sequence matching are achieved through super-fast bitwise operations. For each read, where quality values are available, OSA will first scan the reads from 3-end until the first acceptable quality nucleotide is found. This trimming process removes the ambiguous reads at the end and significantly improves the alignments speed (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Falgueras et al., 2010</ref>). During alignment stage, a 'seed and extend' strategy is used to test each potential matching position. A similar strategy has been used in GSNAP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Wu and Nacu, 2010</ref>) and blat (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Kent, 2002</ref>). In addition, OSA takes advantage of the properties of paired-end reads to filter the alignment results and limit alignment space.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>We simulated 12 sets of 10 million pairs of paired-end RNA-Seq reads with three independent simulations at each of four error rates (0, 0.5, 1 and 2%) using the BEER pipeline (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Grant et al., 2011</ref>). We compare OSA with TopHat (v1.3.3 and v1.4.0), RUM (v1.10) and SOAPsplice (v1.8) on a four-core 3 GHz AMD Phenom(tm) II X4 945 Processor desktop with 16 GB RAM running OpenSUSE Linux (See Supplementary Methods for details). The speed, the alignment accuracy and the percentage of indels and exon junctions correctly identified are evaluated for different tools either with a gene model or without gene model. OSA has superior speed; it is about 4–10 times faster compared with other tools on Linux platform (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). For all the tools, the alignment speed decreases with error rates; this is expected as the aligner has to try more scenarios for non-perfect matching. OSA's speed improvement is more dramatic at high error rates (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). The benchmark results also show that using a gene model slightly improves the alignment speed (except Tophat1.3.3) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>) and accuracy (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S1</ref>). When a gene model is provided, OSA matches most reads to the correct location of the transcriptome/genome; TopHat 1.3.3 is the close second. Both algorithms perform well even without a gene model. RUM and TopHat1.4.0 work much better with a gene model at low error rates and their performances deteriorate when error rate increases to 2% (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S1</ref>). All tools detect &gt;85% of exon junctions. OSA, SOAPsplice and RUM have higher sensitivity than TopHat. However, OSA has much fewer false positives than RUM and SOAPsplice (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S2A</ref>). RUM has the best sensitivity detecting indels. However, it also increases the percentage of the false positives and decreases the positive prediction value (PPV). TopHat detects a much smaller number of indels, this might be improved after integration with the latest Bowtie 2.0, which supports indel detection at the alignment stage. OSA achieves good sensitivity at detecting indels while controlling the false positives (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S3A</ref>). Due to sequencing errors (or random error introduced during simulation), one read can match to a different location on the genome with a better or equal matching score. A large portion of these false positives could be attributed to these sequencing/random errors. We tested the junction and indel detecting again after adjusting the metrics for these reads and we can see that the PPV of all tools improves, especially SOAPsplice and RUM. However, the overall detection pattern is still the same (Supplementary Tables S2B and S3B). We also tested OSA against TopHat 1.3.3, which performs better than other tools we benchmarked against, with eight randomly selected NGS datasets from NCBI SRA. These datasets include both single-and paired-end reads, reads with different length, and from both human and mouse species with various sequencing depths. Similar to the simulation outcomes, we find that OSA is several times faster than TopHat and maps 3–4% more reads. Moreover, it also identifies much more known and novel exon junctions (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S4</ref>).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [10:49 18/6/2012 Bioinformatics-bts294.tex] Page: 1934 1933–1934 J.Hu et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Speed of various RNA-Seq alignment tools at different error levels. 10 M paired-end RNA-Seq reads are simulated at four different error rates. These reads are mapped to the mouse genome using different tools either with gene model (GM) or without. The time taken to align the reads is recorded. Results are averaged from three independent simulated datasets. The exact numeric values are summarized in Supplementary Table S1. (Win: Windows)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Conflict of Interest: J.H., M.N., and K.L. have financial interest in OmicSoft Corporation. The research reported in this paper is in the field in which OmicSoft is developing commercial software.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> IMPLEMENTATION OSA indexes the reference genomes into a 64-bit 14-mer library by default using an approach similar to GSNAP (Wu and Nacu, 2010) (see Supplementary Information for OSA index system detail). During RNA-Seq alignment, where a well-annotated gene model is available, OSA will first build the transcriptome reference library from the provided gtf(gff) gene model file. The alignment pipeline can be divided into four sub-steps. First, the RNA-Seq reads will be aligned to the transcriptome and translated to corresponding genome coordinates considering introns. From our benchmark results and previous publications, aligning the RNA-Seq reads to an annotated transcriptome can improve the speed and accuracy. Similar strategies have been successfully used by RUM, RNASEQR and latest TopHat 1.4 beta (Chen et al., 2011; Grant et al., 2011). Second, the unmapped reads will be mapped against the reference genome for un-annotated exons and novel exon junctions. The exon junction detection is based on an extended middle indel detection algorithm (Wu and Nacu, 2010). Only deletions were considered (as introns are deletions from the reference), and only canonical donor–acceptor patterns (GT-AG, GC-AG and AT-AC) are considered, as they constitute the majority of splice sites (Burset et al., 2001). Third, the exon junction detection algorithm will not be able to detect novel exon junctions with a distal short fragment. Thus, a step to rescue these reads was added. The remaining unmapped reads that fail to align to both the standard transcriptome and genome will be matched against the newly identified exon junctions in Step 2. Finally, all mapped reads from the previous steps will be combined for output. © The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of splice junctions from paired-end RNA-seq data by SpliceMap</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Au</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4570" to="4578" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SpliceDB: database of canonical and non-canonical mammalian splice sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Burset</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="259" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNASEQR—a streamlined and accurate RNA-seq sequence analysis program</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SeqTrim: a high-throughput pipeline for pre-processing any type of sequence read</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Falgueras</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">38</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative analysis of RNA-Seq alignment algorithms and the RNA-Seq unified mapper (RUM)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Grant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2518" to="2528" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SOAPsplice: genome-wide ab initio detection of splice junctions from RNA-Seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">46</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BLAT—the BLAST-like alignment tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Kent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="656" to="664" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Langmead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA-seq: an assessment of technical reproducibility and comparison with gene expression arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Marioni</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1509" to="1517" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Next-generation transcriptome assembly</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Martin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="682" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA sequencing: advances, challenges and opportunities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Ozsolak</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Milos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TopHat: discovering splice junctions with RNA-Seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Trapnell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1105" to="1111" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative isoform regulation in human tissue transcriptomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">456</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="470" to="476" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MapSplice: accurate mapping of RNA-seq reads for splice junction discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">178</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA-Seq: a revolutionary tool for transcriptomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast and SNP-tolerant detection of complex variants and splicing in short reads</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Nacu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="873" to="881" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>