
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-11T00:00+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis PAPA: a flexible tool for identifying pleiotropic pathways using genome-wide association study summaries</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yan</forename>
								<surname>Wen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Trace Elements and Endemic Diseases of Ministry of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">School of Public Health, Health Science Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Xi&apos;an Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Xi&apos;an</addrLine>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wenyu</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Trace Elements and Endemic Diseases of Ministry of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">School of Public Health, Health Science Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Xi&apos;an Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Xi&apos;an</addrLine>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xiong</forename>
								<surname>Guo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Trace Elements and Endemic Diseases of Ministry of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">School of Public Health, Health Science Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Xi&apos;an Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Xi&apos;an</addrLine>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Feng</forename>
								<surname>Zhang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Trace Elements and Endemic Diseases of Ministry of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">School of Public Health, Health Science Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Xi&apos;an Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Xi&apos;an</addrLine>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Oliver</forename>
								<surname>Stegle</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Trace Elements and Endemic Diseases of Ministry of Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">School of Public Health, Health Science Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Xi&apos;an Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Xi&apos;an</addrLine>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis PAPA: a flexible tool for identifying pleiotropic pathways using genome-wide association study summaries</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv668</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 5, 2015; revised on November 3, 2015; accepted on November 7, 2015</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Pleiotropy is common in the genetic architectures of complex diseases. To the best of our knowledge, no analysis tool has been developed for identifying pleiotropic pathways using multiple genome-wide association study (GWAS) summaries by now. Here, we present PAPA, a flexible tool for pleiotropic pathway analysis utilizing GWAS summary results. The performance of PAPA was validated using publicly available GWAS summaries of body mass index and waist-hip ratio of the GIANT datasets. PAPA identified a set of pleiotropic pathways, which have been demonstrated to be involved in the development of obesity. Availability and implementation: PAPA program, document and illustrative example are available at http://sourceforge.net/projects/papav1/files/.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Pleiotropy describes the genetic phenomenon of a single gene affecting multiple phenotypes. It can be explained by single gene product having various biological functions, or acting as a signal factor implicated in the development of different phenotypes. Pleiotropy is common in the genetic architectures of complex diseases (<ref type="bibr">Sivakumaran et al., 2011</ref>). A total of 16.9% of genes recorded in the NHGRI Catalog of published genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have pleiotropic effects (<ref type="bibr">Sivakumaran et al., 2011</ref>). Clarifying the molecular mechanism of pleiotropy is helpful for pathogenetic studies and drug development of human complex diseases. Recent achievements in GWAS provide a good opportunity for systematical pleiotropy studies of complex diseases. A simple approach is to analyse disease phenotypes separately using univariate approaches. The study results of different disease phenotypes are compared, which may result in low statistical power. To address this issue, multiple pleiotropy analysis approaches and tools have been proposed (<ref type="bibr">Lee et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Nyholt, 2014</ref>). A group of genes with pleiotropic effects were identified for complex diseases (<ref type="bibr">Elliott et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">International Schizophrenia et al., 2009</ref>). However, current pleiotropic mechanism studies of complex diseases mostly focus on individual pleiotropic genes, which are sometimes functionally independent. Some individual pleiotropic genes participate in multiple cellular processes. The biological functions of a part of genes remain elusive now. Therefore, identifying individual pleiotropic genes often provides limited information for genetic studies of complex diseases. Inspired by the gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA) of microarray data (<ref type="bibr">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>), pathway-based GWAS were proposed (<ref type="bibr">Wang et al., 2007</ref>) and successfully applied in the genetic studies of complex diseases (<ref type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2010</ref>). However, to the best of our knowledge, no analysis tool has been developed for identifying pleiotropic pathways using GWAS summary results by now. In this study, we extended the pathway analysis algorithm proposed by<ref type="bibr">Wang et al. (2007)</ref>, and developed a pleiotropic pathway analysis tool PAPA. We applied PAPA to public available GWAS summaries of V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com body mass index (BMI) and waist-hip ratio (WHR) of the Genetic Investigation of ANthropometric Traits datasets (<ref type="bibr">Speliotes et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Heid et al., 2010</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Implementation</head><p>Step 1 – Assigning association testing statistics to genes We suppose that GWAS summaries of M genes and N phenotypes were available. Let S ij denote the association testing statistic (for instance, chi-square values for qualitative traits) of jth SNP for ith phenotype (i ¼ 1,2,. .. ,N). SNPs are assigned to genes by distance. A physical distance of 500 kb is used to connect a SNP to a gene in this study. For ith phenotype and mth gene (m ¼ 1,2,. .. ,M), we select the largest S ij from the SNPs assigned to the gene as the score of the gene, denoted as S im. All genes are ranked by sorting their scores S im from largest to smallest (S r i1 !S r i2 !::::S r iM ), which is denoted as S r i ¼ ½S r i1; S r i2 ; ::::S r iM .</p><p>Step 2 – Calculating enrichment scores For a given pathway P consisting of M P genes, let G v denote the vth gene (v ¼ 1,2,. .. ,M P ) of pathway P. Let ES P i denote the enrichment score (ES) of pathway P for ith phenotype. ES P i is calculated by Kolmogorov–Smirnov-like running sum statistic (<ref type="bibr">Wang et al., 2007</ref>):</p><formula>ES P i ¼ max 1 v M ( X Gu2P;u v jS r iu j N Ri À X Gu6 2P;u v 1 M À M P ) ; where N Ri ¼ X Gu2P jS r iu j:</formula><p>Step 3 – Permutation and centralization To obtain the null distribution of ES P i , permutations were conducted through circular genome permutation (<ref type="bibr">Cabrera et al., 2012</ref>). For kth permutation, let ES Pnull ik denote the ES value of pathway P for ith phenotype, calculating from permutated data. After K times permutations, we can obtain the null distribution of ES P i , denoted as</p><formula>ES Pnull i ¼ ½ES Pnull i1 ; ES Pnull i2</formula><p>; :::; ES Pnull iK . For pathway P, we calculate the centered ES (CES) of observed data (denote as CES P ) and permutated data (denote as CES Pnull ¼ ½CES Pnull</p><formula>1 ; CES Pnull 2 ; :::; CES Pnull K ) of N phenotypes, defined by CES P ¼ X N i¼1 ES P i meanðES Pnull i Þ Â w i and CES Pnull k ¼ X N i¼1 ES Pnull ik meanðES Pnull i Þ Â w i ;</formula><p>Where k (k ¼ 1,2,. .. ,K) denotes kth permutation. w i is the weight parameter of ith phenotype. For instance, w i can be assigned as the proportion of GWAS samples of ith phenotype in total samples.where k (k ¼ 1,2,. .. ,K) denotes kth permutation. After normalization, the NCES values of pathways with different sizes can be directly compared with each other (<ref type="bibr">Wang et al., 2007</ref>).</p><p>Step 5 – Calculating P values Statistical testing P value of each pathway is calculated as the proportion of NCES P being smaller than NCES Pnull in K times permutations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Application to GWAS summaries of BMI and WHR</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results and discussion</head><p>As shown by Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>, the top three significant pathways functionally involved in adipocyte differentiation, Wnt signalling and synthesis of bile acids and bile salts, which have been demonstrated to be involved in the development of obesity (<ref type="bibr">Mori et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Prinz et al., 2015</ref>). The computational cost of PAPA program is affordable. The GWAS datasets of BMI and WHR were analyzed (1000 permutations) on a Dell computer with Intel Xeon CPU E5620 (2.4 GHz) and 4 GB memory. PAPA spent 98 h to complete data analysis. In this study, we extended the GSEA algorithm (<ref type="bibr">Subramanian et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wang et al., 2007</ref>), and developed a pleiotropic pathway analysis tool PAPA. Because of integrating GWAS results and prior knowledge of biological pathways, PAPA may provide novel clues for clarifying the pleiotropic mechanisms of human complex diseases. It should be noted that the definition of biological pathways may affect the performance of PAPA. In PAPA package, we provided two pathway gene annotation files, which were collected from public pathway database, including KEGG Pathway Database, Reactome Pathway Database, BioCarta, Ambion GeneAssist Pathway Atlas, Gene Ontology and GSEA Molecular Signatures Database.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>The study was supported by National Natural Scientific Fund of China (81472925).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>GWAS summaries of BMI were obtained from Speliotes et al. (2010), containing 123 865 study subjects of European ancestry. GWAS summaries of WHR were collected from Heid et al. (2010), including 77 167 study subjects of European ancestry. 3269 pathways or gene ontology categories collecting from the Molecular Signatures Database of GSEA were analyzed (Subramanian et al., 2005). The weighting parameters of BMI and WHR were 0.62 and 0.38, respectively. 1000 permutations were conducted by PAPA to calculate the empirical P value of each pathway.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Conflict of Interest: none declared. References Cabrera,C.P. et al. (2012) Uncovering networks from genome-wide association studies via circular genomic permutation. G3, 2, 1067–1075. Elliott,K.S. et al. (2013) Evaluation of the genetic overlap between osteoarthritis with body mass index and height using genome-wide association scan data, Ann. Rheum. Dis., 72, 935–941. PAPAHeid,I.M. et al. (2010) Meta-analysis identifies 13 new loci associated with waist-hip ratio and reveals sexual dimorphism in the genetic basis of fat distribution, Nat. Genet., 42, 949–960. International Schizophrenia,C. et al. (2009) Common polygenic variation contributes to risk of schizophrenia and bipolar disorder. Nature, 460, 748–752. Lee,S.H. et al. (2012) Estimation of pleiotropy between complex diseases using single-nucleotide polymorphism-derived genomic relationships and restricted maximum likelihood. Bioinformatics, 28, 2540–2542. Mori,H. et al. (2012) Secreted frizzled-related protein 5 suppresses adipocyte mitochondrial metabolism through WNT inhibition. J. Clin. Invest., 122, 2405–2416 Nyholt,D.R. (2014) SECA: SNP effect concordance analysis using genomewide association summary results. Bioinformatics, 30, 2086–2088. Prinz,P. et al. (2015) Plasma bile acids show a positive correlation with body mass index and are negatively associated with cognitive restraint of eating in obese patients. Front. Neurosci., 9, 199. Speliotes,E.K. et al. (2010) Association analyses of 249 796 individuals reveal 18 new loci associated with body mass index. Nat. Genet., 42, 937–948. Sivakumaran,S. et al. (2011) Abundant pleiotropy in human complex diseases and traits. Am. J. Hum. Genet., 89, 607–618. Subramanian,A. et al. (2005) Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledgebased approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 102, 15545–15550. Wang,K. et al. (2007) Pathway-based approaches for analysis of genomewide association studies. Am. J. Hum. Genet., 81, 1278–1283. Zhang,L. et al. (2010) Pathway-based genome-wide association analysis identified the importance of regulation-of-autophagy pathway for ultradistal radius BMD. J. Bone. Miner. Res., 25, 1572–1580.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Y.Wen et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>