
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:43+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">pez: phylogenetics for the environmental sciences</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">William</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Pearse</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ecology, Evolution, and Behavior</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Minnesota</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Saint Paul</settlement>
									<region>MN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">McGill University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Montré al</addrLine>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dé partement des Sciences Biologiques</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université du Qué bec a ` Montré al</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Succursale Centre-ville</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Montré al</addrLine>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Marc</forename>
								<forename type="middle">W</forename>
								<surname>Cadotte</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto Scarborough</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Scarborough</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jeannine</forename>
								<surname>Cavender-Bares</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ecology, Evolution, and Behavior</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Minnesota</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Saint Paul</settlement>
									<region>MN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anthony</forename>
								<forename type="middle">R</forename>
								<surname>Ives</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Zoology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Wisconsin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Madison</settlement>
									<region>WI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Caroline</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Tucker</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Colorado</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Boulder</settlement>
									<region>CO</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Steve</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Walker</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics and Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">McMaster University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hamilton</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country>Canada,</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matthew</forename>
								<forename type="middle">R</forename>
								<surname>Helmus</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Animal Ecology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vrije Universiteit</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">pez: phylogenetics for the environmental sciences</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv277</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 13, 2015; revised on April 7, 2015; accepted on April 25, 2015</note>
					<note>Phylogenetics *To whom correspondence should be addressed Associate Editor: David Posada</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>pez is an R package that permits measurement, modelling and simulation of phylogen-etic structure in ecological data. pez contains the first implementation of many methods in R, and aggregates existing data structures and methods into a single, coherent package. Availability and implementation: pez is released under the GPL v3 open-source license, available on the Internet from CRAN (http://cran.r-project.org). The package is under active development, and the authors welcome contributions (see</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Community phylogenetics (or eco-phylogenetics) combines ecology and evolutionary biology, linking ecological phenomena with the evolutionary processes that generate species and their traits (see<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Webb et al., 2002</ref>). This growing field has produced a number of statistical tools and software code to implement them (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Kembel et al., 2010</ref>), but this code is disparate and handles data differently, making routine data analyses challenging. In many cases, published methods are not formally implemented in a software package and are available only as supplementary materials to papers. Without active (public) maintenance, these valuable techniques are effectively lost to the scientific community. Here, we present the pez R (R Core<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Team, 2015</ref>) package which provides an intuitive framework that merges existing tools and supports the development of the next generation of eco-phylogenetic methods. It is based around an R class (comparative.comm) that links phylogenetic, community, environmental and trait data in a single object. With a comparative.comm object, one can presently calculate over 30 phylogenetic and trait diversity metrics (described in the documentation for pez.metrics), including more than 10 that were previously unavailable in R. pez additionally implements statistical models (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Cavender-Bares et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ives and Helmus, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Rafferty and Ives, 2013</ref>) to infer the processes that underlie patterns in community phylogenetic and trait data. Users can also perform simulations under various community assembly and evolutionary processes, to help test hypotheses about the structure of biodiversity.<ref type="bibr">, 2013</ref>). pez integrates and makes use of much existing R code (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bortolussi et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Genz et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Koenker, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Labierté et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Oksanen et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Paradis et al., 2004</ref>), and its comparative.comm class is directly compatible with all caper (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Orme et al., 2013</ref>) code, easing comparative analysis of species trait data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Description</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data manipulation and storage</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Metrics</head><p>Following the classification of<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Pearse et al. (2014)</ref>, pez simplifies the calculation and comparison of over 30 metrics by grouping them into four categories: shape, evenness, dispersion, and dissimilarity. Shape metrics measure the structure of a community phylogeny, while evenness metrics additionally incorporate species abundances. Dispersion metrics are used to examine whether phylogenetic biodiversity in an assemblage differs from the expectation of random assembly from a given set of species—a species pool. Finally, dissimilarity metrics measure the pairwise difference in phylogenetic biodiversity between assemblages. This classification links directly onto the kind of data the investigator has at hand: assemblage occupancy (shape), assemblage abundance (evenness), source pool (dispersion) and assemblage comparisons (dissimilarity). Other packages (notably picante;<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Kembel et al., 2010</ref>) allow for the calculation of some of the metrics contained within pez. pez unifies these metrics with other metrics not previously implemented under a common interface that can be extended to trait and transformed phylogenetic matrices (sensu<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Letten and Cornwell, 2015</ref>). For example, pez provides the first implementation of the traitgram framework (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ackerly, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cadotte et al., 2010</ref>), allowing direct comparison of the extent of phylogenetic and functional trait community structure. pez also contains a flexible metric estimation and null-model generation suite (the generic.metric family), that can be used to easily compare different metrics and perhaps generate new dispersion metrics. New null models based around species' trait values (using trait.asm), and expected mean pairwise phylogenetic and trait distances (using ConDivSim) can also be simulated. The speed and ease by which pez allows for the user to compare many metrics is important because different metrics reveal separate aspects of eco-phylogenetic structure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cadotte et al., 2010</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Statistical models</head><p>pez implements the Cavender<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bares et al. (2004)</ref>regression framework (fingerprint.regression), and extends it to include more metrics of trait evolution. While community phylogenetics has been criticised for relying on the assumption of niche conservatism to explain ecological assembly (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Mayfield and Levine, 2010</ref>), this early (yet previously unavailable) approach does not rely on niche conservatism. Instead, it regresses the correlation between species' trait similarity and observed degree of co-occurrence against summary statistics of the evolution of those traits. The approach goes beyond simply describing the phylogenetic or ecological structure of an assemblage, and instead draws links between how traits have evolved and how they play-out in their present-day ecological context. The pglmm family of functions permit regression modelling of community (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ives and Helmus, 2011</ref>) and interaction network data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Rafferty and Ives, 2013</ref>) using the Phylogenetic Generalised Linear Mixed Model (PGLMM) framework. PGLMMs permit tests of the mechanisms that underlie ecological and evolutionary structure in multiple communities. By fitting random effect terms that account for phylogenetic and trait co-variance, the user can statistically estimate how likely similar and dissimilar species are to (co-)occur as a function of their traits, environmental conditions, and the presence of interacting species.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Simulations</head><p>Hypothesis testing and the development of new eco-phylogenetic methods require simulation of data under known conditions, and pez contains functions to facilitate this. The scape family of functions (following Helmus and Ives, 2012) simulate species' distributions across environmental gradients. Species' environmental tolerances, range size and negative species interactions can be simulated to contain phylogenetic signal and generate patterns of phylogenetic structure at different spatial scales. The sim.meta.phy.comm family of functions simulate phylogeny, trait evolution and assemblage structure simultaneously across a landscape. Species' abundances across the landscape are proportional to the fit of each species' trait value to the conditions in each assemblage, and individuals migrate at random across the landscape. The sim.meta.phy.comm functions do not require the user to specify a phylogeny, and combined with the phy.sim family, provide a toolkit for the development of new simulation scenarios.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>pez provides a unified class to contain eco-phylogenetic data, and provides wrapper functions to manipulate the species and site V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 2888 Bioinformatics, 31(17), 2015, 2888–2890 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv277</figDesc><table>Advance Access Publication Date: 5 May 2015 
Applications Note composition of community, trait, environmental and phylogenetic 
data. Using the phy.build family of functions, users can generate 
phylogenies for their dataset (making use of methods previously im-
plemented in phyloGenerator; Pearse and Purvis</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conservatism and diversification of plant functional traits: evolutionary rates versus phylogenetic signal Proc</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Ackerly</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19699" to="19706" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ecology of differences: assessing community assembly with trait and evolutionary distances</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Bortolussi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1234" to="1244" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic diversity metrics for ecological communities: integrating species richness, abundance and evolutionary history</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Cadotte</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic overdispersion in Floridian oak communities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Cavender-Bares</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Nat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">163</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="823" to="843" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ade4 package: implementing the duality diagram for ecologists</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Dray</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Dufour</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stat. Softw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">mvtnorm: Multivariate Normal and t Distributions. R package version 1</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Genz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="0" to="2" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic diversity-area curves</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Helmus</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Ives</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized linear mixed models for phylogenetic analyses of community structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Ives</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Helmus</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol. Monogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="525" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Picante: R tools for integrating phylogenies and ecology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Kembel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1463" to="1464" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">quantreg: Quantile Regression. R package version 5</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Koenker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">FD: measuring functional diversity from multiple traits, and other tools for functional ecology. R package version 1</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Labierté</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="0" to="12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trees, branches and (square) roots: why evolutionary relatedness is not linearly related to functional distance</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Letten</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Cornwell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods in Ecology &amp; Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="444" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Opposing effects of competitive exclusion on the phylogenetic structure of communities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Mayfield</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Levine</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1085" to="1093" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">vegan: Community Ecology Package. R package version 2</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Oksanen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="3" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">caper: comparative analyses of phylogenetics and evolution in R</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Orme</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>R. package version 0.5.2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">APE: analyses of phylogenetics and evolution in R language</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Paradis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">phyloGenerator: an automated phylogeny generation tool for ecologists</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Pearse</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Purvis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="692" to="698" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Metrics and models of community phylogenetics. Modern Phylogenetic Comparative Methods and their Application in Evolutionary Biology—Concepts and Practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Pearse</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R Core</forename>
				<surname>Team</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<pubPlace>Vienna, Austria</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic trait-based analyses of ecological networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Rafferty</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Ives</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2321" to="2333" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenies and community ecology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Webb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Ecol. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="475" to="505" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>