
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:55+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetics Phylowood: interactive web-based animations of biogeographic and phylogeographic histories</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Landis</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Integrative Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">UC Berkeley</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Trevor</forename>
								<surname>Bedford</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Evolution</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>EH9 3JT</postCode>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Vaccine and Infectious Disease Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>98109</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>WA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetics Phylowood: interactive web-based animations of biogeographic and phylogeographic histories</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="124"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt635</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 2, 2013; revised on October 28, 2013; accepted on October 29, 2013</note>
					<note>Advance Access publication November 4, 2013 Associate Editor: David Posada</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Phylowood is a web service that uses JavaScript to generate in-browser animations of biogeographic and phylogeographic histories from annotated phylogenetic input. The animations are interactive , allowing the user to adjust spatial and temporal resolution, and highlight phylogenetic lineages of interest. Availability and implementation: All documentation and source code for Phylowood is freely available at https://github.com/mlandis/phylo wood, and a live web application is available at https://mlandis.github. io/phylowood.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The fields of phylogeography and biogeography study the processes that give rise to the observed geographical distributions of life. Methods to infer migration processes and reconstruct ancestral geographical distributions in a phylogenetic context have recently enjoyed increased popularity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Landis et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Lemey et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Ree and Smith, 2008</ref>). The resulting ancestral reconstructions are inherently high dimensional; they describe distributions across space, time and phylogenetic lineage and consequently can be difficult to interpret. Here, we introduce Phylowood, a web utility that generates interactive animations to facilitate the exploration and summarization of such complex reconstructions. Phylowood takes phylogeographic output from BEAST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Drummond et al., 2012</ref>) or biogeographic output from BayArea (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Landis et al., 2013</ref>) in the form of NEWICK trees with internal nodes annotated with inferred ancestral locations. Phylowood plots the reconstructed geographic distributions and explores temporal dynamics through animation. Although similar in basic approach to the program SPREAD (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bielejec et al., 2011</ref>), Phylowood is designed for ease-of-use and frictionless sharing. It is entirely implemented within the web browser, requiring no further software installation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">USE AND IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>Phylowood has two primary display panels: the phylogeny panel and the geography panel (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). The phylogeny panel (left) contains a time-calibrated phylogeny, where lineages are assigned unique colors that reflect phylogenetic proximity. The geography panel (right) contains colored area markers corresponding to phylogenetic lineages that specify discrete or continuous geographic distributions. Below the tree, standard media buttons control the animation speed, direction and location. The animation time slider shows the current time point and indicates the lineages that exist at this time, which comprise targets for animation. Filtering out uninteresting data is a key to exploration and summarization. Phylowood allows users to mask, unmask and highlight sets of branches using simple doubleclick, click and mouseover events through either the phylogeny or geography displays. For example, mask and unmask commands may be used to remove all but 10 lineages from a dataset containing 1000 taxa. Mouseover events provide information about highlighted lineage and help users match phylogenetic lineages to their geographic counterparts. The geography panel contains a dynamic map, capable of zooming and panning, and area markers representing geographic distributions at the current time point for unmasked phylogenetic lineages. To reflect the underlying model assumptions that produced the ancestral area reconstructions, we allow several styles: continuous phylogeography, discrete phylogeography and discrete biogeography. For continuous phylogeographic animations, the reconstructed state for each node in the phylogeny is a unique latitude and longitude. For discrete phylogeography and discrete biogeography, each node's reconstructed state corresponds to geographical coordinates representative of a number of the specified discrete areas. For a given phylogenetic branch, the radius of a corresponding geographic marker is proportional to the value assigned to that geographic state. Depending on reconstruction methodology, such values may represent a posterior probability, confidence metric or parsimony score. Intermediate values along phylogenetic branches are interpolated between reconstructed internal phylogenetic nodes. In the discrete phylogeographic or biogeographic scenarios, interpolation represents the e.g. posterior probability of assignment along a branch of the phylogeny. In the continuous phylogeographic scenario, interpolation represents the reconstructed continuous location along a branch of the phylogeny. Similar to the branches in the phylogenetic panel, area markers respond to the highlight mouseover command. *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><p>We provide several demonstration datasets, encompassing continuous phylogeographic, discrete phylogeographic and discrete biogeographic scenarios. Users can easily animate their own datasets through the web service. Additionally, the hosting of code and data on GitHub allows users to easily fork the repository and provide one-click links to their own custom visualizations. This is intended to make sharing of specific visualizations easy. Phylowood was developed in JavaScript and thus compatible with any HTML5-compliant web browsers with no installation required. Scalable Vector Graphics objects are managed and animated using D3.js (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bostock et al., 2011</ref>). Map tiles are fetched from Cloudmade using Polymaps. Source code is published under the Massachusetts Institute of Technology Software License and made freely available at http://github.com/mlandis/phylowood. Animations are generated from a NEXUS format file, specifying the animation settings, geographical coordinates and a New Hampshire extended format (NEWICK) tree annotated with ancestral area values. We provide Ruby scripts to convert BEAST output to Phylowood format, with more to be developed on demand. BayArea natively produces Phylowood format files.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">EXAMPLE: VIREYA</head><p>Rhododendron section Vireya is a group of flowering plants distributed throughout Malesia (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). From the posterior probabilities of ancestral range reconstructions,<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Landis et al. (2013)</ref>infer the ancestor common to Malesian Vireya originated on continental Asia, concurring with results reported in Webb and Ree (2012). Approximately 35–45 Mya, a single Vireya lineage first colonized islands east of both Wallace's and Lydekker's lines, known barriers to dispersal events. Interestingly, descendants of the lineage remain strictly to the east of Lydekker's line, whereas all remaining taxa remain to its west. This scenario is made evident using Phylowood by filtering and animating these otherwise high-dimensional data: (i) masking clades whose colors appear west of Lydekker's line, just west of New Guinea, (ii) panning the map over Malesia, (iii) filtering out areas with low probability and (iv) beginning the animation at 45 Mya.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>Phylogeographic and biogeographic methods combine genetic and geographic data across individuals or across species to infer complex spatiotemporal processes. Joint phylogenetic and geographic reconstructions produced by these methods benefit from sophisticated visualization techniques that highlight connections between geography and genotype. As phylogeographic and biogeographic datasets continue to increase in size and complexity, harnessing appropriate visualization techniques will become increasingly important. We present Phylowood as a method to explore and share geographically tagged phylogenies. To learn more about Phylowood's features, visit http://github. com/mlandis/phylowood/wiki for help and tutorials.of the phylogenetic tree has been masked using mouse-issued commands, leaving two clades and their shared ancestry unmasked. The media slider indicates the current position of the animation with respect to the time-calibrated phylogeny for which time six unmasked lineages are animated. For the current animation time, each extant lineage is allocated an equal width slice of the pie. For each color, the depth of the slice indicates the approximate marginal posterior probability of the lineage occupying the area at that time. Pie slices are sorted phylogenetically, making the relative position of absent slices informative. Consulting the geography panel, we find the taxa from the top clade appear to be allopatric with respect to taxa from the bottom clade at 15.5 Mya. The interactive animation is available at http://mlandis. github.io/phylowood/?url¼examples/vireya.nhx</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Sample still frame from Phylowood. The results shown are from the discrete biogeographic analysis of Rhododendron section Vireya throughout Malesia using BayArea. Much of the phylogenetic tree has been masked using mouse-issued commands, leaving two clades and their shared ancestry unmasked. The media slider indicates the current position of the animation with respect to the time-calibrated phylogeny for which time six unmasked lineages are animated. For the current animation time, each extant lineage is allocated an equal width slice of the pie. For each color, the depth of the slice indicates the approximate marginal posterior probability of the lineage occupying the area at that time. Pie slices are sorted phylogenetically, making the relative position of absent slices informative. Consulting the geography panel, we find the taxa from the top clade appear to be allopatric with respect to taxa from the bottom clade at 15.5 Mya. The interactive animation is available at http://mlandis. github.io/phylowood/?url¼examples/vireya.nhx</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.J.Landis and T.Bedford at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spread: spatial phylogenetic reconstruction of evolutionary dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Bielejec</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2910" to="2912" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">D 3 data-driven documents</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Bostock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. Comput. Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2301" to="2309" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian phylogenetics with BEAUti and the BEAST 1.7</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Drummond</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1969" to="1973" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian analysis of biogeography when the number of areas is large</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Landis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="789" to="804" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian phylogeography finds its roots</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Lemey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000520</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximum likelihood inference of geographic range evolution by dispersal, local extinction, and cladogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Ree</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Historical biogeography inference in Malesia Biotic Evolution and Environmental Change in Southeast Asia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Webb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Ree</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Gower,D. et al.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="215" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>