
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:46+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Phylogenomic clustering for selecting non-redundant genomes for comparative genomics</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">7 2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gabriel</forename>
								<surname>Moreno-Hagelsieb</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zilin</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wilfrid Laurier University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>N2L 3C5</postCode>
									<settlement>Waterloo</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Stephanie</forename>
								<surname>Walsh</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wilfrid Laurier University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>N2L 3C5</postCode>
									<settlement>Waterloo</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Aisha</forename>
								<surname>Elsherbiny</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Phylogenomic clustering for selecting non-redundant genomes for comparative genomics</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="947" to="949"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">7 2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt064</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 1, 2012; revised on January 31, 2013; accepted on February 5, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: David Posada</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Analyses in comparative genomics often require non-redundant genome datasets. Eliminating redundancy is not as simple as keeping one strain for each named species because gen-omes might be redundant at a higher taxonomic level than that of species for some analyses; some strains with different species names can be as similar as most strains sharing a species name, whereas some strains sharing a species name can be so different that they should be put into different groups; and some genomes lack a species name. Results: We have implemented a method and Web server that clusters a genome dataset into groups of redundant genomes at different thresholds based on a few phylogenomic distance measures. Availability: The Web interface, similarity and distance data and R-scripts can be accessed at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Genomic databases contain several sequenced strains for species of high interest, whereas other species contain only one genome and no evolutionarily close relatives (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al., 2009</ref>). These biases might result in different qualities when predicting such features as functional interactions by comparative genomics. The problem has often been solved by using a measure of phylogenetic distance either directly as a score (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Overbeek et al., 1999</ref>) or for normalizing scores (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Zheng et al., 2005</ref>). The problem has also been solved by choosing single representatives for particular clades (e.g. Moreno<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hagelsieb and Janga, 2008</ref>). However, selecting representatives by species name can be problematic because strains of different species, for example Escherichia coli and Shigella flexneri, can be so evolutionarily close that they should share their names, whereas strains of single species such as Prochlorococcus marinus might be very distant to each other (Moreno<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hagelsieb and Janga, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">van Passel et al., 2006</ref>). Besides, some sequenced genomes do not have a species name, and the level of acceptable similarity among genomes for some applications might be lower than the most common for species (Moreno<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hagelsieb and Janga, 2008</ref>). The Genomic Similarity Score (GSS) and other phylogenomic measures have been shown to concur with more computationally demanding phylogenetic distances (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alcaraz et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kunin et al., 2005</ref>). We have used GSS to produce datasets of non-redundant genomes, maximizing the number of predicted interactions by phylogenetic profiles (Moreno-Hagelsieb and<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Janga, 2008</ref>), and other practical uses, such as displaying the relationship between conservation of gene order and genomic similarity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Janga and Moreno-Hagelsieb, 2004</ref>). The datasets were built by ordering the genomes available by importance (e.g. Escherichia coli K12 would take priority because of its annotation quality), and then from largest to smallest. We would then take the first genome in the list, and put any genome with a GSS above a chosen threshold into the list of redundant genomes. In the present work, we tested instead two clustering methods to group genomes, besides a couple variants of the GSS and DNA signatures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Campbell et al., 1999</ref>). As other research groups have asked us for lists of non-redundant genomes, here we make them available to the wider community.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">DATA AND METHODS</head><p>We used 2160 prokaryotic genomes available at the RefSeq database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Pruitt et al., 2007</ref>) (ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/genomes/ Bacteria/) by November 2012. Orthologs were reciprocal best hits (RBH), as described previously (Moreno<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hagelsieb and Latimer, 2008</ref>). We plan to update the data every 6 months. We calculated the GSSs for each genome pair as follows (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Janga and Moreno-Hagelsieb, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Moreno-Hagelsieb and Janga, 2008</ref>):</p><formula>GSS a ¼ X n i¼1 compScore i selfScore i ð1Þ</formula><p>where compScore is the score of the alignment of protein i in genome A against its RBH in genome B, and selfScore is the score of the alignment of protein i against itself. Because the selfScore for proteins in genome A might differ from the selfScore for proteins in genome B, the final GSS a is the average of the calculation from the perspective of both genomes. We also calculated two modified versions of the GSS:</p><formula>GSS b ¼ X n i¼1 compScore i =compAlignLength i selfScore i =selfAlignLength i ð2Þ</formula><p>Here the scores were normalized against the length of the alignments. Because selfScores normally come from longer alignments than compScores, GSS b is larger than GSS a. The final GSS b is the average of this calculation from the perspective of both genomes under analysis. *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p><formula>GSS c ¼ P n i¼1 compScore i P m j¼1 selfScore j ð3Þ</formula><p>Instead of the selfScores of proteins finding RBH, we calculated the total sum of selfScores of all proteins in the genome of reference. This has the effect of producing a smaller GSS. Again, the final GSS c was the average from the perspective of both genomes under analysis. We also clustered our genomes by di-, tri-and tetra-nucleotide DNA signatures with Manhattan distances (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Campbell et al., 1999</ref>). To build groups of redundant genomes, we used a hierarchical clustering method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Hastie et al., 2009</ref>). We used 1 À GSS to construct a dissimilarity matrix to run the clustering algorithms. All computations were carried out using R (R Development Core<ref type="bibr">Team, 2012</ref>). The commands agnes and diana in the cluster package were used to run the two main strategies in hierarchical clustering: agglomerative or bottoms-up and divisive or top-down, respectively. To assess the clustering structures, we used the agglomerative/ divisive coefficients defined as 1 minus the average ratio of dissimilarity of one unit to the cluster it first merges with, to the dissimilarity of its merging in the final step of the algorithm. A coefficient close to 0 means that the algorithm did not find a natural cluster structure (the data consist of a single cluster), whereas a coefficient close to 1 means that clear clusters have been identified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>GSS a and GSS b concentrate strains sharing species names (1103 strains in 224 species) into the 0.9–1.0 range of the GSS distribution, whereas GSS c spreads several of them between the 0.7 and 0.9 range (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). Thus, GSS c might be the least adequate for clustering redundant genomes. Because DNA signatures are faster to calculate than GSSs, we are starting to experiment with DNA signatures for our work in comparative genomics. Thus, we have also clustered our genome dataset based on di-, tri-and tetra-nucleotide signature distances. DNA signature distances among same-species strains concentrate at 50.03. The divisive coefficients were higher, and thus better, than the agglomerative coefficients using all three GSSs and DNA signature distances (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). The coefficients using GSS c were the lowest among all three GSSs for both algorithms, thus confirming that GSS c is the least adequate for clustering genomes. However, DNA signature distances produced the best overall clusters, with divisive coefficients 40.95. The appropriate threshold for defining groups of redundant genomes depends on the application (e.g. Moreno<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hagelsieb and Janga, 2008</ref>). Thus, we recommend experimenting with different thresholds. The Web site provides 10 thresholds per measure that should suffice for such experimentation. Should other users prefer to experiment at thresholds other than those provided through the Web site, we also provide the R scripts used to derive these groups, and the pertinent distance/similarity data. With some effort, inexperienced users would be able to modify these scripts to obtain groups at other thresholds. Finally, we also provide cluster files that can be read by software for drawing and manipulating phylogenetic trees (Newick format).<ref type="figure">1.0   1.1</ref>1.2 1.3 d i-n u c l t r i-n u c l t e t r a-n u c l</p><formula>G S S a G S S b G S S c Coefficient</formula><p>Agglomerative Divisive<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. Same-species clustering. Most of the same-species strains have GSSs 40.90 and DNA signature distances 50.25. GSS b concentrates most of the same-species strains above the 0.9 score, and GSS c spreads them the most. DNA signatures produce the best clusters, as shown by agglomerative/divisive coefficients, with divisive clustering producing slightly better clusters</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">G.Moreno-Hagelsieb et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Non-redundant genomes for comparative genomics at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding the evolutionary relationships and major traits of bacillus through comparative genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Alcaraz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">332</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome signature comparisons among prokaryote, plasmid, and mitochondrial DNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Campbell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9184" to="9189" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Elements of Statistical Learning: Data Mining, Inference, and Prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Hastie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">series in statistics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd. edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conservation of adjacency as evidence of paralogous operons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Janga</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Moreno-Hagelsieb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5392" to="5397" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring genome conservation across taxa: divided strains and united kingdoms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Kunin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="616" to="621" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Operons and the effect of genome redundancy in deciphering functional relationships using phylogenetic profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Moreno-Hagelsieb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Janga</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="344" to="352" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Choosing BLAST options for better detection of orthologs as reciprocal best hits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Moreno-Hagelsieb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Latimer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="324" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The use of gene clusters to infer functional coupling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Overbeek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2896" to="2901" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NCBI reference sequences (RefSeq): a curated non-redundant sequence database of genomes, transcripts and proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Pruitt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Development</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Core</forename>
				<surname>Teamr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Vienna, Austria</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The reach of the genome signature in prokaryotes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Van Passel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">84</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A phylogeny-driven genomic encyclopaedia of Bacteria and Archaea</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">462</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1056" to="1060" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic detection of conserved gene clusters in microbial genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Zheng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">243</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>