
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis PING 2.0: an R/Bioconductor package for nucleosome positioning using next-generation sequencing data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sangsoon</forename>
								<surname>Woo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Vaccine and Infectious Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Public Health Sciences Divisions</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>98109-1024</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>WA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xuekui</forename>
								<surname>Zhang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21205</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Renan</forename>
								<surname>Sauteraud</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Vaccine and Infectious Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Public Health Sciences Divisions</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>98109-1024</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>WA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Franç</forename>
								<surname>Ois Robert</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Chromatin and Genomic Expression</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Institut de Recherches Cliniques de Montreal</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>H2W 1R7</postCode>
									<settlement>Montreal</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Raphael</forename>
								<surname>Gottardo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Vaccine and Infectious Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Public Health Sciences Divisions</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>98109-1024</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>WA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis PING 2.0: an R/Bioconductor package for nucleosome positioning using next-generation sequencing data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2049" to="2050"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt348</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on November 15, 2012; revised on May 20, 2013; accepted on June 13, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Michael Brudno Contact: rgottard@fhcrc.org Supplementary Information: Supplementary material is available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>MNase-Seq and ChIP-Seq have evolved as popular techniques to study chromatin and histone modification. Although many tools have been developed to identify enriched regions, software tools for nucleosome positioning are still limited. We introduce a flexible and powerful open-source R package, PING 2.0, for nucleosome positioning using MNase-Seq data or MNase– or sonicated– ChIP-Seq data combined with either single-end or paired-end sequencing. PING uses a model-based approach, which enables nucleosome predictions even in the presence of low read counts. We illustrate PING using two paired-end datasets from Saccharomyces cerevisiae and compare its performance with nucleR and ChIPseqR. Availability: PING 2.0 is available from the Bioconductor website at http://bioconductor.org. It can run on Linux, Mac and Windows.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The nucleosome is the basic structural unit of chromatin, which is composed of a nucleosomal core including 147 bp of DNA wrapped around a central histone octamer (H2A, H2B, H3 and H4) and 'linker' DNA connecting nucleosomal core to the next. Nucleosomes control cellular processes by affecting the accessibility of proteins to the DNA, which can act on gene expression and other DNA-dependent processes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Radman-Livaja et al., 2010</ref>). Projects like ENCODE (ENCODE Project<ref type="bibr">Consortium, 2011</ref>) have generated large amounts of ChIP-Seq and MNase-Seq data that can be used to improve our understanding of nucleosome positioning and its impact on gene regulation. However, these data require efficient tools that can be used regardless of the experimental protocols employed. Several statistical approaches were recently developed for analyzing nucleosome-based data.<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Weiner et al. (2010)</ref>introduced the Template Filter method that models forward and reverse reads based on predefined peak shapes.<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Zhang et al. (2008)</ref>developed the Nucleosome Positioning from Sequencing (NPS) method that uses read pile-ups followed by wavelet de-noising for identifying positioned nucleosomes. More recent pile-up–based approaches include the ChIPseqR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Humburg et al., 2011</ref>) and nucleR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Flores et al., 2011</ref>) R packages, available from Bioconductor. In a Bayesian context,<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Polishko et al. (2012)</ref>have developed NOrMAL, which uses mixture models to infer nucleosome positions. All the tools described above were originally developed for single-end (SE) sequencing data, where data provide only one side of DNA fragments, and as such the length of the DNA fragments must be provided as input or estimated from the data. To resolve this ambiguity and give more information, paired-end (PE) protocols have been developed and are gradually being highlighted in experiments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kent et al., 2010</ref>). Because PE data provide important information about DNA fragment length, they can potentially lead to more precise estimates of nucleosome positions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Fullwood et al., 2009</ref>), though formal comparisons of nucleome positioning obtained from SE and PE data are still lacking. Here we present a new software tool for nucleosome positioning, PING 2.0, which extends our probabilistic framework for SE ChIPSeq and MNase-Seq data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Zhang et al., 2011</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Zhang et al., , 2012</ref>). PING 2.0 is a major update of an early (unpublished) version of the software and includes a novel statistical framework for PE data, new functions for pre-processing and reading raw data, and better integration with other Bioconductor packages. The result is a complete framework for nucleosome positioning within Bioconductor that can handle sonicated and MNase protocols combined with either SE or PE sequencing. We compare PING 2.0 with two other Bioconductor packages, nucleR and ChIPseqR using two novel PE Saccharomyces cerevisiae datasets (available from GEO: GSE47073) generated specifically for this work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>Hereafter, we use boldface to refer to software packages and teletype font to refer to object, classes and functions. For simplicity, we also use the term ChIP-seq to refer to both ChIP-Seq and MNase-Seq. Architecture: In PING, we provide a user-friendly R interface to our underlying C code, which is written for optimal utilization of system resources. PING facilitates parallel processing for large datasets via the parallel package. Also, PING uses the S4 system to define object-oriented classes and methods. Data input: PING's basic data input is a GRanges object containing the directional aligned reads (SE data) or reconstructed DNA fragments (PE data). The GRanges class serves as the foundation for representing *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>y</head><p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. genomic locations within the Bioconductor project. GRanges can be derived from classical formats such as BED and BAM using Bioconductor's infrastructure. For convenience, PING includes a bam2gr function that can be used to convert BAM objects to a GRanges object. bam2gr can be applied to both SE and PE data, and in the case of PE data, discards mismatched pairs. We hope to support mismatched reads in a future version of PING, as these could provide additional information. Genome segmentation: Because ChIP-seq data are sparse, consisting of large regions with few or no reads, we first preprocess the data by segmenting the genome into regions, each of which has a minimum number of reads that aligned to the genome of interest. This is done with the segmentPING function that scans the genome with a sliding-window approach to identify a set of candidate regions; seg5-segmentPING(gr, PE¼TRUE), where gr is the GRanges object including aligned reads. For PE data, the PE argument should be set to TRUE, and its value is stored in the result. Statistical inference: After genome segmentation, the PING model is fit to all regions: ping5-PING(seg). For SE data, the forward and reverse read positions are modeled separately using t-distributions. However, for PE data, the paired reads are jointly modeled using a bivariate t-distribution; see Supplementary Material. The PING function returns nucleosome positions (i.e. their centers), as well as nucleosome enrichment scores (reflecting the number of reads within the nucleosomes) and fuzziness (defined as the standard errors of the estimated centers) (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). Post-processing: Because PING is based on a parametric model, departures from the model assumptions, e.g. background noise or repetitive regions, could lead to noisy nucleosome estimates. The postPING function was devised to detect and correct such problematic estimates. The function takes both a PING result and a segmentation result objects: psPING5postPING(ping, seg), and returns a data frame containing all estimated parameters for each nucleosome. The makeRangedDataOutput function can then convert these results into a GRanges object for exporting to the BED or WIG formats. Post-processing only modifies a small fraction of estimated nucleosomes (55% for the data used here), most of which have small score. More information about the correction procedure can be found in the Supplementary Material. Graphical representation: PING 2.0 provides the plotSummary function, for rapid visualization of identified nucleosomes. The function is basically an interface to the plotTracks function of the Gviz package and takes as input a PING result and the GRanges used in segmentPING to show pile-up profiles along with the predicted nucleosome positions and calculated scores. The user can also include a list of several PING results corresponding, for example, to different biological conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>We applied PING 2.0 to two PE S.cerevisiae datasets generated for this article (Total and H2A.Z MNase) and compared its performance with nucleR and ChIPseqR. As can be seen in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>, the PE version of PING leads to the detection of more nucleosomes that are supported by additional variation in the pile-up profile. However, the SE version also leads to accurate nucleosome positioning. This is confirmed in our comparison study where we show that PING 2.0 SE-based predictions match their PE-based ones well and better than nucleR and ChIPseqR. In particular, nucleR's PE predictions appear to be biased toward high-density regions where the algorithms tend to predict many overlapping nucleosomes (Supplementary Figs S3 and S4). In our comparison, we also looked at the stability of the predictions when the datasets are subsampled. Globally, nucleR and PING lead to stable predictions for both SE and PE, while ChIPseqR's predictions are more noisy and poorly match the results from the full data. See Supplementary Material for more details.<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. Nucleosome positions identified by PING in a subset of ChrI from our Total MNase data using both SE and PE data. The SE data were generated by simply discarding one PE read at random, and the corresponding pile-up profile was obtained by extended reads to an average length of the PE DNA fragments. The number of nucleosomes estimated from PE is greater, as it provides more detailed information as shown by the PE pile-up profile</p></div>
			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">S.Woo et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head><p>The authors thank Gordon Robertson for helpful discussion.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A user&apos;s guide to the encyclopedia of DNA elements (ENCODE)</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ENCODE Project Consortium. PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1001046</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">nucleR: a package for non-parametric nucleosome positioning</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Flores</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2149" to="2150" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Next-generation DNA sequencing of paired-end tags (PET) for transcriptome and genome analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Fullwood</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="532" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ChIPseqR: analysis of ChIP-seq experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Humburg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">39</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chromatin particle spectrum analysis: a method for comparative chromatin structure analysis using paired-end mode next-generation DNA sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Kent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">26</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NORMAL: accurate nucleosome positioning using a modified Gaussian mixture model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Polishko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="242" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nucleosome positioning: how is it established, and why does it matter</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Radman-Livaja</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">339</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="258" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-resolution nucleosome mapping reveals transcriptiondependent promotor packaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Weiner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="100" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying positioned nucleosomes with epigenetic marks in human from ChIP-Seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">537</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PICS: probabilistic inference for ChIP-seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic inference for nucleosome positioning with MNasebased or sonicated short-read data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">32095</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>