
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:30+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Pipit: visualizing functional impacts of structural variations</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ryo</forename>
								<surname>Sakai</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering-ESAT</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">KU Leuven</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">SCD-SISTA</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3001</postCode>
									<settlement>Leuven</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Future Health Department</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>iMinds</addrLine>
									<postCode>3001</postCode>
									<region>Leuven</region>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matthieu</forename>
								<surname>Moisse</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Vesalius Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">VIB and KU Leuven</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3000</postCode>
									<settlement>Leuven, Belgium</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Oncology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Infectious Diseases–Diagnostics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Translational Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">KU Leuven</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Janssen Pharmaceuticals</addrLine>
									<postCode>3000, 2340</postCode>
									<settlement>Leuven, Beerse</settlement>
									<country>Belgium, Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joke</forename>
								<surname>Reumers</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jan</forename>
								<surname>Aerts</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering-ESAT</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">KU Leuven</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">SCD-SISTA</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3001</postCode>
									<settlement>Leuven</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Future Health Department</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>iMinds</addrLine>
									<postCode>3001</postCode>
									<region>Leuven</region>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Janssen</forename>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<surname>Hancock</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Pipit: visualizing functional impacts of structural variations</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2206" to="2207"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt367</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 1, 2013; revised on May 31, 2013; accepted on June 18, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Pipit is a cross-platform Java applica-tion that visualizes structural variation data from Genome Variation Format files. Availability: Executables, source code, sample data, documentation and screencast are available at https://bitbucket.org/biovizleuven/ pipit. Contact: ryo.sakai@esat.kuleuven.be Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Pipit is a gene-centric interactive visualization tool designed to study structural genomic variations. Through focusing on individual genes as the functional unit, researchers are able to study and generate hypotheses on the biological impact of different structural variations, for instance, the deletion of dosage-sensitive genes or the formation of fusion genes.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Structural variation is defined as a change of genomic DNA greater than 1 kb in size and can be either balanced or unbalanced (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Stankiewicz and Lupski, 2010</ref>). A structural variation may be benign, it may influence phenotypes, it may predispose to or cause diseases, and it may be transmitted to next generations. In addition, it may also result in the formation of new transcripts through gene fusion or exon skipping when breakpoints disrupt gene structures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Feuk et al., 2006</ref>). Understanding the structural change in the genome, as well as its functional impact, is critical for studying phenotypic variations and genetic diseases in human and model organisms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Korbel et al., 2007</ref>). When structural variations are studied, the structure of these variants are usually visualized by encoding breakpoints on a linear or circular layout (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Herbig et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Krzywinski et al., 2009</ref>). Other visual encodings such as dot plot and graph representations show the changes in the reference genome introduced by the structural rearrangement (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Nielsen and Wong, 2012</ref>). These visual encodings pose two challenges in analysis of structural variation data. First, they focus on size and position, rather than the consequence of structural rearrangement. Second, they introduce an implicit correlation between size and effect, whereas small structural variations may have more severe effects than some large variations. Therefore, an effective visual encoding of structural and copy-number variations based on functional units is essential to gain insights into impact on human health and disease. We introduce an exploratory visualization tool, named Pipit, which uses a novel gene-centric visual encoding to examine how gene structures individually are affected by structural variants. Pipit takes a Genome Variation Format file as input and encodes an affected gene structure as a disk, showing how it is modified and oriented towards other genes. By means of this data abstraction, the focus of the structural variants is shifted from the genomic distance to the biologically relevant feature, i.e. the underlying genes. This encoding enables swift visual inspection of genes that are affected by structural variants, which may be examined further if deemed interesting. Not constrained or biased by variation sizes, Pipit permits in-depth analysis and exploration of structural variation data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">FEATURES</head><p>Pipit is an interactive visualization tool developed in Processing, an open source programming language and integrated development environment based on Java. The executables are available for Linux, Mac OS X and Windows. The input file is in Genome Variation Format because it is a well-standardized format for genomic structural variation data, extended from the Generic Feature Format (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Reese et al., 2010</ref>), and both the European Bioinformatics Institute and the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) curate, archive and make data publicly available in this format via DGVa (http://www. ebi.ac.uk/dgva) and dbVar (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/ dbvar), respectively (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Lappalainen et al., 2013</ref>). Pipit also uses the gene track, cytoband and gene ontology (GO) information obtained from the UCSC table browser database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Karolchik et al., 2004</ref>). The current version supports the data from human (NCBI build 36 and 37) and mouse (NCBI build 37/mm9 and GRCm build 38/mm10), but the user can load the data for other model organisms. In addition, the user can load a comma-separated values file containing the Ensembl gene ID and ordinal or categorical information, such as haploinsufficiency scores (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Huang et al., 2010</ref>) and known oncogenes (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>and Supplementary Material). Each affected gene is represented as a disk and filled according to which part of its structure is influenced by a structural variation (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>types are based on the data file and colour coded as shown on the right panel. Unaffected genes are compressed into a line connecting affected genes. The default promoter length upstream of the gene sequence can be set when loading the data. There are four layouts to explore the structural variation data. The default view is the collapsed ordered gene view (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). In this view, a coloured disk may represent an affected gene or consecutively ordered genes that are affected by the same type of structural variation. In the expanded view, all affected genes are individually visualized. The chromosome position view shows affected variants mapped to their genomic positions. Lastly, the unit plot view visualizes affected genes by their type of structural variant event, such as deletion, tandem-duplication and so forth (see Supplementary Material). When a disk unit is selected (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1A</ref>), the underlying genes and structural variation events are shown on the bottom panel, along with the chromosome with cytobands and transcripts with their exonic regions coloured in dark grey (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1B</ref>). The gene name shown in this panel links to the Ensembl browser and displays the genomic region. In the right panel (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1C</ref>), the coloured square boxes for each structural variant types serve as radio buttons to hide or show a selected type of variant. The text field below searches for a specific gene amongst affected genes. GO terms associated with affected genes are listed, and conversely selecting a GO term highlights associated genes in the main view. A screenshot can be saved as a PDF by pressing the 'p' on the keyboard.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DISCUSSION</head><p>Pipit introduces a novel visualization paradigm and user interaction method to examine structural variants based on the affected gene region. It facilitates the study of structural variants from a gene-centric perspective to investigate various events, for instance, how known dosage-sensitive genes are affected or whether gene fusions are formed. Future work includes extending the functional unit to encompass important regulatory elements as elaborated in the ENCODE project (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Birney et al., 2007</ref>). Additionally, functions to compare multiple samples from various data formats, such as Variant Call Format (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Danecek et al., 2011</ref>), and options to incorporate other conventional linear or circular representations are essential for more comprehensive study of structural variants. Funding: iMinds<ref type="bibr">[SBO 2012]</ref>, University of Leuven Research Council<ref type="bibr">[</ref></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Pipit visualizing the structural variation data of the mouse genome (estd118). (A) The deletion of the Met gene on chromosome 6 is selected. (B) The associated genomic information of the region is shown on the bottom panel. (C) Categories of the known oncogenes for the mouse are listed, and the Oncogenes category is selected. GO terms associated with affected genes are listed below on the right panel</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>; see Supplementary Material). Structural variant *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification and analysis of functional elements in 1% of the human genome by the ENCODE pilot project</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Birney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">447</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="799" to="816" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The variant call format and VCFtools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Danecek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2156" to="2158" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural variation in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Feuk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GenomeRing: alignment visualization based on SuperGenome coordinates</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Herbig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterising and predicting haploinsufficiency in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1001154</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The UCSC Table Browser data retrieval tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Karolchik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="493" to="496" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Paired-end mapping reveals extensive structural variation in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Korbel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">318</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="420" to="426" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circos: an information aesthetic for comparative genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Krzywinski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1639" to="1645" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DbVar and DGVa: public archives for genomic structural variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Lappalainen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Aacids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="936" to="941" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Points of view: representing genomic structural variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Nielsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Wong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">631</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A standard variation file format for human genome sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Reese</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">88</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural variation in the human genome and its role in disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Stankiewicz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Lupski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>