
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Predicting G protein-coupled receptor downstream signaling by tissue expression</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yun</forename>
								<surname>Hao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departments of Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Systems Biology, and Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10032</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nicholas</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Tatonetti</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departments of Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Systems Biology, and Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10032</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Predicting G protein-coupled receptor downstream signaling by tissue expression</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw510</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 12, 2016; revised on July 12, 2016; accepted on July 28, 2016</note>
					<note>Systems biology *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Contact: nick.tatonetti@columbia.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: G protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) are central to how cells respond to their environment and a major class of pharmacological targets. However, comprehensive knowledge of which pathways are activated and deactivated by these essential sensors is largely unknown. To better understand the mechanism of GPCR signaling system, we integrated five independent genome-wide expression datasets, representing 275 human tissues and cell lines, with protein-protein interactions and functional pathway data. Results: We found that tissue-specificity plays a crucial part in the function of GPCR signaling system. Only a few GPCRs are expressed in each tissue, which are coupled by different combinations of G-proteins or b-arrestins to trigger specific downstream pathways. Based on this finding, we predicted the downstream pathways of GPCR in human tissues and validated our results with L1000 knockdown data. In total, we identified 154,988 connections between 294 GPCRs and 690 pathways in 240 tissues and cell types. Availability and Implementation: The source code and results supporting the conclusions of this article are available at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>G protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) comprise the largest family of transmembrane signaling molecules—more than 800 distinct human proteins. Each member of this family shares in a common seven transmembrane (7TM) a-helical fold. As highly versatile membrane sensors, they regulate many physiological processes including immunization, sensation, behavioral and mood regulation, homeostasis modulation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Katritch et al., 2012</ref>). GPCRs also emerge as crucial players in growth and metastasis of many tumors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Dorsam and Gutkind, 2007</ref>). Mutations in GPCRs have been linked to many human genetic diseases including retinitis pigmentosa (RP), hypo-and hyperthyroidism, nephrogenic diabetes insipidus, bleeding disorder and even carcinomas (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Insel et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schoneberg et al., 2004</ref>). GPCRs are activated by a heterogeneous set of endogenous ligands. These ligands may be light-sensitive compounds, odors, pheromones, hormones and neurotransmitters. Due to their accessibility on cellular membranes, their central role in cell communication, and the wide variety of potential functions, GPCRs are the targets for nearly one third of modern small molecule therapeutics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Hopkins and Groom, 2002</ref>). GPCRs are transducers of extracellular stimuli to signal intracellular changes. In their inactive state, GPCRs are bound to a heterotrimeric G protein complex including three subunits, G a , G b and G c. The binding of an extracellular ligand will initiate a conformation change in GPCR, which then activates the bound G a subunit. The activated G a subunit dissociates from the complex by an exchange from GTP to GDP. The dissociated G a and G bc subunits binds to other intracellular proteins to trigger downstream signaling or metabolic pathways separately (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Digby et al., 2006</ref>). Meanwhile, G-protein-coupled receptor kinases (GRKs) are recruited to the ligand-bound GPCR and phosphorylate the receptor. Once phosphorylated, GPCR binds to b-arrestins, preventing further coupling of GPCR to G proteins. b-arrestins have a dual role, however, and can also interact with intracellular proteins inducing downstream effects (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Metaye et al., 2005</ref>). In the whole process, the signal of ligand is passed from GPCR to two types of transducer molecules: G protein and b-arrestin, contributing to G protein-dependent signaling and G protein-independent signaling, respectively. GPCRs are usually expressed at low levels, with 1% of genes in the genome only accounting for 0.001–0.01% of expressed sequence tags (Fredriksson and Schiö th, 2005). What's more, expression levels of GPCRs vary dramatically by tissue. Regard et al. analyzed transcript levels of 353 GPCRs in 41 adult mouse tissues and found that GPCRs that are highly expressed in a given tissue usually exhibit important function to that tissue. For example, light-detecting opsins are highly and specifically expressed in eye, and dopamine, gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA) receptors are highly expressed in central nervous system (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Regard et al., 2008</ref>). These findings suggest that GPCR signaling system consists of different expressed proteins depending on the tissue type and target different downstream pathways to fulfill tissue-specific functions. Driven largely by their utility in drug development, the study of individual GPCR function and their downstream target pathways has become a research topic of great importance. With this information, many new avenues of research are available. For example, the action of pathways without any direct drug targets can be modulated through targeting the GPCRs that trigger them. In addition, the downstream pathways in the target tissue of a drug can be connected to cellular mechanism or on-target side effects of the drug while the downstream pathways in other tissues can be connected to the off-target side effects. However, the low expression level and difficulty in crystallization have made comprehensive analyses so challenging that most GPCRs still remain the 'terra incognita', or unexplored territory, in functional genomics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Katritch et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Regard et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Tobin et al., 2008</ref>). Importantly, GPCRs do not interact with intracellular proteins directly, but through the coupling of G protein or recruitment of b-arrestin. Studying the direct partners of GPCRs will not reveal their downstream effects. Research has shown that transducer isotypes can have distinct interacting partners and signaling roles. For example, G as subunit can activate cAMP-dependent pathway by stimulating the production of cAMP while G ai inhibits the production (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Birnbaumer, 2007</ref>). b-arrestin2 mediates dopaminergic synaptic transmission while b-arrestin3 actives ERK-1/2 pathway (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Beaulieu et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Oakley et al., 2000</ref>). Exactly which b-arrestins and G proteins associate with each GPCR and if this varies by tissue type remains unknown, further complicating the systematic identification of GPCR-targeted pathways. We introduced a data-driven method GOTE, to systematically predict GPCR Downstream Pathways Signaling by Tissue Expression (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). With many genome-wide expression profiling datasets of different human tissues or cell types available, we were able to identify the expressed proteins of GPCR signaling system in each tissue type, these include the GPCR proteins themselves as well as the transducer proteins (G-proteins and b-arrestins). We hypothesized that if the proteins of a pathway significantly interact with the transducer isotypes in a particular tissue, then the pathway is more likely to be the signaling outcome of the GPCRs that are highly expressed in that tissue.</p><p>Based on this hypothesis, we designed a statistical test to evaluate the association between pathways and GPCRs in each tissue and applied it to five independent datasets (four from normal tissues, one from cancer cell lines). We tested the robustness of GOTE by comparing the similarity of results across the normal human tissue datasets. We found both concordance and discordance in the predicted pathways.</p><p>The predicted pathways of some GPCRs such as CASR, TBXA2R, CXCR4 and GPR56 can be connected to their molecular function or cause of disease by our method. Due to the lack of true standard specifying the true relationship between GPCR and pathways, we used GPCR knockdown datasets to perform a weak validation, in which we observed whether the expression of a pathway is significantly changed after the knockdown of GPCR. We concluded with a discussion of the potential uses of these results, such as the study of complex human disease or molecular mechanism of drugs. All of our data and code are made publicly and freely available.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Materials and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Materials</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.1">Genes in GPCR signaling system</head><p>We downloaded 401 GPCRs and their class information from GtoPdb (http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/DATA/targets_and_ families.csv) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Southan et al., 2015</ref>), 53 G-proteins from gpDB (http:// biophysics.biol.uoa.gr/gpDB/retrieve.jsp) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Theodoropoulou et al., 2008</ref>). All GPCRs were classified into 6 main classes by GtoPdb: A, B, C, D (Adhesion), F (Frizzled) and O (Others). The gene symbol ID we used for 4 b-arrestins are SAG, ARRB1, ARRB2 and ARR3. The binding proteins of G-proteins and b-arrestins were identified through BioGRID Human PPI network release of 3.4 (<ref type="bibr">ChatrAryamontri et al., 2013</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2">Gene expression data</head><p>We chose five gene expression datasets deriving from three different platforms and covering both cancer cell line and normalIn the first step we used tissue expression data to find specifically expressed GPCR in each tissue. Second, for each transducer (G-protein or b-arrestin), we obtained a list of binding proteins using the BioGRID PPI data. Third, the list of binding proteins is filtered by tissue expression, resulting in lists of tissue-specific binding proteins. Fourth, pathway enrichment analysis is performed based on the tissue-specific binding proteins of each transducer using Fisher's Exact Test. For each pathway, a Z-score is calculated for each transducer. Fifth, for each pathway, the Z-scores of all G-proteins are combined together using Stouffer's Method. The weight of each Z-score is in proportion to the tissue expression of each G-protein. The same analysis is repeated for the Z-scores of all b-arrestins. Finally, pathways with significant Z-scores are connected to GPCRs expressed in the same tissue as G-protein dependent pathways (those which are associated with G-proteins) or G-protein independent pathways (those which are associated with b-arrestins) human tissues (i) Human U133A Gene Atlas (referred as U133A in this paper) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Su et al., 2004</ref>): a compendium of all transcript expression data in 84 human tissues running on the Affymetrix U133A microarray platform. This dataset was downloaded from BioGPS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wu et al., 2016</ref>). (ii) Human NCI60 Cell Lines (referred as NCI60 in this paper): a collection of all transcript expression data in 108 cancer cell lines running on the Affymetrix U133A microarray platform. This dataset was also downloaded from BioGPS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wu et al., 2016</ref>). (iii) HPM_RNA and (iv) HPM_PRT were both released from the Human Proteome Map (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Kim et al., 2014</ref>). They used Mass spectrometry to measure the levels of peptide sequences in 30 human tissues and mapped them to Human Refseq protein sequences (HPM_PRT) and corresponding Refseq genes to infer RNA level expression (HPM_RNA). (v) GTEx Analysis V6 RNA-seq data (referred as GTEx in this paper) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Melé et al., 2015</ref>): a collection of transcriptome data in 53 human normal tissues running on the Illumina TrueSeq RNA sequencing platform (we used the 'Gene RPKM' file provided). We mapped all the array or gene IDs in five datasets to Uniprot protein ID (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">UniProt Consortium, 2014</ref>) and the average expression value was calculated if multiple arrays were mapped to a same Uniprot ID. Next, we converted all the expression value x to log 2 (x þ 2) to adjust for 0 and extremely large values, so that all the converted values are no less than 1. We then normalized the expression of each gene by the median of all tissues, and took the log conversion again so that the final value will follow an approximate normal distribution across all the genes. Then, we calculated a Z-score based on the normal distribution to represent the level of differential expression of a gene in a tissue. Z-score was converted to P-value with the 'pnorm' function in R.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.3">Reactome pathways</head><p>We used Reactome pathways as data source for pathways (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Croft et al., 2014</ref>). The Uniprot to pathway mapping file was downloaded from http://www.reactome.org/download/current/UniProt2Reacto me.txt. In this paper, we considered 2223 pathways with size between 5 and 500.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1">Predicting downstream pathways of GPCRs</head><p>There are four parameters in GOTE: P-value threshold of GPCR t 1 and a threshold for GPCR specificity score t 2 , P-value threshold of binding protein t 3 , P-value threshold of enriched pathways t 4. We set t 1 , t 3 and t 4 , as 0.05 and t 2 as 0 in this paper. First, we found the GPCRs that are specifically expressed in each tissue. To quantify the correlation between a GPCR and all the tissues in one dataset, we calculated a GPCR specificity score S gpcr for a tissue defined as following:</p><formula>T gpcr ¼ 0ðp gpcr ! t 1 Þ 1ðp gpcr &lt; t 1 Þ S gpcr ¼ T gpcr P All Tissues T gpcr (</formula><p>where p gpcr is the expression P-value of GPCR in that tissue. And those with S gpcr greater than t 2 were considered as GPCRs specifically expressed in that tissue. Next, we connected downstream pathways to specific GPCRs in that tissue through the binding proteins of transducers (G-protein or b-arrestin). For each transducer, we found its binding protein through BioGRID PPI network and those with expression P-value less than t 3 were selected as highly expressed binding proteins. We then assessed the correlation between binding proteins and each Reactome pathway by one side Fisher's Exact Test (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Fisher, 1922</ref>). Then, we combined the Z-scores from every transducer by Stouffer's Z-score method to obtain a final Z-score for each pathway (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Stouffer, 1949</ref>).</p><formula>Z combine ¼ P w i Z i ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi P w 2 i q</formula><p>Here, the Z-score of every transducer were combined with a weight w i , referring to the expression of tranducer i. Thus, a transducer with high expression in the tissue will have more influence on the downstream pathway. Eventually, we used 'pnorm' function in R to transform Z-score into P-value. The pathways with P-value less than t 4 were considered as our predicted downstream pathways for those specific GPCR mentioned above. The pathways were classified into G-protein dependent pathways (deriving from the binding proteins of G-protein) and G-protein independent pathways (deriving from the binding proteins of b-arrestin).2.2.3 Defining a weak reference standard for GPCR target pathways Since the absolute value of Z-score represents the level of gene expression change after the knockdown, we quantified the expression change of a pathway by using Stouffer's method to combining all the Z-scores (absolute value) of genes in the pathway.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2">Expression</head><formula>Z pathway ¼ P N i¼1 jZ i j ffiffiffiffi ffi N p</formula><p>N represents the number of genes in a pathway. A pathway with Z pathway greater than 4.08 (correspond to P-value &lt; 2.2eÀ05, corrected for multiple hypothesis testing) is considered to experience significant change after the knockdown of a GPCR in a cell line. Such pathways are defined in our weak standard as a 'positive' and the rest, with no significant change, are defined as 'negative'. If GOTE identified a number of pathways as 'positive' for a GPCR g in a cell line c, we obtained the reference standard of 'positive' and 'negative' from the experiment with g knocked down in c. Then we calculated precision (TP/TP þ FP), recall (TP/ TP þ FN) and specificity (TN/TN þ FP). The performance of GOTE was compared to the following two methods: (i) HighExp: we created this method as a comparison to GOTE. GOTE Systematic prediction of GPCR downstream signalingconnects the tissue-specific GPCRs to the pathways that are enriched by the tissue-specific binding proteins of transducers, while HighExp connects the tissue-specific GPCRs to all the tissuespecific pathways without considering the information from transducers. In each tissue, we found all the proteins with expression Pvalue less than t 3 and performed pathway enrichment analysis with Fisher's Exact Test based on these proteins. The pathways with P-value less than t 4 are defined as tissue-specific pathways. The pathways predicted by GOTE are usually a subset of the pathways predicted by HighExp. (ii) Random: we created this method to represent null distribution. In this method, we randomly assigned pathways to each GPCR without considering any other information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">GPCR signaling system has different expressed proteins in distinct tissues</head><p>We found that the GPCR signaling system is highly tissue-specific across all five datasets. Each GPCR is highly expressed in 3–5% of all tissues in five datasets (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figs</ref><ref type="figure">Fig. S5A</ref>) and the remainder exhibit no or very low expression in both RNA (Supplementary Figs S1–S3 and S5) and protein level (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S4</ref>). We found tissue specificity for 57 signaling transducers, 53 G-proteins and 4 barrestins, as well (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S7</ref>–S11). On average, only 1–2 transducers are highly expressed in each tissue (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6A</ref>) and each transducer is highly expressed in 3–5% of all the tissues (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6B</ref>). We then looked at the binding proteins of transducers. About 31 of 53 G-proteins and 4 of 4 beta-arrestins have protein–protein interaction data available from BioGRID. Among 31 G-proteins, 15 belong to a subunit, 5 belong to b subunit and 11 belong to c subunit (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S12</ref>). The binding proteins of different transducer are enriched with different Reactome pathways (Supplementary Tables S1 and S2). For example, GNA12 mediates the cell-cell junction and adherence (P-value &lt; 10 À3 , Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>) while GNAI1 initiates the adenylate cyclase inhibitory pathway (P-value &lt; 10 À4 , Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). For b-arrestins, isotype 3 is significantly associated with protein translation while isotype 4 interacts with NOTCH1 signaling process (P-value &lt; 10 À2 , Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table S2</ref>). We found that binding proteins were also tissue-specific. On average, only 3–5% binding proteins are highly expressed in each tissue and each binding protein is highly expressed in 3–5% of all the tissues (Supplementary Figs S13–S17).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Using tissue-specific expression to predict downstream pathways of GPCRs</head><p>A workflow of GOTE is shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>(for details, refer to Section 2). As a data-driven method, the goal of GOTE is to use expression data to find specific GPCRs and pathways in each tissue and connect them together. The specific pathways were found through enrichment analysis of proteins binding to each transducer (G-proteins and b-arrestins) of GPCR with more highly expressed transducers having more influence on the recruitment of downstream pathways.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Concordance and discordance of findings in five datasets</head><p>We used GOTE to predict downstream pathways of GPCRs in five expression datasets described in the section 2.1.2. General statistics of results were summarized in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. Of all five datasets, GTEx has results for the largest number of GPCRs in both G-protein dependent pathways and G-protein independent pathways (237 and 215). With the exception of U133A dataset, we found more G-protein dependent pathways than G-protein independent pathways. On average, each GPCR were connected to pathways in 1–9 tissues. The standard deviations of all these statistics are large, suggesting the number of pathways and tissues varies by GPCR. We also compared the size of predicted pathways in five datasets (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.  S18</ref>). The median size of predicted pathways is relatively consistent among five datasets (distributed between 60and 80) and with no significant difference from the size distribution of all pathways from Reactome (P-value &gt; 0.05, t-test). Next, we compared the G-protein dependent and independent pathways predicted in each tissue. The results of HPM_PRT dataset is shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>and the other datasets are shown in Supplementary Table S4. In HPM_PRT, we connected 277 G-protein dependent pathways and 167 G-protein independent pathways to 119 GPCRs. For simplicity, we classified all 30 tissues in HPM_ PRT dataset into eight systems (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table S3</ref>). All the systems except Immune have more G-protein dependent pathways than G-protein independent pathways. Reproductive system has the most G-protein dependent pathways while Immune system has the most G-protein independent pathways. The overlap between G-protein dependent and independent pathways in each system is not). This is consistent in all five datasets (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S4</ref>). However, the Gprotein dependent and independent pathways predicted across all systems are significantly overlapped with each other (P-value ¼ 6. 96eÀ06), suggesting the overlap happens between different systems. This is also consistent in all five datasets (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S4</ref>). Many pathways were repeatedly predicted in more than one tissue (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S5</ref>). For G-protein independent pathways, the common pathways are consistently associated translation and cell cycle process across five datasets. For example, 'Eukaryotic Translation Elongation' is one of the top 10 most common pathways in all five datasets. In addition, many G-protein independent pathways in the cancer cell lines dataset-NCI60 are related to apoptosis, consistent with other studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ahn et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Revankar et al., 2004</ref>). By comparison, the common G-protein dependent pathways represent a variety of biological process and vary by datasets. For example, neural pathways such as 'Transmission across Chemical Synapses', 'GABA receptor activation' are commonly predicted in HPM and GTEx dataset. Pathways about other signal transduction system such as 'Signaling by Hippo', 'Activated TLR4 signaling' and 'Nuclear events mediated by MAP kinases' are commonly predicted in U133A and NCI60 dataset. In addition, we also found G-protein dependent pathways participate in the regulation of ion channel through pathways such as 'Activation of G protein gated Potassium channels' and 'Inhibition of voltage gated Ca 2þ channels via Gbeta/gamma subunits' in GTEx dataset.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Class C and D GPCRs are commonly connected to pathways in nervous system</head><p>We used bar plot to show the number of G-protein dependent (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2A</ref>) and independent (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2C</ref>) pathways predicted for each GPCR in HPM_PRT (The other four datasets are shown in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S19</ref>–S22). We chose HPM_PRT because the tissues in the dataset are diverse and cover eight various human anatomy systems. All the GPCRs were grouped by their class annotation from GtoPdb. Class A, B and F GPCRs have downstream pathways in various systems while class C and D show preference on particular systems. For example, class C GPCRs, including calcium-sensing,V: Various S: Sensory R: Respiratory P: Antiparasitic N: Nervous M: Musculo-skeletal L: Immunomodulating J: Antiinfectives H: Hormonal G: Genito-urinary D: Dermatologicals C: Cardiovascular B: Blood A: Alimentary tract Drug<ref type="figure" target="#tab_0">Target  0</ref>Systematic prediction of GPCR downstream signalingGABA and glutamate receptors are commonly connected to G-protein dependent pathways in nervous system. Class D (Adhesion) GPCRs are commonly connected to G-protein dependent pathways in nervous and cardiovascular system. Class D is also commonly connected to G-protein independent pathways in the immune system. The number of predicted pathways varies greatly by GPCR. For example, CALCRL, a calcitonin-gene-related peptide receptor has 223 predicted G-protein dependent pathways from a variety of systems, the most among all GPCRs (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2A</ref>) while GPCRs such as CCKAR, a Cholecystokinin receptor that Mediates smooth muscle contraction of the gall bladder and stomach only have one predicted G-protein dependent pathway in the digestive system. G-protein dependent pathways appear in all eight systems while G-protein independent pathways mainly appear in immune, reproductive and cardiovascular system (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2A</ref>and C).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">GPCR—pathway associations recapture known pharmacology</head><p>ATC is a pharmacological classification system based on the organ or system of action. Since GPCR are the targets of nearly one third of modern drugs, we compared the tissues and downstream pathways of GPCRs predicted by GOTE with the ATC classification of the drugs that target them (Supplementary Methods). For each GPCR, we calculated the proportion of drugs that belong to each ATC category (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2B</ref>). Most drugs in ATC system target class A and C GPCRs. Many overlaps can be found when comparing the systems of a drug given by ATC and the systems connected to the GPCR by GOTE. For example, all three drugs targeting PTGIR act in 'Blood or blood forming organs (B)' according to ATC system, while in our results, PTGIR is connected platelets (cardiovascular system,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2B</ref>). In platelets, PTGIR is connected to 39 downstream pathways in such as 'Platelet activation, signaling and aggregation' (P-value ¼ 0.0016, ranking No. 3 in G-protein independent pathways, Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S6</ref>). Extracellular calcium-sensing receptor (CASR) is the target of cinacalcet, a drug that acts as a calcimimetic to lower calcium level in blood (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Shoback et al., 2003</ref>). This drug is classified into 'systemic hormonal preparations (H)' by ATC and its target CASR is connected to endocrine system by GOTE since it is uniquely expressed in pancreas (the pancreas belongs to both endocrine and digestive system, we classified it into endocrine system). Thirty-two downstream pathways are connected to CASR in pancreas by GOTE. The most significant one is 'Depolarization of the Presynaptic Terminal Triggers the Opening of Calcium Channels' (P-value ¼ 1.50eÀ06, ranking No.1 in G-protein dependent pathways, Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S6</ref>). Many GPCRs are the targets of drugs belonging to the 'Nervous (N)' class according to ATC. They are significantly overlapped with the GPCRs connected to the nervous system by GOTE (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2D</ref>). Pearson correlation coefficient between them is 0.543 (P-value ¼ 1.76eÀ10). The Pearson correlation coefficient between GPCRs connected to digestive system by GOTE and GPCRs with drug classified into ATC-Alimentary tract (A) is 0.435 (P-value ¼ 7.60eÀ07). The Pearson correlation coefficient between GPCRs connected to urinary, reproductive system by GOTE and GPCRs with drug classified into ATC Genito-urinary(G) is 0.424 (P-value ¼ 1.57e-06).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">The similarity of results depends on the similarity of cell types</head><p>We expect GOTE to predict similar pathways in similar tissues or cell types. To evaluate this hypothesis, we calculated the pairwise Jaccard similarity of predicted pathways between the same type of cell lines in NCI60. We paired together cell lines of the same and different cell types. The Jaccard similarity is shown as barplot in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 3A</ref>. On average, the G-protein dependent pathways predicted among similar cell types have a Jaccard similarity of 0.141 6 0.028, higher than those predicted among different cell types 0.067 6 0.006 (one side t-test P-value ¼ 5.26eÀ06). The results are similar for G-protein independent pathways (0.141 6 0.049 versus 0.063 6 0.005, one side t-test P-value ¼ 1.83eÀ03). We also calculated pairwise Jaccard similarity of predicted pathways for all tissues in U133A dataset. The result is shown as heatmap in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 3B</ref>(G-protein independent pathways) and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure S23</ref>(G-protein dependent pathways). Two clusters of tissues can be observed. Tissues in the same cluster have high Jaccard similarity to each other and belong to the same system, either neural (green cluster) or immune (red cluster).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.7">Distinct datasets show consistency in predicted pathways</head><p>We calculated the pairwise Jaccard similarity of predicted pathways between the same tissue type in different datasets to test the robustness of GOTE against systematic error deriving from different platforms. The results were compared with a null distribution (Random) deriving from randomly assigning pathways to tissues (Supplementary Methods). The Jaccard similarity was shown as barplot in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 3C</ref>. The comparison was conducted pairwise between four datasets containing normal tissues: U133A, HPM_RNA, HPM_PRT and GTEx. The results between GTEx and two HPM datasets were not shown because few overlapped tissues exist between them. Of all four datasets, HPM_RNA and HPM_PRT have the highest Jaccard similarity in predicted pathways. The average is 0.79 (95% CI: 0.66–0.92, P-value ¼ 6.34eÀ11 compared to Random) for Gprotein dependent pathways and 0.70 (95% CI: 0.50–0.87, P-value ¼ 1.1eÀ05) for G-protein independent pathways. U133A and GTEx have high Jaccard similarity in predicted G-protein independent pathways. The average is 0.15 (95% CI: 0.10–0.20, P-value ¼ 0.001 compared to Random). The similarity between U133A and two HPM datasets was not significant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.8">Predicted pathways go through expression change after GPCR knockdown experiment</head><p>We validated our GPCR-tissue-pathway predictions using an independent dataset from the L1000 experiment which measured the expression change of all genes after a GPCR was knocked down (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Duan et al., 2014</ref>). Using these expression data, we defined a weak reference standard that connects GPCRs to pathways by identifying significantly differentially expressed pathways in the knockdown experiment. For comparison, the performance of GOTE was compared to two other methods we created: HighExp and Random. HighExp looks at any pathway that is highly expressed in the tissue (not just the subset of pathways predicted for the GPCR by GOTE). Random represents the null distribution (Section 2.2.3). We focused on the results of GOTE in NCI60 dataset since the cell lines used overlap with those used in the L1000 dataset. The precision, recall and specificity of results were calculated for three methods (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>). For G-protein dependent pathways, 92 connections between of GPCR and tissue can be evaluated (11% of all results). On average, the precision of GOTE is 0.22 6 0.05, significantly outperforms two other methods (HighExp: 0.13 6 0.03, Random: 0.08 6 0.03). The recall of GOTE is 0.03 6 0.01, outperforms Random (0.007 6 0.001) but lower than HighExp (0.51 6 0.06). The specificity of GOTE is 0.994 6 0.001, outperforms HighExp (0.851 6 0.003). For G-protein independent pathways, 38 connections between of GPCR and tissue can be evaluated (8% of all). The results have the same tendency as G-protein dependent pathways. On average, the precision, recall and specificity of GOTE is 0.28 6 0.08, 0.10 6 0.04 and 0.989 6 0.002.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.9">Increasing the cutoff of GPCR specificity contributes to high-confident results</head><p>We studied the influence of four parameters on the results of GOTE. These four parameters are as follows: (1) The P-value threshold for highly expressed GPCRs t 1 is to control the number of highly expressed GPCR in each tissue; (2) The GPCR specificity score threshold t 2 is to control the connections between GPCR and tissue.<ref type="bibr">(3)</ref>The P-value threshold for highly expressed binding proteins of transducers t 3 is to control the number of binding proteins used for enrichment analysis; (4) The P-value threshold for enriched pathways t 4 is to control the number of enriched pathways. In a default setting, we use 0.05, 0, 0.05 and 0.05 for the four parameters to generate results. Here, the range of each parameter was expanded to a wider range to test influence on a benchmark statistics representing how much GOTE outperforms HighExp in precision. The line graphs in<ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>show the benchmark statistics against each of four parameters. The P-value threshold of GPCR, binding protein and pathway do not have a strong influence on the accuracy of results (<ref type="figure">Fig. 4A</ref>, C and D). In contrast, different threshold ofCI: confidence interval. The performance of three methods is compared: GOTE, HighExp and Random. Each column indicates the mean of precision: TP/(TP þ FP), recall: TP/(TP þ FN) and specificity: TN/(TN þ FP). The number in bracket indicates 95% confidence interval of mean value calculated by bootstrap.Systematic prediction of GPCR downstream signalingGPCR specificity can lead to a dramatic change in the benchmark statistics (<ref type="figure">Fig. 4B</ref>). As the threshold for GPCR specificity score approaches to 1, GOTE significantly outperforms HighExp in precision.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Jaccard</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Discussion</head><p>In this paper, we presented a data-driven method, GOTE, to systematically identify the downstream pathways of GPCRs in each tissue. We used gene expression datasets to find highly expressed binding proteins of G-proteins or b-arrestins in each tissue and performed pathway enrichment analysis to find enriched pathways. Then we connected the enriched pathways to specifically expressed GPCRs in the tissue as their downstream pathways. We found that the predicted pathways differ by tissue and GPCR while similar tissues have similar predicted pathways. With no true standard available, we created a 'weak' standard on our own with an independent dataset from L1000 gene knockdown experiment, to validate our GPCR-tissue-pathway predictions. In the validation, we tested the correlation between the knockdown of GPCR and the change of expression in downstream pathways. As co-expression is only a prerequisite of actual connection, this standard is less stringent and will unavoidably bring in some false positives. We controlled for this error by comparing the results to a null distribution Random and another reference method HighExp that connects highly expressed pathways to GPCRs in each tissue. GOTE outperforms both two methods in precision and specificity. GOTE has lower recall than HighExp because it chooses the tissue-specific pathways that are also enriched by the binding proteins of transducers. Thus GOTE is more stringent and is expected to have fewer predictions than HighExp. As a data-driven method, our prediction results are dependent on the expression dataset used. Unfortunately, most current expression data are derived from different platforms. We tested the robustness of GOTE among four datasets with normal human tissue, each using a different technology. The similarity of predicted pathways between datasets is in alignment with the expression similarity (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S24</ref>), where the results are highly consistent between two mass spectrometry datasets and less consistent between these two mass spectrometry dataset and the microarray dataset. In addition, the five datasets do not employ a standard tissue naming scheme. This may contribute to a situation where a same name of tissue can refer to different types of cells in the tissue, which adds the difficulty of comparing predicted pathways between different datasets. Another limitation of GOTE is our current strategy of mapping GPCRs to their transducers. The relationship between GPCRs and transducers has not been well studied. Therefore, we used co-expression in the same tissue to connect GPCRs to transducers in GOTE. Consequently, this may bring in some false positive pairs of GPCRs and transducers since the correlation in expression does not necessarily mean the existence of actual connection between GPCRs and transducers. To mitigate these potential false positives, we provided a parameter in GOTE that controls GPCR tissue specificity. We showed that by setting a high threshold of this parameter, users can get more confident connections between GPCR and downstream pathways at the cost of fewer predictions. We found our findings on many GPCRs agree with their molecular function, cause of disease, or the action of corresponding drug provided by other resources. For example, we found class C and D GPCRs are commonly connected to G-protein dependent pathways in nervous system. While class C GPCRs consists of calcium-sensing, GABA and glutamate receptors, which are synaptic receptors located primarily on neuronal cells, and class D GPCRs are reported to play an important role in brain development (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Yona et al., 2008</ref>). We also found the tissues connected to GPCR in our results correlate with the ATC classification of corresponding drug. GPCRs such as CASR, PTGIR are predicted with pathways in agreement with the molecular mechanism of their corresponding drugs (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S6</ref>). Some GPCRs have predicted pathways validated by other studies. For example, CXCR4, one of the co-receptors of HIV-1 in immunological cells participate in the activation of ion channels after the binding of gp120 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Lee et al., 2003</ref>). We found this GPCR is connected to both HIV-related pathways (such as 'HIV Transcription Initiation') and ion channel-related pathways (such as 'Voltage gated Potassium channels') in CD8 Cells (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S7</ref>). Another GPCR GPR56 is regulated by Blimp-1 in NK cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chang et al., 2016</ref>), which is a transcription factor and modulates the MHC Class I antigen-processing and peptide-loading pathway (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Doody et al., 2007</ref>). In our results, this GPCR is connected to the 'Class I MHC mediated antigen processing &amp; presentation' pathway in NK cells (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S8</ref>). Eventually, since GPCRs participate in controlling an extraordinary variety of physiological functions, mutations in GPCR can cause many complex diseases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Insel et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schoneberg et al., 2004</ref>). The pathways we predicted for these GPCRs may help us study the mechanism of these diseases. For example, mutations in TBXA2R, a thromboxane receptor (TP), will cause a bleeding disorder in human body (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Hirata et al., 1994</ref>). In our results, this GPCR is connected to blood clotting pathways such as 'Platelet activation, signaling and aggregation' (Pvalue ¼ 1.62*eÀ03, ranking 3, Supplementary Table S9) in platelets. Meanwhile, we also found other interesting pathways such as<ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>. Influence of four parameters on the prediction results of GOTE. GDP: G-protein dependent pathways. GIP: G-protein independent pathways. In each of four line graphs, the x-axis indicates the threshold (or 1/threshold in B) of one parameter. The y-axis indicates how much GOTE outperforms HighExp in precision when setting the parameter to the threshold of x-axis (the other three parameters as default setting). The four parameters are: (A) t 1 : the P-value threshold for highly expressed GPCRs. (B) t 2 : the GPCR specificity score threshold. (C) t 3 : the P-value threshold for highly expressed binding proteins of transducers. (D) t 4 : the P-value threshold for enriched pathways 'Hyaluronan uptake and degradation' (P-value ¼ 3.93*eÀ03, ranking 5, Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S9</ref>), 'Hyaluronan metabolism' (P-value ¼ 4.93*eÀ03, ranking 6, Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S9</ref>). Hyaluronan plays an important role in skin wound healing events. Together with fibrin, it increases or stabilizes the volume and porosity of the clot and then serves as a physical support through which cells are trapped in the clot (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Weigel et al., 1986</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A B C D</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health (R01GM107145) and the Herbert Irving Fellows award. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Workflow and data used in GOTE. The left side shows the workflow of GOTE. The center gives a simple description of each step. The right side shows the data used in each step. In the first step we used tissue expression data to find specifically expressed GPCR in each tissue. Second, for each transducer (G-protein or b-arrestin), we obtained a list of binding proteins using the BioGRID PPI data. Third, the list of binding proteins is filtered by tissue expression, resulting in lists of tissue-specific binding proteins. Fourth, pathway enrichment analysis is performed based on the tissue-specific binding proteins of each transducer using Fisher's Exact Test. For each pathway, a Z-score is calculated for each transducer. Fifth, for each pathway, the Z-scores of all G-proteins are combined together using Stouffer's Method. The weight of each Z-score is in proportion to the tissue expression of each G-protein. The same analysis is repeated for the Z-scores of all b-arrestins. Finally, pathways with significant Z-scores are connected to GPCRs expressed in the same tissue as G-protein dependent pathways (those which are associated with G-proteins) or G-protein independent pathways (those which are associated with b-arrestins)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>dataset from L1000 gene knockdown experiment We downloaded the expression dataset of 448 737 gene knockdown experiments from lincscloud.org with perturbation type of 'trt_sh' (Duan et al., 2014). In each experiment, a gene was knocked down in a particular cancer cell line and the expression of all the genes was measured before and after the knockdown. In total, 11 617 experiments were found to knock down a GPCR gene. Altogether, 145 unique GPCRs and 16 cell lines from NCI60 were included in L1000 gene knockdown dataset. Four levels of data are provided by lincscloud.org: raw, unprocessed flow cytometry data (level 1), Gene expression values (level 2), normalized expression value (level 3) and signatures with differentially expressed genes computed by robust z-scores for each profile relative to population control (level 4). We used level 4 data, Z-score of each gene representing the level of expression change after the gene knockdown. We then preprocessed the dataset by mapping array IDs to Uniprot IDs. The average Z-score was calculated if multiple array IDs were mapped to a same Uniprot ID.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>S1–S5). We found that on average 7.84 6 1.11 GPCRs in U133A, 8.83 6 0.60 GPCRs in NCI60, 12.23 6 2.00 GPCRs in HPM_RNA, 10.40 6 2.00 GPCRs in HPM_PRT and 27.56 6 3.00 GPCRs in GTex are highly expressed in each tissue when using P-value of 0.05 as a threshold for high expression (Supplementary</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Results of HPM_PRT dataset. (A,C) Bar plot showing the number of predicted G-protein dependent (A) and independent (C) pathways, respectively. The xaxis indicates different GPCRs, which are grouped by six families. Each bar with a unique color indicates the number of predicted pathways in a tissue type. (B) A heatmap shows a mapping between GPCR and the Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) Classification System categories of the drugs known to bind them. The first row indicates whether or not the GPCR is a known drug target. Each cell colored from white to deep purple indicates the percentage of drugs that target the GPCRs that are classified into each category. (D) Correlation between ATC classification and the results of GOTE. The purple cell of top row shows the GPCR targeted by drugs belonging to the Nervous category of ATC classification. The purple cell of bottom row shows the GPCRs which are connected to nervous system by GOTE (r ¼ 0.543, P-value ¼ 1.76eÀ10</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Barplot of Jaccard similarity. GDP: G-protein dependent pathways. GIP: G-protein independent pathways. (A) Comparison of GOTE's results between different cell lines in NCI60 dataset. Each bar indicates the mean pairwise Jaccard similarity of cell lines belonging to same or different cell type. The error bar indicates 95% confidence interval of mean value calculated by bootstrap. For both G-protein dependent pathways (green) and G-protein independent pathways (pink), the Jaccard similarity between same cell types is significantly higher than Jaccard similarity between different cell types. (B) A heatmap showing the pairwise jaccard similariy of G-protein independent pathways among tissues in U133A dataset. Each column or row indicates a tissue. The color of each cell is proportion to the Jaccard similarity between the column and row. Two clusters of tissues are highlighted in the heatmap: green cluster of neural tissues at the bottom and red cluster of immune tissues in the middle. (C) Comparison of GOTE's results among four different datasets: U133A, HPM_RNA, HPM_PRT and GTEx. Each bar indicates the mean pairwise jaccard similarity of same tissue from two datasets. The error bar indicates 95% confidence interval of mean value calculated by bootstrap</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1.</figDesc><table>Summary of results in all five datasets 

U133A NCI60 
HPM_RNA HPM_PRT GTEx 

General statistics of results for G protein dependent pathway (#:number) 
# GPCRs 
118 
112 
129 
119 
237 
# Pathways 
293 
305 
217 
277 
238 
# Tissues 
66 
98 
26 
27 
50 
# Connections 12484 
15078 
6957 
5834 
32665 
number of G protein independent pathways per GPCR 
average 
46.78 
75.75 
43.98 
41.97 
76.91 
SD 
42.61 
65.68 
30.9 
40.3 
58.96 
Maximum 
174 
246 
161 
221 
218 
Minimum 
1 
2 
1 
1 
2 
number of tissues per GPCR 
average 
4.92 
7.79 
2.43 
2.36 
5.97 
SD 
5.16 
9.27 
1.89 
1.88 
4.16 
Maximum 
24 
40 
9 
9 
18 
Minimum 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 
General statistics of results for G protein independent pathway 
# GPCRs 
102 
102 
112 
90 
215 
# Pathways 
443 
303 
159 
167 
185 
# Tissues 
50 
55 
15 
15 
32 
# Connections 32706 
13149 
4061 
2743 
29311 
number of G protein independent pathways per GPCR 
average 
124.18 
78.91 
30.09 
27.31 
62.17 
SD 
81.38 
62.73 
26.89 
28.75 
30.46 
Maximum 
356 
258 
104 
110 
135 
Minimum 
3 
2 
2 
2 
1 
number of tissues per GPCR 
average 
4.64 
4.62 
1.75 
1.74 
4.89 
SD 
4.81 
5.12 
1.09 
1.08 
3.54 
Maximum 
21 
23 
5 
6 
16 
Minimum 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. Summary of results for each system in HPM_PRT dataset</figDesc><table>System 
#GPCR 
#GDP 
#GIP 
#Overlap 

Endocrine 
7 
17 
0 
0 
Digestive 
51 
71 
9 
1 
Nervous 
44 
49 
46 
7 
Cardiovascular 
29 
74 
39 
5 
Respiratory 
8 
12 
11 
0 
Reproductive 
29 
152 
52 
22 
Urinary 
15 
19 
0 
0 
Immune 
25 
60 
86 
15 
Average 
26 
56.75 
30.38 
6.25 
Total 
119 
277 
167 
90 

#: number. GDP: G-protein dependent pathways. GIP: G-protein independ-
ent pathways. Overlap: between GDP and GIP. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 3. Validation of GOTE using L1000 GPCR knockdown data</figDesc><table># positive pathways (95% CI) 
Precision (95% CI) 
Recall (95% CI) 
Specificity (95% CI) 

G-protein dependent pathways 
GOTE 
173 (110–246) 
0.22 (0.17–0.28) 
0.03 (0.02–0.04) 
0.994 (0.993–0.996) 
HighExp 
0.13 (0.1–0.17) 
0.51 (0.45–0.57) 
0.851 (0.848–0.855) 
Random 
0.08 (0.05–0.12) 
0.007 (0.005–0.008) 
0.994 (0.993–0.995) 
G-protein independent pathways 
GOTE 
223 (110–349) 
0.28 (0.2–0.36) 
0.10 (0.06–0.14) 
0.989 (0.987–0.991) 
HighExp 
0.16 (0.1–0.22) 
0.45 (0.37–0.52) 
0.853 (0.85–0.857) 
Random 
0.1 (0.05–0.15) 
0.015 (0.012–0.018) 
0.986 (0.983–0.989) 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">Y.Hao and N.P.Tatonetti at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">b-Arrestin-2 mediates anti-apoptotic signaling through regulation of BAD phosphorylation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Ahn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8855" to="8865" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Akt/b-arrestin 2/PP2A signaling complex mediates dopaminergic neurotransmission and behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Beaulieu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="261" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expansion of signal transduction by G proteins: the second 15 years or so: from 3 to 16 a subunits plus bc dimers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Birnbaumer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta (BBA) Biomembr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1768</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="772" to="793" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The adhesion G protein-coupled receptor GPR56/ ADGRG1 is an inhibitory receptor on human NK cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Chang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1757" to="1770" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The BioGRID interaction database: 2013 update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Chatr-Aryamontri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="816" to="823" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Reactome pathway knowledgebase</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Croft</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="472" to="477" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some G protein heterotrimers physically dissociate in living cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Digby</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17789" to="17794" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PRDM1/BLIMP-1 modulates IFN-c-dependent control of the MHC class I antigen-processing and peptide-loading pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Doody</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">179</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7614" to="7623" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">G-protein-coupled receptors and cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Dorsam</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Gutkind</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LINCS Canvas Browser: interactive web app to query, browse and interrogate LINCS L1000 gene expression signatures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Duan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="460" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the interpretation of v2 from contingency tables, and the calculation of P</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Fisher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Stat. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="1922" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The repertoire of G-protein–coupled receptors in fully sequenced genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Fredriksson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Schiö Th</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1414" to="1425" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Arg60 to Leu mutation of the human thromboxane A2 receptor in a dominantly inherited bleeding disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Hirata</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Investig</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1662</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The druggable genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Hopkins</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Groom</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Drug Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="727" to="730" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of GPCRs in clinical medicine: monogenic diseases, genetic variants and drug targets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Insel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1768" to="994" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diversity and modularity of G protein-coupled receptor structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Katritch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Pharmacol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A draft map of the human proteome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">509</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="575" to="581" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Macrophage activation through CCR5-and CXCR4-mediated gp120-elicited signaling pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Leukoc. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="676" to="682" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human transcriptome across tissues and individuals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Melé</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">348</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="660" to="665" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathophysiological roles of G-protein-coupled receptor kinases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Metaye</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Signal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="917" to="928" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential affinities of visual arrestin, barrestin1, and barrestin2 for G protein-coupled receptors delineate two major classes of receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Oakley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">275</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17201" to="17210" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anatomical profiling of G protein-coupled receptor expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Regard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="561" to="571" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Arrestins block G protein-coupled receptor-mediated apoptosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Revankar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24578" to="24584" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutant G-protein-coupled receptors as a cause of human diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Schoneberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacol. Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The calcimimetic cinacalcet normalizes serum calcium in subjects with primary hyperparathyroidism</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Shoback</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5644" to="5649" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The IUPHAR/BPS Guide to PHARMACOLOGY in 2016: towards curated quantitative interactions between 1300 protein targets and 6000 ligands</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Southan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1054" to="1068" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Adjustment during Army Life</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Stouffer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1949" />
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A gene atlas of the mouse and human protein-encoding transcriptomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Su</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6062" to="6067" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">gpDB: a database of GPCRs, G-proteins, effectors and their interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Theodoropoulou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1471" to="1472" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Location, location, location.. .site-specific GPCR phosphorylation offers a mechanism for cell-type-specific signalling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Tobin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Pharmacol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="413" to="420" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UniProt: a hub for protein information</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Uniprot</forename>
				<surname>Consortium</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="204" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A model for the role of hyaluronic acid and fibrin in the early events during the inflammatory response and wound healing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Weigel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="234" />
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioGPS: building your own mash-up of gene annotations and expression profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="316" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adhesion-GPCRs: emerging roles for novel receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Yona</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Biochem. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="491" to="500" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Systematic prediction of GPCR downstream signaling</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>