
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:40+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS DISCOVERY NOTE Genome analysis Promoter-proximal CCCTC-factor binding is associated with an increase in the transcriptional pausing index</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sur</forename>
								<surname>Herrera Paredes</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Curriculum in Bioinformatics and Computational Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Carolina Center for Genome Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<settlement>Chapel Hill</settlement>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">F</forename>
								<surname>Melgar</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Genome Technology Branch</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">National Human Genome Research Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Institutes of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20892</postCode>
									<settlement>Bethesda</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Praveen</forename>
								<surname>Sethupathy</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Carolina Center for Genome Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<settlement>Chapel Hill</settlement>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<settlement>Chapel Hill</settlement>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS DISCOVERY NOTE Genome analysis Promoter-proximal CCCTC-factor binding is associated with an increase in the transcriptional pausing index</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1485" to="1487"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts596</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 9, 2012; revised on September 14, 2012; accepted on September 30, 2012</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Ivo Hofacker Contact: praveen_sethupathy@med.unc.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: It has been known for more than 2 decades that after RNA polymerase II (RNAPII) initiates transcription, it can enter into a paused or stalled state immediately downstream of the transcription start site before productive elongation. Recent advances in high-throughput genomic technologies facilitated the discovery that RNAPII pausing at promoters is a widespread physiologically regulated phenomenon. The molecular underpinnings of pausing are incompletely understood. The CCCTC-factor (CTCF) is a ubiquitous nuclear factor that has diverse regulatory functions, including a recently discovered role in promoting RNAPII pausing at splice sites. Results: In this study, we analyzed CTCF binding sites and nascent transcriptomic data from three different cell types, and found that promoter-proximal CTCF binding is significantly associated with RNAPII pausing.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Promoter-proximal pausing of RNA polymerase II (RNAPII) has emerged as a widespread and important step in the regulation of transcription (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Core et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Gilchrist and Adelman, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Li and Gilmour, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Seila et al., 2009</ref>). The role of pausing is not completely understood, but initial evidence suggests that it allows for precise and rapid transcriptional response to stimuli such as developmental cues or cellular stressors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Espinosa, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Li and Gilmour, 2011</ref>). The underlying mechanisms of RNAPII pausing are thought to be complex (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Landick, 2009</ref>). Recent publications have reported a few key factors that regulate polymerase pause site entry and release, including GAGA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Lee et al., 2008</ref>), c-MYC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Rahl et al., 2010</ref>), ELL (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Byun et al., 2012</ref>) and XRN2 (<ref type="bibr">Brannan et al., 2012</ref>); however, it is not clear whether and how many other complexes are also involved. As such, this area merits further investigation. The CCCTC-factor (CTCF) is a multifaceted gene regulator, with demonstrated roles in transcriptional activation/repression, insulation, imprinting and chromatin remodeling (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Ohlsson et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Phillips and Corces, 2009</ref>). In 2011, Shukla et al. published a seminal article, which reported for the first time that CTCF can facilitate exon inclusion by promoting RNAPII pausing at splice sites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Shukla et al., 2011</ref>). Another recent study postulated that CTCF may regulate vascular endothelial growth factor transcription in part by mediating RNAPII pausing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Lu and Tang, 2012</ref>). Given these reports, and recent observations that at least 20–25% of CTCF-binding events are proximal to promoters (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Jothi et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kim et al., 2007</ref>), we hypothesized that CTCF binding may be a cofactor in mediating promoterproximal RNAPII pausing. To investigate this possibility, we analyzed genome-wide nascent RNA data (global nuclear run-on followed by sequencing; GRO-seq) and empirically determined CTCF-binding sites from the only three cell types for which both datasets are publicly available: human cell lines IMR90 (lung fibroblast) and MCF-7 (breast cancer) and mouse embryonic stem cells (mES).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Datasets</head><p>Empirically determined CTCF-binding sites were downloaded from http://licr-renlab.ucsd.edu/download.html (CTCF chromatin immunoprecipitation followed by microarray analysis<ref type="bibr">[ChIP-chip]</ref>in IMR90 cells), http://genome.ucsc.edu/ENCODE/downloads.html (CTCF chromatin immunoprecipitation followed by high-throughput sequencing<ref type="bibr">[ChIP-seq]</ref>in MCF-7 cells) and Chen et al., 2008 (mES ChIP-seq). All coordinates were mapped to either the mm9 (mES) or the hg18 (IMR90, MCF-7) genome builds using the command line liftOver program with the –minMatch parameter set to 0.95. CTCF-binding sites were also computationally predicted by scanning for matches to the canonical motif (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kim et al., 2007</ref>) using the PWM-scan algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Levy and Hannenhalli, 2002</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Analysis</head><p>Promoter-proximal pausing indices were calculated in the following manner: first, for each annotated RefSeq transcript longer than 3 kb (n ¼ 27 863 for human, n ¼ 22 547 for mouse), we set the transcription start site (TSS) as position 0, and defined 0–500 nt downstream as the promoter-proximal region and 500-gene end as the gene body. Second, we computed the density of RNAPII in both promoter-proximal regions and gene bodies by calculating GRO-seq reads/nt/mapability using the same mapability data as in<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Melgar et al., 2011.</ref>Third, for all genes that had at *To whom correspondence should be addressed. least one read mapping to the gene body (n ¼ 24 988 for IMR90, n ¼ 24 613 for MCF-7, n ¼ 20 512 for mES), we computed pausing index as the ratio of RNAPII density in the promoter-proximal region to RNAPII density in the gene body, similar to previous studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Core et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Min et al., 2011</ref>). Promoters were divided into two categories: those with and those without a CTCF-binding site overlapping X to Y nt downstream of the TSS, where X and Y were set in independent experiments to 0 and 100, 101 and 200, 201 and 300, 301 and 500, 501 and 1000 or 1001 and 2000. To compare pausing indices between categories, we computed the Jaccard distance in median pausing index as follows: (x À y)/(x þ y), where x is the median pausing index at CTCF-bound promoters and y is the median pausing index at promoters where CTCF is not bound. The significance of the difference in pausing indices between the two promoter categories was assessed by one-sided permutation and non-parametric Mann– Whitney–Wilcoxon (MWW) tests. This analysis was repeated for the same distances upstream of the TSS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>For each cell type, we divided promoters according to whether CTCF was bound upstream/downstream of the TSS (Section 2). The number of promoter-proximal CTCF-binding sites was highly variable across cell types (Supplementary Material 1). GRO-seq data provide a density map of transcriptionally engaged RNAPII across the genome by purifying, sequencing and mapping nascent RNAs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Core et al., 2008</ref>). Using recently published GRO-seq data, we calculated RNAPII pausing indices at RefSeq-annotated promoters in three different cell types, and assessed whether promoter-proximal CTCF binding is associated with elevated RNAPII pausing indices (Section 2). We made two novel observations: (1) Genes that exhibit promoter-proximal CTCF binding (defined as within 100 nt downstream of the TSS) have a significantly greater RNAPII pausing index than genes that do not (Supplementary Material 1). For example, in IMR90 cells, the median pausing index at promoters with proximal CTCF-binding sites is $2-fold greater (permutation test P 5 0.0001, Mann– Whitney–Wilcoxon test P ¼ 1.8 Â 10 À 38) than at promoters without proximal CTCF-binding sites (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). The highly overlapping range of pausing indices between the two categories of promoters indicates that while CTCF binding may be associated with pausing, it is by no means necessary or sufficient. Regions of CTCF binding are enriched for motifs with elevated cytosine (C) content (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Jothi et al., 2008</ref>). As such, the observed association between CTCF-binding events and increased pausing index could be explained by nucleotide composition (i.e. cytosine enriched regions may be responsible for the association with pausing, independent of CTCF binding). To test this, we repeated the analysis in each cell type with computationally predicted CTCF-binding sites (Section 2), based on the known C-rich motif (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kim et al., 2007</ref>). We did not observe any association with pausing (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>; Supplementary Material 1), which strongly suggests that sequence composition alone is not sufficient to explain the association signal, but rather, the physical binding of CTCF is required.</p><formula>(2)</formula><p>The association between CTCF binding and the promoterproximal pausing index is position-dependent—that is, the further upstream/downstream from the TSS CTCF is bound, the less of an association there is with RNAPII pausing (<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>;<ref type="figure">1</ref>. The association between CTCF binding and pausing index is shown. Each IMR90 promoter was classified based on the presence (Yes) or absence (No) of an empirically determined (IMR90 ChIPchip), or computationally predicted CTCF-binding site in the first 100 nt downstream of its TSS (x-axis). The pausing index at each promoter was calculated (Section 2) and transformed using the formula log 10 (pausing index þ 1) for visualization purposes (y-axis). The boxes in the plot cover percentiles 25–75, and the bar within each box represents the median. The whiskers extend to the most extreme data point that is no more than 1.5 times the interquartile range from the box. Mann– Whitney–Wilcoxon non-parametric test P-values are indicated for the relevant comparisons<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. The position-specific effect on the association of CTCF binding with promoter-proximal RNAPII pausing is shown. The x-axis represents the distance (nt) from the TSS (vertical dashed line) of annotated (RefSeq) genes longer than 3 kb. The y-axis depicts a normalized difference in median pausing index between promoters with a CTCF-binding event (ChIP-seq/ChIP-chip peak) and promoters without a CTCFbinding event (no ChIP-seq/ChIP-chip peak). As such, the value 0.0 (horizontal dashed line) represents 'no difference' in median pausing index between the two groups, a positive value represents increased pausing in promoters with a CTCF-binding event and a negative value represents decreased pausing in promoters with a CTCF-binding event. Results are shown for three cell lines (two human: IMR90, MCF-7; one mouse: mES cells) Supplementary Material 1). For example, in mES cells, CTCF binding within 101–200 nt downstream of TSSs is highly significantly associated with pausing (permutation test P50.0001); however, this association is dramatically weakened for CTCF binding within 1001–2000 nt upstream/downstream of TSSs (permutation test P40.5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>A recent study identified a novel role for CTCF in polymerase pausing at splice sites to facilitate exon inclusion (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Shukla et al., 2011</ref>). Our findings provide the first indication that CTCF is associated with promoter-proximal pausing. It is important to note that the study does not demonstrate that CTCF binding is necessary or sufficient for promoter-proximal pausing. Substantial additional experimental work is required to uncover the molecular underpinnings of the observed association between CTCF binding and RNAPII dynamics. The greatest degree of association with pausing is observed for CTCF-binding sites that are immediately downstream of the TSS. Therefore, an appealing mechanism for the observed association is steric hindrance—that is, stably bound CTCF may serve to hinder RNAPII processivity. If this is the case, it is likely that many other transcription factors with binding sites immediately downstream of TSSs also associate with RNAPII pausing. It will be possible to test this hypothesis as more transcription factor (TF) ChIP-seq and GRO-seq data are generated from the same cell type. We note, however, that because even sites that are upstream of the TSS are somewhat associated with pausing, steric hindrance is not likely to be the only mechanism involved.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Global nuclear run-on followed by high-throughput sequencing (GRO-seq) data were downloaded from Core et al., 2008 (IMR90), Hah et al., 2011 (MCF-7) and Min et al., 2011 (mES).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The association between CTCF binding and pausing index is shown. Each IMR90 promoter was classified based on the presence (Yes) or absence (No) of an empirically determined (IMR90 ChIPchip), or computationally predicted CTCF-binding site in the first 100 nt downstream of its TSS (x-axis). The pausing index at each promoter was calculated (Section 2) and transformed using the formula log 10 (pausing index þ 1) for visualization purposes (y-axis). The boxes in the plot cover percentiles 25–75, and the bar within each box represents the median. The whiskers extend to the most extreme data point that is no more than 1.5 times the interquartile range from the box. Mann– Whitney–Wilcoxon non-parametric test P-values are indicated for the relevant comparisons</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">S.H.Paredes et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Promoter-proximal CTCF binding at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2012) mRNA decapping factors and the exonuclease Xrn2 function in widespread premature termination of RNA polymerase II transcription</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Brannan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="324" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ELL facilitates RNA polymerase II pause site entry and release</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Byun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">633</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nascent RNA sequencing reveals widespread pausing and divergent initiation at human promoters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Core</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1845" to="1848" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The meaning of pausing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Espinosa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="507" to="508" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coupling polymerase pausing and chromatin landscapes for precise regulation of transcription</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Gilchrist</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Adelman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1819" to="700" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A rapid, extensive, and transient transcriptional response to estrogen signaling in breast cancer cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Hah</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">145</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="622" to="634" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide identification of in vivo protein-DNA binding sites from ChIP-Seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Jothi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5221" to="5231" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of the vertebrate insulator protein CTCF-binding sites in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1231" to="1245" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptional pausing without backtracking</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Landick</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8797" to="8798" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NELF and GAGA factor are linked to promoter-proximal pausing at many genes in Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3290" to="3300" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of transcription factor binding sites in the human genome sequence</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Levy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hannenhalli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mamm. Genome</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="510" to="514" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Promoter proximal pausing and the control of gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Gilmour</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CTCF-dependent chromatin insulator as a built-in attenuator of angiogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Lu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Tang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transcription</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovery of active enhancers through bidirectional expression of short transcripts</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Melgar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">113</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulating RNA polymerase pausing and transcription elongation in embryonic stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Min</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="742" to="754" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does CTCF mediate between nuclear organization and gene expression?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Ohlsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioessays</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CTCF: master weaver of the genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Phillips</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Corces</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1194" to="1211" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">) c-Myc regulates transcriptional pause release</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Rahl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="432" to="445" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Divergent transcription: a new feature of active promoters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Seila</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Cycle</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2557" to="2564" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CTCF-promoted RNA polymerase II pausing links DNA methylation to splicing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Shukla</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">479</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>