
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:48+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression ProteoStats—a library for estimating false discovery rates in proteomics pipelines</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Amit</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Kumar</forename>
								<surname>Yadav</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">G.N.R. Knowledge Center for Genome Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">CSIR-Institute of Genomics and Integrative Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Delhi-110020</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kumar</forename>
								<surname>Kadimi</surname>
								<roleName>Puneet</roleName>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">G.N.R. Knowledge Center for Genome Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">CSIR-Institute of Genomics and Integrative Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Delhi-110020</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dhirendra</forename>
								<surname>Kumar</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">G.N.R. Knowledge Center for Genome Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">CSIR-Institute of Genomics and Integrative Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Delhi-110020</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Debasis</forename>
								<surname>Dash</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">G.N.R. Knowledge Center for Genome Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">CSIR-Institute of Genomics and Integrative Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Delhi-110020</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Janet</forename>
								<surname>Kelso</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">G.N.R. Knowledge Center for Genome Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">CSIR-Institute of Genomics and Integrative Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Delhi-110020</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression ProteoStats—a library for estimating false discovery rates in proteomics pipelines</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2799" to="2800"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt490</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 11, 2013; revised on August 2, 2013; accepted on August 14, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Contact: ddash@igib.res.in or aky.compbio@gmail.com or amit.yadav@igib.in Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Statistical validation of peptide assignments from a large-scale shotgun proteomics experiment is a critical step, and various methods for evaluating significance based on decoy database search are in practice. False discovery rate (FDR) estimation of peptide assignments assesses global significance and corrects for multiple comparisons. Various approaches have been proposed for FDR estimation but unavailability of standard tools or libraries leads to development of many in-house scripts followed by manual steps that are error-prone and low-throughput. The ProteoStats library provides an open-source framework for developers with many FDR estimation and visualization features for several popular search algorithms. It also provides accurate q-values, which can be easily integrated in any proteomics pipeline to provide automated, accurate, high-throughput statistical validation and minimize manual errors. Availability: https://sourceforge.net/projects/mssuite/files/ProteoStats/.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>High-throughout shotgun proteomics generates millions of spectra that are assigned to peptides by database searching in an automated manner. A scoring function is used to calculate the level of similarity found between the experimental spectrum and the theoretical spectrum from a peptide. This quantitative value, known as the score, may be a probability, an expectation value or a simple score. Owing to random matching of peaks in a peptide spectral match (PSM), there is a fuzzy boundary between true and false matches leading to sensitivity versus specificity trade-off at any chosen threshold score. Conventional metrics like P-value/E-value are intended for significance assessment of a single hit (or PSM) but are not suitable for global significance assessment in large-scale datasets. A multiple testing correction procedure known as false discovery rate (FDR) is applied to the results for controlling the false positives globally. Target-decoy (TD) search-based FDR estimation is used as a standard method for global significance assessment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Elias and Gygi, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kall et al., 2008</ref>). Several challenges can arise in (i) dealing with multiple nonstandard file formats, (ii) presence of correct peptides in decoy results, which should be removed prior to FDR calculation and (iii) q-value calculation. Leucine/Isoleucine cannot be distinguished by collision-induced dissociation, resulting in identical scores for both target and decoy peptides. Such peptides need to be removed from decoy hits. This is a non-trivial exercise if carried out manually but critical for accurate estimation of FDR because even one such peptide may penalize hundreds of matches in target database. The calculation can be tedious for large datasets and numerous files. FDR estimation has recently been a major field of research in statistical proteomics, and several methods and their refined variants have been proposed. Unfortunately, not as many tools are available as there are FDR estimation methods. Most methods involve custom in-house scripts that may not implement all nuances of the algorithm and thus lack provenance. Custom pipelines only include the most popular methods like concatenated (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Elias and Gygi, 2007</ref>) or separate (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kall et al., 2008</ref>) methods, even though the refined methods improve the results. FDRAnalysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Wedge et al., 2011</ref>) provides FDR for three algorithms but only provides FDR for concatenated search. The barrier to their widespread adoption is the lack of software. This may also lead to different implementations of same method, code duplication and a considerable waste of research effort.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">DESCRIPTION OF PROTEOSTATS</head><p>To address the issues mentioned earlier, we have developed an open-source cross-platform scripting library, ProteoStats, which uses several FDR estimation procedures. The library is written in Perl and can be easily interfaced with other pipelines. The library also provides a simple programming interface for visualizing these results and quality control of PSMs. ProteoStats supports OMSSA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Geer et al., 2004</ref>), MassWiz (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Yadav et al., 2011b</ref>), Mascot (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Perkins et al., 1999</ref>), X!Tandem (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Craig and Beavis, 2004</ref>), Sequest (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Eng et al., 1994</ref>), MyriMatch (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Tabb et al., 2007</ref>) and Comet (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Eng et al., 2013</ref>), besides the generic PepXML and text file formats (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>Concatenated searches: The spectra are searched in a single concatenated database formed by combining the target and decoy proteins. The target and decoy candidate peptides compete against each other. Each spectrum will be assigned either a target or a decoy peptide as the best hit.</p><p>The two approaches are different only in the context of TD competition, which can be held a posteriori (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Fitzgibbon et al., 2008</ref>). Because it is easy to perform the TD competition even after a separate search, ProteoStats library requires results from separate search irrespective of the FDR method a user wants to select. The ProteoStats library supports many formulations on FDR:</p><p>Concatenated FDR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Elias and Gygi, 2007</ref>) Separate FDR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kall et al., 2008</ref>) FDR with percentage of incorrect target correction (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kall et al., 2008)</ref>Refined FDR on separate method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Navarro and Vazquez, 2009</ref>)</p><p>Refined method on concatenated FDR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Cerqueira et al., 2010)</ref>The ProteoStats library estimates FDR using the desired method in a series of steps that involve (i) native result file reading and conversion to text format, (ii) removing decoy peptides identical to target peptides, (iii) preparing target and decoy score arrays, (iv) estimating false positives based on FDR method, (v) iteratively calculating FDR for every decoy score as threshold and (vi) calculating q-values and writing output to a file. For visual analysis, receiver-operating characteristic curves (ROC) and various types of scatter plots and histograms can be plotted from FDR files (see Supplementary Data). The output is formatted in an easy to manipulate CSV/text file for further processing using any scripting language making subsequent analysis hassle-free. For charts, Excel spreadsheets can be created. These files can be easily imported into R environment for further data visualization/post-processing. The test datasets, sample input and expected outputs with ROC curves are provided along with a comparative table for various FDR methods across search engines (Supplementary Data). ProteoStats library has been extensively used in<ref type="bibr">MassWiz, GenoSuite (Kumar et al., 2013</ref>) and integrated multi-algorithmic analysis on plasma (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Yadav et al., 2011a</ref>). The FlexiFDR method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Yadav et al., 2012</ref>) was also developed on top of the core framework of this library.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Overview of ProteoStats library design</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>). TD searches can be conducted as follows: Separate searches: The spectra are searched separately against the target and decoy databases independent of each other. Each spectrum has two best hits—one from the target and another from decoy.</figDesc><table>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. 

ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> CONCLUSION Proteostats is a highly versatile, platform independent, opensource, extensible and easy-to-use framework for FDR estimation and statistical control of results from shotgun proteomics database search. Apart from providing an assorted list of different FDR estimation procedures, it also provides single PSM metric-like q-values, and visualization features like ROC, histogram, Venn diagram and scatterplot for data quality assessment and comparative analysis.</note>

			<note place="foot">A.K.Yadav et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MUDE: a new approach for optimizing sensitivity in the target-decoy search strategy for large-scale peptide/protein identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Cerqueira</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2265" to="2277" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TANDEM: matching proteins with tandem mass spectra</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Craig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Beavis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1466" to="1467" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Target-decoy search strategy for increased confidence in large-scale protein identifications by mass spectrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Elias</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Gygi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="214" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An approach to correlate tandem mass spectral data of peptides with amino acid sequences in a protein database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Eng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Soc. Mass Spectrom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="976" to="989" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comet: an open-source MS/MS sequence database search tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Eng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modes of inference for evaluating the confidence of peptide identifications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Fitzgibbon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open mass spectrometry search algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Geer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="958" to="964" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assigning significance to peptides identified by tandem mass spectrometry using decoy databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Kall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proteogenomic analysis of Bradyrhizobium japonicum USDA110 using Genosuite, an automated multi-algorithmic pipeline</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Kumar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell Proteomics, [Epub ahead of print</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-07-23" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A refined method to calculate false discovery rates for peptide identification using decoy databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Navarro</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Vazquez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1792" to="1796" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probability-based protein identification by searching sequence databases using mass spectrometry data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Perkins</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electrophoresis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3551" to="3567" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MyriMatch: highly accurate tandem mass spectral peptide identification by multivariate hypergeometric analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Tabb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="654" to="661" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FDRAnalysis: a tool for the integrated analysis of tandem mass spectrometry identification results from multiple search engines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Wedge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2088" to="2094" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic analysis of eluted fraction of plasma post immunoaffinity depletion: implications in biomarker discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Yadav</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24442</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MassWiz: a novel scoring algorithm with target-decoy based analysis pipeline for tandem mass spectrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Yadav</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2154" to="2160" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning from decoys to improve the sensitivity and specificity of proteomics database search results</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Yadav</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50651</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>