
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics Protein Peeling 3D: new tools for analyzing protein structures</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jean-Christophe</forename>
								<surname>Gelly</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dynamique des Structures et Interactions des Macromolécules Biologiques</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">INSERM UMR-S 665</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Paris Diderot-Paris 7</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Institut National de la Transfusion Sanguine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>6, rue Alexandre Cabanel</addrLine>
									<postCode>75739, Cedex 15</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alexandre</forename>
								<forename type="middle">G</forename>
								<surname>De Brevern</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dynamique des Structures et Interactions des Macromolécules Biologiques</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">INSERM UMR-S 665</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Paris Diderot-Paris 7</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Institut National de la Transfusion Sanguine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>6, rue Alexandre Cabanel</addrLine>
									<postCode>75739, Cedex 15</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics Protein Peeling 3D: new tools for analyzing protein structures</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="132" to="133"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq610</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 31, 2010; revised on October 20, 2010; accepted on October 21, 2010</note>
					<note>Page: 132 132–133 Associate Editor: Burkhard Rost</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present an improved version of our Protein Peeling web server dedicated to the analysis of protein structure architecture through the identification of protein units produced by an iterative splitting algorithm. New features include identification of structural domains, detection of unstructured terminal elements and evaluation of the stability of protein unit structures. Availability: The website is free and open to all users with no login requirements at http://www.dsimb.inserm.fr/dsimb-tools/</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Analyzing the architecture and organization of protein structures is essential for understanding protein flexibility, folding, functions and interactions. We previously proposed an innovative representation of protein architecture that gives a detailed description of protein structure anatomy. Proteins are split into sets of compact subregions, called protein units (PUs). A PU corresponds to one sequence fragment characterized by a high number of intra-PU contacts and a low number of inter-PU contacts. Contact probabilities between residues are computed as distances between Cα atoms using a logistic function. Using this contact probability matrix and an optimization procedure based on Matthews's correlation coefficient (MCC) between submatrices, the algorithm defines optimal cutting points that separate the region examined into two or three PUs. This methodology is called Protein Peeling (PP) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Gelly et al., 2006a</ref>). The process is iterated until the compactness of the PUs reaches a given limit. An index assesses the compactness quality and relative independence of each PU. PUs bridge the representation and description gap between secondary structures and structural domains. PP is a useful tool for better understanding and analyzing the organization of protein structures. The PP 2 web server (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Gelly et al., 2006b</ref>) has been developed to accommodate advanced parameters. Here, we present a new version of our PP web server that offers substantial improvements and new features: recognition of unstructured N-or C-terminal segments, a novel scoring function for PU characterization and identification of structural domains. * To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Unstructured extremity recognition</head><p>Unstructured N-or C-terminal segments can be problematic for protein analysis or molecular simulation. Using PP, this type of segment was observed in half of the protein structures found in Protein Data Bank (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Faure et al., 2009</ref>). We thus included a new assignment method in the web server. A PU is considered unstructured if it is isolated at the first cutting event and never thereafter.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Energy calculation</head><p>PUs show a wide range of shapes and many differences in the type or density of internal contacts. These characteristics are related to internal energy. To evaluate stability and contact energy, we implemented the DOPE statistical potential (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Shen and Sali, 2006</ref>) to compute the pseudo-energy of PUs. This value gives an approximation of the internal energy of PUs and insight on the structural significance of observed PUs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Structural domain identification</head><p>One major potential for the PP web server was the possibility to use the PP method to identify protein domains. We, therefore, developed a new algorithm called domain reconstruction (DR). The identification process includes two steps: (i) PUs are isolated using the basic PP top-down induction approach and (ii) PUs obtained at the final level of PP are assembled using the DR algorithm with a bottom-up strategy, similar to hierarchical agglomerative clustering, as follows. Starting from the final PU set, the algorithm combines each, unique PU to another PU at each recursive step. Thus, PUs are gradually merged at each step, forming many possible domain delineations. The best merging events are chosen among all the possible events according to the contact ratio (CR) criterion, derived from the Protein Domain Parser method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alexandrov and Shindyalov, 2003</ref>). This criterion is based on contact probability matrix computed in PP and helps estimate the quality of merging events. The CR criterion measured for PUs i and j is</p><formula>CR = cp(i,j)/S(i) a ×S(j) a c(ij)×S(ij)</formula><formula>(1)</formula><p>where cp(i, j) is contact probability between PU i and PU j , S(i) and S(j) are the length of PU i and PU j. Finally, c(ij) and S(ij) are, respectively, the contact probability and the size of the whole domain formed by merging PU i and PU j. The α value is 0.43 as in the PDP method. High CR values indicate a high number of contacts between PU i and PU j ; consequently, theses PUs are good candidates for merging them into one domain. During the process, a second measure, the average contact probability density (CPD), also used in other method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Holm and Sander, 1994</ref>), is computed to estimate the quality of newly formed domains. The assembly routine is reiterated and the number of domains gradually decreases until all PUs are merged into a unique domain corresponding to the whole protein. After producing different levels of potential domain delineation, a postprocessing step is launched to examine and choose the best domaindelineations. First, domain partitions at each level are sorted according to the mean CPD of domain delineation. Second, starting from the highest level, i.e. the full protein, each level is examined and accepted or not, according to a criterion that combines both the minimum CPD measured between domains and the maximum CR measured among all domains. Domains with a size of less than 30 are discarded. The criterion combining CR and CPD and the domain size threshold were optimized in a leave-one-out experiment on a published benchmark dataset of protein domains (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Jones et al., 1998</ref>). This experiment led to 82% of similar domain delineations, based on the same performance measurement method as<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Jones et al. (1998)</ref>. It has been demonstrated that human expert and automatic methods often show discrepancies in the number and minimal size of domains, presence or absence of fragments within domains and domain boundaries (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Day et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Veretnik and Shindyalov, 2007</ref>). Results of different human expert may even disagree, leading to unclear and sometimes ambiguous principles of domain partitioning. To overcome the difficulties raised by these studies, our DR algorithm can propose alternative domain partitions. Thus, different levels of partitioning and consequently different sizes and complexities of the resulting domains are produced by the DR algorithm. This results in broader and more flexible definition of structural domains (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). Considering alternative domain delineations increases the rate of agreement on<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Jones et al. (1998)</ref>benchmark dataset to 95% for an average of five alternative propositions and to 98% for 15 alternative propositions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">SERVER</head><p>Given the 3D coordinates of a protein, the server is able to identify PUs, domain delineations, and, if they exist, unstructured extremities. The server also provides some analysis on isolated PUs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Input</head><p>PP 3D only accepts protein structure in PDB file format (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Berman et al., 2000</ref>). The file is checked (to verify consistency of the format), cleaned (alternative positions are removed and non-standard residues are renamed) and renumbered. In multi-protein chain files, only the first chain is treated. Various parameters can be adjusted, such as parameters that direct cutting, those used for calculating the contact probability map and that only regular secondary structures should be taken into account.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Output and graphics</head><p>Many graphics and raw output files are available through the web server at the end of process. The graphical results include the contact probability map, different representations of protein structures in which PUs or domains can be easily identified by color, and representations of primary structure, in which PUs and domains are colored and clearly delimited.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Comparison between two delineations (A) and (B) of actin (PDB code: 1atnA) using DR. Delineation (A) is identical to SCOP (Murzin et al., 1995) and (B) is identical to the one determined in Jones et al. (1998) benchmark dataset.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: French Ministry of Research, Université Paris DiderotParis 7; National Institute for Blood Transfusion (INTS); National Institute for Health and Medical Research (INSERM); Orchid Partenariat Hubert Curien. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PDP: protein domain parser</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Alexandrov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Shindyalov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="429" to="430" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Protein Data Bank</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Berman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A consensus view of fold space: combining SCOP, CATH, and the Dali Domain Dictionary</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Day</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2150" to="2160" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of protein contacts into protein units</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Faure</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochimie</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="876" to="887" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein Peeling&apos;: an approach for splitting a 3D protein structure into compact fragments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Gelly</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein Peeling 2: a web server to convert protein structures into series of protein units</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Gelly</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parser for protein folding units</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Holm</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Sander</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="256" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Domain assignment for protein structures using a consensus approach: characterization and analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SCOP: a structural classification of proteins database for the investigation of sequences and structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Murzin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">247</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="536" to="540" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical potential for assessment and prediction of protein structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Shen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Sali</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2507" to="2524" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational methods for domain partitioning of protein structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Veretnik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Shindyalov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computational Methods for Protein Structure Prediction and Modeling</title>
		<editor>Xu,Y., Xu,D. and Liang,J.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="145" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>