
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining PUGSVM: a caBIG TM analytical tool for multiclass gene selection and predictive classification</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Guoqiang</forename>
								<surname>Yu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Bradley Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>22203</postCode>
									<settlement>Arlington</settlement>
									<region>VA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Huai</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Bioinformatics Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">RRB</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Institute on Aging</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">NIH</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21224</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sook</forename>
								<surname>Ha</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Bradley Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>22203</postCode>
									<settlement>Arlington</settlement>
									<region>VA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ie-Ming</forename>
								<surname>Shih</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pathology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Oncology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21231</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Robert</forename>
								<surname>Clarke</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Oncology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Lombardi Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Georgetown University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20057</postCode>
									<settlement>Washington</settlement>
									<region>DC</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eric</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Hoffman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Research Center for Genetic Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Children&apos;s National Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20010</postCode>
									<settlement>Washington</settlement>
									<region>DC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Subha</forename>
								<surname>Madhavan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Oncology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Lombardi Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Georgetown University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20057</postCode>
									<settlement>Washington</settlement>
									<region>DC</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jianhua</forename>
								<surname>Xuan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Bradley Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>22203</postCode>
									<settlement>Arlington</settlement>
									<region>VA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yue</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Bradley Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>22203</postCode>
									<settlement>Arlington</settlement>
									<region>VA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining PUGSVM: a caBIG TM analytical tool for multiclass gene selection and predictive classification</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="736" to="738"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq721</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on November 2, 2010; revised on December 19, 2010; accepted on December 20, 2010</note>
					<note>[18:13 17/2/2011 Bioinformatics-btq721.tex] Page: 736 736–738 Associate Editor: John Quackenbush Contact: yuewang@vt.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Phenotypic Up-regulated Gene Support Vector Machine (PUGSVM) is a cancer Biomedical Informatics Grid (caBIG TM) analytical tool for multiclass gene selection and classification. PUGSVM addresses the problem of imbalanced class separability, small sample size and high gene space dimensionality, where multiclass gene markers are defined by the union of one-versus-everyone phenotypic upregulated genes, and used by a well-matched one-versus-rest support vector machine. PUGSVM provides a simple yet more accurate strategy to identify statistically reproducible mechanistic marker genes for characterization of heterogeneous diseases.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Microarray gene expression studies provide new opportunities for the molecular characterization of heterogeneous diseases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Clarke et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Wang et al., 2008</ref>). Multiclass gene selection is an imperative task for identifying phenotype-associated mechanistic genes and achieving accurate diagnostic classifications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Liu et al., 2002</ref>). Most existing multiclass gene selection methods heavily rely on the direct extensions of two-class gene selection methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dudoit et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Golub et al., 1999</ref>). However, simple extensions of binary discriminant analysis to multiclass gene selection are suboptimal and not well matched to the unique characteristics of a multicategory classification problem. Specifically, the existing methods will select gene subsets that preserve the distances of well-separated classes, while likely create error-prone large overlap between neighboring classes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Loog et al., 2001</ref>). In Phenotypic Up-regulated Gene Support Vector Machine (PUGSVM; see schematic flowchart and mathematic descriptions * To whom correspondence should be addressed. of the method in the Supplementary Material) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Yu et al., 2010</ref>), we select genes that are highly expressed in one phenotype relative to each of the remaining phenotypes, namely One-Versus-Everyone Phenotypic Up-regulated Genes (OVEPUG). OVEPUG provides evenhanded gene resources for discriminating both neighboring and well-separated classes, and intends to assure the statistical reproducibility and biological plausibility of the selected genes. OVEPUG is well suited for small sample size problems (a concern with many current microarray datasets). We also implement other competing peer methods for multiclass gene selection, including signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Golub et al., 1999</ref>), t statistic (t-stat) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Liu et al., 2002</ref>), pooled ratio of between-groups to withingroups sum of squares (BW) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dudoit et al., 2002</ref>) and SVM-based recursive feature elimination (SVMRFE) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Li and Yang, 2005</ref>). In the classification component of PUGSVM, we implement the OVRSVM committee classifier, which has proved highly successful in multicategory classifications with finite or limited amounts of high-dimensional data in real-world applications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Rifkin and Klautau, 2002</ref>). We also include several other popular multicategory classifiers, including k nearest neighborhood (kNN) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Golub et al., 1999</ref>), naïve Bayes classifier (NBC) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Liu et al., 2002</ref>) and OVOSVM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Liu et al., 2005</ref>). PUGSVM was developed through the caBIG (cabig.nci.nih.gov) In Silico Research Centers of Excellence (ISRCE) effort, and offers users across the broader cancer research community a unique yet effective tool for identifying multiclass gene markers and predicting clinical outcomes in cancer treatment. PUGSVM is an open-source software package. The Java and Matlab codes and documents are freely available at the authors' web site, enabling users to easily modify the program and add new functions or extensions (http://www.cbil.ece.vt.edu/caBIG-PUGSVM.htm).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">DESCRIPTION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Software</head><p>The components of PUGSVM and their input/output relationships are illustrated in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. We use caBIG existing tools to load, preprocess and normalize gene expression data from in-house (i.e. Georgetown Database of Cancer; GDOC) or public databases(e.g. caArray, TCGA). The processed data with class labeling are fed to the gene selection component. The selected PUGs are then used to train and test the classifiers for predictive classification. The output of PUGSVM is a set of gene markers with generalizable performance. The OVEPUG and other algorithms in the gene selection component are implemented in Matlab. We use Matlab compiler to generate C++ shared function libraries. The OVRSVM algorithm and other classifiers are implemented in C++ with simple calling interfaces. The user interface is implemented in Java, and C++ shared libraries are called from Java using the Java Native Interface. PUGSVM has been tested on Microsoft Windows and Linux platforms. Users can run PUGSVM directly on a computer without an installed version of MATLAB.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Case study</head><p>We applied PUGSVM on the benchmark Global Cancer Map dataset (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ramaswamy et al., 2001</ref>) that is widely used for evaluating multicategory classification algorithms. Besides OVRSVM coupled with OVEPUGs, the combinations of competing gene selection methods (SNR, t-stat, BW and SVMRFE) with OVRSVM are also tested for comparisons.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>shows that OVEPUGs significantly improves the overall multicategory classification compared to all other combinations. Furthermore, gene markers selected by PUGSVM are confirmed to be important tumor-associated genes by literature survey and our domain experts. For example, the top 10 PUGs associated with prostate cancer include several genes strongly associated with prostate cancer including prostate-specific antigen and its alternatively spliced form 2 and prostatic secretory protein 57. Estrogen receptor α (ESR1), a PUG marker for uterine cancer, is known to be overexpressed in human uterine cancer, and the Hox7 gene, another PUG marker, is known to contribute to uterine function in cow and mouse models, especially at the onset of pregnancy. Norway AScites (NAS) dataset is a unique dataset with samples taken from ascites. We applied PUGSVM on NAS data and obtained a significantly improved classification performance than competing methods as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>. Several top-ranking gene products identified by OVEPUG have been well established as tumor-type specific markers and many of them have been used in clinical diagnosis. For example, mucin 16, also known as CA125, is a food and drug administration (FDA)-approved serum marker to monitor disease progression and recurrence in ovarian cancer patients. Fattyacid synthase (FASN) is often upregulated in breast cancer and this enzyme is amenable for drug targeting using FASN inhibitors, suggesting that it can be used as a therapeutic target in breast cancer. Additional case studies on the Human Ovarian Tumors, National Cancer Institute 60 cancer cell lines dataset, University of Michigan cancer dataset, Central Nervous System tumors and Muscular Dystrophy dataset can be found in the Supplementary Material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DISCUSSION</head><p>PUGSVM is a comprehensive open-source tool that consists of interconnected components for multiclass gene selection and predictive classification. The core algorithms in the package are OVEPUG and OVRSVM, which address several critical yet subtle issues in molecular characterization of heterogeneous diseases for both biological research and clinical applications. PUGSVM emphasizes the statistical reproducibility of the selected gene markers under small sample size, supported by their biologically plausible interpretations. Several competing gene selection and classification methods are also incorporated into the package to demonstrate the superior performance of PUGSVM via objective comparisons. Through the caBIG ISRCE effort, we plan to adapt PUGSVM to identify gene markers as druggable targets and predict breast cancer resistance and recurrence after tamoxifen treatment. We have established several workflow pipelines for using PUGSVM. For example, we first download breast cancer gene expression datasets from TCGA and G-DOC, and then normalize and label the data using caBIG tools, such as GenePattern. We feed the processed data to PUGSVM. The gene candidates identified by PUGSVM will be sent to VIsual Statistical Data Analyzer for visualization, mapping onto known signaling pathways and further analysis. We are currently working to create Taverna workflow modules for all analyses and making them publicly available to the cancer community.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The components and input/output of PUGSVM.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Illustration of PUG scheme (left) and the classification error rates with different gene selection methods on three datasets (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: This work is supported in part by the National Institutes of Health, under Contract No. HHSN261200800001E and Grants CA109872, CA149147, CA139246, NS029525. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>btq721. .tex]</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="736" to="738" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Yu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">REFERENCES</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The properties of high-dimensional data spaces: implications for exploring gene and protein expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Clarke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of discrimination methods for the classification of tumors using gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Dudoit</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular classification of cancer: class discovery and class prediction by gene expression monitoring</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Golub</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">286</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="531" to="537" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of recursive gene selection approaches from microarray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3741" to="3747" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparative study on feature selection and classification methods using gene expression profiles and proteomic patterns</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiclass cancer classification and biomarker discovery using GA-based algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2691" to="2697" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiclass linear dimension reduction by weighted pairwise Fisher criteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Loog</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="762" to="766" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiclass cancer diagnosis using tumor gene expression signatures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15149" to="15154" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In defense of one-vs-all classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Rifkin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Klautau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mach. Learn. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approaches to working in high-dimensional data spaces: gene expression microarrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br. J. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1023" to="1028" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Matched gene selection and committee classifier for molecular classification of heterogeneous diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Yu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mach. Learn. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2141" to="2167" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>