
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:47+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Quantifying uniformity of mapped reads</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">20 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Valerie</forename>
								<surname>Hower</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Richard</forename>
								<surname>Starfield</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Environmental Science</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Adam</forename>
								<surname>Roberts</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lior</forename>
								<surname>Pachter</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular and Cell Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>California</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Miami</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>33146</postCode>
									<settlement>Coral Gables</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Quantifying uniformity of mapped reads</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2680" to="2682"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">20 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts451</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on September 20, 2012; revised on July 4, 2012; accepted on July 5, 2012</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE Associate Editor: Martin Bishop Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We describe a tool for quantifying the uniformity of mapped reads in high-throughput sequencing experiments. Our statistic directly measures the uniformity of both read position and fragment length, and we explain how to compute a P-value that can be used to quantify biases arising from experimental protocols and mapping procedures. Our method is useful for comparing different protocols in experiments such as RNA-Seq. Availability and implementation: We provide a freely available and open source python script that can be used to analyze raw read data or reads mapped to transcripts in BAM format at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>In biological experiments, controlling the quality of data is fundamental to the reliability and reproducibility of the results. Quality control is especially important in modern sequencing experiments, where small biases in the preparation of DNA libraries can be amplified in the subsequent sequencing steps which typically yield millions of reads. Sequenced reads ideally represent fragments sampled uniformly at random from a library, and expected coverage statistics can be obtained from the classic Lander–Waterman model Lander and<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Waterman (1988)</ref>. However, a key aspect of current experiments is variable fragment length, requiring the extension of the Lander– Waterman model to account for random fragment position as well as length. Such a generalization was described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Evans et al. (2010)</ref>where it was shown that the data from a sequencing experiment can be modeled by a two-dimensional spatial Poisson process. We present a statistical test for uniformity in the reads of a sequencing experiment based on this idea and show how it can be used to compare multiple sets of reads in order to assess different protocols. Our test requires the alignment of paired-end reads to a reference transcriptome so that fragment positions and lengths can be determined. Fortunately, such alignments are routinely produced after sequencing experiments, so that our test can easily be incorporated into sequencing analysis pipelines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>An aligned read can be represented as an integer point in R 2 as follows: The 't-coordinate' corresponding to the read is its left-end point while the 'l-coordinate' is the length of the fragment. In<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Evans et al. (2010)</ref>, it is shown that for any choice of fragment length distribution, the collection of points f(t, l)} from a sequencing experiment forms a two-dimensional Poisson process. This principle guides our further analysis of these points f(t, l)}, as we test for uniformity in both the t and l coordinates. The output of ReadSpy is a list of test statistics and P-values for each transcript. A statistically significant (low) P-value means we reject the fact that the dataset is uniform on that transcript. Thus, a higher P-value corresponds to a set of reads sampled uniformly, which is desired. In the next two sections, we describe the statistical test applied a each transcript. The test is formulated in terms of the genomic segment<ref type="bibr">[a, b]</ref>. We handle ambiguous reads in ReadSpy by first reporting all possible alignments, using eXpress Roberts and Pachter (Submitted for publication) (http://bio.math.berkeley.edu/eXpress/) to assign a probability to each alignment and then selecting one t-value per fragment according to the observed probabilities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Hypothesis test for dataset</head><p>First, we describe the statistical test for a set of aligned reads from one sequencing experiment. The (t, l) coordinates corresponding to reads aligned to<ref type="bibr">[a, b]</ref>satisfy t ! a and t þ l b:</p><p>We define shifted coordinates in the (x, y)-plane as follows:</p><formula>x ¼ t À a b À l À a and y ¼ l:</formula><p>The new point set S of transformed datapoints satisfies x 2 ½0; 1; y 2 ½0; 1Þ and is still homogeneous along the x-axis. We use a simple 2 statistic to test this partial homogeneity assumption using test constants C and D. First, we partition the points into horizontal strips</p><formula>H k ¼ fðx i ; y i Þ 2 Sjb kÀ1 5y i b k g;</formula><p>where À1 ¼ b 0 5b 1 5b 2 5.. .5b m ¼ 1 and the boundaries b k are chosen such that each jH k j ! C. Next, we ignore the y-coordinates within each strip and test the uniformity of the x coordinates. We divide the interval<ref type="bibr">[0,</ref><ref type="bibr">1]</ref>into D subintervals and define O kj ¼ jfðx; yÞ 2 H k jðj À 1Þ=D5x j=Dgj:</p><p>If the original point set forms a spatial Poisson process, then</p><formula>T k ¼ X d j¼1 ðO kj À E k Þ 2 =E k $ 2 DÀ1 ;</formula><p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p><p>where E k ¼ jHkj D. Since all T k s come from mutually independent strips, we have</p><formula>X m k¼1 T k $ 2 mDÀm :</formula><p>This allows us to calculate a P-value for the collection of aligned reads. This value may vary depending on the choice of constants C and D—a reasonable choice seems to be C ¼ 200 and D ¼ 20.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 1</ref>shows the aligned reads for two yeast genes both in the (t, l)-plane and the (x,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Comparing multiple datasets</head><p>Assume we want to compare multiple sets of reads aligned to the same genomic interval<ref type="bibr">[a, b]</ref>. Since the P-value of the above test depends on how the plane is divided into strips, the boundaries b k are chosen to be the same across all the transformed point sets S i ; i ¼ 1;. .. ; n. We impose the requirement that for each point set S i , the horizontal strip H k ðiÞ contains at least C points. The resulting H k ðiÞs are then subsampled to produce H 0 k ðiÞ such that for all i, we have jH 0 k ðiÞj ¼ min j¼1;...;n jH k ðjÞj:</p><p>We then apply our statistical test to each point set S i using the horizontal strips H 0 k ðiÞ with vertical subdivisions given by the constant D as above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>We applied our statistical test to examine a variety of popular RNA-Seq protocols. Using data analyzed in<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Levin et al. (2010)</ref>, we compare seven paired-end methods on 1464 transcripts in the yeast genome. Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>gives transcriptby-transcript summary statistics for the log probabilities. There are multiple criteria for selecting an RNA-Seq protocal, but using ReadSpy we find that the dUTP protocol is statistically most random—meaning least biased—which agrees with<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Levin et al. (2010)</ref>. Additionally, we make pairwise comparisons between the methods, which can be found in Supplementary Table S2. For each pair, the binomial test addresses statistically whether or not one method 'wins' on more often than the other. The P-values for this test are also listed in Supplementary Table S2. Our findings mostly agree with the results of<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Levin et al. (2010)</ref>; however, our method illustrates the variability in sequence uniformity among genes. For instance,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 1</ref>gives the point sets for dUTP protocol and two yeast genes: YDR007W (in A) and YJL078C (in B). When comparing all seven methods, dUTP achieved p ¼ 1:2e À 19 for YJL140W and p ¼ .27 for YKL041W. A low P-value indicates that the reads aligning to the transcript are not uniform, which is undesirable. One can visually see the difference in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 1</ref>between non-random (in A) and random (in B).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>y)plane. We also depict the vertical and horizontal grids for C ¼ 200 and D ¼ 20. The raw reads come from an RNA-Seq experiment using the dUTP protocol Levin et al. (2010) and were aligned to the yeast genome using Bowtie Langmead et al. (2009) using the '-X 600-aS-n 3-e 100' option.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: V.H. was funded in part by NSF fellowship DMS-0902723. A.R and L.P. were funded in part by NIH R01 HG006129. A.R. was also funded in part by an NSF graduate research fellowship.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. An illustration of the method. Fragments aligning to the Yeast genes YJL140W (A) and YKL041W (B) using dUTP protocol for RNA-Seq are depicted before (t, l-coordinates) and after (x, y-coordinates) our transformation. The horizontal boundaries in the (x, y)-plane are selected by requiring at least C ¼ 200 points fall in each subdivision while the D ¼ 20 vertical subdivisions are equally spaced. When comparing the these dUTP data sets to those from other RNA-Seq protocols, the point set in A is highly biased with a p-value of 1.2eÀ19 while B appears to be a random collection of points (p ¼ 0.27)</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of The Society for Financial Studies. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions.com. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coverage statistics for sequence census methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Evans</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">430</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic mapping by fingerprinting random clones: a mathematical analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Lander</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Waterman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="239" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Langmead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive comparative analysis of strand-specific RNA sequencing methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Z</forename>
				<surname>Levin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Meth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="709" to="715" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Hower</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>