
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:44+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies RamiGO: an R/Bioconductor package providing an AmiGO Visualize interface</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Markus</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Schrö Der</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Biomolecular and Biomedical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Conway Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University College Dublin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Dublin 4</addrLine>
									<settlement>Belfield</settlement>
									<country key="IE">Ireland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biostatistics and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02215</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Daniel</forename>
								<surname>Gusenleitner</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biostatistics and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02215</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Boston University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02215</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<surname>Quackenbush</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biostatistics and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02215</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Cancer Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02215</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02215</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Aedín</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Culhane</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biostatistics and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02215</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02215</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Benjamin</forename>
								<surname>Haibe-Kains</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Bioinformatics and Computational Genomics Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Institut de recherches cliniques de Montré al</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>H2W 1R7</postCode>
									<settlement>Montreal</settlement>
									<region>Quebec</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies RamiGO: an R/Bioconductor package providing an AmiGO Visualize interface</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="666" to="668"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts708</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 24, 2012; revised on December 10, 2012; accepted on December 12, 2012</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Martin Bishop Contact: markus.schroeder@ucdconnect.ie Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The R/Bioconductor package RamiGO is an R interface to AmiGO that enables visualization of Gene Ontology (GO) trees. Given a list of GO terms, RamiGO uses the AmiGO visualize API to import Graphviz-DOT format files into R, and export these either as images (SVG, PNG) or into Cytoscape for extended network analyses. RamiGO provides easy customization of annotation, highlighting of specific GO terms, colouring of terms by P-value or export of a simplified summary GO tree. We illustrate RamiGO functionalities in a genome-wide gene set analysis of prognostic genes in breast cancer. Availability and implementation: RamiGO is provided in R/Biocon-ductor, is open source under the Artistic-2.0 License and is available with a user manual containing installation, operating instructions and tutorials. It requires R version 2.15.0 or higher.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">USING THE RAMIGO PACKAGE</head><p>The main functions within the RamiGO package are as follows: getAmigoTree(goIDs,color,filename,picType) readAmigoDot(object,filename) AmigoDot.to.<ref type="bibr">Cyto(object)</ref>which retrieve a GO tree from AmiGO Visualize in the preferred format type, read Graphviz-DOT format files and communicate with Cytoscape, respectively. The AmigoDot.to.Cyto() function displays the tree from an AmigoDot object in Cytoscape using the RCytoscape package. RCytoscape requires the Cytoscape plugin CytoscapeRPC, and the installation of this is described *To whom correspondence should be addressed. yThe authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the last two authors should be regarded as joint Last Authors. in more detail in the RCytoscape manual. Additional functions to convert the AmigoDot S4 objects to graphAM and graphNEL formats are also provided (AmigoDot.to.graphAM, AmigoDot.to.graphNEL).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">AN EXAMPLE</head><p>To showcase an analysis pipeline (Supplementary Material) that integrates the RamiGO package, we used the Bioconductor data package breastCancerVDX, which includes Affymetrix Human U133A microarray profiles from 344 breast cancer patients (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Wang et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Minn et al., 2007</ref>). We ranked the genes based on their prognostic value by computing the concordance index to estimate the association of each gene with distant metastasis-free survival using the package survcomp (Schro¨der<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Schro¨der et al., 2011</ref>). This ranked list was then used to run a pre-ranked Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>), using the C5 (GO) subset of the Molecular Signature Database (v3.0) gene sets (http://broadinstitute.org/gsea/ msigdb/collections.jsp).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>shows a subset of the GO cellular component gene sets that were reported with a false discovery rate 50.15. Using the customized colouring option in RamiGO, the nodes for gene sets with a positive Normalized Enrichment Score (NES) are red and nodes for gene sets with a negative NES are blue. The clustering of red and blue nodes is clearly visible and would have been missed when only looking at the GO gene set terms alone.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>shows the PNG image file of the tree from AmiGO Visualize. By changing the picType parameter of the getAmigoTree() function, we can also specify SVG and DOT for the requested file type or it can be viewed in Cytoscape by exporting AmigoDot object using AmigoDot.to.Cyto (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>The R/Bioconductor package RamiGO provides an easy-to-use R interface to the AmiGO Visualize web server. It provides a simple and elegant way to retrieve Graphviz trees that display hundreds of GO IDs at once and efficiently study clusters or subcomponents of the GO tree in graph form. RamiGO provides functions to convert a GO tree into different formats and display it in Cytoscape without leaving the R environment. RamiGO is therefore a perfect companion to GSEA and GO analyses in R, as it helps one better analyse and interpret the long, and sometimes complex, lists of GO identifiers that these analyses produce.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: This work was supported by the National Human Genome Research Institute (1P50 HG004233 to M.S.S.); Fulbright Commission for Educational Exchange to (B.H.-K.); US National Institutes of Health (#1U01CA151118-01A1 to J.Q., R01 LM010129-01 to B.H.-K. and J.Q.); Claudia Adams Barr Program in Innovative Basic Cancer Research (A.C.C. and</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Subset of GO terms (cellular component) reported from the pre-ranked GSEA analysis of the prognostic value of genes in the breastCancerVDX data with an FDR50.15. Red nodes represent GO terms with a positive NES, which show high expression of nuclear genes in high risk patients, whereas the blue nodes represent GO terms with a negative NES, which show loss of expression of membrane genes in low risk patients</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Cytoscape representation of the GO tree hierarchy from Figure 1</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> INTRODUCTION The Gene Ontology (GO) is a controlled vocabulary of gene annotation that was developed to provide consistent functional classification for genes across species; GO is also widely used in gene set enrichment analyses (Gene Ontology Consortium, 2012). It is organized as a directed acyclic graph with top-level ontologies molecular function, biological process and cellular component. Although several web-based or standalone tools are available for visualization of lists of GO terms as GO tree structures, these are not easily accessible through R/Bioconductor, where one has to either rebuild the GO tree using R packages such as GO.db or GOstats, or copy and paste the GO terms of interest into an external web service such as AmiGO Visualize (Carbon et al., 2009, http://amigo.geneontology.org) to display the GO tree. The free open source web application AmiGO provides users with access to ontology and gene annotation data. Visualization of the queried ontology data is provided by AmiGO Visualize, which uses Graphviz libraries to create GO trees. Graphviz is a collection of software for viewing and manipulating abstract graphs (Gansner and North, 2000). We developed RamiGO to provide R functions that connect directly with the AmiGO Visualize API and retrieve GO trees in various formats. The most common format being PNG or SVG image file, but a file representation of the GO tree in the Graphviz-DOT format is also possible. RamiGO provides a parser for the Graphviz-DOT format that returns an R S4 object, called AmigoDot, that includes (i) the tree as a graph object, (ii) the adjacency matrix of the tree, (iii) the annotation of the nodes, (iv) the relation between the nodes and (v) a list of the leaves of the tree. The GO tree is displayed with the set of input GO IDs and all parents of those GO IDs to the root of each GO category where relations between the nodes are represented using the same colour palette as AmiGO Visualize; green, red, black, blue and light blue represent &apos;positively regulates&apos;, &apos;negatively regulates&apos;, &apos;regulates&apos;, &apos;is a&apos; and &apos;part of&apos;, respectively. In addition using RamiGO, one can display and interactively modify GO tree colours, annotations and relationships between nodes in Cytoscape directly from R.</note>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">RamiGO at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.S.Schrö der et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Career Development grant from DFCI Breast Cancer SPORE: CA089393, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute Women&apos;s Cancer Program (to A.C.C)</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J.Q</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conflict of Interest: none declared AmiGO: online access to ontology and annotation data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">REFERENCES Carbon, Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="288" to="289" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Gene Ontology: enhancements for 2011</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gene Ontology Consortium. Nucleic Acids Res., Database Issue</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="559" to="564" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An open graph visualization system and its applications to software engineering. Software Practice and Experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Gansner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>North</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1203" to="1233" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lung metastasis genes couple breast tumor size and metastatic spread</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Aj</forename>
				<surname>Minn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6740" to="6745" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">survcomp: an R/Bioconductor package for performance assessment and comparison of survival models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Schro¨derschro¨der</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3206" to="3208" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Subramanian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15545" to="15550" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene-expression profiles to predict distant metastasis of lymph-node-negative primary breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">365</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="679" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>