
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:42+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Rchemcpp: a web service for structural analoging in ChEMBL, Drugbank and the Connectivity Map</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gü</forename>
								<surname>Nter Klambauer</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johannes Kepler University Linz</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Altenbergerstr. 69</addrLine>
									<postCode>4040</postCode>
									<settlement>Linz</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Martin</forename>
								<surname>Wischenbart</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johannes Kepler University Linz</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Altenbergerstr. 69</addrLine>
									<postCode>4040</postCode>
									<settlement>Linz</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<surname>Mahr</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johannes Kepler University Linz</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Altenbergerstr. 69</addrLine>
									<postCode>4040</postCode>
									<settlement>Linz</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
								<surname>Unterthiner</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johannes Kepler University Linz</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Altenbergerstr. 69</addrLine>
									<postCode>4040</postCode>
									<settlement>Linz</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andreas</forename>
								<surname>Mayr</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johannes Kepler University Linz</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Altenbergerstr. 69</addrLine>
									<postCode>4040</postCode>
									<settlement>Linz</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sepp</forename>
								<surname>Hochreiter</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johannes Kepler University Linz</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Altenbergerstr. 69</addrLine>
									<postCode>4040</postCode>
									<settlement>Linz</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Rchemcpp: a web service for structural analoging in ChEMBL, Drugbank and the Connectivity Map</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv373</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 11, 2015; revised on April 27, 2015; accepted on June 11, 2015</note>
					<note>Databases and ontologies *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Janet Kelso Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We have developed Rchempp, a web service that identifies structurally similar compounds (structural analogs) in large-scale molecule databases. The service allows compounds to be queried in the widely used ChEMBL, DrugBank and the Connectivity Map databases. Rchemcpp utilizes the best performing similarity functions, i.e. molecule kernels, as measures for structural similarity. Molecule kernels have proven superior performance over other similarity measures and are currently excelling at machine learning challenges. To considerably reduce computational time, and thereby make it feasible as a web service, a novel efficient prefiltering strategy has been developed, which maintains the sensitivity of the method. By exploiting information contained in public databases, the web service facilitates many applications crucial for the drug development process, such as prioritizing compounds after screening or reducing adverse side effects during late phases. Rchemcpp was used in the DeepTox pipeline that has won the Tox21 Data Challenge and is frequently used by researchers in pharmaceutical companies. Availability and implementation: The web service and the R package are freely available via</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>One strategy to remedy the steadily declining efficiency of the drug development process is to utilize the vast information on chemical compounds that is already present in public and internal databases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arrowsmith, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Scannell et al., 2012</ref>). To this end, compounds that are structurally similar to the current drug candidate have to be identified in public databases. This 'structural analoging' step can enhance the drug development process at different phases: After high-throughput screening, a number of compounds are selected, of which typically very little information about their biological effects is available. Querying these compounds in a database can yield similar compounds that have already been measured in various biological experiments and provide relevant information (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Klambauer et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Robert et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Rodriguez et al., 2005</ref>) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). This information can improve the drug development process at various stages and decreases the risk of late failures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Verbist et al., 2015</ref>). The best-performing similarity measures for identifying structurally similar compounds in a database are molecule kernels. Molecule kernels have been developed for similarity-based machine learning methods, such as Support Vector Machines, and their efficiency and precision have been demonstrated in various tasks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Mahé and Vert, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mahe (2005);</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Mohr et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ralaivola et al., 2005</ref>). The drawback of molecule kernels is that they are computationally demanding, since they consider all possible common substructures of a compound. To reach a query time of a few seconds, which is desired for web services, we have V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com developed a novel and computationally fast criterion that maintains the sensitivity of the molecule kernels. We have extensively tested the presented software in our computational pipeline for prediction of toxic effects of chemical compounds. This computational pipeline 'DeepTox' has won both the Tox21 Data Challenge (http://www.ncats.nih.gov/ news-and-events/features/tox21-challenge-winners.html) and the prediction of average cytotoxicity at the NIEHS-NCATS-UNC DREAM Toxicogenetics Challenge (https://www.synapse.org/ #!Synapse:syn2208373/wiki/). We provide a web service, called Rchemcpp, to identify structurally similar compounds in ChEMBL (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Gaulton et al., 2012</ref>), Drugbank (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Law et al., 2014</ref>) and the Connectivity Map (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Lamb et al., 2006</ref>). This provides researchers with various types of information about chemical compounds and thereby helps to prioritize structures and facilitates decisions based on biological measurements. Rchemcpp combines efficiently implemented molecule kernels with a new prefiltering strategy and offers a user-friendly interface to adjust the kernel parameters. Rchemcpp is a valuable tool for researchers in many areas in particular in drug design, toxicity prediction and cancer research. The web service Rchemcpp has many advantages over a programming library for molecule kernels. To use molecule kernels requires extensive programming efforts. Therefore, many researchers are restricted to database queries provided by the database interfaces, which are based on simple substructure searches. We provide molecule kernels as a hands-on tool for researchers of all areas and backgrounds. Furthermore, the preparation, curation and clean-up of the databases that is necessary for applying molecule kernels is included the Rchemcpp web service. Additionally, the problem of high computational power that restricts queries in the large databases such as the ChEMBL has been solved by our prefiltering strategy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>The method consists of computation of the molecule kernel and a prefiltering step for speeding up the calculations. For large databases, such as ChEMBL, a prefiltering step is necessary to identify structural analogs in reasonable time for a web service.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Molecule kernels</head><p>A molecule kernel is a function that maps two chemical compounds to a similarity value. The similarity measure is typically based on structural similarity, i.e. the number of substructures that occur in both compounds. If we consider two molecules X and Y, then the kernel K is:where P is the set of substructures, and the function N(p, X) counts how often the substructure p occurs in molecule graph X. The function N(p, X) is specific for the different kernel types (see Supplementary Section S4).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Prefiltering</head><p>For query compound X and each compound Y from the database, a small set of features is calculated in advance to make the comparison computationally fast. We investigated how this prefiltering strategy changes the result compared to a database query without prefiltering. With the prefiltering strategy, a speed-up is obtained that is necessary for a web service, while at the same, some highly similar molecules might be lost. We calculated how much the sensitivity of the method is decreased by filtering out a certain percentage of molecules from the database (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>): Overall, the decrease in sensitivity is small, e.g. when removing 99.5% of the compounds in the prefiltering step, i.e. a speed-up of 200-fold, still a sensitivity of 55% is kept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Example: a query compound</head><p>To illustrate our structural analoging approach, we use a query compound (left in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>), of which only the chemical structure is known. In the following, we show how to obtain information on this query compound using our novel web service Rchemcpp.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Biomolecular targets from CHEMBL</head><p>The query for structural analogs in ChEMBL, a database with 1 million molecules, provided compound 'CHEMBL57990' as the closest analog to our query compound (top in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). For this compound, ChEMBL reports strong inhibitory activity against the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR). This receptor is crucial for the proliferation of cancer cells. A compound with inhibitory activity against EGFR can be a potential drug for certain cancer types. All 10 closest structural analogs to the query compound are strong EGFR inhibitors (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>), therefore we can hypothesize that the query compound may act as an EGFR inhibitor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Gene expression signature from the Connectivity Map</head><p>When we identified the closest structural analogs from the Connectivity Map, gefitinib was ranked first, followed by a tyrphostin AG 1478, a compound named 'CP-645525-01' and amodiaquine (middle in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). From compounds with a similarity greater than 0.90, a gene expression signature was derived from the Connectivity Map data (see Supplementary Section S2). The gene expression data of the Connectivity Map were preprocessed with FARMS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Hochreiter et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Talloen et al., 2007</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Talloen et al., , 2010</ref>) and informative/non-informative (I/NI) calls (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Clevert et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hochreiter et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Hochreiter, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Klambauer et al., 2012</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Mechanism of action from Drugbank</head><p>The closest structural analogs in Drugbank are gefitinib, compounds with the identifiers DB03365, DB02984, DB02848 and erlotinib, the Connectivity Map (middle) and ChEMBL (top) that are similar to a query compound (left) are identified. Information on the biological effects of the analogs, like mechanism of action, gene expression and bioassay measurements, from these databases also characterize the query compound Rchemcpp(bottom in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). The Drugbank contains information on the mechanism of action of these compounds. The database reports that both gefitinib and erlotinib are marketed drugs for the treatment of certain tumor types. Both have EGFR as biomolecular target. For gefitinib, the mechanism of action is known: it binds to the ATPbinding site of EGFR, inactivates the Ras signal transduction cascade and thereby inhibits malignant cells. We have now obtained a second hint that the query compound may act as an EGFR inhibitor. In summary, we have acquired information about a query compound: bioassay measurements from ChEMBL, a potential gene expression signature from the Connectivity Map and a potential mechanism of action from Drugbank. The results indicate that the query compound could be an EGFR inhibitor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Structural analoging: compounds in Drugbank (bottom), the Connectivity Map (middle) and ChEMBL (top) that are similar to a query compound (left) are identified. Information on the biological effects of the analogs, like mechanism of action, gene expression and bioassay measurements, from these databases also characterize the query compound</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>This work was supported by the Institute for the Promotion of Innovation by Science and Technology in Flanders [IWT 135122]. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trial watch: phase III and submission failures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Arrowsmith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Drug Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2007" to="2010" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">cn.FARMS: a latent variable model to detect copy number variations in microarray data with a low false discovery rate</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D.-A</forename>
				<surname>Clevert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ChEMBL: a large-scale bioactivity database for drug discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Gaulton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1100" to="1107" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hapfabia: Identification of very short segments of identity by descent characterized by rare variants in large sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hochreiter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">202</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new summarization method for affymetrix probe level data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hochreiter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="943" to="949" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FABIA: factor analysis for bicluster acquisition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hochreiter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1520" to="1527" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2012) cn.MOPS: mixture of Poissons for discovering copy number variations in next-generation sequencing data with a low false discovery rate</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Klambauer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">69</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DEXUS: identifying differential expression in RNAseq studies with unknown conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Klambauer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="198" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Connectivity Map: using gene-expression signatures to connect small molecules, genes, and disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Lamb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="1929" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drugbank 4.0: shedding new light on drug metabolism</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Law</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1091" to="1097" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graph kernels based on tree patterns for molecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Mahé</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J.-P</forename>
				<surname>Vert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mach. Learn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graph kernels for molecular structure-activity relationship analysis with support vector machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Mahé</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="939" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A maximum common subgraph kernel method for predicting the chromosome aberration test</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Mohr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1821" to="1838" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graph kernels for chemical informatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Ralaivola</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neural Netw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1093" to="1110" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural analog of sildenafil identified as a novel corrector of the f508del-cftr trafficking defect</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Robert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="478" to="489" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A close structural analog of 2-methyl-6-(phenylethynyl)-pyridine acts as a neutral allosteric site ligand on metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5 and blocks the effects of multiple allosteric modulators</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Rodriguez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1793" to="1802" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diagnosing the decline in pharmaceutical r&amp;d efficiency</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Scannell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Drug Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">) I/NI-calls for the exclusion of non-informative genes: a highly effective filtering tool for microarray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Talloen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2897" to="2902" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Filtering data from high-throughput experiments based on measurement reliability</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Talloen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="174" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using transcriptomics to guide lead optimization in drug discovery projects: Lessons learned from the QSTAR project</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Verbist</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Drug Discov. Today</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="505" to="513" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>