
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis RRBSMAP: a fast, accurate and user-friendly alignment tool for reduced representation bisulfite sequencing</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yuanxin</forename>
								<surname>Xi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dan L Duncan Cancer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>One Baylor Plaza</addrLine>
									<postCode>77030</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christoph</forename>
								<surname>Bock</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Stem Cell and Regenerative Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02138</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Informatics</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Saarbrücken</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Fabian</forename>
								<surname>Müller</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Stem Cell and Regenerative Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02138</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Informatics</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Saarbrücken</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Deqiang</forename>
								<surname>Sun</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dan L Duncan Cancer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Baylor College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>One Baylor Plaza</addrLine>
									<postCode>77030</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alexander</forename>
								<surname>Meissner</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Stem Cell and Regenerative Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02138</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wei</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alex</forename>
								<surname>Bateman</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis RRBSMAP: a fast, accurate and user-friendly alignment tool for reduced representation bisulfite sequencing</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="430" to="432"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr668</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on September 2, 2011; revised on November 18, 2011; accepted on November 29, 2011</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: SD MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [13:49 31/12/2011 Bioinformatics-btr668.tex] Page: 430 430–432 Associate Editor: Contact: wl1@bcm.tmc.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Reduced representation bisulfite sequencing (RRBS) is a powerful yet cost-efficient method for studying DNA methylation on a genomic scale. RRBS involves restriction-enzyme digestion, bisulfite conversion and size selection, resulting in DNA sequencing data that require special bioinformatic handling. Here, we describe RRBSMAP, a short-read alignment tool that is designed for handling RRBS data in a user-friendly and scalable way. RRBSMAP uses wildcard alignment, and avoids the need for any preprocessing or post-processing steps. We benchmarked RRBSMAP against a well-validated MAQ-based pipeline for RRBS read alignment and observed similar accuracy but much improved runtime performance, easier handling and better scaling to large sample sets. In summary, RRBSMAP removes bioinformatic hurdles and reduces the computational burden of large-scale epigenome association studies performed with RRBS. Availability: http://rrbsmap.computational-epigenetics.org/</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>DNA methylation is an important mechanism of epigenetic regulation in development and disease. Many methods for DNA methylation profiling have been developed, but only bisulfite sequencing gives rise to comprehensive DNA methylation maps at single-base pair resolution (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Laird, 2010</ref>). Bisulfite treatment converts unmethylated cytosines (Cs) into uracils, which gives rise to C-to-T polymorphisms after subsequent Polymerase Chain Reaction amplification, while leaving methylated cytosines unchanged. By aligning and comparing bisulfite sequencing reads to the genomic DNA sequence, it is thus possible to infer base pair-resolution DNA methylation patterns. Bisulfite-converted DNA can be subjected to whole-genome resequencing, giving rise to comprehensive methylomes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Laurent et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Lister et al., 2009</ref>). However, this procedure requires deep sequencing of entire genomes, rendering it expensive in terms of sequencing cost as well as the required amount of input DNA. Reduced representation bisulfite sequencing (RRBS) addresses these limitations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gu et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Meissner 2005</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Meissner , 2008</ref>) and provides a complementary technology to whole-genome bisulfite sequencing. In RRBS, DNA is first digested with a restriction enzyme that includes a CpG in its recognition site and cuts DNA independent of the methylation status of this CpG. Subsequently, small DNA fragments are size selected to enrich for CpG-rich genomic regions (which are often associated with epigenetic regulation) and subjected to high-throughput bisulfite sequencing. By concentrating on a small but informative portion of the genome, RRBS provides high-sequencing depth at affordable cost, making RRBS well suited for detecting subtle differences in large patient cohorts. Furthermore, RRBS is readily applicable to small amounts of DNA and formal-fixed, paraffin-embedded samples (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gu et al., 2010</ref>). RRBS is actively used by a number of groups (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baranzini et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bock et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Gertz et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Smallwood et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Steine et al., 2011</ref>). To our knowledge, no alignment tools have been published that are tailored to RRBS data. Although some existing tools for bisulfite sequencing data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bock et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Chen et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Krueger and Andrews, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Li et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Lutsik et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Xi and Li, 2009</ref>) can also be applied to RRBS, doing so requires custom pre-and post-processing, thus limiting the accessibility of RRBS for researchers with limited bioinformatic support. Here we describe RRBSMAP, a short-read alignment tool that is specifically tailored to RRBS. We show that RRBSMAP provides a major advance in terms of runtime performance and usability compared to a well-validated MAQ-based pipeline, while maintaining high mapping accuracy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>In RRBS, only those DNA fragments that start and end with a restriction digestion site and fall within the range of experimental size selection are subjected to bisulfite sequencing. For example, MspI, the restriction enzyme most commonly used in RRBS, cuts the DNA at CCGG sites in a way that produces DNA fragments starting with CGG and ending with CCG after reestablishment<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Meissner et al., 2008</ref>). Depending on the methylation status of the Cs, several types of reads can be observed after bisulfite sequencing. RRBSMAP utilizes prior knowledge about the distribution of restriction digestion sites in the genome to significantly improve runtime performance and memory efficiency compared to whole-genome bisulfite alignment. Rather than building an alignment seed table for the entire genome, RRBSMAP indexes only those genomic regions that are compatible with the RRBS protocol parameters (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S1A</ref>). The bisulfite alignment is performed using a wildcard alignment algorithm originally developed for BSMAP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Xi and Li, 2009</ref>). The algorithm implements a bitwise mask to account for C-toT conversions introduced by bisulfite treatment (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S1B</ref>). It avoids aligning Ts in the reference to Cs in the reads, which is a common source for bias when converting all Cs to Ts first and then performing the three-nucleotide alignment (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S2</ref>). (Note that the post-processing step by which three-nucleotide bisulfite aligners remove incorrect alignments cannot completely resolve this issue because spurious hits could already have masked correct hits during the alignment step.) RRBSMAP implements many features that facilitate the routine handling of large RRBS datasets. First, RRBSMAP operates directly on BAM/SAM files as input and output, and it does not require any preprocessing or post-processing steps or temporary files, which makes it straightforward to run RRBSMAP as a part of large-scale sequencing pipelines. Second, RRBSMAP provides flexible options for trimming adapter sequences and low-quality nucleotides prior to alignment. Third, RRBSMAP allows the user to choose alternative restriction enzymes beyond the default MspI, providing flexibility to explore new bisulfite sequencing protocols. Fourth, RRBSMAP efficiently aligns both single-end and paired-end sequencing with flexible read lengths. Fifth, RRBSMAP fully supports multicore and multiprocessor hardware and lets the user specify how many threads should be run in parallel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>We compare RRBSMAP with a MAQ-based pipeline that has been extensively used in our previous studies. This pipeline involves five steps: (i) in silico digestion of the target genome and indexing of size-selected restriction fragments; (ii) conversion of BAM files into BFA files; (iii) alignment using the bisulfite alignment mode of MAQ (http://maq.sourceforge.net/); (iv) conversion of the MAP files into BAM files; and (v) coordinate mapping of the aligned reads to remove the effects of in silico digestion. This custom pipeline provides high accuracy, and we used it successfully in a number of publications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Carone et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gu et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Harris et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ock et al., 2010;</ref>. However, it is neither user-friendly nor easily portable and currently not publicly available. The comparison was performed on a total of nine RRBS libraries that were prepared from human embryonic stem cell DNA and sequenced on Illumina GAIIx (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S2</ref>). For pairs of biological replicates sequenced with 36bp single-ended reads (rows 1–6 in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S2</ref>), we observed equal consistency between replicates and equal bisulfite conversion rates, but slightly higher aligned read numbers and CpG coverage for RRBSMAP than for MAQ. The central processing unit (CPU) time was 5-fold lower and the actual (wall clock) time on a multicore processor node was 30-fold lower for RRBSMAP than for MAQ. The memory consumption of RRBSMAP was 3-fold lower than for MAQ. We also tested RRBSMAP and MAQ on technical replicates sequenced with 76 bp paired-end reads (rows 7–9 in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S2</ref>), which is a rarely used configuration for RRBS that we had not previously tested with the MAQ-based pipeline. Compared to 36 bp single-end, RRBSMAP almost doubles the CpG coverage that is achievable with RRBS, while not sacrificing accuracy or performance. In contrast, the MAQ-based pipeline does not work well for 76 bp paired-end reads, resulting in substantially lower alignment rates while maintaining high accuracy and consistency between replicates. In summary, RRBSMAP performs at least as well as an extensively validated MAQ-based pipeline on the key performance metrics of bisulfite sequencing, and it significantly outperforms the MAQbased pipeline in terms of runtime performance and in terms of genomic coverage for 76 bp paired-end reads. The performance of RRBSMAP is sufficient to process thousands of RRBS libraries, a situation that is become increasingly realistic as DNA methylation profiling follows genome-wide association studies and tackles large samples cohorts.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: SD MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [13:49 31/12/2011 Bioinformatics-btr668.tex] Page: 431 430–432 RRBSMAP of double-stranded DNA (</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: National Institutes of Health Roadmap Epigenomics (grant U01DA025956 to Y.X. and W.L.); (U01ES017155 to A.M.); Cancer Prevention and Research Institute of Texas (grant RP110471-C3 to Y.X. and W.L.); 973 project 2010CB944900 of China (to W.L.), in part; Pew Charitable Trusts (to A.M.); Feodor Lynen Fellowship (Alexander von Humboldt Foundation) and a Charles A. King Trust Postdoctoral Fellowship (Charles A. King Trust, N.A., Bank of America, Co-Trustee) (to C.B.). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors.</note>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome, epigenome and RNA sequences of monozygotic twins discordant for multiple sclerosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Baranzini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">464</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1351" to="1356" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BiQ Analyzer: visualization and quality control for DNA methylation data from bisulfite sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Bock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4067" to="4068" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative comparison of genome-wide DNA methylation mapping technologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Bock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1106" to="1114" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reference maps of human ES and iPS cell variation enable high-throughput characterization of pluripotent cell lines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Bock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">144</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="452" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Paternally induced transgenerational environmental reprogramming of metabolic gene expression in mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Carone</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1084" to="1096" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BS Seeker: precise mapping for bisulfite sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">203</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of DNA methylation in a three-generation family reveals widespread genetic influence on epigenetic regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Gertz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002228</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-scale DNA methylation mapping of clinical samples at single-nucleotide resolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Gu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preparation of reduced representation bisulfite sequencing libraries for genome-scale DNA methylation profiling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Gu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="468" to="481" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of sequencing-based methods to profile DNA methylation and identification of monoallelic epigenetic modifications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Harris</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1097" to="1105" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bismark: a flexible aligner and methylation caller for Bisulfite-Seq applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Krueger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Andrews</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1571" to="1572" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Principles and challenges of genome-wide DNA methylation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Laird</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic changes in the human methylome during differentiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Laurent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="320" to="331" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bioinformatics-btr668.tex] Page</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="80" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Xi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping short DNA sequencing reads and calling variants using mapping quality scores</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1851" to="1858" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human DNA methylomes at base resolution show widespread epigenomic differences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Lister</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">462</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BiQ Analyzer HT: locus-specific analysis of DNA methylation by high-throughput bisulfite sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Lutsik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="551" to="556" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reduced representation bisulfite sequencing for comparative high-resolution DNA methylation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Meissner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5868" to="5877" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-scale DNA methylation maps of pluripotent and differentiated cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Meissner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">454</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="766" to="770" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic CpG island methylation landscape in oocytes and preimplantation embryos</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Smallwood</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="811" to="814" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Updates to the RMAP short-read mapping software</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2841" to="2842" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-throughput bisulfite sequencing in mammalian genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="226" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genes methylated by DNA methyltransferase 3b are similar in mouse intestine and human colon cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Steine</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1748" to="1752" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BSMAP: whole genome bisulfite sequence MAPping program</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Xi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">232</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>