
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:39+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Seq2pathway: an R/Bioconductor package for pathway analysis of next-generation sequencing data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bin</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Section of Hematology/Oncology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Chicago</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Cunningham</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Section of Hematology/Oncology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Chicago</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xinan</forename>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Section of Hematology/Oncology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Chicago</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Holly</forename>
								<surname>Yang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Section of Hematology/Oncology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Chicago</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Seq2pathway: an R/Bioconductor package for pathway analysis of next-generation sequencing data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv289</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 4, 2015; revised on March 31, 2015; accepted on May 2, 2015</note>
					<note>Genome analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Inanc Birol Contact: xyang2@uchicago.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Seq2pathway is an R/Python wrapper for pathway (or functional gene-set) analysis of genomic loci, adapted for advances in genome research. Seq2pathway associates the biological significance of genomic loci with their target transcripts and then summarizes the quantified values on the gene-level into pathway scores. It is designed to isolate systematic disturbances and common biological underpinnings from next-generation sequencing (NGS) data. Seq2pathway offers Bioconductor users enhanced capability in discovering collective pathway effects caused by both coding genes and cis-regulation of non-coding elements. Availability and implementation: The package is freely available at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Functional gene-set analysis (fGSA) improves biological interpretability of genomic features with respect to prior knowledge and has led to important biological discoveries (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Khatri et al., 2012</ref>). Its power lies in the fact that it detects statistical significance over an entire dataset of gene-sets and yields biologically meaningful interpretations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>). Recently, researchers revealed driver pathways that predispose individuals to disease (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Vandin et al., 2012</ref>) and shed light on the development of targeted therapy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Gonzalez-Perez et al., 2013</ref>) by performing fGSA on genes proximal to significantly disease-associated loci. However, with the increasing growth of genomic sequencing measurements, noncoding regulatory loci pose a critical challenge to fGSA, as nearly 99% of the nucleotides in the human genome do not code for proteins but instead richly harbor functional regulators of genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kellis et al., 2014</ref>). 'Gene-based' fGSA methods neglect non-coding regulatory information because they have no readily annotated gene function and cannot be assigned to a specific biological pathway. For example, HOMER (Hypergeometric Optimization of Motif EnRichment), a popular tool for discovering cis-regulatory regions before any subsequent fGSA, links genomic loci to only the nearest genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Wang et al., 2011</ref>). Other fGSA algorithms take into account singlenucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) only located in or near coding genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Koster et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Nam et al., 2010</ref>) or exonic mutations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Boca et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Gonzalez-Perez et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Leiserson et al., 2013</ref>). 'Sequence-derived' fGSA regarding the functional impact of not only coding genes, but also non-coding regulators, is necessary. A growing body of evidence supports the strategy of connecting genomic loci and coding genes using a many-to-many mapping and considering long-distance cis-regulation. First, non-coding regions richly harbor functional regulatory elements in humans (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kellis et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Schierding et al., 2014</ref>). Second, nearly half of the diseaseassociated SNPs are located in gene deserts (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Visel et al., 2009</ref>). Third, our recent study suggests that a disease-associated SNP located in an intron could be the enhancer of a neighboring gene rather than of its host gene (van den<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Boogaard et al., 2014</ref>). The first sequence-derived fGSA method is GREAT (the Genomic Regions Enrichment of Annotations Tool) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">McLean et al., 2011</ref>). GREAT quantifies an fGSA score by determining if the total</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3043</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.number of loci within the regulatory domain of genes in a gene-set is greater than expected. The ChIP-Enrich method then empirically adjusts the length of the gene body and its surrounding non-coding sequence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Welch et al., 2014</ref>). However, both GREAT and ChIPEnrich treat all loci equally, despite the fact that a threshold for significance is always experimentally context-dependent and arbitrary. We propose a new sequence-derived fGSA tool named 'seq2pathway' that fills the non-coding region gap in fGSA by considering quantitative sequencing measurements. We initially developed FAIME (Functional Analysis of Individual Microarray/ RNAseq Expression) to compare the cumulative quantitative effects of genes inside an ontology (set of functionally related genes) with those outside, thus overcoming a number of difficulties in prior fGSA methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Yang et al., 2012</ref>). We here provide the community a Bioconductor package that (i) quantifies the functional impact of both coding genes and non-coding loci, (ii) generalizes four fGSA methods, including FAIME, to variable next-generation sequencing (NGS) data and (iii) wraps gene locus definitions for human and mouse genomes from the GENCODE project (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Harrow et al., 2012</ref>) into R objects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bioinformatics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Main features</head><p>Seq2pathway is designed for knowledge discovery using a variety of NGS data (e.g. ChIP-seq, RNA-seq, SNPs, etc) by taking the contribution of non-coding loci and their experimental significance scores into consideration. Users can apply the 'seq2pathway' function jointly, or in a two-step algorithm consisting of 'seq2gene' and 'gene2pathway' components separately (For workflow see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). The seq2gene step links both coding and non-coding regions to coding genes in a many-to-many mapping (For detailed Pseudo code see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Yang et al., 2015b</ref>). Using seq2gene with a search radius of 100 kb, our recent study in vivo defined a novel cis-regulatory element from both ChIP-seq and transcriptomic data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Hoffmann et al., 2014</ref>). Compared with other methods, seq2gene outputs candidate targets with detailed loci-to-gene mappings (e.g. exon, intron, CDS (CoDing sequence), UTR (UnTranslated Region), promoter and neighbor). This feature allows researchers to understand the function of the region and design creative downstream analyses for the genomic locus hits, an effort only previously achieved by annotation tools HOMER and ChIP-Enrich. The gene2pathway step integrates several cutting-edge fGSA algorithms, characterized by the improved FAIME method (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>). We also provide other three alternative methods: Fisher's exact test, the Kolmogorov–Smirnov test, and the cumulative rank test (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>). All of these implemented analyses condense gene-by-sample measurements (gene profiles) to gene-set-by-sample measurements (gene-set profiles), which are gene-coverage-difference tolerable and free of gene-set size preference for gene-sets with five or more genes (Supplementary Figs S4A, S6A, and S8A). Significance of biologically-defined loci of genomic aberrations or functional elements has been lacking of attention than their recurrence. Confidence of threshold-based significance is likely to depend on the choice of genomic background and the test statistic; thus, empirical approaches are recommended (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Glaab et al., 2012</ref>). Seq2pathway calculates empirical P-values for each gene-set in a sample by shuffling the gene scores derived from genomic locus hits of this sample to generate gene-set scores from the null hypothesis. This empirical assessment overcomes common biases of gene length in pathway analysis of NGS data (Supplementary Figs S4B and S6B). Additionally, we collapsed significant scores per gene when a gene was mapped to multiple neighboring genomic loci, removing the bias of linkage disequilibrium for the downstream pathway analysis (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6C</ref>). Finally, researchers can run seq2pathway against user-supplied gene-sets and the wrapped Gene Ontology (GO). This feature essentially allows unbiased comparisons of methods and results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Case study</head><p>To highlight the earlier features, we demonstrate the application of seq2pathway on a variety of different NGS datasets, point out the novel insights obtained only by seq2pathway, and summarize the take home message (Supplementary Document). We first compared seq2pathway with ChIP-Enrich and GREAT to test GO enrichment in a set of H3K27me3 peaks using the same criteria (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S5</ref>, false discovery rate (FDR) &lt; 0.01, count 5 and search radius ¼ 5 kb). Both seq2pathway and GREAT identified the biological process GO:0008285 (negative regulation of cell proliferation), while seq2pathway concentrates better with less identified GO terms than the other two methods. Interestingly, the significance of GO:0003705 (distal enhancer region for RNA polymerase II), a molecular function significantly enriched by bivalent genes marked with both H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Li et al., 2013</ref>), was obtained only with seq2pathway (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig.  S5B</ref>). We next tested 460 human height-associated SNP loci and compared the output with the seq2pathway (setting the parameterSNP ¼ T) to the results of GREAT (Binomial FDR &lt; 0.05, observed regions &gt;3, region fold enrich &gt;2). We applied a search radius ¼ 5 kb for both methods. The valuable biological processes obtained only with seq2pathway include GO:0001701 (in utero embryonic development) that was predicted recently (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>) in a comprehensive study on human height (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Wood et al., 2014</ref>). When we applied seq2pathway to RNA-seq data, individualized gene-set profiles allow the derivation of statistics at the pathway level directly rather than at the gene level. The advantages of seq2pathway lie in noise and dimension reduction, its desired biological interpretability, as well as a platform for novel integrative systems biology analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Yang et al., 2015a)</ref></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The identification of biological process from 460 height-associated SNPs. (A) Results of both methods were comparable to the prediction of a comprehensive study on human height (Wood et al., 2014). (B) A demonstration of the case that both common and different genes are identified by two methods for the same GO term (GO:0006397). (C) Common and different SNPs are identified by two methods for the genes in Panel B. (D) Selective biological process terms identified by two or three methods, followed by the commonly identified (in black) and seq2pathway specifically identified (in blue, underlined) genes and SNPs shown in panels B–C.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>, 31(18), 2015, 3043–3045 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv289 Advance Access Publication Date: 15 May 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">B.Wang et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> Conclusion It is a breakthrough in genome analytics coordinates to assign region significance scores such as binding affinity estimates from ChIP-Seq onto a uniform gene-set scale. This feature facilitates the integrative analysis of multiple datasets (Yang et al., 2015a). The most critical issue in functionally interpreting genomic loci is to bridge noncoding regions with gene function. Seq2pathway offers the capacity to discover collective pathway effects caused by long-distance cis-regulation of non-coding elements. Importantly, seq2pathway enhances an alternative tool to integrate a number of &apos;omics&apos; datasets into a condensed space of quantitative gene-set scores. This functional level integration will help generate assumptions, constraints, and interpretation in systems biology.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We acknowledge Joshua Stevens-Stein for manuscript proof-reading and initial package testing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patient-oriented gene set analysis for cancer mutation data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Boca</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EnrichNet: network-based gene set enrichment analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Glaab</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="451" to="457" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IntOGen-mutations identifies cancer drivers across tumor types</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Gonzalez-Perez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1081" to="1082" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GENCODE: the reference human genome annotation for the ENCODE project</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Harrow</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1760" to="1774" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Foxf genes integrate tbx5 and hedgehog pathways in the second heart field for cardiac septation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hoffmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1004604</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining functional DNA elements in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kellis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6131" to="6138" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ten years of pathway analysis: current approaches and outstanding challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Khatri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002375</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathway-based analysis of GWAs data identifies association of sex determination genes with susceptibility to testicular germ cell tumors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Koster</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mol. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6061" to="6068" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneous identification of multiple driver pathways in cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Leiserson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003054</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BGDB: a database of bivalent genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Database</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">57</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human-specific loss of regulatory DNA and the evolution of human-specific traits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Mclean</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="471" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GSA-SNP: a general approach for gene set analysis of polymorphisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Nam</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="749" to="754" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The missing story behind genome wide association studies: single nucleotide polymorphisms in gene deserts have a story to tell</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Schierding</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">39</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledgebased approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Subramanian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15545" to="15550" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A common genetic variant within SCN10A modulates cardiac SCN5A expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Van Den Boogaard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1844" to="1852" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">De novo discovery of mutated driver pathways in cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Vandin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="375" to="385" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic views of distant-acting enhancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Visel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">461</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reprogramming transcription by distinct classes of enhancers functionally defined by eRNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">474</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="390" to="394" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ChIP-Enrich: gene set enrichment testing for ChIP-seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Welch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining the role of common variation in the genomic and biological architecture of adult human height</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Wood</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1173" to="1186" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single sample expression-anchored mechanisms predict survival in head and neck cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002350</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic computation with functional gene-sets among leukemic and hematopoietic stem cells reveals a favorable prognostic signature for acute myeloid leukemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">97</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of epigenetic modifications that contribute to pathogenesis in therapy-related AML: effective integration of genome-wide histone modification with transcriptional profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Med. Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">seq2pathway: Pathway analysis of next-generation sequencing data</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>