
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics SKINK: a web server for string kernel based kink prediction in-helices</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Tim</forename>
								<surname>Seifert</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Software Engineering and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johannes Gutenberg University of Mainz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>55128</postCode>
									<settlement>Mainz</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andreas</forename>
								<surname>Lund</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johann Wolfgang Goethe-University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Benny</forename>
								<surname>Kneissl</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Data Science, Pharma Research and Early Development Informatics (pREDi)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Roche Diagnostics GmbH</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>82377</postCode>
									<settlement>Penzberg</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sabine</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Mueller</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saarland University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>66421</postCode>
									<settlement>Homburg</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christofer</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Tautermann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Lead Identification and Optimization Support, Boehringer-Ingelheim Pharma GmbH &amp; Co. KG</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>88397</postCode>
									<settlement>Biberach</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andreas</forename>
								<surname>Hildebrandt</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Software Engineering and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johannes Gutenberg University of Mainz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>55128</postCode>
									<settlement>Mainz</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics SKINK: a web server for string kernel based kink prediction in-helices</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1769" to="1770"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu096</idno>
					<note type="submission">Frankfurt am Main, 60054 Frankfurt am Main, Received on November 11, 2013; revised on January 31, 2014; accepted on February 7, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The reasons for distortions from optimal-helical geometry are widely unknown, but their influences on structural changes of proteins are significant. Hence, their prediction is a crucial problem in structural bioinformatics. Here, we present a new web server, called SKINK, for string kernel based kink prediction. Extending our previous study, we also annotate the most probable kink position in a given-helix sequence. Availability and implementation: The SKINK web server is freely accessible at http://biows-inf.zdv.uni-mainz.de/skink. Moreover, SKINK is a module of the BALL software, also freely available at www.ball</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>In our previous study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Kneissl et al., 2011</ref>), we presented a new method for predicting kinks from amino acid sequences of-helices implemented in the Biochemical Algorithm Library (BALL;<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Hildebrandt et al., 2010</ref>). Using string kernel based support vector machines (SVM), we were able to predict kinks in $80% of all cases correctly, exceeding recently reported accuracies of alternative approaches (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Hall et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Langelaan et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Meruelo et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Rigoutsos et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Yohannan et al., 2004</ref>). To make our approach publicly available by providing a user-friendly interface, we developed the web server SKINK. Moreover, we annotate the most probable kink position and calculate the corresponding probability value described shortly in the Section 2. In consequence, the region around the identified residue can be treated as flexible, e.g. in Molecular Dynamics (MD) simulations, while the remainder of the helix can be restrained.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>The prediction (classification) of an input sequence as kinked or nonkinked is described in our previous study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Kneissl et al., 2011</ref>) in detail. In addition, the most probable position of a putative kink is computed. Therefore, we divided the original sequence into overlapping k-mers of all odd sizes between 7 and 15 amino acids. Let the kink be in the center position of the k-mer; this corresponds to one to two neighbored helical turns, which are taken into account. These fragments are then predicted with the corresponding support vector machine as kinked or non-kinked. Using a trapezoidal-shaped function, the probability p s that the kink is located at position s in the currently considered subsequence is calculated by</p><formula>p s ¼ X 7 i¼3 X i j¼Ài 7 À jjj 7 Á k sþjÀi, sþjþi , ð1Þ</formula><p>where k a,b is 1 if subsequence [a: b] is predicted as kinked and otherwise 0. Hence, a position is more likely to be the kink if it appears near the center position of the k-mers that are labeled as kinked. The calculated probabilities are then normalized by the maximum possible value at each position such that each amino acid in the input sequence is assigned with a value between 0 and 1. Because we are not interested in kinks located at the end of a helix, the first and last two turns (seven positions) are ignored. Finally, the maximum values are chosen to determine the kink positions. If there are multiple maxima, two are merged if they are closer than four positions, else they are annotated as two kinks. Applying this kink annotation approach on our previously used training dataset (downloadable from the Web site), we are able to identify 85.6% of 339 correctly predicted kinks (out of 366) within one helical turn.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">SKINK</head><p>The SKINK web server is kept deliberately simple but well-structured to maintain clarity and is geared to the abilities of the users (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). First, there is a page Documentation, where some information about the dataset format as well as the precomputed support vector machine models is given. A detailed description and some analysis results of the datasets can be found in the page Data Sets. Moreover, all datasets can be downloaded here. The two main functionalities are provided in the pages Predict Kinks and Create Model. Users can query the server via the input text field or upload a file containing all sequences, which shall be classified as kinked or non-kinked. We allow two different input formats: The sequence can be in plain text (one sequence per line) or in the FASTA format. In addition, they can upload a file containing *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com all sequences in one of these two formats. Before continuing, the user has to choose at least one of the precomputed models or upload his/her own one in the LIBSVM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Chang and Lin, 2011</ref>) format. All chosen support vector machines are then applied on each input sequence. The classification whether the sequence is kinked or not is quite fast (about 15 s), whereas the annotation of the kink position can be up to three times longer because of the computation of all feature vectors of the different subsequences. The results are presented in a new page, where all information (input sequences, chosen models, logfile) of the request is collected. For each model a subdirectory is created where the corresponding result file is stored. In this file, each input sequence is labeled as non-kinked (0) or kinked (1), whereas in the latter case the kink position and the probability value are given, too. To create a new model, the user has to choose a training dataset, which can either be one of the provided ones on the Web site or an own dataset. In both cases, the BALL::ParameterFile format is required. Thereafter, he/she has to decide how many different string kernels and how many different LIBSVM parameter setups he/she wants to apply, which can be combined for each training run on the following setup page. Hence, for one dataset all generated support vector machines are located in a separate subdirectory. Clicking 'continue' shows the setup page. Here, the user can re-check the uploaded dataset and choose different parameters for the string kernel functions. Each setup can be named in a unique userspecified name. Finally, the LIBSVM parameters, e.g. for the cost function or the number of cross validation folds, can be set. Clicking 'continue' shows the result page, where for each fold a separate SVM is created. Moreover, it shows a file with all sequences and the corresponding predicted labels as well as a file containing a short analysis, e.g. the confusion matrix and prediction accuracies.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: Boehringer Ingelheim Pharma GmbH &amp; Co. KG. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Snapshots of the web server input pages: input page for kink prediction (left), page for creating own models (center) and page for setting the corresponding LIBSVM parameters (right)</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">T.Seifert et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LIBSVM: a library for support vector machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Chang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Trans. Intell. Syst. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Position of helical kinks in membrane protein crystal structures and the accuracy of computational prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Hall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Graph. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="944" to="950" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BALL–Biochemical Algorithms Library 1.3</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Hildebrandt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">531</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">String kernels and high-quality data set for improved prediction of kinked helices in-helical membrane proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Kneissl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3017" to="3025" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved helix and kink characterization in membrane proteins allows evaluation of kink sequence predictors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Langelaan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2213" to="2220" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TMKink: a method to predict transmembrane helix kinks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Meruelo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1256" to="1264" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural details (kinks and non-alpha conformations) in transmembrane helices are intrahelically determined and can be predicted by sequence pattern descriptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Rigoutsos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4625" to="4631" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of transmembrane helix kinks and the structural diversity of G protein-coupled receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Yohannan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="959" to="963" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>