
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:50+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics SLiM on Diet: finding short linear motifs on domain interaction interfaces in Protein Data Bank</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Willy</forename>
								<surname>Hugo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National University of Singapore</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>13 Computing Drive S(117417)</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Data Mining Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute for Infocomm Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 Fusionopolis Way, S(138632)</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Fushan</forename>
								<surname>Song</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National University of Singapore</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>13 Computing Drive S(117417)</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zeyar</forename>
								<surname>Aung</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Data Mining Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute for Infocomm Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 Fusionopolis Way, S(138632)</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">See-Kiong</forename>
								<surname>Ng</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wing-Kin</forename>
								<surname>Sung</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National University of Singapore</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>13 Computing Drive S(117417)</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Data Mining Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute for Infocomm Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 Fusionopolis Way, S(138632)</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Information and Mathematical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Genome Institute of Singapore</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>60 Biopolis Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>S(138672</postCode>
									<country key="SG">Singapore</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics SLiM on Diet: finding short linear motifs on domain interaction interfaces in Protein Data Bank</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1036" to="1042"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq065</idno>
					<note>Copyedited by: AP MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [09:52 1/4/2010 Bioinformatics-btq065.tex] Page: 1036 1036–1042 Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Contact: ksung@comp.nus.edu.sg Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: An important class of protein interactions involves the binding of a protein&apos;s domain to a short linear motif (SLiM) on its interacting partner. Extracting such motifs, either experimentally or computationally, is challenging because of their weak binding and high degree of degeneracy. Recent rapid increase of available protein structures provides an excellent opportunity to study SLiMs directly from their 3D structures. Results: Using domain interface extraction (Diet), we characterized 452 distinct SLiMs from the Protein Data Bank (PDB), of which 155 are validated in varying degrees—40 have literature validation, 54 are supported by at least one domain–peptide structural instance, and another 61 have overrepresentation in high-throughput PPI data. We further observed that the lacklustre coverage of existing computational SLiM detection methods could be due to the common assumption that most SLiMs occur outside globular domain regions. 198 of 452 SLiM that we reported are actually found on domain– domain interface; some of them are implicated in autoimmune and neurodegenerative diseases. We suggest that these SLiMs would be useful for designing inhibitors against the pathogenic protein complexes underlying these diseases. Our findings show that 3D structure-based SLiM detection algorithms can provide a more complete coverage of SLiM-mediated protein interactions than current sequence-based approaches.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Protein–protein interactions are vital to virtually every biological process. Some important biological processes, such as the signaling pathways, require protein–protein interactions that are designed for fast response to stimuli. These interactions are usually transient, easily formed and disrupted, and specific. While other protein– protein interactions are mediated by the binding of two large globular domain interfaces (domain–domain interactions), these transient interactions typically involve the binding of a protein domain to * To whom correspondence should be addressed. a short stretch (3–10) of amino acid residues, which is usually characterized by a simple sequence pattern, i.e. a short linear motif (SLiM). We call these domain–SLiM interactions. Numerous well-known and biologically important domains such as SH2, SH3, WW, 14-3-3, FHA and PDZ (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Puntervoll et al., 2003</ref>) have been found to interact with their partners via domain–SLiM interactions. The small binding areas on the SLiMs result in weak binding affinity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Neduva and Russell, 2005</ref>) that makes them suitable for mediating the transient interactions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Pawson and Nash, 2003</ref>). Compared with the larger domain–domain interaction interfaces, domain–SLiM interfaces are also better candidates for intervention by small molecules (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Neduva and Russell, 2006</ref>). However, current wet lab experiments for detecting SLiMs are laborious and time consuming. It is also a challenge to detect these motifs in silico, due to their short length and highly degenerative nature (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Neduva and Russell, 2005</ref>). One popular approach is to mine SLiMs that are overrepresented in a set of non-homologous proteins known to be interacting with a particular protein/domain or known to share a similar biological function [e.g. DILIMOT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Neduva et al., 2005</ref>) and SLiMFinder (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Edwards et al., 2007)]</ref>. Another line of computational approach finds SLiMs from sets of densely interacting protein pairs, for example, the work of<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Li et al. (2006)</ref>and D-STAR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Tan et al., 2006</ref>). There are several drawbacks with these approaches. First, as the SLiMs are highly degenerative, most of these algorithms mask conserved structured regions (which are assumed not to have many SLiMs) such as globular domains to reduce false positives. Recently, it was found that such filtering has caused some true motifs to be missed (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Edwards et al., 2007</ref>). Second, the motifs identified via the sequence-based approaches are not guaranteed to occur on the binding interface. Such atomic level of details can only come from high-resolution 3D structures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Aloy and Russell, 2006</ref>). Third, the algorithms are highly dependent on the accuracy of the interaction identification experiments. However, these interaction data are well known to be noisy (von<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Mering et al., 2002</ref>). The rapid increase of protein structure data in the Protein Data Bank (PDB) database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Berman et al., 2000</ref>) offers an excellent opportunity to detect SLiMs directly from 3D structures instead of the proteins' sequences. Some researchers have begun to exploit the structural data by using the structures as templates to find seed binding motifs, which are subsequently enriched using the available Protein-Protein Interaction (PPI) data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Betel et al., 2007</ref>). They therefore suffer from the accuracy and coverage limitations of the PPI data like the previous methods. In this work, we directly find de</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SLiM on Diet: short linear motifs on domain interfaces</head><p>novo SLiMs on domain interfaces extracted from 3D structures of protein–protein interactions (domain interface extraction or Diet). The SLiMs are extracted from structurally clustered domain–SLiM interaction classes for all PFAM domains that have available structures in the PDB database. Our SLiMDIet method comprises two steps: (i) Domain interface clustering: interaction interfaces belonging to the same domain are grouped together and classified using structural clustering; and (ii) SLiM extraction: interaction interfaces in each domain interface cluster are structurally aligned and the corresponding SLiM is extracted from the alignment. We reported 452 distinct SLiMs found on the domain interaction interfaces where 40 of them are known in the literature, 54 have at least one supporting domain–short peptide structure (a PDB structure which shows that a single short peptide instance of the SLiM is sufficient for binding the protein domain) and another 61 SLiMs are found to be overrepresented in the PPI data collected from the BioGRID (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Breitkreutz et al., 2008</ref>). Our data also revealed that the common assumption that SLiMs occur outside the globular domain regions could be a cause for the lacklustre coverage of current SLiM detection methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Edwards et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Neduva et al., 2005</ref>). Among the 452 distinct SLiMs that we reported, 198 of them have been detected on domain–domain interaction interfaces (we call these domain– domain SLiMs). Current SLiM detection methods are not amenable to mining these domain–domain SLiMs since they rely on a motif's overrepresentation over a set of non-homologous protein sequences. It is virtually impossible to detect the overrepresentation of a domain–domain SLiM using sequence-based methods since the domain's homology would overwhelm the SLiM's much weaker similarity. We conducted a further study on four novel domain–domain SLiMs, which we have found. The first one is a domain–domain SLiM bound by the tumor necrosis factor (TNF; ID: PF00229) domain on the BAFF proteins that have been implicated in B-cell hyperplasia and development of severe autoimmune diseases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Gross et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Khare et al., 2000</ref>). A previous experiment reported in the literature has showed that an instance of our predicted SLiM (a short peptide DLLVRHWV) can prevent the pathogenic condition from BAFF overexpression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Gordon et al., 2003</ref>). Another domain–domain SLiM of interest is a novel SLiM found on the dimer interfaces of the glyceraldehyde-3phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) enzyme, which is associated with neurodegenerative disorders such as Huntington's disease, Alzheimer's disease, Parkinson's disease and Machado–Joseph disease (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Berry and Boulton, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Tatton et al., 2003</ref>). We also discovered two SLiMs that are implicated in amyloid fibril formation implicated in several debilitating human diseases such as Alzheimer's disease, prion-based encephalopathies, liver cirrhosis and lung emphysema (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Carrell and Gooptu, 1998</ref>). The class of domain–domain SLiMs could, therefore, be particularly useful for designing inhibitors to disrupt the domain–domain interactions, which underlie the formation of pathogenic protein complexes. In conclusion, the fine atomic details offered by structural data made them an attractive data source for discovering SLiMs that are beyond the coverage of existing sequence-based methods. With the number of available protein structures expecting to grow rapidly, we can expect to discover even more biologically significant novel SLiMs in the near future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">SLiMDIet's workflow</head><p>In this study, we devised a method named SLiMDIet, a de novo SLiM discovery method by Diet from 3D protein structure data. SLiMDIet consists of two steps: a Diet step, followed by a SLiM step. The Diet step takes a set of protein structures from PDB as input, finds all known domains within the input structures and extracts the domain interfaces associated with each of them. A domain interface comprises two sets of amino acid residues: one found along a domain chain (the set is called the domain face) while the other on a partner chain (partner face), which are in close vicinity of each other. The interaction interfaces of each domain are then clustered based on structural similarity. The resulting domain interface clusters represent various modes of interactions for the domain. In the SLiM step, we conduct an approximate structural multiple alignment to align the domain faces and the partner faces in each cluster. We then check if the alignment of the partner faces contains any conserved linear region (called a 'block') of length 3–12 residues. To ensure robustness, we require that a block is constructed only from nonhomologous partner chains and we require at least four of them. Finally, we construct a (linear) gapped position specific scoring matrix (PSSM) from the block to represent the predicted SLiMs. An illustration of SLiMDIet algorithm can be seen in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Domain identification</head><p>A structural dataset was downloaded from PDB on August 24, 2009, containing 57 559 structures. We chose structures containing at least one protein chain and whose resolution is 3.0 Å or better, giving a total of 54 981 legible structures with 130 488 protein chains. PFAM domain annotations on each PDB chain are computed by running the hmmpfam program from the HMMER library version 2.3.2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Eddy, 1998</ref>) using the latest PFAM 23.0 library (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bateman et al., 2004</ref>). We use PFAM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bateman et al., 2004</ref>) as our choice of protein domain definition as opposed to SCOP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Andreeva et al., 2008</ref>) or CATH (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Cuff et al., 2009</ref>) because of the relatively better coverage of PFAM. PFAM was previously reported to have 57% coverage on SWISSPROT+TREMBL sequences, while SCOP covers 31% (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Elofsson and Sonnhammer, 1999</ref>). PFAM also has higher PDB chain coverage on the current dataset<ref type="bibr">[</ref>. However, PFAM domain does have its own limitation. It currently does not define structural domains that are formed by multiple protein chains. Nevertheless, one can always apply SLiMDIet on SCOP/CATH domain definition without major change on the program.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Interface extraction</head><p>For each PDB structure, we find the PFAM domains in its chains. For each domain, we computed the domain interfaces as follows. First, we define the distance between two amino acid residues to be the nearest distance between any pair of non-hydrogen atoms between the two residues. As done in PSIMAP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Dafas et al., 2004</ref>), we also use a contact distance cutoff of 5 Å here. A domain interface comprises two sets of amino acid residues: the domain and partner faces. Each amino acid on one face must be within the defined contact distance from some amino acid on the other face. The residues on each face must originate from a single protein chain (named domain and partner chain, respectively). However, they need not be located consecutively in their respective chains. For the domain face, the residues must also be within a single protein domain region of the domain chain. To curb possible non-biological (crystal) interfaces, which are generally of smaller area, we set a threshold of having domain interfaces involving a minimum of eight amino acids on the domain face and four amino acids on</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>W.Hugo et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>….</head><p>Cluster 1 Cluster n</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>….</head><p>Cluster 2 II. Cluster by interface shape similarity using MatAlignAB III. For each cluster, align the both domain and partner faces and extract SLiMs in the form of flexible gapped PSSM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>….</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cluster 1</head><p>Linear gapped PSSM 1 Cluster n</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>….</head><p>I. Collect domain interfaces belonging to one particular domainThe domain interfaces of each PFAM domain are clustered by their structural similarity. Next, from each cluster, the domain and partner faces are structurally aligned and we build a gapped PSSM based on the contacts on the partner faces. The gapped PSSM has flexible gaps defined by the minimum and maximum gaps observed between two consecutive PSSM positions. We define a gapped PSSM as linear when the total length of its non-gap positions is 3–12 residues with gaps of at most four residues between any consecutive residue positions. To detect domain– SLiM interfaces, we collect domain interface clusters whose partner faces are covered by a linear gapped PSSM. the partner face. This lower bound corresponds to a binding area &gt;800 Å 2 — which is roughly the average size of a domain interface (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Kim et al., 2006</ref>). For intrachain domain interfaces, we also require that the residues on the partner face are not within 10 residues from the ends of the domain, to avoid recognizing local contacts as interaction interfaces. This resulted in 270 739 domain interfaces involving 4780 PFAM domains.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Pairwise structural alignment within each domain interface group</head><p>To classify similar interfaces that correspond to the same domain interaction class, we define the similarity of two interfaces using the modified 1 S-score function from (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alexandrov and Fischer, 1996</ref>) as follows:</p><formula>S norm = 1 (1+) · N min(|A|,|B|)</formula><p>where is the root mean square distance (RMSD) between the two structures being aligned, N the number of aligned residues between the two interfaces, and |A| and |B| the sizes of the aligned interfaces. Usually, the RMSD between two proteins is approximated by the RMSD of their backbone's C α atoms. Since SLiMDIet's domain interfaces only consist of the contact residues (instead of the whole protein or domain), the C α representation is rather inadequate. To capture the similarity better, we measure the similarity of two interfaces using the backbone and side chain conformation of the residues on each interface. We use the C β atom position to represent the direction of the side chain with respect to its backbone C α (a similar C β approximation was mentioned in<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Torrance et al., 2005</ref>). When comparing two interfaces, we treat both domain and partner faces of each domain interface as one rigid continuous structure. We designed MatAlignAB for comparing domain interfaces, a modified algorithm of MatAlign (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Aung and Tan, 2006</ref>), which only aligns residues from the same face type (i.e. residues from domain face in one interface can only be aligned to residues in the domain face of the other) and aligns atoms of the same atom type<ref type="bibr">[</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Hierarchical agglomerative clustering on the domain interfaces using average linkage</head><p>For every domain, we cluster its interfaces into domain interface clusters by following the steps of hierarchical agglomerative clustering algorithm using average linkage, where the similarity of two clusters is defined to be the average pairwise similarity between all the members of the two clusters (as done in<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Kim et al., 2006</ref>). The algorithm starts by setting every domain interface as a cluster with one member. Next, it picks the pair of clusters that has the highest pairwise similarity and combine the pair. Then, it computes the average similarity of the combined cluster with the rest of the cluster. The latter two steps are repeated until the similarity score between every possible pair of the clusters is below a certain threshold. In SLiMDIet, we use the following range of thresholds 0.15, 0.2, 0.25 and 0.3 to generate sets of (possibly overlapping) clusters each under the corresponding threshold level. For those clusters that have &gt;70% overlap, we group them together and report one of the clusters as the representative (see Supplementary Material 2 for details).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">Quantification of the clustering performance</head><p>Suppose C is a cluster of domain interfaces computed by a particular algorithm and R the reference cluster [in our case, R is the set of domain interfaces (manually) grouped according to the literature]. We use the F-score, which is the harmonic mean of the sensitivity and specificity scores (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Rijsbergen, 1979</ref>), to quantify the similarity of the predicted cluster C and the reference cluster R.</p><formula>F-score (C,R) = 2 × Spec (C,R) × Sens (C,R) Spec (C,R) + Sens (C,R)</formula><p>where Spec (C,R) is the specificity of the cluster C with respect to a reference cluster R, which is computed by Spec (C,R) =|C ∩ R|/|C|. Sens (C,R) is the sensitivity of the cluster C with respect to R, which is computed by Sens (C,R) =|C ∩ R|/|R|. The F-score of an algorithm for a particular reference cluster R is the best score among its computed cluster C. The F-score measure is used to compare the clustering performance of SLiMDIet to SCOWLP's on the benchmark data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SLiM on Diet: short linear motifs on domain interfaces</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7">SLiM extraction from the interface clusters</head><p>We employ a PSSM with flexible gaps, called gapped PSSM to define the binding motif on the interaction interfaces. The gaps are defined between any two consecutive positions in the PSSM. Given a cluster of domain interfaces, the construction of a gapped PSSM is performed in two steps. First, interfaces from the same cluster are aligned to the cluster center, which is the domain interface with the best average similarity to the rest of the interfaces in a cluster, to generate an approximate multiple interface alignment of the interfaces. Then, we ensure that the alignment contains four non-homologous interfaces. An interface I a is defined as homologous to I b when I a and I b 's aligned residues in the alignment are exactly the same and their full partner chains share &gt;50% sequence similarity. This means that two interfaces whose partner chains share high sequence similarity can still be defined as non-homologous as long as their aligned interface residues differs. In the alignment of the non-homologous interfaces, a block is defined as a set of 3–12 consecutive alignment positions with gaps of at most four residues in between. The SLiM corresponding to an interface alignment is computed from the longest block in it. A SLiM is said to be covering an interface when it covers at least half of the contact residues on the partner face of that interface. To make sure that the computed SLiM represents the interfaces of a domain interface cluster, we require it to cover at least half of the non-redundant interfaces in it. With a block that satisfies the coverage constraint, we construct a gapped PSSM by extrapolating the score of all 20 amino acids based on the BLOSUM62 substitution score (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Henikoff and Henikoff, 2005</ref>) of all observed amino acids in each column in the block. The detailed steps of the gapped PSSM construction is included in Supplementary Material 1 (Section 2). From 39 170 domain clusters with at least four members, SLiMDIet found 7473 with at least four non-homologous interfaces. Out of these, only 1592 met the coverage constraint. We then grouped interface clusters from different similarity cutoffs when they have at least 70% member overlap. The grouping yields 452 distinct gapped PSSMs involving 280 PFAM domains. The full listing of SLiMDIet's predicted SLiMs and their gapped PSSM are listed in Supplementary Material 2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.8">Computing the statistical significance of the SLiM using PPI data</head><p>When a SLiM is extracted from a particular domain–SLiM interface clusters, we conduct statistical tests to see if the motif occurs significantly more in the interaction partners of the domain as compared to any random interaction. Given a protein sequence S, the gapped PSSM score of one particular position j in S is just the maximum sum of the gapped PSSM's residue scores starting at j over all possible gap combination in the PSSM. For example, the best score of position 0 in the string FSDTK based on the gapped PSSM 2For a position in a protein with a gapped PSSM score s, it is defined as an occurrence of the PSSM if the probability of scoring s or better by random is at most equal to 10 −4. To this end, we created 10 000 random protein sequences, each of length 500, with their amino acid distribution following the one observed in our PPI data from BioGRID (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Breitkreutz et al., 2008</ref>). For each gapped PSSM, we computed the scores of all positions in the random dataset (of approximately 5 million positions) and sorted the scores in nonincreasing order. The 500th score on the sorted score list would have an empirical P-value of 10 −4 and is chosen as the cutoff score for the occurrence of the gapped PSSM. Given a SLiM's gapped PSSM, the probability of observing a certain number of occurrences in the partners of a protein domain by random can be computed by the standard hypergeometric distribution function</p><formula>P-value = |I M | |I DM | (|I|−|I M |) (|I D |−|I DM |) |I| |I D |</formula><p>where I is the whole set of the high-throughput PPI data, I M the subset of I that contain an occurrence of the motif M, I D the subset of I containing the domain D and I DM the subset of I D that contain an instance of M. The correctness of the hypergeometric scoring function on the PPI data is presented in Supplementary Material 1 (Section 5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Both known and novel SLiMs are discovered</head><p>SLiMDIet detected 452 distinct SLiMs from the whole PDB dataset (dated August 2009). Forty of that are known in the literature. Amongst the remaining 412 candidate novel SLiMs, 54 have at least an instance of a domain–short peptide structure in their respective domain–SLiM clusters. The presence of such a domain– short peptide structure is a strong indicator that the domain is capable of binding a linear peptide defined by the predicted SLiM. Indeed, all of the literature-backed SLiMs have at least one domain–short peptide structure. From the remaining 358 candidate novel SLiMs, we found 61 are overrepresented in the interaction partners of their respective domains within the high-throughput PPI data (P-value ≤ 0.05). It is important to note that SLiMs with poor P-value are not necessarily erroneous since the PPI data is far from complete. Indeed, as many as 145 of the remaining 297 SLiMs (those with P-value &gt; 0.05) have &lt;10 distinct interaction data—99 of them have no PPI data support at all. This shows the limitation of SLiM detection methods that relied solely or heavily on PPI data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">SLiMs with validations from the literature</head><p>We compared our predicted SLiMs with those listed in the ELM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Puntervoll et al., 2003</ref>) and MiniMotif database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Balla et al., 2006</ref>). SLiMDIet reported 40 SLiMs with strong similarity with the known SLiMs in literature. Since there is a significant overlap in the entries of ELM and MiniMotif, most of our SLiMs correspond to more than one database entry in both databases. In summary, our SLiMs covered 30 out of 136 known ELM SLiMs and 72 of 524 MiniMotif SLiMs (from the publicly available MiniMotif version 1). The coverage is significant considering that the SLiMs are solely computed from a more limited structural data source. The detailed listing of the 40 SLiMs with their corresponding literature SLiM is given in Supplementary Material 4. As a comparison, we also checked the discovery of these literature-backed SLiMs in the profiles collected by D-MIST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Betel et al., 2007</ref>). D-MIST, like SLiMDIet, constructs binding profiles of different domains based on the structural data. However, it relies on the high-throughput PPI data to refine their predicted motifs. Out of the 40 literature-backed SLiMs found by SLiMDIet, we could only find the corresponding D-MIST profiles for nine of them. For the missing 31 SLiMs, D-MIST did not have any profile related to the SLiM's domain for 24 of them and for the remaining seven SliMs, D-MIST's profiles are too divergent from the literature SLiMs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>W.Hugo et al.</head><p>Such poor coverage could be due to the fact that D-MIST was collected from a subset of PDB (10064 structures). However, we observe that even the older, well-studied SLiMs recognized by domains like SH2(Grb2), WW, FHA, PDZ and PID(PTB) were also missing. We present the detailed listing of matched D-MIST profiles in the Supplementary Material 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Different SLiM classes have different interface geometries</head><p>It has been known that some SLiM-recognizing domains can bind multiple classes of SLiMs. The SH3 domain, for example, is known to recognize two classes of SLiMs;<ref type="bibr">[KRY]</ref>..P..P (SH3 class 1 SLiM) and P..P.<ref type="bibr">[KR]</ref>(SH3 class 2 SLiM) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Puntervoll et al., 2003</ref>). We hypothesize that the existence of such different classes of SLiM that can bind to the same domain is due to observable differences in their corresponding domain interface geometries. In other words, one can differentiate domain–SLiM interfaces belonging to different classes of SLiMs through geometric comparison. To verify our conjecture, we hand-curated a benchmark set of 230 domain–SLiM interfaces from three well-studied domains—SH2 (123 interfaces), SH3 (80 interfaces) and 14-3-3 (27 interfaces)— whose interaction classes are well annotated in the literature. The detailed listing of the benchmark interfaces is given in the Supplementary Material 3. We compare the structural clustering of SLiMDIet with an existing domain interface clustering method SCOWLP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Teyra et al., 2008</ref>) on the benchmark clusters.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>shows that SLiMDIet's clustering has better average specificity, sensitivity and F-score for all three domains in the benchmark. However, we should note that SCOWLP was not designed specifically for clustering domain– SLiM interfaces. We compared with SCOWLP because it was the only existing method we found suitable for clustering domain–SLiMinterfaces. The discussion on the performance of both methods on each benchmark domain is presented in Supplementary Material 3. The overall high correspondence of SLiMDIet's structural clusters with the literature reference clusters indicates that different classes of domain–SLiM interfaces indeed are associated with different domain interface geometries. It also shows that SLiMDIet, which took in account the interface geometries of the SLiMs, is more suitable for domain–SLiM interface clustering as compared with such an existing domain interface clustering method as SCOWLP.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Known and Novel SLiMs are found on domain–domain interaction interfaces</head><p>Interestingly, we observed that 198 of the total 452 predicted SLiMs are domain–domain SLiMs. A domain–domain SLiM is a SLiM found in an interface cluster with at least four non-homologous interfaces whose partner faces occur within some (not necessarily the same) PFAM domain. We found two of our 198 reported domain– domain SLiMs have literature support. They are the SH3_1 and ubiquitin domain. All of the instances of our predicted SLiM for ubiquitin are found within a domain called ubiquitin interacting motif (UIM, ID: PF02809). We also found another six domain– domain SLiMs with supporting domain–short peptide structures and 35 with overrepresentation in the PPI data. We also observe that 143 out of 198 domain–domain SLiMs that we found are overrepresented in their respective PFAM domains. The complete listing of the domain–domain SLiMs and the procedure to compute their overrepresentation within the PFAM domain in which they are found are given in Supplementary Material 6. Finding such domain–domain SLiMs can be an important discovery since it is commonly believed that SLiMs occur outside the globular domain regions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Puntervoll et al., 2003</ref>). In fact, most of the current SLiM detection methods remove domain regions from the search space (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Edwards et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Neduva et al., 2005</ref>) because of this belief. The discovery of such domain–domain SLiMs also indicates that many of the apparent domain–domain interactions could be mediated by domain–SLiM interactions. Indeed, a recent study had actually found genuine occurrences of ELM SLiMs on the accessible parts of a globular domain (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Via et al., 2009</ref>). One particularly interesting novel domain–domain SLiM found by SLiMDIet is a SLiM that is bound by the GAPDH, C-terminal (Gp_dh_C) domain (ID: PF02800). The Gp_dh_C domain is the C-terminal domain of GAPDH enzyme. The enzyme exists as a tetramer of identical chains, each containing two conserved functional domains, the Gp_dh_N (ID: PF00044) and Gp_dh_C (ID: PF02800) domain.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 2A</ref>shows the structure of half of the tetramer, comprising of two chains of GAPDH (one chain on the left and one on the right).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 2B</ref>and C illustrates only the Gp_dh_C domain surfaces with the linear peptide regions of Gp_dh_N on them. GAPDH has an important role in glycolysis and gluconeogenesis, and it is also involved in the signaling mechanism for programmed cell death (apoptosis;<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Berry and Boulton, 2000</ref>). Several studies associated the enzyme with neurodegenerative disorders such as Huntington's disease, Alzheimer's disease, Parkinson's disease and Machado–Joseph disease (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Berry and Boulton, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Tatton et al., 2003</ref>). The SLiM computed by SLiMDIet for Gp_dh_C is<ref type="bibr">[YH]</ref>..<ref type="bibr">[KRQ]</ref><ref type="bibr">[YH]</ref>D<ref type="bibr">[ST]</ref>, which is found within the Gp_dh_N domain. The predicted SLiM is found within nine non-homologous</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SLiM on Diet: short linear motifs on domain interfaces</head><p>A B CThe dimer of the GAPDH complex (PDB ID:1gd1). The cyan (light) part is the C-terminal domain and the red (dark) part mark the N-terminal domain. The C-terminal domain binds to a linear region on the N-terminal domain of the opposite chain (highlighted in ball-and-stick mode). SLiMDIet's predicted SLiM for this region is<ref type="bibr">[YH]</ref>..<ref type="bibr">[KRQ]</ref>GAPDH dimers. It was reported in an earlier study that inhibition on the formation of GADPH tetramer protects against neuronalinduced cell-death (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Fukuhara et al., 2001</ref>), a phenomenon frequently seen in many neurogenerative diseases. Interestingly, the dimeric and monomeric form of the enzyme retain its glycolysis and gluconeogenesis functionality and research had shown that they have higher catalytic activity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Minton and Wilf, 1981</ref>). We suggest that our domain–domain SLiM could be used as a template for designing inhibitors to disrupt the enzyme's complex formation and keep it in its monomeric form. Another notable example of domain–domain SLiMs is a SLiM interacting with the TNF domain (ID: PF00229) of BAFF proteins. SLiMDIet predicted that it binds a SLiM D<ref type="bibr">[LHS]</ref>L<ref type="bibr">[LV]</ref><ref type="bibr">[RH]</ref>..<ref type="bibr">[IV]</ref>on its domain partners [BaffR-Tall_bind (ID: PF09256), BCMATall_bind (ID: PF09257) and TACI-CRD2 (ID: PF09305)]. BAFF protein overexpression was previously shown to result in B-cell hyperplasia and development of severe autoimmune diseases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Gross et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Khare et al., 2000</ref>). In fact, it has already been reported that an instance of the SLiM can confer BAFF binding and block the signaling pathway leading to the pathogenic condition from BAFF overexpression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Gordon et al., 2003</ref>). However, there were no TNFbinding SLiM for BAFF reported in the literature and SLiMDIet managed to predict one. The predicted SLiM could provide further insights for designing more effective treatments.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 3</ref>shows two PDB structures in which two TNF domains are binding a short peptide and a full partner domain, respectively; both containing our predicted SLiMs. A third domain–domain SLiM is found on the dimer interface of RNaseA domains (ID: PF00074) of Ribonuclease protein. Theprotein is known to form dimers using two modes of domain swapping. The major mode swaps the C-terminal beta sheets (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Liu et al., 2001</ref>) while the minor mode swaps the N-terminal helix (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Liu et al., 1998</ref>). Previous experiments have shown that a peptide instance of the N-terminal helix could compete with the minor mode of the domain swapping and disrupt dimer formation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Liu et al., 1998</ref>). It has also been reported that domain swapping is one possible mechanism of amyloid fibril formation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Carrell and Gooptu, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Liu et al., 2001</ref>) and based on the domain swapping observed in RNase, Liu et al. proposed a model of amyloid fibril formation, which is stabilized by the swapped domain binding (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Liu et al., 2001</ref>). The formation of amyloid is associated with a variety of neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer's disease, Huntington's disease and the new variant Creutzfeldt–Jakob disease (nvCJD). It is also implicated in other diseases such as the sickle cell anemia, α-antitrypsin related liver cirrhosis and emphysema (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Carrell and Gooptu, 1998</ref>). In such a model, knowing the SLiM bound by the domain would enable one to design an inhibitor to destabilize and prevent the amyloid formation. SLiMDIet predicted two distinct novel SLiMs that correspond to the two swapping modes of the RNase domain, namely YVPVH<ref type="bibr">[FYL]</ref>[DAN]AS (major mode) and AA..<ref type="bibr">[FAM]</ref>ERQH.DS (minor mode).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A B</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>SLiMs are important mediators of protein–protein interactions but they are difficult to detect experimentally and computationally. In this work, we showed that it is possible to systematically detect de novo SLiMs on domain interaction interfaces extracted directly from structural data. The atomic level of details available in the highresolution 3D structures provide a rich source of data for discovering SLiMs that are guaranteed to occur on the binding surfaces. In fact, by mining the different domain–SLiM interaction classes from the PDB database, our SLiMDIet method detected many novel SLiMs, including the domain–domain SLiMs. The discovery of domain–domain SLiMs uncovered a limitation in the current SLiM detection approaches. These SLiMs are located in regions that are routinely masked out by the current SLiM</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>W.Hugo et al.</head><p>detection methods. They cannot be detected simply by turning off the masking step—the strong similarity of the domain regions would bury the weak signal of the degenerate SLiM(s) in them. This class of SLiM is, therefore, currently under-represented in the known databases and literature, and they present real opportunities for domain–domain interaction inhibitor design. Current SLiM detection methods also rely heavily on PPI data and are thus affected by its accuracy. An earlier study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Neduva et al., 2005</ref>) has reported that some of the known SLiMs were not detected in the PPI due to noisy and incomplete interaction data. In our study, we also observed a similar problem where as many as 111 SLiMs do not have any PPI data containing their binding domains. Among them, two are known in the literature, namely the Toxin_1 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Scherf et al., 1997</ref>) and fn1 domains (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Bingham et al., 2008</ref>) and 10 have domain-short peptide evidences. As the structural genomic initiatives continue to make more and more high-quality structural data available, we can have a viable chance of detecting the SLiMs that mediate many of our important protein–protein interactions directly from 3D structural data. As future work, we plan to continue to improve SLiMDIet's capability by refining the notion of interface similarity to take into account the interface residues' chemical properties and their connectivity within the domain interfaces. Funding: Ministry of Education, Singapore (AcRF grant R-252-000326-112 to H.W. and W.-K.S); Agency for Science, Technology and Research (A*STAR) of Singapore.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of Interest: none declared.</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>version 23.0, released July 2008, covering 112 424 chains (86.16% coverage)] as compared to SCOP [version 1.75, dated June 2009, covering 87 064 chains (66.72% coverage)] and CATH [version 3.2.0, dated July 2008, covering 86 105 chains (65.99% coverage)]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: AP MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [09:52 1/4/2010 Bioinformatics-btq065.tex] Page: 1038 1036–1042</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. SLiMDIet's overview. The domain interfaces of each PFAM domain are clustered by their structural similarity. Next, from each cluster, the domain and partner faces are structurally aligned and we build a gapped PSSM based on the contacts on the partner faces. The gapped PSSM has flexible gaps defined by the minimum and maximum gaps observed between two consecutive PSSM positions. We define a gapped PSSM as linear when the total length of its non-gap positions is 3–12 residues with gaps of at most four residues between any consecutive residue positions. To detect domain– SLiM interfaces, we collect domain interface clusters whose partner faces are covered by a linear gapped PSSM.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><figDesc>i.e. C α (C β , respectively) to C α (C β , respectively)]. As with the original algorithm, MatAlignAB produces alignments that follow the sequential ordering of the residues within their respective domain and partner sequences. The final results of this step consist of the similarity scores and pairwise alignments among all pairs of domain interfaces of each domain.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: AP MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [09:52 1/4/2010 Bioinformatics-btq065.tex] Page: 1039 1036–1042</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: AP MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [09:52 1/4/2010 Bioinformatics-btq065.tex] Page: 1040 1036–1042</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: AP MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [09:52 1/4/2010 Bioinformatics-btq065.tex] Page: 1041 1036–1042</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Domain–SLiM interface between Gp_dh_C domain (ID: PF02800) and Gp_dh_N (ID: PF00044). (A) The dimer of the GAPDH complex (PDB ID:1gd1). The cyan (light) part is the C-terminal domain and the red (dark) part mark the N-terminal domain. The C-terminal domain binds to a linear region on the N-terminal domain of the opposite chain (highlighted in ball-and-stick mode). SLiMDIet's predicted SLiM for this region is [YH]..[KRQ][YH]D[ST]. (B) The surface representation of the Gp_dh_C domain of Holo-GAPDH from Bacillus stearothermophilus (PDB ID:1gdl). The linear region HLLKYDSVHGR of the opposite N-terminal domain bound to the domain is shown in ball-and-stick representation. (C) The structure of linear sequence YQMKHDTVHGR bound to the Gp_dh_C domain of Leishmania mexicana's glycosomal GAPDH (PDB ID:1a7k).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Domain–SLiM interfaces of TNF domain of BAFF proteins recognizing the SLiM D[LHS]L[LV][RH]..[IV]. (A) The TNF interface from BAFF with a part of BAFF receptor protein (PDB ID:1oqe). The linear region is shown in ball-and-stick display, comprising the residues DLLVRHCV. (B) The structure between the TNF domain of BAFF complexed with only the minimal peptide DLLVRHWV (shown in ball-and-stick, PDB ID:1osg)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: AP MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [09:52 1/4/2010 Bioinformatics-btq065.tex] Page: 1042 1036–1042</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Clustering performance comparison of SLiMDIet and SCOWLP</figDesc><table>Interaction class 
SLiMDIet 
SCOWLP 

Sens 
Spec 
F-Scr 
Sens 
Spec 
F-Scr 

SH3-class 1 
0.97 
1.00 
0.98 
0.71 
0.55 
0.62 
SH3-class 2 
0.98 
0.92 
0.95 
0.88 
0.54 
0.67 
SH3 P.[VI][DN]R..KP 
1.00 
1.00 
1.00 
0.25 
1.00 
0.40 

SH2-(class 1A) 
0.75 
0.86 
0.80 
0.62 
0.67 
0.65 
SH2-(class 1B) 
0.67 
1.00 
0.80 
0.75 
1.00 
0.86 
SH2-(class 1C) 
1.00 
1.00 
1.00 
0.83 
0.59 
0.69 
SH2-(class 2A) 
0.25 
1.00 
0.40 
0.50 
1.00 
0.67 
SH2-(class 2B) 
0.67 
0.86 
0.75 
0.67 
1.00 
0.80 

14-3-3 Mode 1 
1.00 
0.50 
0.67 
0.50 
1.00 
0.67 
14-3-3 Mode 2 
1.00 
1.00 
1.00 
0.67 
1.00 
0.80 
14-3-3 Mode 3 
0.50 
1.00 
0.67 
1.00 
0.33 
0.50 

We collected the interfaces of the SH2, SH3 and 14-3-3 domains whose domain–SLiM 
interaction class is defined in their respective reference papers. The grouping from 
the literature constitutes the reference clusters, against which the accuracy of both 
SLiMDIet and SCOWLP are computed. The cases where one method outperforms the 
other are printed in bold. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> The function is normalized by the size of the interface and scaled to yield similarity score between 0 and 1.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> This is a mini-version of gapped PSSM for exemplary purpose, the real gapped PSSM would have scores for all 20 amino acids.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of topological and nontopological structural similarities in the PDB: new examples with old structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Alexandrov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Fischer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="354" to="365" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural systems biology: modelling protein interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Aloy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Russell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="188" to="197" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data growth and its impact on the SCOP database: new developments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Andreeva</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="425" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MatAlign: precise protein structure comparison by matrix alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Aung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Tan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bioinform. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1197" to="1216" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MiniMotif miner: a tool for investigating protein function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Balla</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Pfam protein families database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Bateman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Protein Data Bank</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Berman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase and apoptosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Berry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Boulton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure-templated predictions of novel protein interactions from sequence information</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Betel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">182</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crystal structures of fibronectin-binding sites from Staphylococcus aureus FnBPA in complex with fibronectin domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Bingham</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12254" to="12258" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The BioGRID interaction database: 2008 update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Breitkreutz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="637" to="640" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conformational changes and disease-serpins, prions and Alzheimer&apos;s</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Carrell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Gooptu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="799" to="809" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The CATH classification revisited—architectures reviewed and new ways to characterize structural divergence in superfamilies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Cuff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="310" to="314" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using convex hulls to extract interaction interfaces from known structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Dafas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1486" to="1490" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Profile hidden Markov models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Eddy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="755" to="763" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SLiMFinder: a probabilistic method for identifying overrepresented, convergently evolved, short linear motifs in proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Edwards</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">967</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of sequence and structure protein domain families as a basis for structural genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Elofsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Sonnhammer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="480" to="500" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GAPDH knockdown rescues mesencephalic dopaminergic neurons from MPP+ induced apoptosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Fukuhara</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroreport</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2049" to="2052" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BAFF/BLyS receptor 3 comprises a minimal TNF receptorlike module that encodes a highly focused ligand-binding site</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Gordon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5977" to="5983" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TACI and BCMA are receptors for a TNF homologue implicated in B-cell autoimmune disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Gross</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">404</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="949" to="950" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Amino acid substitution matrices from protein blocks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Henikoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Henikoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10915" to="10919" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Severe B cell hyperplasia and autoimmune disease in TALL-1 transgenic mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Khare</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3370" to="3375" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The many faces of protein–protein interactions: a compendium of interface geometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">124</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovering motif pairs at interaction sites from protein sequences on a proteome-wide scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="314" to="324" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The crystal structure of a 3D domain-swapped dimer of RNase A at a 2.1-Å resolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3437" to="3442" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A domain-swapped RNase a dimer with implications for amyloid formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="989" to="996" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative assessment of large-scale data sets of protein– protein interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Von Mering</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">417</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="399" to="403" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of macromolecular crowding upon the structure and function of an enzyme: glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Minton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Wilf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4821" to="4826" />
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic discovery of new recognition peptides mediating protein interaction networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Neduva</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">405</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linear motifs: evolutionary interaction switches</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Neduva</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Russell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEBS Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">579</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3342" to="3345" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peptides mediating interaction networks: new leads at last</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Neduva</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Russell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="465" to="471" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assembly of cell regulatory systems through protein interaction domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Pawson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Nash</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">300</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="452" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ELM server: A new resource for investigating short functional sites in modular eukaryotic proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Puntervoll</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3625" to="3630" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information Retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J V</forename>
				<surname>Rijsbergen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
			<publisher>Butterworth-Heinemann</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Newton, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-dimensional solution structure of the complex of alphabungarotoxin with a library-derived peptide</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Scherf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6059" to="6064" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A correlated motif approach for finding short linear motifs from protein interaction networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Tan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">502</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuroprotection by deprenyl and other propargylamines: glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase rather than monoamine oxidase B</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Tatton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neural Transm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="515" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SCOWLP classification: structural comparison and analysis of protein binding regions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Teyra</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using a library of structural templates to recognise catalytic sites and explore their evolution in homologous families</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Torrance</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">347</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="565" to="581" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A structure filter for the Eukaryotic Linear Motif Resource</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Via</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">351</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>