
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:38+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Structural RNA alignment by multi-objective optimization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
								<surname>Schnattinger</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Theoretical Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ulm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>89069</postCode>
									<settlement>Ulm</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Neural Information Processing</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Research Group Bioinformatics and Systems Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ulm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>89069</postCode>
									<settlement>Ulm</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Uwe</forename>
								<surname>Schö Ning</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Theoretical Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ulm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>89069</postCode>
									<settlement>Ulm</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hans</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Kestler</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Neural Information Processing</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Research Group Bioinformatics and Systems Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ulm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>89069</postCode>
									<settlement>Ulm</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Structural RNA alignment by multi-objective optimization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1607" to="1613"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt188</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 24, 2012; revised on April 15, 2013; accepted on April 17, 2013</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Ivo Hofacker Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The calculation of reliable alignments for structured RNA is still considered as an open problem. One approach is the incorporation of secondary structure information into the optimization criteria by using a weighted sum of sequence and structure components as an objective function. As it is not clear how to choose the weighting parameters, we use multi-objective optimization to calculate a set of Pareto-optimal RNA sequence-structure alignments. The solutions in this set then represent all possible trade-offs between the different objectives, independent of any previous weighting. Results: We present a practical multi-objective dynamic programming algorithm, which is a new method for the calculation of the set of Pareto-optimal solutions to the pairwise RNA sequence-structure alignment problem. In selected examples, we show the usefulness of this approach, and its advantages over state-of-the-art single-objective algorithms. Availability and implementation: The source code of our software (ISO Cþþ11) is freely available at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The central role of RNA is that of being a messenger between transcription and protein translation. However, it is known that non-coding RNA molecules have a wide range of functions in the cell, like catalysis of chemical processes or in gene regulation, and it is assumed that RNA played a central role in the early stages of life (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Doudna and Cech, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Latchman, 2005</ref>). As the functionality of RNA molecules is not only defined by their primary sequences but also the interaction of their base pairs, their secondary structure is well conserved during evolution (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Zuker and Sankoff, 1984</ref>). Based on this observation, RNA can be organized into families with similar sequences and secondary structures. The Rfam database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gardner et al., 2011</ref>) is a collection of RNA sequences, arranged in currently 1973 different families, each represented by a multiple alignment of its members. When the sequence similarity is too low, the construction of reliable sequence alignments is impossible (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Gardner et al., 2005</ref>). In this case, structural information can be used as another criterium to improve these alignments. Although much work has already been put into the development of sequence alignment methods, especially those for multiple sequences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Larkin et al., 2007</ref>), RNA sequence-structure alignment can still be considered as an open problem (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Gardner et al., 2005</ref>). RNA secondary structure consists of base pairs ði k , j k Þ, i k 5j k (positions from 5 0 to 3 0 ) between nucleotides of an RNA sequence. Through stacking effects, these base pairs tend to form helices and various kinds of loops (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>for an example). For complexity reasons, we will restrict ourselves to non-crossing structures that forbid so-called pseudo-knots. This means that if we have two base pairs ði 1 , j 1 Þ and ði 2 , j 2 Þ with i 1 5i 2 , it follows that either i 1 5j 1 5i 2 5j 2 or i 1 5i 2 5j 2 5j 1. There are various methods that predict a secondary structure from a single RNA sequence by free-energy minimization, like the dynamic programming algorithm of Zuker and Stiegler (1981). However, it is known that the prediction of the structure of related RNA sequences can be improved by comparative methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Westhof et al., 1996</ref>). Most structure prediction tools only calculate noncrossing structures, but there are algorithms that predict structures with pseudo-knots. Therefore, they follow a hierarchical approach of predicting the secondary structure first and the pseudo-knots subsequently (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Tinoco and Bustamante, 1999</ref>), even if recent works show that tertiary interactions emerge early in the RNA folding process and suppress incorrect structures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Behrouzi et al., 2012</ref>). One RNA molecule can have the ability to fold into different 'suboptimal' structures, which differ from each other in their stability. McCaskill (1990) gives an efficient algorithm that calculates all secondary structures, together with their occurrence probability in a thermodynamic equilibrium. The result is a matrix of probabilities P, where an entry at position (i,j) reflects *To whom correspondence should be addressed.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>. Example of a RNA molecule. The primary sequence is the sequence of nucleotides (encircled), whereas the base pairings (in light grey) between nucleotides make up the secondary structure the probability of the bases at positions i and j to form a base pair. More precisely, P ij is the sum of probabilities of all secondary structures that have a base pair between the nucleotides at positions i and j. To our knowledge, Sankoff's algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sankoff, 1985</ref>) was the first to solve the alignment and folding of RNA simultaneously. In its pairwise version, it has a time and space complexity of Oðn 6 Þ and Oðn 4 Þ, respectively, and as a consequence, it is often considered too expensive for a practical application. A simplified and more efficient variant of the Sankoff algorithm is Foldalign (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Gorodkin et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Havgaard et al., 2007</ref>), which uses a restricted energy model to reduce the time and space complexity, where Dynalign (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Mathews, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Mathews and Turner, 2002</ref>) features the full energy model, but it reduces the number of reasonable alignments by limiting the range of positions of matching nucleotides. Recently,<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Backofen et al. (2011)</ref>even presented an exact and efficient algorithm that uses sparsification to significantly enhance the runtime behaviour. Another popular implementation is LocARNA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Will et al., 2007</ref>), which is based on the work of<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Hofacker et al. (2004)</ref>, and it incorporates structural information into the alignment process in the form of pre-calculated base pair probabilities. It finds an optimal sequence-structure alignment that maximizes an objective function, which is a weighted sum of a sequence alignment score and the sum of base pair probabilities of a consensus secondary structure. All these alignment methods depend on fixed weighting parameters for their sequence and their structure objectives, which have to be estimated or optimized. Depending on the type of RNA or the degree of structure conservation, a fixed weighting can lead to undesirable sequence-structure alignments. A change of these parameters can have a great influence on which consensus structure is considered as optimal. We treat the sequence alignment and the consensus structure calculation as separate objectives, and we solve both problems simultaneously with a new multi-objective dynamic programming algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Deb, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Laux, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Pareto, 1971</ref>). The result is not one single solution that is optimal in some sense, but a set of Pareto-optimal solutions. This technique has been applied successfully in different fields like the multi-objective routing problem (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Sniedovich, 1988</ref>) or the knapsack problem with multiple criteria (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Henig, 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Klamroth and Wiecek, 2000</ref>). In the bioinformatics area,<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Roytberg et al. (1999)</ref>construct a set of Pareto-optimal alignments of biological sequences by treating the number of gaps and the scores for (mis)matches as separate objectives. Taneda (2010) gives an evolutionary algorithm for pairwise RNA sequence alignment that incorporates RNA structure information to approximate a set of Paretooptimal solutions. Although it also uses the theory of dominating vectors, it only calculates a rough approximation of the set of Pareto-optimal alignments. Apart from that, it depends on many parameters that influence the quality of approximation, as well as the runtime behaviour. We now present an algorithm that calculates the exact set of Pareto-optimal solutions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>When the weighting between two conflicting objectives is not known, the weighting parameters have to be estimated or optimized in some way.</p><p>After that the weighting parameters represent one fixed trade-off between the objectives, which also biases all subsequent solutions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Multi-objective optimization</head><p>If more than one objective is to be optimized, the scoring can be treated as a vector-valued function, where the dimension is the number of objectives. Two different objectives can be conflicting, and in general, there is no solution that maximizes all objective functions. As there is no 'optimal solution' in a vector-valued context, the definition of optimality needs to be generalized. DEFINITION 1 (Dominating vector). Let x ¼ ðx 1 ,. .. , x d Þ 2 R d and y ¼ ðy 1 ,. .. , y d Þ 2 R d. We say x dominates y if x i ! y i for all 1 i d and x j 4y j for at least one 1 j d.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DEFINITION</head><p>2 (Pareto-optimality). Let M &amp; R d , x 2 M. x is Paretooptimal in M if there is no other element y 2 M that dominates x. Now the problem of multi-objective optimization is the calculation of the largest subset of all possible solutions where every element is Paretooptimal. This subset can contain multiple elements and is also known as the non-dominated set or the first Pareto-front (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Laux, 2005</ref>). The task of finding the Pareto-optimal elements of a given finite set is called the maximal vector problem and has several solutions that are efficient in practice. As a special case, the computation of the Pareto-front of a set of 2D vectors takes linear time (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Godfrey et al., 2007</ref>). First, we show that every solution, which can be found by a monoobjective optimization, which maximizes a weighted sum of the objectives, is also Pareto-optimal.for any given weights ! i 40 is also Pareto-optimal. PROOF. Let m 2 M be optimal in respect of (1). Assume m is not Pareto-optimal; therefore, there must exist an y 2 M that dominates m, i.e. 8i : f i ðyÞ ! f i ðmÞ and 9j : f j ðyÞ4f j ðmÞ. Without loss of generality be</p><formula>f 1 ðyÞ4f 1 ðmÞ. It follows that P i ! i f i ðyÞ4 P i ! i f i ðmÞ</formula><p>, which contradicts the fact that m maximizes (1). This result implies that our method is a generalization of any monoobjective method (compare<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ehrgott, 2000</ref>). The set of supported solutions (i.e. there exist weighting parameters ! i for which the solution is optimal) lies on the convex hull of the Pareto set. Restriction on these solutions may lead to non-favourable decisions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Klamroth and Wiecek, 2000</ref>). On the other hand, the elements from the Pareto-front represent every possible trade-off between the different objectives: one cannot get better in one without getting worse in another objective.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">A multi-objective dynamic programming algorithm</head><p>The secondary structure of functional RNAs is often more conserved than their sequence; therefore, it makes sense to use the secondary structure as another criterion to obtain good alignments. A sequence-structure alignment of two RNA sequences A and B consists of a sequence alignment R and a compatible consensus secondary structure S, which means that both sequences can fold into the same structure S. More precisely, ðj, lÞ 2 R means that the nucleotides A j and B l are matched together. ði, j; k, lÞ 2 S means ði, kÞ 2 R and ðj, lÞ 2 R are matched nucleotides, and additionally, A i is base paired with A j , and B k is base paired with B l. We formulate two separate objectives that assign a score to a sequence-structure alignment. The first one in Equation (2) is the wellknown objective function for sequence alignment algorithms: the sum of penalties for the gaps in the alignment and of scores for (mis-)matched unpaired nucleotides.</p><formula>f seq ðR, SÞ ¼ Á N gap þ X ði, kÞ2R unpaired ðA i , B k Þ ð 2Þ</formula><p>The gap penalty should be negative, where the scoring function for aligned nucleotides should satisfy ða, aÞ ! 0 and ða, bÞ 0 for a 6 ¼ b. Note that Equation (2) is a weighted sum itself. To be completely independent of weighting parameters, we could introduce a third objective function, but this would again result in a higher runtime complexity. The second objective function in Equation (3) is the sum of base pair scores for all aligned base pairs in the consensus secondary structure S. f str ðR, SÞ ¼ X ðij;klÞ2S</p><formula>É A ij þ É B kl ð3Þ</formula><p>The score É A ij for the base pair ðA i , A j Þ is defined analogously to<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Hofacker et al. (2004)</ref>, and it is proportional to the logarithm of the respective entry in the base pair probability matrix P A ij (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">McCaskill, 1990</ref>).</p><formula>É A ij ¼ logðP A ij =p min Þ, if P A ij ! p min 0, otherwise: &amp; ð4Þ</formula><p>In the first version of our algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Schnattinger et al., 2012</ref>), we used the recursive definition of<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Hofacker et al. (2004)</ref>for the prototypical implementation. In a more sophisticated algorithm by<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Will et al. (2007)</ref>, the runtime and memory requirements were greatly improved. Therefore, we adapt this new formulation to fit the multi-objective problem definition. Let now S i, j;k, l be the set of Pareto-optimal scoring vectors of alignments of the two subsequences A½i þ 1::j and B½k þ 1::l. S i, j;k, l ¼ Pareto-max of :</p><formula>s þ ~ : s 2 S i, jÀ1;k, l È É [ s þ ~ : s 2 S i, j;k, lÀ1 È É [ s þ ~ ðA j , B l Þ : s 2 S i, jÀ1;k, lÀ1 È É [ S h, q</formula><p>s þ d :</p><formula>s 2 S i, hÀ1;k, qÀ1 , d 2 D h, j;q, l 8 &lt; : 9 = ; 0 B B B B B B @ 1 C C C C C C A ð5Þ D i, j;k, l ¼ s þ ~ É A i, j þ ~ É B</formula><p>k, l : s 2 S i, jÀ1;k, lÀ1 n o ð6Þ with the initializations S i, i;k, l ¼ f~ ðl À kÞg, for l4k ð7Þ S i, j;k, k ¼ f~ ðj À iÞg, for j4i ð8Þ</p><formula>S i, i;k, k ¼ f ~ 0g: ð9Þ</formula><p>Equation (5) takes the Pareto-optimal solutions from all candidate solutions, which originate from the union of four major sets. Each one results from reducing the problem of finding Pareto-optimal sequencestructure alignments of two sequences to smaller subproblems. The first one takes all elements of S i, jÀ1;k, l and adds a gap penalty ~ to them. This stands for the insertion of a gap into the sequence B directly after position l, which is matched with A j. Analogously, the second set describes the scoring vectors of all alignments that have B l matched to a gap in A after position j. As S i, jÀ1;k, lÀ1 is the set of alignments of the subsequences A½i þ 1::j À 1 and B½k þ 1::l À 1, the third set of Equation (5) contains all Pareto-optimal solutions to the alignment of A½i þ 1::j and B½k þ 1::l, which have A j matched (or mismatched) to B l. The scoring of aligning these two nucleotides is done by the function ~ . The fourth part is the union of all candidate solutions, which have a base pair (h,j) in A and (q,l) in B. As a result, a solution vector is the sum of the solution vectors of two partial problems: the alignment of the subsequences A½i þ 1::h À 1 and B½k þ 1::q À 1, and of the subsequences A½h::j and B½q::l with the base pair ðh, j; q, lÞ as an additional condition. Therefore, Equation (6) defines D i, j;k, l to be the set of Pareto-optimal solution vectors of the alignments of the subsequences A½i::j and B½k::l with the condition that A i is matched to B k , A j is matched to B l , and these enclosing nucleotides are base paired. Obviously, it is required that both RNAs can have base pairs at these positions; hence, P A ij 40 and P B kl 40. Note that we do not need the Pareto-max operator here, as S i, jÀ1;k, lÀ1 does not contain dominated solutions. Finally, Equations (7–9) specify the trivial base cases of the recursion. We want to compute both scoring functions for every solution; hence, each element in the matrices S and D is a vector with two components: the sequence score and the structure score of this solution. Therefore, we implement a 2D scoring function with the first component containing the sequence score f seq and the second component containing the structure score f str. Thus, ~ and ~ ðlÞ are the vector-valued gap penalties for the insertion of a gap of length 1 and l, which in our case is defined by ~ ðlÞ :¼ ð Á l, 0Þ. The insertion of a gap into an existing intermediate solution should increase its sequence score by and leave the structure score untouched, which means that ~ can simply be added to the scoring vector of the intermediate solution. Analogously, the scoring function for two aligned nucleotides a and b is ~ ða, bÞ :¼ ðða, bÞ, 0Þ. On the other hand, the vector-valued structure score is ~ É A ij :¼ ð0, É A ij Þ, leaving the sequence score unchanged when added to the scoring vector of an intermediate solution. The number of Pareto-optimal solutions to the sequence-structure alignment problem can be large. To maintain practicability, it is crucial to optimize the runtime and memory requirements of this algorithm. For example, S does not have to be calculated for every combination of i and k, as only those parts of the matrix are needed with either ði, kÞ ¼ ð0, 0Þ or A i and B k are positions where a base pair can start. The set of Paretooptimal scoring vectors of global alignments of A and B is S 0, jAj;0, jBj. The dynamic programming matrix contains the Pareto-optimal scoring vectors for the solutions but not the sequence-structure alignments themselves. To get the desired alignments, a backtracing procedure is used in a second phase of the algorithm, which works as follows. For every scoring vector a, Equations (5) and (6) are used to figure out how this solution was calculated by simulating all steps that may have led to a. This is repeated recursively until one of the base cases from Equations (7–9) is encountered.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Proof</head><p>The recursive formulation of the dynamic programming algorithm is similar to the typical mono-objective formulation, except for the elements being vectors instead of numbers. To show the correctness of a dynamic programming algorithm, the problem must satisfy Bellman's principle of optimality (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bellman, 1957</ref>).<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Henig (1985)</ref>showed that the principle of optimality holds for multi-criteria decision problems if the monotonicity criterion is fulfilled. This means that if a, b 2 S i, j;k, l are solutions to the same subproblem and a dominates b, and the same 'decision' f(a) and f(b) is applied to them, their dominance property must be preserved; hence, f(a) must also dominate f(b). We will show the correctness of our algorithm by showing that (i) for each subproblem ði, j, k, lÞ, all Pareto-optimal solutions are generated and (ii) Bellman's principle of optimality holds; hence, no Pareto-optimal solution is lost by applying the Pareto-max operator during the algorithm. THEOREM 2. Equations (5) and (6), together with the initializations of Equations (7–9) compute the set of Pareto-optimal sequence-structure alignments. PROOF. Suppose that all smaller subproblems have already been calculated. Without the Pareto-max operator, Equations (5–9) produce the set of all possible sequence-structure alignments of A and B. The Paretoset thereof is the desired result. We will now show that the removal of dominated solutions from the sets during the algorithm does not prevent any Pareto-optimal solution to be computed in a future step. Therefore, we first show that a dominated intermediate solution can not be part of a Pareto-optimal solution. This argument covers the first three cases of Equation (5). Without loss of generality, we consider the first case, cases two and three follow analogously. First case. Let x, y 2 S i, jÀ1;k, l be two scoring vectors of the form x ¼ ðx 1 ,. .. , x d Þ and y ¼ ðy 1 ,. .. , y d Þ, with x dominating y, that is x i ! y i for 1 i d and x j 4y j for at least one 1 j d. Furthermore, let ~ ¼ ð 1 ,. .. , d Þ be the d-dimensional gap penalty score. Let now be ^ x ¼ x þ ~ ¼ ðx 1 þ 1 ,. .. , x d þ d Þ and ^ y ¼ y þ ~ ¼ ðy 1 þ 1 ,. .. , y d þ d Þ. It is clear that ^ x i ¼ x i þ i ! y i þ i ¼ ^ y i for 1 i d and ^ x j ¼ x j þ j 4y j þ j ¼ ^ y j for at least one 1 j d, which immediately implies that ^ x dominates ^ y; hence, the monotonicity criterion holds. As a consequence, no Pareto-optimal solution is lost in the computation of S i, j;k, l , if dominated scoring vectors are eliminated in their partial solutions in the first three cases. Last case. For any fixed h and q be v, w 2 S i, hÀ1;k, qÀ1 , v ¼ ðv 1 ,. .. , v d Þ and w ¼ ðw 1 ,. .. , w d Þ with</p><formula>v dominating w, and x, y 2 D h, j;q, l , x ¼ ðx 1 ,. .. , x d Þ and y ¼ ðy 1 ,. .. , y d Þ with x dominating y. Then</formula><p>the scoring vectors ðv þ xÞ, ðv þ yÞ, ðw þ xÞ and ðw þ yÞ are among the generated solutions for S i, j;k, l. From the fact that v dominates w, it follows that ðv þ xÞ dominates ðw þ xÞ, and ðv þ yÞ dominates ðw þ yÞ, as shown earlier in the text. Also x dominates y; thus, ðv þ xÞ dominates ðv þ yÞ and ðw þ xÞ dominates ðw þ yÞ. After the application of the Pareto-max operator, from these four produced solutions, only ðv þ xÞ 2 S i, j;k, l survives in the set, and v and x were the non-dominated vectors. Therefore like aforementioned, by removing dominated solutions from intermediate results, no Pareto-optimal solutions are lost.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Implementation</head><p>The runtime and space requirements depend not only on the length of the input RNA sequences A and B, as it would be the case in the monoobjective algorithm, but also on the number K of Pareto-optimal solutions. This number depends on the sequence and structure conservation of the RNAs. If, for example, A (or B) does not have any secondary structure (i.e. P A ¼ 0), then the fourth case of Equation (5) always evaluates to the empty set. This means that for every ði, j, k, lÞ, there will be no solution with a positive structure score. As a result, the number of Paretooptimal solutions will be K ¼ 1. In the other extreme, A and B have many suboptimal secondary structures; therefore, P A and P B have many nonzero entries. This will result in many sequence-structure alignments with different structure scores, and most likely in many non-dominated, hence, Pareto-optimal solutions. We want to determine this number K (as a function of the sequence length) experimentally for the given 2D objective function. Therefore, we randomly chose 11 000 pairs of RNAs up to length 350 from the Rfam database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gardner et al., 2011</ref>), with each pair being from the same RNA family and differing no more in length than 10 nt. For each pair, we ran our algorithm and computed the size of the largest set of Pareto-optimal solutions among all intermediate solutions S i, j;k, l. The experiment showed that the average quotient of the number of Pareto-optimal solutions and the mean sequence length of the input sequences is 1, and we conclude that K must be in O(n). See<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>for a graphical result of this experiment. The algorithm consists of two major parts. First, the set of Paretooptimal scoring vectors S 0, jAj;0, jBj is calculated using the recursion of Equations (5–9). The runtime complexity of a dynamic programming algorithm is the size of the table, which in our case is Oðn 4 Þ, times the runtime it takes to compute one entry. We saw earlier that the Pareto-max operator for 2D data has a runtime proportional to the number of candidate elements. Assuming that the largest set S i, j;k, l has K elements, it becomes clear that the first three cases of Equation (5) produce at most three K elements.<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Will et al. (2007)</ref>showed that, on average, the number of combinations (h,q) in the fourth case is constant. The elements in this fourth set are the sums of each combination of Pareto-optimal solutions of two smaller subproblems; hence, its size is in the order of K 2 in the worst case. This gives an overall runtime of Oðn 4 Á K 2 Þ. In practice, the runtime can be strongly improved by restricting the alignments in the following way. If we demand from each aligned pair ðA i , B k Þ that the two nucleotides must be at most M positions apart, i.e. ji À kj M, and furthermore that for matched base pairs ði, j; k, lÞ the span of the two involved base pairs jðj À iÞ À ðl À kÞj M differs by no more than M, then the runtime can be reduced by another factor n 2 to Oðn 2 Á K 2 Þ for fixed M (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Hofacker et al., 2004</ref>). Notice, however, that M has to be at least the length difference of A and B. For fixed i and k, the calculation of S i, j;k, l depends only on entries of the form S i, j 0 ;k, l 0 and on entries from D. Therefore, after every iteration of i and k, the matrix S can be discarded, and only D has to be stored. This reduces the space complexity significantly from Oðn 4 Þ to Oðn 2 Þ in the mono-objective case (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Will et al., 2007</ref>). Therefore, in phase one of the multi-objective algorithm, we need Oðn 2 Á KÞ space to store S and D and another OðK 2 Þ for the calculation of the current matrix entry. In the second phase of the algorithm, for every solution s 2 S 0, jAj;0, jBj , a backtracing procedure is executed that recovers the actual alignment and the consensus secondary structure from its solution vector s and the dynamic programming matrices S and D. In the mono-objective algorithms, the backtracing walks once n steps through the matrix towards the optimal solution, and every step takes constant time. Even though some entries of the matrix have to be recalculated, the time and space consumption for this phase is negligible. In our case, we have to be more careful because larger parts of the matrix may have to be recalculated. As we expect a larger number of Pareto-optimal solutions, some maybe similar to each other, many entries will have to be recalculated multiple times. For this reason, we implemented the following hybrid approach. As described, we discard the intermediate solutions in the first part of the algorithm after every iteration of i and k. In the backtracing step, however, we memoize all recalculated entries and thus avoid redundant calculations. This gives us a good time-space trade-off in practice, as we can see in<ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>showing the memory consumption of the three approaches, as well as their runtime by an example of two ykoK leader RNA<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. The size of the set of Pareto-optimal solutions as a function of the mean sequence length. Each of the 11 000 grey dots is the size of the largest set of Pareto-optimal solutions of all subproblems S i, j;k, l of one experiment. The black line is an interpolation using the locally weighted regression and smoothing scatter plots (lowess) method of (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Cleveland, 1979)</ref>sequences. The naı¨venaı¨ve approach that stores the whole DP matrix ('naı¨venaı¨ve') is the fastest, but it requires the most memory, as analysed earlier in the text. By discarding the intermediate solutions after each iteration of i and k ('space saving'), only a fraction of the space of the naı¨venaı¨ve approach is needed, but the recalculation of the missing entries in phase two leads to a poor runtime behaviour. In the hybrid approach ('memoization'), phase one only needs as little space as version 1. However, in phase two, the memoization of recalculated missing entries increases the memory consumption, but it leads to a much better runtime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Alignment of two tRNAs</head><p>We align two RNA sequences using the well-established tool LocARNA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Will et al., 2007</ref>) and compare the results to our multi-objective algorithm. Sequence A is tRNA-Pro from Arabidopsis thaliana chromosome 2 (6810–6881) and sequence B is tRNA-Lys from Marchantia polymorpha mitochondrion (166035–166107), both taken from the Rfam database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gardner et al., 2011</ref>). LocARNA calculates, according to its mono-objective function, the following sequence-structure alignment, correctly suggesting the acceptor-, D-and T-arm of the expected typical tRNA cloverleaf structure (<ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>, Solution 1): structures of the sequence-structure alignments to the reference, we use the Matthews correlation coefficient (MCC) for structures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Havgaard et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Matthews, 1975</ref>).</p><formula>MCC ¼ P t N t À P f N f ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ðP t þ P f ÞðP t þ N f ÞðN t þ P f ÞðN t þ N f Þ p ð10Þ</formula><p>Here, P t is the number of predicted base pairs that are also annotated in the reference alignment, P f is the number of falsely predicted base pairs, N f is the number of annotated base pairs that are not predicted and N t is the number of positions that are unpaired in the prediction and the reference alignment. An MCC value of À1 means that the predicted and the reference secondary structure have no base pair in common, where an MCC value of 1 indicates a perfectly accurate prediction. For the sequence alignment tools Clustal Omega and Cofolga2mo, a direct computation of the MCC is not possible, as they do not calculate secondary structures. We used RNAalifold to calculate a consensus secondary structure for their solutions. In<ref type="figure">Figure 6a</ref>, we observe that the sequence alignment tool Clustal Omega aligns similar sequences pretty well, but it fails when the sequence identity is550%. The decreased performance of PMcomp surprises and could be explained by the fact that the weighting parameters in the objective function are not optimal for the dataset used here. LocARNA, which has a more sophisticated scoring for the sequence alignment part, shows an increased performance. Both multi-objective algorithms Cofolga2mo and MODP perform comparably well when the sequence similarity is440%, but our method achieves good results for dissimilar sequences. As for the MCC score in<ref type="figure">Figure 6b</ref>, which shows the ability of the different methods to predict the reference secondary structure, we see again the expected decreased performance of the purely sequence-based Clustal Omega for RNAs with low sequence similarity. The MCC score of LocARNA and PMcomp both decline as the sequence similarity grows, which could be a consequence of having fixed weighting parameters: if a solution has a high sequence score, the structure score becomes less relevant. Although both multiobjective methods outperform the mono-objective methods, Cofolga2mo seems to behave slightly better for sequence pairs with similarity from 30 to 70%. On the borders, however, our approach achieves the higher MCC scores. The evolutionary algorithm Cofolga2mo does not explore the solution space completely and possibly misses good solutions, whereas we are able to compute all Pareto-optimal solutions.<ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>. Secondary structures for the two highlighted solutions of<ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>. The first row contains the two RNA sequences folded into the structure suggested by Solution 1. The second row contains the more stable structure featuring a fourth stem at the cost of more gaps, as suggested by Solution 2</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>20</head><p>We introduced a novel method for the construction of pairwise RNA sequence-structure alignments that is inspired by the Sankoff algorithm. To overcome the dependence on fixed weighting parameters for the sequence and structure components in our objective function, we use separate scoring functions for sequence and structure and search for solutions that optimize both objectives. The result is a set of Pareto-optimal solutions from which the human expert is able to choose. This is clearly an advantage to single-objective methods that compute one single solution that is optimal in some sense on which the user has no influence. With the BRAliBase II benchmark dataset, we show the effectiveness of our new method compared with wellestablished tools. Although a hypothetical method that generates all possible solutions would win all benchmarks, albeit being computationally infeasible, all used methods compute in reasonable time. Compared with the evolutionary algorithm of Cofolga2mo, our approach has two major features. First, although an evolutionary algorithm is a heuristic method for which statements about the quality of its solutions and the coverage of the solution space are difficult, multi-objective dynamic programming is guaranteed to find all Pareto-optimal solutions to a given problem. Second, we do not only have the ability to produce good sequence alignments but also give all Pareto-optimal solutions to the consensus folding problem of the two RNA sequences. On a practical side, the number of solutions can be limited by clipping the objectives or by using Harrington's (1965) desirability functions, while being able to guarantee finding all solutions in this range. As comparative folding can outperform single-sequence–based methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Westhof et al., 1996</ref>), this might be a useful tool for the analysis of novel RNA families. It may even help finding new alternative stable secondary structures for some families of RNA. All in all, we are able to give a new perspective on the interplay between primary sequence and secondary structure of RNA molecules. These results will also trigger investigations on the potential of multi-objective optimization for the automatic learning of weighting parameters for the established single-objective tools on the basis of published sequence-structure alignments.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Example of a RNA molecule. The primary sequence is the sequence of nucleotides (encircled), whereas the base pairings (in light grey) between nucleotides make up the secondary structure</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>THEOREM1.</head><figDesc>Let M &amp; R d be some solution set, and let f i be a family of objective functions. A solution m 2 M that maximizes X</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">T.Schnattinger et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Structural RNA alignment by multi-objective optimization at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">GGGCAUUUGGUCUAG-UGGUAUGAUUCUCGCUUAGGGUGCGAGAGGUCCCGAGUUCAAUUCUCGGAAUGCCCC GGGUGUAUAGCUCAGUUGGUAGAGCAAUAGGCUUUUAACUUAAAGGUCGCAGGUUCAAGUCCUGCUAUACCCA (((((((..(((.. ... ... ..))).. ... ... ... ... ... ... ...(((((.. ... ..)))))))) )))). If we recalculate the minimum free energy of these two RNA structures, which is a measure of stability, using RNAeval (Hofacker et al., 1994), we get À15:4 kcal mol for A and À18:6 kcal mol for B. Our algorithm, in contrast, calculates a set of 37 Paretooptimal sequence-structure alignments regarding the objective functions from Equations (2) and (3). Among them is the solution aforementioned, but another one is the following (Fig. 4, Solution 2): GGGCAUUUGGUCUAG-UGGUAUGAU—-UCUCGCUUAGGGUGCGAGAGGUCCCGAGUUCAAUUCUCGGAAUGCCCC GGGUGUAUAGCUCAGUUGGUAGAGCAAUAGGCUUUUAACUUAAAGGUC—-GCAGGUUCAAGUCCUGCUAUACCCA (((((((..(((.. ... ... ..))).. ..((((((.. ... ..)))))).. ..(((((.. ... ..)))))))))))). The additional stabilizing stem–loop structure of the anticodon arm leads to minimum free energies of À24:0 kcal mol for A and À20:1 kcal mol for B. Obviously, the mono-objective tool scores the gap penalty higher than the gain for the additional loop, and thus decides against the gaps, where our method leaves this final decision to the user. Figure 4 shows a plot of the Pareto-optimal scoring vectors. Here, each point represents one alignment including its structure information. The horizontal axis shows the sequence score, i.e. the sum of gap penalties and base match scores. The vertical axis represents the structure score, that is the sum É A ij þ É B kl of all matched base pairs ðA i , A j Þ and ðB k , B l Þ. The two solutions that belong to the aforementioned sequence-structure alignments are highlighted. The different consensus secondary structures suggested by these two solutions can be observed in Figure 5. 3.2 Benchmark As a benchmark, we use the dataset 2 of the BRAliBase II benchmark (Gardner et al., 2005), which consists of 117 pairwise reference alignments of tRNA sequences, as well as a dataset of 324 pairwise alignments of per cent identity balanced tRNA and 5S rRNA sequences published by Dowell and Eddy (2006) (Supplementary Material). We compare the results of the mono-objective structural alignment tools LocARNA (Will et al., 2007) and PMcomp (Hofacker et al., 2004), on which the first version of our algorithm was based, the multi-objective evolutionary algorithm Cofolga2mo (Taneda, 2010), and the stateof-the-art sequence alignment program Clustal Omega (Sievers et al., 2011) to our new multi-objective dynamic programming algorithm (MODP). The latter is implemented in an extended version supporting affine gap costs. To allow for a comparison and as the multi-objective algorithms Cofolga2mo and MODP return a set rather than one optimal alignment, we evaluated the performance measures for each solution individually and used their maximum. We want to measure the ability of the tools to reconstruct the reference sequence alignment, as well as the reference consensus structure. The quality of a solution is evaluated using the sum-ofpairs score (Thompson et al., 1999). It is defined as the number of character pairs that are aligned both in the predicted and in the reference alignment divided by the number of aligned character pairs in the reference. To compare the predicted secondary Fig. 4. 2D scatter plot of the Pareto-optimal alignments of two tRNA sequences, with the sequence score f seq on the horizontal and the structure score f str on the vertical axis Fig. 3. Comparison of runtime and space requirement for the alignment of two ykoK leader RNA sequences of length 172 and 177, which results in a set of 157 Pareto-optimal solutions. Version 1 (&apos;naı¨venaı¨ve&apos;) completes after 14.9 s, but it requires 2.3 GB memory. Version 2 (&apos;space saving&apos;) needs only 12 MB memory, but it has a runtime of 106 s. With memoization, version 3 needs 260 MB and completes after 16.7 s. Experiments were conducted on an AMD Opteron(tm) 2431 processor with 2.4 GHz and 32 GB random access memory</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head><p>The authors thank the anonymous reviewers for their very helpful comments that led to significant improvement of this article.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sparse RNA folding: time and space efficient algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Backofen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Discrete Algorithms</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cooperative tertiary interaction network guides RNA folding</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Behrouzi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">149</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="348" to="357" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Dynamic Programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Bellman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1957" />
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust locally weighted regression and smoothing scatterplots</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Cleveland</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="829" to="836" />
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multi-Objective Optimization Using Evolutionary Algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Deb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The chemical repertoire of natural ribozymes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Doudna</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Cech</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">418</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="222" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient pairwise RNA structure prediction and alignment using sequence alignment constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Dowell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Eddy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">400</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multicriteria optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ehrgott</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lecture Notes in Economics and Mathematical Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">491</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A benchmark of multiple sequence alignment programs upon structural RNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Gardner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2433" to="2439" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rfam: Wikipedia, clans and the &apos;decimal&apos; release</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Gardner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithms and analyses for maximal vector computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Godfrey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">VLDB J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding the most significant common sequence and structure motifs in a set of RNA sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Gorodkin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3724" to="3732" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The desirability function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Harrington</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ind. Qual. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="494" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="1965" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast pairwise structural RNA alignments by pruning of the dynamical programming matrix</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Havgaard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">193</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vector-valued dynamic programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Henig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Control Optimiz</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="490" to="499" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The principle of optimality in dynamic programming with returns in partially ordered sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Henig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Oper. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast folding and comparison of RNA secondary structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Hofacker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monatsh. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment of RNA base pairing probability matrices</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Hofacker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2222" to="2227" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic programming approaches to the multiple criteria knapsack problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Klamroth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Wiecek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Naval Res. Logist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Larkin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2947" to="2948" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Gene Regulation: A Eukaryotic Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Latchman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<pubPlace>Taylor &amp; Francis, NewYork</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting a set of minimal free energy RNA secondary structures common to two sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Laux</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Berlin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Germany</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Mathews</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2246" to="2253" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>6th. edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynalign: an algorithm for finding the secondary structure common to two RNA sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Mathews</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Turner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">317</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of the predicted and observed secondary structure of t4 phage lysozyme</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Matthews</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">405</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="442" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The equilibrium partition function and base pair binding probabilities for RNA secondary structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Mccaskill</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biopolymers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1105" to="1119" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Manual of Political Economy Pareto-optimal alignment of biological sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Pareto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Roytberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kelley Publishers</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="565" to="577" />
			<date type="published" when="1971" />
			<publisher>Kelley Publishers</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneous solution of the RNA folding, alignment and protosequence problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Sankoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Appl. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="810" to="825" />
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pareto-optimal RNA sequence-structure alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Schnattinger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">9th International Workshop on Computational Systems Biology 2012</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ulm, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="86" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast, scalable generation of high-quality protein multiple sequence alignments using clustal omega</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Sievers</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">539</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multi-objective routing problem revisited</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Sniedovich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eng. Optimiz</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-objective pairwise RNA sequence alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Taneda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2383" to="2390" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comprehensive comparison of multiple sequence alignment programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Thompson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2682" to="2690" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How RNA folds</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Tinoco</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Bustamante</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">293</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="281" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">DNA and RNA structure prediction (eds) DNA—Protein Sequence Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Westhof</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Rawlings,C.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<publisher>IRL Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="278" />
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inferring noncoding RNA families and classes by means of genome-scale structure-based clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Will</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">65</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA secondary structures and their prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Zuker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Sankoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bull. Math. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="591" to="621" />
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal computer folding of large RNA sequences using thermodynamics and auxiliary information</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Zuker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Stiegler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Structural RNA alignment by multi-objective optimization</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>