
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:55+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression SurvMicro: assessment of miRNA-based prognostic signatures for cancer clinical outcomes by multivariate survival analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Raul</forename>
								<surname>Aguirre-Gamboa</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Investigació n e Innovació n</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Escuela de Medicina</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Tecnoló gico de Monterrey</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>64849</postCode>
									<settlement>Mé xico</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Victor</forename>
								<surname>Trevino</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Investigació n e Innovació n</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Escuela de Medicina</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Tecnoló gico de Monterrey</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>64849</postCode>
									<settlement>Mé xico</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression SurvMicro: assessment of miRNA-based prognostic signatures for cancer clinical outcomes by multivariate survival analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1630" to="1632"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu087</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 10, 2013; revised on January 6, 2014; accepted on February 6, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Ivo Hofacker Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) play a key role in post-transcriptional regulation of mRNA levels. Their function in cancer has been studied by high-throughput methods generating valuable sources of public information. Thus, miRNA signatures predicting cancer clinical outcomes are emerging. An important step to propose miRNA-based biomarkers before clinical validation is their evaluation in independent cohorts. Although it can be carried out using public data, such task is time-consuming and requires a specialized analysis. Therefore, to aid and simplify the evaluation of prognostic miRNA signatures in cancer, we developed SurvMicro, a free and easy-to-use web tool that assesses miRNA signatures from publicly available miRNA profiles using multivariate survival analysis. SurvMicro is composed of a wide and updated database of 440 cohorts in different tissues and a web tool where survival analysis can be done in minutes. We presented evaluations to portray the straightforward functionality of SurvMicro in liver and lung cancer. To our knowledge, SurvMicro is the only bioinformatic tool that aids the evaluation of multivariate prog-nostic miRNA signatures in cancer. Availability and implementation: SurvMicro and its tutorial are freely available at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are $22-nt molecules that play an important post-transcriptional regulatory role (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Reinhart et al., 2000</ref>). This molecular mechanism has been widely studied in cancer. It is known that some miRNAs act like oncogenes or tumor suppressor genes (Esquela<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Kerscher and Slack, 2006</ref>) and whose regulatory roles are linked to cancer hallmarks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Ruan et al., 2009</ref>). MiRNAs have also been proposed as drug targets and biomarkers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Calin and Croce, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Healy et al., 2012</ref>). The roles of miRNAs in the tumor cell have been explored using high-throughput techniques such as microarrays and sequencing. These data have also been used to associate miRNAs to clinical outcome in patients generating signatures for diagnostics and prognostics that are composed of several miRNAs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Calin and Croce, 2006</ref>). A miRNA signature trial has been recently announced (MRX34 trial). A key issue for miRNA signatures for cancer is their validation in diverse cohorts (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kern, 2012</ref>). Such task generates difficulties even though many public cohorts are available. These are related to timeconsuming tasks, such as exploration of repositories, acquisition and processing and the modeling of miRNA levels, to assess their value as prognostic biomarkers. The current approaches for miRNAs signature validation are limited. ProgMir (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Goswami and Nakshatri, 2012</ref>) and MIRUMIR (<ref type="bibr">Antonov et al., 2013</ref>) implement only univariate analyses even though signatures are composed of several miRNAs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Raponi et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wei et al., 2013</ref>). Moreover, both tools are restricted regarding the available cohorts. These characteristics limit the assessment of multivariate miRNA biomarkers. To provide assessment of multivariable prognostic miRNA biomarkers and to simplify the evaluation in several cohorts, we developed SurvMicro. SurvMicro is a curated and updated web tool of miRNA expression levels associated with clinical outcome that provides survival analysis and risk assessment in cancer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Datasets</head><p>Data were collected by searching for keywords related to cancer, clinical outcome, miRNA platforms and 430 samples. The searches were performed in GEO (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo), GEOmetadb (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Zhu et al., 2008</ref>), ArrayExpress (https://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress/) and TCGA (https://tcga-data.nci.nih.gov/tcga). TCGA data were obtained at level 3 from the May 2013 run. TCGA read counts generated by RNAseq were log2 transformed. All datasets were quantile-normalized and log2 transformed if needed. Datasets were grouped using disease ontologies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Schriml et al., 2012</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Web interface implementation</head><p>Two intuitive input pages and a results section were implemented using Java server pages, JavaScript, R, Ajax, Apache and MySQL. The first input page requires the list of miRNAs, the selection of the cohort and the treatment for multiprobe miRNAs. We annotate miRNAs using the miRBase nomenclature (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Griffiths-Jones et al., 2006</ref>).Owing to the presence of miRNA variants, we implemented two types of searches, a 'strict' for specific variant evaluation and a 'relaxed' one that reports every variant of the miRNA entered by the user (À3p, À5p and *). After web submission, the following analysis page obtains the rows corresponding to the entered miRNAs in the selected dataset as well as the available clinical characteristics. In this page, the user can customize the output of the analysis including risk group methodology, risk groups stratification, model fitting, heatmap and boxplot graphs, figure format, PDF report *To whom correspondence should be addressed. and others. Details of the implementation and options are thoughtfully documented in the tutorial. Finally, the results section displays the biomarker evaluation in publication-ready graphs and tables containing statistical parameters for easy exportation and manipulation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">MiRNA-based risk assessment</head><p>To perform the risk prediction from the list of miRNAs submitted by the user, SurvMicro uses the Cox multivariate fitting from R (<ref type="bibr">Therneau, 2013</ref>). The risk groups are obtained by ranking the prognostic index, which is obtained by the sum of the products of the Cox coefficients and the expression values of corresponding miRNAs. The groups are generated splitting the prognostic index by the median, by the quantiles or by using a simple Log-Rank P-value optimization algorithm. The risk groups are used to generate the Kaplan–Meier plots and statistics (LogRank, concordance index and hazard ratios). Moreover, to analyze biomarkers computed with models other than Cox, the user can specify coefficients for each miRNA. Details are provided in the tutorial.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Database and web interface</head><p>To our knowledge, SurvMicro provides the biggest compilation of miRNA datasets related to clinical outcomes, comprising 440 datasets and 6300 samples grouped in 14 tissues. We also encourage any user to suggest datasets. As shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>, SurvMicro is easily operated by providing only the list of miRNAs and selecting the target cohort in the input page. A link to a comprehensive tutorial and an example button for a quick example are located in the input page. The analysis page is generated in a few seconds. Finally, the results section is obtained in less than a minute (might vary if advance plots are selected) deploying the outcome plots and tables.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Validation and applications</head><p>To assess the capabilities of SurvMicro in the evaluation of multivariate prognostic biomarkers, we performed an analysis of a miRNA signature for liver hepatocellular carcinoma survival, an examination of a signature for lung squamous cell carcinoma (LSCC) and a performance comparison of two LSCC survival signatures. In liver, we evaluated a 20-miRNA signature for survival carcinoma (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wei et al., 2013</ref>) in two additional independent cohorts. The summary of the survival analyses is shown in<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>(Kaplan–Meier curves are shown in Section 5.1 of the Tutorial). The performance was highly significant in two datasets and acceptable in one cohort. Moreover, using the stratification option of SurvMicro, we examined the prognostic power of this signature in early lesions compared with advanced tumors (shown in the Tutorial). This explorative evidence suggests that the signature could be related to advanced tumors (Grade 3 or Stage III). For lung, a 20-miRNA signature proposed for survival and relapse in LSCC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Raponi et al., 2009</ref>) was evaluated in three LSCC datasets including the original dataset and a lung adenocarcinoma dataset. The results are shown in<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>(detailed in Tutorial Section 5.2). The Kaplan–Meier curves and statistical information in all datasets appear acceptable even though only two miRNAs were significant or marginally significant using a Cox model in the Raponi dataset. By using the fitting information option of SurvMicro in the Analysis Page,Columns means Log-Rank P-value, CI for concordance index, HR for hazard ratio, miRNAs for the number of miRNAs found in the dataset. *P50.05. LIHC, LUAD, and LUSC means Liver hepatocellular carcinoma, Lung adenocarcinoma, and Lung squamous cell carcinoma respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fig. 1. An overview of SurvMicro workflow and implementation</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Assessment of three miRNA signatures</figDesc><table>Database 
Log-Rank CI 
HR 
miRNAs Samples 

Wang liver biomarker 
Wei Wang 
3.0e-7 
70.02 3.52* 20 
58 
Li Gu 
1.2e-2 
58.91 1.59* 10 
156 
TCGA LIHC 
3.1e-4 
78.68 5.86* 14 
166 
Raponi lung biomarker 
Raponi 
6.0e-6 
77.41 5.18 
20 
71 
TCGA LUAD 5.0e-5 
66.86 3.58 
14 
112 
TCGA LUSC 
2.0e-3 
63.51 2.43 
14 
147 
Yu 
1.0e-3 
65.83 3.07 
10 
224 
Yu lung biomarker 
Raponi 
6.3e-1 
60.62 1.19 
5 
71 
TCGA LUAD 5.0e-2 
66.08 1.54 
4 
112 
TCGA LUSC 
8.2e-2 
56.06 1.61 
4 
147 
Yu 
1.0e-1 
58.52 1.87 
5 
224 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="10"> of the 20 miRNAs are significant if fitted in the high-risk group suggesting that these miRNAs are important. For a comparison analysis of two signatures, we tested the 20 miRNAs of the Raponi signature and a 5-miRNA signature associated to survival in LSCC proposed by Yu et al.(2008). The summary shown in Table 1 (the details are included in the Tutorial Section 5.3) suggests that the Raponi signature is superior. 4 CONCLUSION The evaluations demonstrate that a curated database and systematic tool for biomarker evaluation can rapidly produce valuable information for the validation of miRNA signatures in various cohorts. We conclude that SurvMicro is a free and easy-to-use web tool to assess the performance of prognostic miRNA-based biomarkers. Funding: The authors thank CONACyT grant 140601 and Ca´tedraCa´tedra Bioinforma´ticaBioinforma´tica CAT220 from ITESM for funding and scholarships. Conflict of Interest: none declared. REFERENCES Antonov,A.V. et al. (2013) MIRUMIR: an online tool to test microRNAs as biomarkers to predict survival in cancer using multiple clinical data sets. Cell Death Differ., 20, 367.</note>

			<note place="foot">SurvMicro at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">R.Aguirre-Gamboa and V.Trevino at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MicroRNA signatures in human cancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Calin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Croce</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="857" to="866" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oncomirs—microRNAs with a role in cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Esquela-Kerscher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Slack</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="269" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PROGmiR: a tool for identifying prognostic miRNA biomarkers in multiple cancers using publicly available data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Goswami</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Nakshatri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Bioinforma</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">miRBase: microRNA sequences, targets and gene nomenclature</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="140" to="144" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systemic mirnas as potential biomarkers for malignancy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Healy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2215" to="2222" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why your new cancer biomarker may never work: recurrent patterns and remarkable diversity in biomarker failures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Kern</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6097" to="6101" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MicroRNA classifiers for predicting prognosis of squamous cell lung cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Raponi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5776" to="5783" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The 21-nucleotide let-7 RNA regulates developmental timing in Caenorhabditis elegans</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Reinhart</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">403</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="901" to="906" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MicroRNAs: novel regulators in the hallmarks of human cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Ruan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">285</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="116" to="126" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disease Ontology: a backbone for disease semantic integration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Schriml</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="940" to="946" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Modeling Survival Data: Extending the Cox Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Therneau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Grambsch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical significance and prognostic value of microRNA expression signatures in hepatocellular carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Wei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4780" to="4791" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MicroRNA signature predicts survival and relapse in lung cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Yu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GEOmetadb: powerful alternative search engine for the Gene Expression Omnibus</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Zhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2798" to="800" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>