
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:32+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis SVA: software for annotating and visualizing sequenced human genomes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dongliang</forename>
								<surname>Ge</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Duke University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>27708</postCode>
									<settlement>Durham</settlement>
									<region>North Carolina</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename>
								<forename type="middle">K</forename>
								<surname>Ruzzo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kevin</forename>
								<forename type="middle">V</forename>
								<surname>Shianna</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Min</forename>
								<surname>He</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kimberly</forename>
								<surname>Pelak</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Erin</forename>
								<forename type="middle">L</forename>
								<surname>Heinzen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anna</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Need</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename>
								<forename type="middle">T</forename>
								<surname>Cirulli</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jessica</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Maia</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Samuel</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Dickson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mingfu</forename>
								<surname>Zhu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Abanish</forename>
								<surname>Singh</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andrew</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Allen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Duke University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>27708</postCode>
									<settlement>Durham</settlement>
									<region>North Carolina</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<forename type="middle">B</forename>
								<surname>Goldstein</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Human Genome Variation</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis SVA: software for annotating and visualizing sequenced human genomes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1998" to="2000"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr317</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on January 18, 2011; revised on April 11, 2011; accepted on May 22, 2011</note>
					<note>[10:29 21/6/2011 Bioinformatics-btr317.tex] Associate Editor: John Quackenbush Contact: d.ge@duke.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Here we present Sequence Variant Analyzer (SVA), a software tool that assigns a predicted biological function to variants identified in next-generation sequencing studies and provides a browser to visualize the variants in their genomic contexts. SVA also provides for flexible interaction with software implementing variant association tests allowing users to consider both the bioinformatic annotation of identified variants and the strength of their associations with studied traits. We illustrate the annotation features of SVA using two simple examples of sequenced genomes that harbor Mendelian mutations. Availability and implementation: Freely available on the web at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Recent advances in next-generation sequencing (NGS) technologies have made it possible to search through entire genomes for variants that influence traits of interest (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Choi et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Lupski et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Ng et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Roach et al., 2010</ref>). However, analyzing NGS data still requires addressing a number of considerable computational challenges. A variety of methods have been developed to firstly align the sequence reads (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Langmead et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Li and Durbin, 2009</ref>), and secondly to identify the genetic variants (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bentley et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Chen et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Hormozdiari et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Li et al., 2009</ref>). In this work, we focus on the downstream annotation necessary for the analysis of variants and provide simple means of visualizing variants in their genomic context using a built-in genome browser (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). One fundamental difference from the previous approach of using genome-wide association studies (GWAS) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">McCarthy et al., 2008</ref>), is that many of the variants identified in NGS will be newly discovered. A second fundamental difference is that unlike GWAS data, sequence data, at least in principle, provides complete<ref type="figure">1</ref>. A screenshot of SVA, highlighting a frameshift indel that is located on exon 14 of the Factor VIII gene and is the cause of type A hemophilia. information about the variation present in a genome. For both of these reasons, it is essential to develop a computational environment that can assess the likely functions of the variants observed, and whether or not they are present in existing variant databases. In most contexts, such functional assignments will need to be considered along with statistical association evidence in order to prioritize variants in terms of their likelihoods of influencing traits of interest. We also emphasize that in the early days of interpreting sequence data for complex traits, the sequence data itself will often not be sufficient to provide statistical confidence of association. Instead, the bioinformatic prioritization helps to point towards variants of interest that can be evaluated in much larger sample sets by direct genotyping. We have designed Sequence Variant Analyzer (SVA) to meet these challenges, and in this report, we use two examples to illustrate some of the annotation features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>SVA was developed using the Java programming language, using the NetBeans IDE (Oracle, Redwood Shores, CA, USA). The graphical user interface was developed using Java Swing. A standard edition of SVA is available by DVD ROM, or a downloadable package (http://www.svaproject.org/). Additionally, we provide a much smaller evaluation edition. SVA uses a customized indexing, storing and optimizing<ref type="bibr">Page: 1999</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Page: 1998</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Page: –2000</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sequence Variant Analyzer</head><p>mechanism. Therefore, to run SVA, installation and optimization of database systems is not required. SVA is also multiple-core aware, although Input/Output (I/O) consumes the majority of the computational time. SVA is an elaboration of WGAViewer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Ge et al., 2008</ref>), which was designed for the interpretation of GWAS datasets. A number of publicly available genomic and biological databases are used by SVA for the annotation of genomic variants. We used the NCBI RefSeq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Pruitt et al., 2007</ref>) as the reference genome in SVA. Both human reference genome builds 36 and 37 are currently supported. We used the Ensembl core and variation databases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Flicek et al., 2010</ref>) as the main source of annotation features for genes and variations. We also provide options to include user-specified annotation tracks, for example, gene annotation dataset or transcription factor binding sites downloadable from the UCSC genome browser. We used the HUGO Gene Nomenclature Committee (HGNC) database as the primary source for naming canonical genes. Gene functions were annotated by integrating information from the Ensembl core, the gene ontology (GO) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ashburner et al., 2000</ref>), and the KEGG pathway databases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Kanehisa et al., 2010</ref>). We used RefSNP, HapMap (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Frazer et al., 2007</ref>), the 1000 Genomes Project (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Durbin et al., 2010</ref>), and the DGV databases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Iafrate et al., 2004</ref>) for checking the novelty of identified genetic variants. We will release compiled annotation databases when new reference genome builds become available. Within each reference genome build, users may update their gene annotation databases by directly downloading the annotation data files following our online instructions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>The SVA tool utilizes a knowledgebase of 8.9 GB, which is compiled and compressed into DVD ROM or can be downloaded from the SVA website. The main annotation functionality is performed locally and does not require an active internet connection. This tool has two distinct modules that allow analysis of the genomes included in a given project: the annotation module is used to determine genomic context and to predict the potential biological function of the identified variants (for example, synonymous or nonsynonymous, essential splice, etc.) in each genome. The results can then be visualized in SVA's built-in genome browser (visualization module). The annotated variants can also be exported to a separate statistical tool, for example ATAV (http://www.duke.edu/~minhe/atav/), to assess their statistical associations with traits. Importantly, SVA is designed to conveniently connect its bioinformatic annotations with the statistical association tests so that users are allowed to consider them both and even suggestive association evidence may catch the users' attention. There are also a number of integrated bioinformatic listing functions in SVA designed to help prioritize genetic variants. In broad overview, therefore, SVA inputs a set of identified variants for each genome, annotates them for possible functionality, and permits the user a variety of ways to visualize and filter the resulting data with relationship to phenotypic information. The basic principles of these core analyses are fairly simple, but the strength of these analyses is their ability to be seamlessly run across multiple genomes to prioritize all variants and genes at once. Two examples illustrate SVA's utility: To illustrate the simple annotation features of SVA we have analyzed the sequence data for subjects with two different Mendelian diseases. (1) Hemophilia A is an X-linked recessive disorder that is characterized by excessive bleeding due to improper clotting. Genetic mutations in the Factor VIII gene are known to cause Hemophilia A; therefore, it is possible to use this disease as a positive control. We annotated 10 case and 10 control genomes and found that the gene with the most cases harboring a rare mutation was Factor VIII (F8) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Pelak et al., 2010</ref>). An SVA genome browser view of one of the identified indels is shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. (2) Metachondromatosis (MC) is an autosomal dominant condition affecting bone growth. Our center performed a whole-genome sequencing of one MC patient, following a linkage analysis that implicated six candidate regions spanning a total of 42 MB. We took a three-step strategy: we first applied SVA's genomic region filter; we next applied SVA's novelty filters to identify variants that were absent in dbSNP and absent in all eight control genomes; and finally, we applied SVA's functional filters to identify proteintruncating variants. These filtering steps quickly identify an 11-bp frameshifting deletion on the PTPN11 gene as the cause, which was validated in a separate family (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sobreira et al., 2010</ref>). We note that for these simple cases no association tests are required (beyond rarity or absence in controls), whereas in the case of complex traits SVA would normally be used alongside a program like ATAV to facilitate the consideration of variants that are both annotated as functional and that show some degree of statistical association with trait values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSIONS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>The overriding philosophy of SVA is that the interpretation of wholegenome sequence data benefits from simultaneous consideration of multiple lines of evidence, in particular bioinformatic annotation of variant function and statistical genetic association with trait values. We note this philosophy contrasts with what emerged as best practice for GWAS in which all variants were implicitly considered equally likely a priori to show association with traits (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">McCarthy et al., 2008</ref>). While there are several genome browser and annotation programs available today that are suitable for different needs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Fiume et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Robinson et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Wang et al., 2010</ref>; SeattleSeq: http://gvs.gs.washington.edu/SeattleSeqAnnotation/), we are unaware of any that performs the integrated features of SVA including: variant annotation and filtering by function and/or calling QC, visualization in a built-in browser and convenient export of user selected variants for statistical association testing. These features allow users to interact directly with the full set of data that are relevant to making a judgment about which variants show the strongest combined evidence of influencing the trait of interest. We also note that the SVA framework is fully generalizable, and over time we expect a number of new annotation features to be incorporated which will take advantage of knowledge of the functional regions of the human genome emerging from the ENCODE project (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Birney et al., 2007</ref>) and related activities. Additionally, in principle, SVA could be modified to perform annotations in other species. Future development plans include developing versions of SVA in highly used model organisms.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. A screenshot of SVA, highlighting a frameshift indel that is located on exon 14 of the Factor VIII gene and is the cause of type A hemophilia.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>[10:29 21/6/2011 Bioinformatics-btr317.tex]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: The Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation (grant 157412); National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases Center for HIV/AIDS Vaccine Immunology (grant AI067854); National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (grant RC2NS070344); National Institute of Mental Health (grant RC2MH089915). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2000"> at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Ge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate whole human genome sequencing using reversible terminator chemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Bentley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">456</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification and analysis of functional elements in 1% of the human genome by the ENCODE pilot project</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Birney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">447</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="799" to="816" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BreakDancer: an algorithm for high-resolution mapping of genomic structural variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="677" to="681" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Genetic diagnosis by whole exome capture and massively parallel DNA sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Choi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<publisher>PNAS</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19096" to="19101" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A map of human genome variation from population-scale sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Durbin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">467</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1061" to="1073" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Savant: genome browser for high-throughput sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Fiume</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1938" to="1944" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ensembl&apos;s 10th year</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Flicek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="557" to="562" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A second generation human haplotype map of over 3.1 million SNPs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Frazer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">449</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="851" to="861" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WGAViewer: software for genomic annotation of whole genome association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Ge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="640" to="643" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combinatorial algorithms for structural variation detection in high-throughput sequenced genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Hormozdiari</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1270" to="1278" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of large-scale variation in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Iafrate</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="949" to="951" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KEGG for representation and analysis of molecular networks involving diseases and drugs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kanehisa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="360" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Langmead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast and accurate short read alignment with BurrowsWheeler transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Durbin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1754" to="1760" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The sequence alignment/map format and SAMtools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2078" to="2079" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole-genome sequencing in a patient with Charcot-MarieTooth neuropathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Lupski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New England J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">362</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1181" to="1191" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide association studies for complex traits: consensus, uncertainty and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Mccarthy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="356" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exome sequencing identifies the cause of a mendelian disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Ng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The characterization of twenty sequenced human genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Pelak</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1001111</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NCBI reference sequences (RefSeq): a curated non-redundant sequence database of genomes, transcripts and proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Pruitt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of genetic inheritance in a family quartet by wholegenome sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Roach</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">328</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="636" to="639" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrative genomics viewer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole-genome sequencing of a single proband together with linkage analysis identifies a Mendelian disease gene</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L M</forename>
				<surname>Sobreira</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000991</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ANNOVAR: functional annotation of genetic variants from highthroughput sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">164</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>