
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:59+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis SVGenes: a library for rendering genomic features in scalable vector graphic format</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Graham</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Etherington</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">The Sainsbury Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Norwich Research Park</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>NR4 7UH</postCode>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Daniel</forename>
								<surname>Maclean</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>dan.maclean@tsl.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">The Sainsbury Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Norwich Research Park</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>NR4 7UH</postCode>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">The Sainsbury Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Norwich Research Park</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>NR4 7UH</postCode>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis SVGenes: a library for rendering genomic features in scalable vector graphic format</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1890" to="1892"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt294</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 7, 2013; revised on April 19, 2013; accepted on May 20, 2013</note>
					<note>Availability: The library is provided as a Ruby Gem from https://ruby-gems.org/gems/bio-svgenes under the MIT license, and open source code is available at https://github.com/danmaclean/bioruby-svgenes also under the MIT License. Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Drawing genomic features in attractive and informative ways is a key task in visualization of genomics data. Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) format is a modern and flexible open standard that provides advanced features including modular graphic design, advanced web interactivity and animation within a suitable client. SVGs do not suffer from loss of image quality on re-scaling and provide the ability to edit individual elements of a graphic on the whole object level independent of the whole image. These features make SVG a potentially useful format for the preparation of publication quality figures including genomic objects such as genes or sequencing coverage and for web applications that require rich user-interaction with the graphical elements. Results: SVGenes is a Ruby-language library that uses SVG primi-tives to render typical genomic glyphs through a simple and flexible Ruby interface. The library implements a simple Page object that spaces and contains horizontal Track objects that in turn style, colour and positions features within them. Tracks are the level at which visual information is supplied providing the full styling capability of the SVG standard. Genomic entities like genes, transcripts and histograms are modelled in Glyph objects that are attached to a track and take advantage of SVG primitives to render the gen-omic features in a track as any of a selection of defined glyphs. The feature model within SVGenes is simple but flexible and not dependent on particular existing gene feature formats meaning graphics for any existing datasets can easily be created without need for conversion.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Visualization, analysis and communication of genome data is an important task in genomics. Numerous desktop computer programs exist for rendering images of genomic data, usually in analytic pipelines including Artemis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Carver et al., 2008</ref>). Genome browsers such as Gbrowse (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Stein et al., 2002</ref>), JBrowse (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Skinner et al., 2009</ref>), Savant (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Fiume et al., 2010</ref>) and IGV (Thorvaldsdo´ttir<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Thorvaldsdo´ttir et al., 2013</ref>) provide interactive visualization of the data for whole genomes and draft assemblies. Output from these is typically limited to an exported bitmap or screen grab in the program's particular fixed style. Graphics libraries such as GD and ImageMagick have been used in projects like BioPerl (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Stajich et al., 2002</ref>) and BioRuby (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Goto et al., 2010</ref>) to create uniquely styled bitmap images like PNG and JPEG programmatically. BioRubys bio-graphics package has similar functionality to bio-svgenes and relies on external libraries such as Cairo, Pango and ImageMagick. The Bio.Graphics module in Biopython (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cock et al., 2009</ref>) also supports output in SVG through the use of third-party software [ReportLab (http://www.reportlab.com/)]. Bitmap images are limited in that they are not easy to re-annotate, re-scale and often cannot be reproduced for publication or presentation with high-fidelity because of limitations of the original bitmaps. Bitmaps can be difficult to manipulate and are not easily amenable to the addition of interactive features. Interactive graphics can be provided in web-browsers through JavaScript libraries such as D3.js but there are no such libraries available specifically for easy rendering of genomic data. Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) is an XML-based graphic standard under development by the World Wide Web Consortium that provides many advantages for those seeking to produce rich, attractive images. SVG is a vector format so does not suffer image quality degradation on rescaling, has advanced image features such as alpha masks and filter effects, web-interactivity and can be styled with Cascading Style Sheets. Furthermore, as a textbased format, SVG is well suited for searching and indexing in databases and is amenable to lossless compression. SVG can be rendered by modern web-browsers and graphics software including Adobe's Illustrator and the open source Inkscape programs. SVG output is available from some applications. CGView (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Grant et al., 2012</ref>) and Circos (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Krzywinski et al., 2009</ref>) are good tools for viewing circular genomes in particular. GenomeDiagram (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Pritchard et al., 2006</ref>) is designed to display large amounts of comparative genomics data. MGV (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kerkhoven et al., 2004</ref>) is a database-driven web application designed specifically for microbial data and AnnotationSketch (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Steinbiss et al., 2009</ref>), which is dependant on third-party software. SVGenes is a pure Ruby language library that allows a user to set styles for tracks of genomic features and will automatically layout and generate SVG images composed of several pre-defined genomics glyphs, including genes, transcripts, data and single-nucleotide features. *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">APPROACH</head><p>SVGenes uses a simple feature Page-Track-Feature model to organize the genomic data and to apply style information provided to it.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">The page and track object</head><p>The page object represents the area into which feature tracks are drawn, it has straightforward width, height and background attributes. Height is not fixed and is recalculated if more space is required to render all the constituent features at the specified sizes. The background attribute of the page can be styled, and an automatically generated scale bar is created and added to the top of the rendered page. Instantiating new track objects is the main way that styling information is specified, the track attributes set the final visual style of the genomic features and is responsible for placing them within the track on the page.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Glyphs and feature objects</head><p>SVGenes can render genomic features using various glyphs including gene, transcript and point features. Data tracks representing, e.g. sequence read coverage can be rendered as histograms and the flexible styling options allow for a great deal of variety of appearance (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>shows some examples). Each glyph takes style information from the track, and full SVG styling syntax can be used for arbitrary styling information including opacity settings. HTML colours and some pre-defined gradient fills are available through keyword declaration, greatly simplifying basic styling. The feature object represents genomic features simply and flexibly. As a minimum, start and stop positions are required for the basic glyphs. Grouped features such as transcripts are represented by start and stop information for the parent object and start and stops for the block elements within, such as exons and untranslated regions. Data glyphs are bars with start, width and height elements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Workflow</head><p>SVGenes provides programmatic and configuration-based rendering workflows. Within a Ruby script, a user may manually instantiate a page object and attach tracks as required, then create and add the feature objects to the appropriate tracks. This workflow does not rely on any particular feature file format. For input from the popular GFF format, a configuration-based workflow is provided. In this, the user is able to create a JSON configuration file that describes each track and contains links to a file containing the features or data values to be rendered in each track.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSION</head><p>SVGenes is a useful and flexible library for creating easily manipulated, high-quality, web-friendly images of genomic data quickly and easily in SVG format without embedding a bitmap. The library can be used for visualization at many levels; in highthroughput pipelines and web applications, but individual users preparing figures for publication will also find the library extremely useful, as the individual elements of the images can be independently manipulated and annotated and composited.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Thanks to Diane Saunders and Florian Jupe for feedback on the use and development of the library. Funding: Gatsby Charitable Foundation. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Rendering of features from the TAIR 10 annotation of the Arabidopsis genome (Lamesch et al., 2012). The region shown is Chromosome 3: 19 597 235–19 637 249. Tracks contain (from top to bottom) (i) Genes with the 'directed' glyph, (ii) mRNAs with the 'transcript' glyph, (iii) cDNA matches with the 'directed' glyph, (iv) microarray probes with the 'generic' glyph, (v) insertions with the 'down triangle' glyph, (vi) deletions with the 'up triangle' glyph, (vii) TE insertions with the 'circle' glyph, (viii) a data track showing simulated NGS data (height calculated from a sine function of the genome position) and (ix) a data track showing random bar heights</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Artemis and act: viewing, annotating and comparing sequences stored in a relational database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Carver</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2672" to="2676" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biopython: freely available Python tools for computational molecular biology and bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Cock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1422" to="1423" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Savant: genome browser for high-throughput sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Fiume</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1938" to="1944" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioRuby: bioinformatics software for the Ruby programming language</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Goto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2617" to="2619" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparing thousands of circular genomes using the CGView Comparison Tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Grant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">202</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization for genomics: the microbial genome viewer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Kerkhoven</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1812" to="1814" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circos: an information aesthetic for comparative genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Krzywinski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1639" to="1645" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The arabidopsis information resource (TAIR): improved gene annotation and new tools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Lamesch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1202" to="1210" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GenomeDiagram: a python package for the visualization of large-scale genomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Pritchard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="616" to="617" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">JBrowse: a next-generation genome browser</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Skinner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1630" to="1638" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The bioperl toolkit: Perl modules for the life sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Stajich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1611" to="1618" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The generic genome browser: a building block for a model organism system database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Stein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1599" to="1610" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AnnotationSketch: a genome annotation drawing library</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Steinbiss</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="533" to="534" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrative genomics viewer (IGV): high-performance genomics data visualization and exploration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Thorvaldsdo´ttirthorvaldsdo´ttir</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="192" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Etherington</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Maclean</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>