
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis svviz: a read viewer for validating structural variants</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Noah</forename>
								<surname>Spies</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Genome Scale Measurements Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute of Standards and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Justin</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Zook</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Genome Scale Measurements Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Institute of Standards and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Gaithersburg</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Marc</forename>
								<surname>Salit</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Genome Scale Measurements Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute of Standards and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Arend</forename>
								<surname>Sidow</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis svviz: a read viewer for validating structural variants</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv478</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 15, 2015; revised on July 20, 2015; accepted on August 10, 2015</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Inanc Birol Contact: nspies@stanford.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Visualizing read alignments is the most effective way to validate candidate structural variants (SVs) with existing data. We present svviz, a sequencing read visualizer for SVs that sorts and displays only reads relevant to a candidate SV. svviz works by searching input bam(s) for potentially relevant reads, realigning them against the inferred sequence of the putative variant allele as well as the reference allele and identifying reads that match one allele better than the other. Separate views of the two alleles are then displayed in a scrollable web browser view, enabling a more intuitive visualization of each allele, compared with the single reference genome-based view common to most current read browsers. The browser view facilitates examining the evidence for or against a putative variant, estimating zygosity, visualizing affected genomic annotations and manual refinement of breakpoints. svviz supports data from most modern sequencing platforms. Availability and implementation: svviz is implemented in python and freely available from http:// svviz.github.io/.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The human eye has an unparalleled ability to identify patterns from visual representations of data. Although the identification of mutations from high-throughput sequencing has been largely automated, visual inspection of putative variants using tools such as the integrative genomics viewer (IGV;<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Robinson et al., 2011</ref>) remains an important step in ensuring the quality and relevance of these variant calls. However, existing read visualizing tools such as IGV are largely constrained by a reference-genome-centric display model. Hence, point mutations can be represented easily as mismatched bases within sequencing data but more complex structural variants (SVs) including insertions, deletions, translocations and inversions are more difficult to parse visually against the linear reference genome sequence. Newer tools are able to represent short indels within sequencing data but do not help in representing larger SVs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Edmonson et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Gymrek, 2014</ref>). Support for SVs can be displayed within IGV by highlighting reads with certain characteristics, including read-pairs mapping to distant regions of the genome or in unexpected orientations, or truncated alignments. However, it is difficult to identify from these highlighted, discordantly mapping reads whether they all agree with a putative variant, and if so, which variant. Furthermore, IGV relies on the quality and completeness of the alignments provided in input BAM files, which are produced en masse against a huge reference genome and hence may not optimally represent read support for a given variant. Finally, most existing viewers (a notable exception being TargetSeqView;<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Halper-Stromberg et al., 2014</ref>) show all read data in the vicinity of a putative SV, making it difficult to discriminate reads supporting the SV, reads supporting the reference allele and reads that are not relevant to an SV. To overcome these limitations, we present svviz, a read visualizer for SVs that sorts and displays only reads relevant to the</p><p>Published by Oxford University Press 2015. This work is written by US Government employees and is in the public domain in the US. current SV. As with IGV, svviz only visualizes variants and does not identify them. svviz runs locally on a standard OS X or Linux desktop machine and requires as input read data, a reference genome and SVs. The flexible approach employed by svviz means it can display arbitrary SV types such as translocations, deletions and insertions, inversions and mobile-element insertions. Visualizations are rendered in scalable vector graphics (SVG), an open web standard graphics format, and shown in a locally hosted interactive web browser viewer or exported in publication-ready form. svviz supports read data in BAM format from any sequencing platform, including short-read [Illumina (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bentley et al., 2008)</ref>] single-and paired-end as well as mate-pair or longer read [Pacific Biosciences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Eid et al., 2009</ref>), Oxford Nanopore or Illumina's synthetic long-reads] sequencing technologies. In batch mode, multiple SVs can be provided as input in the standard variant call format (VCF), producing summary statistics and PDF or SVG visualizations for hundreds or thousands of SVs with a single command. Annotations such as gene models or repeats can be shown relative to each allele.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>svviz performs several preprocessing steps before visualizing a particular SV: 1. Breakpoints for the input SV are processed to produce a representation of the unique genomic sequence of the SV. 2. Reads are identified that map near all SV breakpoints. 3. For paired-end data, read mates are collected. 4. Reads are realigned both to the alternate (SV) allele and to the reference allele by Smith-Waterman alignment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Zhao et al., 2013</ref>). 5. Reads are assigned to the reference or alternate allele if they better support one allele over the other; otherwise, they are labeled as ambiguous. The criteria for this step are described later. 6. Reference and alternate alleles are visualized separately with individual tracks for each input sample for each allele. Ambiguous reads, typically mapping near but outside of the breakpoints, can also be visualized in a third set of tracks.</p><p>Realigned reads are assigned to the allele with the higher alignment score, or (if scores are identical), the allele with the better match to the empirical insert size distribution (derived from the input BAM file). Reads that cannot confidently be assigned to one allele or the other are instead marked as ambiguous, for example when read-pair orientations are incorrect or the alignment score is below that expected for the given sequencing platform. This process extends the approach adopted in TargetSeqView (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Halper-Stromberg et al., 2014</ref>), enabling allele assignment of arbitrary length reads (eg, those produced by long-read technologies) and taking advantage of the insert size distribution, which can be more informative than the alignment score.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>The Genome in a Bottle consortium (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Zook et al., 2014</ref>) has recently begun sequencing an Ashkenazi Jewish trio from the Personal Genome Project with a number of high-throughput sequencing platforms, providing a rich resource for identifying and validating variants using orthogonal experimental methods. SVs were called from Complete Genomics data for mother, father and son separately. From these variant calls, we randomly chose an 11.5 kb inversion on Chromosome 4 to visualize and validate using long mate-pair Illumina data. The visual representation is split into two sections. The top section (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1a</ref>) shows reads supporting the alternate 'inversion' allele, while the bottom section (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1b</ref>) shows those supporting the reference allele. Each read is shown only once, relative to its assigned allele. For the alternate allele, mate-pair reads tile across the breakpoints in both parents, while no reads were found in the son. All three individuals show ample coverage of the reference allele breakpoints. The number of reads assigned by svviz to each allele suggests the son is homozygous reference and both parents are heterozygous for the inversion. Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S1</ref>shows the same data represented in IGV, with likely non-reference reads SonReads supporting the reference allele, with non-inverted region again shown in blue at bottom (but arrows pointing to the right). Red reads are on the minus strand and purple reads are on the plus strand, with gray lines linking mate-pairs (note that the mate-pair data shown here are sequenced in À/+ orientation, and have an average insert size of $6.5 kb). Ambiguous reads, those unable to distinguish between the alleles, are not shown svvizcolored maroon and blue, suggestive of a SV but difficult to interpret as an inversion. Additional visualization examples are shown in the supplement: a putative 1200 bp deletion for which svviz shows very little supporting evidence, and which we thus estimate is a falsepositive (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>); an inversion with PacBio reads spanning both breakpoints (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>); svviz being used to refine imprecisely called breakpoints (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig.  S4</ref>); a mobile-element insertion (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S5</ref>); a fusion gene present in a cancer sample but not the matched normal sample (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6</ref>); a heterozygous deletion with reads in flanking regions shown to demonstrate the reduction in read coverage within the deletion (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S7</ref>) and a screenshot of the web view, zoomed in to show a single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) present only in the alternate allele (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S8</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>No reads found</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Usage</head><p>svviz can be installed on OS X and Linux using the single command 'sudo pip install svviz' (requires python and pip to be installed; see the online documentation at http://svviz.github.io/ for detailed installation instructions). It takes $10–30 s to analyze and visualize a single variant in a single sample on a 2014 Mac Pro. The number of samples that can be visualized simultaneously is limited only by practical concerns; processing time scales with the number of samples and reads as well as the size of the variant and lengths of the reads. The inversion shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>can be visualized using the command 'svviz demo' and the mobile-element insertion in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S5</ref>can be visualized using the command 'svviz demo 2'.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. svviz visualization of a Chromosome 4 inversion. (a) Reads supporting the alternate allele in three individuals. Blue region with arrows pointing to the left demarcate the inverted region. (b) Reads supporting the reference allele, with non-inverted region again shown in blue at bottom (but arrows pointing to the right). Red reads are on the minus strand and purple reads are on the plus strand, with gray lines linking mate-pairs (note that the mate-pair data shown here are sequenced in À/+ orientation, and have an average insert size of $6.5 kb). Ambiguous reads, those unable to distinguish between the alleles, are not shown</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">Bioinformatics, 31(24), 2015, 3994–3996 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv478 Advance Access Publication Date: 18 August 2015 Applications Note at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">N.Spies et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors thank the Genome in a Bottle Consortium and Complete Genomics for making the data publicly available. Certain commercial equipment, instruments or materials are identified in this document. Such identification neither does imply recommendation or endorsement by the National Institute of Standards and Technology nor does it imply that the products identified are necessarily the best available for the purpose.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate whole human genome sequencing using reversible terminator chemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Bentley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">456</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bambino: a variant detector and alignment viewer for next-generation sequencing data in the SAM/BAM format</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Edmonson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="865" to="866" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time DNA sequencing from single polymerase molecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Eid</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">323</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PyBamView: a browser-based application for viewing short read alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Gymrek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3405" to="3407" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization and probability-based scoring of structural variants within repetitive sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Halper-Stromberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1514" to="1521" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrative genomics viewer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SSW library: an SIMD Smith-Waterman C/Cþþ library for use in genomic applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Zhao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">82138</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating human sequence data sets provides a resource of benchmark SNP and indel genotype calls</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Zook</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="246" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>