
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:43+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis SWEEPFINDER2: increased sensitivity, robustness and flexibility</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<surname>Degiorgio</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology and Institute for CyberScience</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>University Park</addrLine>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christian</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Huber</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Melissa</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Hubisz</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Statistics and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Cornell University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ithaca</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ines</forename>
								<surname>Hellmann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department Biologie II</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität Mü nchen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Planegg-Martinsried</addrLine>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rasmus</forename>
								<surname>Nielsen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Integrative Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis SWEEPFINDER2: increased sensitivity, robustness and flexibility</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received on 28 May 2015; revised on 6 January 2016; accepted on 19 January 2016</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Janet Kelso Contact: mxd60@psu.edu</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>SWEEPFINDER is a widely used program that implements a powerful likelihood-based method for detecting recent positive selection, or selective sweeps. Here, we present SWEEPFINDER2, an extension of SWEEPFINDER with increased sensitivity and robustness to the confounding effects of mutation rate variation and background selection. Moreover, SWEEPFINDER2 has increased flexibility that enables the user to specify test sites, set the distance between test sites and utilize a recombin-ation map. Availability and implementation: SWEEPFINDER2 is a freely-available (www.personal.psu.edu/mxd60/ sf2.html) software package that is written in C and can be run from a Unix command line.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Polymorphism frequency spectra provide sensitive statistics for identifying signatures of positive selection. SWEEPFINDER (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Nielsen et al., 2005</ref>) is a widely used program (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Li et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Pavlidis et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Svetec et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Williamson et al., 2007</ref>) that uses an empirical background frequency spectrum for identifying genomic sites affected by recent positive selection. Specifically, SWEEPFINDER performs a composite likelihood ratio test for positive selection (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Kim and Stephan, 2002</ref>), in which the likelihood of the null hypothesis is calculated from the neutral (or genome-wide) frequency spectrum, and the likelihood of the alternative hypothesis is calculated from a model in which the neutral spectrum was altered by a recent selective sweep. Footprints of positive selection can be confounded by other evolutionary forces. One important confounding factor that is rarely considered in the studies of positive selection is background selection, which is a loss of neutral variation due to purging of linked deleterious alleles by negative selection (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Charlesworth, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Charlesworth et al., 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hudson and Kaplan, 1995a</ref>). Recent studies have shown that background selection is ubiquitous in humans (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Lohmueller et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">McVicker et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Wilson Sayres et al., 2014</ref>), with estimates of mean reductions in genetic diversity due to background selection ranging from 19 to 26% and 12 to 40% on autosomes and the X chromosome, respectively (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">McVicker et al., 2009</ref>). Thus, the influence of background selection on genetic diversity has important ramifications for making inferences about past adaptive processes from patterns of diversity. In particular, when a beneficial allele is carried to fixation by positive selection, there is a substantial decrease in diversity locally in the genome and a reduction in diversity relative to divergence with other species, both of which can span megabases in length (Maynard<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Smith and Haigh, 1974</ref>). Background selection can similarly affect diversity levels (<ref type="bibr">Akashi et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Boyko et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Charlesworth, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Charlesworth et al., 1993</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Charlesworth et al., 1995</ref><ref type="bibr">Hudson and Kaplan, 1995a,b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">McVean and Charlesworth, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Nordborg et al., 1996</ref>), particularly in regions of low recombination. V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</p></div>
			<note place="foot">Bioinformatics, 32(12), 2016, 1895–1897 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw051 Advance Access Publication Date: 15 February 2016 Applications Note at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from Because patterns of background selection can mimic those of positive selection, methods for identifying signatures of positive selection that are based on diversity reduction alone may be confounded by background selection. These conflicting signals have likely contributed to a current debate of the role of recent positive selection in shaping the landscape of human genetic variation (Akey, 2009; Enard et al., 2014; Granka et al., 2012; Hawks et al., 2007, Hernandez et al., 2011; Lohmueller et al., 2011; Williamson et al., 2007), emphasizing the need for methods that can identify sweeps while accounting for background selection. Further, because the effects of background selection may be pronounced in regions of low recombination, it is important that methods jointly account for background selection and local recombination rate, which is also expected to affect patterns of a selective sweep. 2 SWEEPFINDER2 SWEEPFINDER2, which is based on the statistical framework of SWEEPFINDER (Nielsen et al., 2005), jointly accounts for background selection and local recombination rate by modeling the effect of background selection on genetic diversity. It does this by modifying the neutral derived frequency spectrum with respect to B-values and by including invariant sites (specifically substitutions), as introduced by Huber et al. (2015). B-values range from 0 to 1 and are proportional to local reductions in genetic diversity or effective population size due to background selection. McVicker et al. (2009) provide a method for inferring B-values using comparative data, thereby providing an opportunity for separating background selection from the effect of selective sweeps inferred from within-population polymorphism data. Because background selection reduces diversity by a factor B, we multiply each polymorphic frequency class (i.e. allele counts 1, 2,. .. , nÀ1 in a sample of n) by B, as shown in Figure 1A (Huber et al., 2015). Furthermore, because background selection affects diversity relative to divergence with another species, we scale the fixed difference class (i.e. allele count n), and then renormalize the frequency spectrum to sum to 1 (Fig. 1A). Note that this effect depends on the current and ancestral population sizes, as well as on the divergence time in generations between the pair of species. Further, our correction is a first-order approximation, as background selection can alter the frequency spectrum in other ways (e.g. Charlesworth et al., 1993, 1995; Nicolaisen and Desai, 2013; Seger et al., 2010). This point is exemplified by empirical results indicating that diversity reduction in regions with low recombination rates is less than expected under simple models of background selection (e.g. Kaiser and Charlesworth, 2009), though our approach is conservative under this scenario. Figure 1B illustrates how this procedure modifies the neutral frequency spectrum, such that diversity decreases and the proportion of fixed differences increases with increasing effect of background selection (i.e. decreasing B-value). Our method detects selective sweeps in regions under background selection by scaling the neutral frequency spectrum locally in the genome by estimated B-values (Fig. 1), using the scaled spectrum in the null hypothesis, and the spectrum under a model of a selective sweep (accounting for local recombination rate) in the alternative hypothesis (Huber et al., 2015). Regions with reductions in diversity and low B-values show little evidence of selective sweeps under this test because frequency spectra under the null and alternative hypotheses are similar (Fig. 1C). However, regions with reductions in diversity and relatively high B-values may provide evidence of recent selective sweeps, because frequency spectra under the alternative hypothesis will exhibit lower diversity than those under the null hypothesis. In addition, recent positively-selected alleles within regions undergoing background selection can still be detected (Fig. 1D). Furthermore, changes in B-values across the genome can be incorporated by modifying frequency spectra to preserve the spatial structure in genetic variation leveraged by SWEEPFINDER. While B-value maps are currently available only for humans (McVicker et al., 2009) and Drosophila melanogaster (Comeron, 2014), the methodology introduced by McVicker et al. can be employed to generate maps for other species. SWEEPFINDER2 is the first method that accounts for the effects of negative selection on diversity when searching for adaptive alleles. In addition, it incorporates novel features that provide the user with increased flexibility, such as the ability to specify a set of test sites, set distances between test sites and employ a recombination map. Thus, our new composite likelihood ratio test generalizes the one implemented in SWEEPFINDER (Nielsen et al., 2005), and provides a substantial improvement in power and flexibility to the popular SWEEPFINDER software. Conflict of Interest: none declared. References Akashi,H. et al. (2012) Weak selection and protein evolution. Genetics, 192, 15–31. Fig. 1. Generating derived frequency spectra from a neutral frequency spectrum under background selection in a sample of 10 alleles and an outgroup sequence. (A) Polymorphic sites (allele counts 1–9) are scaled by a factor B, reducing diversity by 1-B. The proportion of fixed sites (allele count 10) is scaled by (T þ 2BN/n)/(T þ 2N/n), and the spectrum is then normalized to sum to 1. The scaling factor for the fixed difference class assumes a model in which a pair of species split T generations ago, with all populations having effective size N (SWEEPFINDER2 implementation permits unequal sizes). (B) Modified frequency spectra for 0, 20, 40 and 60% reductions in diversity due to background selection (B-values of 1.0, 0.8, 0.6 and 0.4, respectively). As Bvalue decreases, the level of diversity decreases, and the ratio of diversity to divergence decreases. (C, D) Simulation results (Huber et al., 2015) indicating composite likelihood ratio test statistics as a function of position along a sequence without (C) and with (D) a fixed selective sweep in the center of the sequence. The gray region represents a reduction in recombination rate by two orders of magnitude. Including the B-value map decreases false inferences of positive selection (C), yet still can identify positively-selected alleles in regions with background selection (D). Though panel D only displays results when correcting for background selection, it should be noted that the selection signal is overestimated when not controlling for background selection, and could lead to biased estimates of selection coefficients</note>

			<note place="foot">M.DeGiorgio et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Constructing genomic maps of positive selection in humans: where do we go from here?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Akey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="711" to="722" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing the evolutionary impact of amino acid mutations in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Boyko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of background selection in shaping patterns of molecular evolution and variation: evidence from variability on the Drosophila X chromosome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Charlesworth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of deleterious mutations on neutral molecular variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Charlesworth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1289" to="1303" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The pattern of neutral molecular variation under the background selection model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Charlesworth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1619" to="1632" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Background selection as baseline for nucleotide variation across the Drosophila genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Comeron</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1004434</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome wide signals of pervasive positive selection in human evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Enard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="885" to="895" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Limited evidence for classic selective sweeps in African populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Granka</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">192</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1049" to="1064" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent acceleration of human adaptive evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Hawks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20753" to="20758" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classic selective sweeps were rare in recent human evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hernandez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">331</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="920" to="924" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting recent selective sweeps while controlling for mutation rate and background selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Huber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deleterious background selection with recombination</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Hudson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Kaplan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1605" to="1617" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The coalescent process and background selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Hudson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Kaplan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">349</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effects of deleterious mutations on evolution in non-recombining genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Kaiser</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Charlesworth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting a local signature of genetic hitchhiking along a recombining chromosome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Stephan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">160</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="765" to="777" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global patterns of genetic diversity and signals of natural selection for human ADME genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mol. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="528" to="540" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Natural selection affects multiple aspects of genetic variation at putatively neutral sites across the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Lohmueller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002326</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The hitch-hiking effect of a variable gene</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Maynard</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Haigh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effects of Hill-Robertson interference between weakly selected mutations on patterns of molecular evolution and variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Mcvean</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Charlesworth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="929" to="944" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Widespread genomic signatures of natural selection in hominid evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Mcvicker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000471</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distortions in genealogies due to purifying selection and recombination</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Nicolaisen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Desai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">194</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="230" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Genomic scans for selective sweeps using SNP data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Nielsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1566" to="1575" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of recombination on background selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nordborg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Searching for footprints of positive selection in whole-genome SNP data from non-equilibrium populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Pavlidis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">185</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="907" to="922" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene genealogies strongly distorted by weakly interfering mutations in constant environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Seger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">184</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="545" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent strong positive selection on Drosophila melanogaster HDAC6, a gene encoding a stress surveillance factor, as revealed by population genomic analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Svetec</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1549" to="1556" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Localizing recent adaptive evolution in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Williamson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">90</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Natural selection reduced diversity on human Y chromosomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Wilson</forename>
				<surname>Sayres</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1004064</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>