
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">TAPAS: tools to assist the targeted protein quantification of human alternative splice variants</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">20 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jae-Seong</forename>
								<surname>Yang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">EMBL/CRG Systems Biology Research Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">Centre for Genomic Regulation (CRG)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eduard</forename>
								<surname>Sabid</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Proteomics Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Centre for Genomic Regulation (CRG)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08003</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Luis</forename>
								<surname>Serrano</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">EMBL/CRG Systems Biology Research Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">Centre for Genomic Regulation (CRG)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Instituci o Catalana de Recerca i Estudis Avanç ats (ICREA)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08010</postCode>
									<settlement>Barcelona</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christina</forename>
								<surname>Kiel</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">EMBL/CRG Systems Biology Research Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">Centre for Genomic Regulation (CRG)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">TAPAS: tools to assist the targeted protein quantification of human alternative splice variants</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2989" to="2990"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">20 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu428</idno>
					<note type="submission">Systems biology Advance Access publication July 4, 2014 Received on March 21, 2014; revised on June 22, 2014; accepted on June 29, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: In proteomes of higher eukaryotes, many alternative splice variants can only be detected by their shared peptides. This makes it highly challenging to use peptide-centric mass spectrometry to distinguish and to quantify protein isoforms resulting from alternative splicing events. Results: We have developed two complementary algorithms based on linear mathematical models to efficiently compute a minimal set of shared and unique peptides needed to quantify a set of isoforms and splice variants. Further, we developed a statistical method to estimate the splice variant abundances based on stable isotope labeled peptide quantities. The algorithms and databases are integrated in a web-based tool, and we have experimentally tested the limits of our quantification method using spiked proteins and cell extracts. Availability and implementation: The TAPAS server is available at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Higher eukaryotic proteomes have greatly expanded during evolution by the variation created by alternatively spliced forms of the same gene, duplication into orthologous genes and differentially processed proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Nilsen and Graveley, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Rappsilber and Mann, 2002</ref>). These multiple protein isoforms play significant roles in differentiation, development and disease (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Irimia and Blencowe, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Maniatis and Tasic, 2002</ref>). High-throughput genomic, transcriptomic and mass spectrometry (MS) technologies have facilitated the genome-wide identification of alternative splicing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Nagaraj et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Pan et al., 2008</ref>). It was shown that shifts in the relative splice transcript abundance between different cells and tissues are more frequently observed than all-or-none switch-like behaviors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Shen et al., 2012</ref>). Thus, knowing the amount of an expressed splice variant is highly desirable to understand cellular functions. Peptide-centric high-throughput shotgun MS approaches have achieved remarkable detection coverage (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Nagaraj et al., 2011</ref>). However, inferring protein isoform identities and estimating their abundances by peptide-centric shotgun MS is not straightforward, as many peptides are shared between isoforms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Nesvizhskii and Aebersold, 2005</ref>). Recently, statistical methods have addressed these problems by using both unique and shared peptides (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Blein-Nicolas et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Dost et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Gerster et al., 2014</ref>). While these methods have improved protein quantifications from peptide intensities, they were not specifically designed for a targeted MS approach of isoform analysis. In this work, we developed efficient computational optimization techniques to infer a minimal list of unique and shared peptides needed to accurately quantify a set of isoforms. This algorithm is integrated in a web-based tool (TAPAS) that assists in the design of stable isotope labeled (SIL) peptides for targeted MS experiments. experiments. It uses a numerical optimization method implemented in the Stan's C++ framework to find the desired solution, i.e. the quantities of splice variants, by minimizing the gaps between the estimated and observed abundances of peptides (Equation 1).</p><formula>X i log N logðA i Þjlog X k i;k k ! ; 2 E ! ! ð1Þ</formula><p>where A i is the abundance of peptide i and k is the estimated amount of splice variant k. i,k is indicator function that gives 1 when peptide i belongs to splice variant k, otherwise it gives zero. N(xj, 2 ) represents probability of x from normal distribution function with mean , and SD. To estimate the protein abundances of selected splicing variants, TAPAS requires the observed abundance of peptides, identification of peptidases and splice variant sequences as inputs. Validation of the quantification method: We tested our method with a simulation dataset modeled by lognormal distributions. TAPAS quickly converged to a solution and gave robust results on different simulations conditions. Moreover, we found that TAPAS accurately estimated amount of splice variants from experimentally measured peptides amounts. The average percentage of error in the estimated amounts of splice variants was 24.0%. We validated our computational approach by purifying and mixing two Grb2 splice variants and performing absolute quantitation of both splice variants using selected reaction monitoring (SRM) based on SIL reference peptides (Supplementary Material). Estimation of quantifiable splice variants: Through a systematic analysis of databases with MS-detected peptides (mostly of trypsin origin;<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Mallick et al., 2007</ref>), we theoretically estimated that 50% of the human isoforms and splice variants could be quantifiable. This number goes up to 92% if multiple specific proteases are independently used and the results are combined (Supplementary Material).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION</head><p>TAPAS is a framework that brings together experimental design and computational analysis for the absolute quantification of splice variants. It designs experiments by selecting the minimal combination of shared and unique peptides needed to analyze a specific set of splice variants. By taking advantage of quantitative SIL-based proteomics, TAPAS can estimate the quantities of splice variants. Our method also allows users to query protein family members with homologous sequences. We tested TAPAS with SRM-based MS approaches, but we anticipate that this splice variant quantification strategy can be applied to other targeted MS approaches, such as multiplexed MS/MS (MSX) and Sequential Window Acquisition of all THeoretical Mass Spectra (SWATH), which would enable numerous splice variants to be quantified in a single experiment.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Overall workflow of splice variants quantifications and the components of TAPAS</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> METHODS AND IMPLEMENTATION TAPAS has been implemented using Django, a web framework based on the Python programming language. With this software, the user will be able to retrieve the optimal experimental design and estimates for absolute protein abundances for a selected set of splicing variants of interest motivated from a specific biological problem (Fig. 1). Experimental design: TAPAS generates lists of unique and shared peptides that can be used in SIL-based targeted proteomics approaches to quantify selected alternative spliced variants. The peptides are specific for one or more input genes, but are not shared with other genes to avoid non-specificity. TAPAS uses two complementary algorithms, recursive set subtraction and Gaussian elimination to generate a minimal combination of peptides required for quantifying each splice variant or a group of splice variants (Supplementary Material). Furthermore, TAPAS provides additional information to the user such that suitable peptides can be chosen: TAPAS warns if a peptide has a possible posttranslational modification or an incomplete peptidase digestion, which could lead to an underestimate of the peptide quantity. Furthermore, it prioritizes peptides based on previous experimental evidence obtained by MS. To perform its function, TAPAS requires inputs for the query genes, the query databases (Swiss-Prot/TrEMBL) and/or the user-defined splice variant sequences. Absolute quantification of splice variants: TAPAS estimates the amounts of alternative splice variants by considering the abundance of peptides measured from SIL-based targeted MS *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">J.S.Yang et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Including shared peptides for estimating protein abundances: a significant improvement for quantitative proteomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Blein-Nicolas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2797" to="2801" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate mass spectrometry based protein quantification via shared peptides</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Dost</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="348" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical approach to protein quantification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Gerster</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="666" to="677" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative splicing: decoding an expansive regulatory layer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Irimia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Blencowe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="323" to="332" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational prediction of proteotypic peptides for quantitative proteomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Mallick</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative pre-mRNA splicing and proteome expansion in metazoans</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Maniatis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Tasic</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">418</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="236" to="243" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deep proteome and transcriptome mapping of a human cancer cell line</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Nagaraj</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">548</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interpretation of shotgun proteomic data: the protein inference problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Nesvizhskii</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Aebersold</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1419" to="1440" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expansion of the eukaryotic proteome by alternative splicing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Nilsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Graveley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">463</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="463" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deep surveying of alternative splicing complexity in the human transcriptome by high-throughput sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Pan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1413" to="1415" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What does it mean to identify a protein in proteomics?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Rappsilber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Mann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Biochem. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MATS: a bayesian framework for flexible detection of differential alternative splicing from RNA-seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Shen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>