
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:52+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis The code structure of the p53 DNA-binding domain and the prognosis of breast cancer patients</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Keiko</forename>
								<surname>Sato</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>Contact: keiko@is.noda.tus.ac.jp or hara@is.noda.tus.ac.jp</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tokyo University of Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>278-8510</postCode>
									<settlement>Noda</settlement>
									<region>Chiba</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Toshihide</forename>
								<surname>Hara</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tokyo University of Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>278-8510</postCode>
									<settlement>Noda</settlement>
									<region>Chiba</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Masanori</forename>
								<surname>Ohya</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tokyo University of Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>278-8510</postCode>
									<settlement>Noda</settlement>
									<region>Chiba</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<surname>Hancock</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tokyo University of Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>278-8510</postCode>
									<settlement>Noda</settlement>
									<region>Chiba</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis The code structure of the p53 DNA-binding domain and the prognosis of breast cancer patients</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2822" to="2825"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt497</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 1, 2013; revised on July 30, 2013; accepted on August 16, 2013</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The tumor-suppressor gene TP53 mutations are diverse in the central region encoding the DNA-binding domain. It has not been clear whether the prognostic significance for survival in breast cancer patients is the same for all types of mutations. Are there specific types of mutations carrying a worse prognosis? To understand the correlation between the mutations in the gene encoding the DNA-binding domain and the prognosis of breast cancer, we studied the code structure of the DNA-binding domain of breast cancer patients by using various artificial codes in information transmission. Results: We indicated that the prognostic significance of all types of mutations in the DNA-binding domain is not the same, and that the DNA-binding domain having a certain code structure is important for estimating the prognosis of breast cancer patients.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Breast cancer is the most common cancer among women. Approximately 1.38 million people around the world are diagnosed with breast cancer each year, and $458 000 people die from this disease, according to the report of International Agency for Research on Cancer. The tumor-suppressor gene TP53 is one of the most frequently mutated genes in human cancer including breast cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Makwane and Saxena, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Suzuki and Matsubara, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Takahashi et al., 2000</ref>). The protein p53 encoded by the TP53 gene is a DNA sequence-specific transcription factor involved in the induction of diverse effects such as cell cycle arrest, apoptosis, repair of DNA lesions, senescence and angiogenesis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Takahashi et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Varna et al., 2011</ref>). Mutant p53 not only loses the wild-type function but also gains new abilities to promote tumorigenesis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Brosh and Rotter, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Murphy and Rosen, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Suzuki and Matsubara, 2011</ref>). Most studies have reported that mutations in the TP53 gene confer a worse overall survival and disease-free survival in breast cancer cases, and this effect is independent of other risk factors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Olivier et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Olivier et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Petitjean et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Pharoah et al., 1999</ref>).<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Langerød et al. (2007)</ref>have reported that the breast cancer death rate for patients with TP53 mutations is four to five times higher than that for those without mutations. TP53 mutations are mostly missense point mutations and concentrate in the central region encoding the DNA-binding domain (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kucera et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Suzuki and Matsubara, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Varna et al., 2011</ref>). Several studies have shown that mutations in the DNA-binding domain including L2 and L3 loops are associated with poor disease-free and overall survival (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Gentile et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Lothe et al., 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Young et al., 2007</ref>). On the other hand,<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Powell et al. (2000)</ref>have indicated that the survival of patients with mutations in the L2/L3 loops is not significantly different to the survival of patients with mutations outside of these domains, and<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Caleffi et al. (1994)</ref>have indicated that there is no significant difference in the overall survival rates between patients with mutant and wild-type p53 tumors. There are many patterns for p53 mutations in breast cancer. Various mutations in the TP53 gene cause single amino acid changes at many different positions. It is not clear whether the prognostic significance is the same for all types of mutations. Are there specific types of mutations carrying a worse prognosis? We need further work to understand the significance concerning the different mutations in breast cancer prognosis. In information theory, the concept of information has two aspects, one of which expresses the amount of complexity of the whole system such as a sequence itself, and the other concerns the structure of the system such as the rule stored in the order of sequence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ingarden et al., 1997</ref>). Concerning the first concept of information, according to Shannon's philosophy, if a system has larger complexity, then the system carries larger information, expressed through the entropy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ohya and Sato, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Ohya and Volovich, 2011</ref>). Here, the idea of Kolmogorov, the complexity of sequences, might be used (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Chaitin, 1969</ref>). Concerning the second concept of information, one looks for the structure of sequences (in genome). For this purpose, coding theory might be useful for the sequence analysis. The code structure of TP53 gene is studied by applying artificial codes in coding theory. The aim of this study is to investigate whether the gene encoding the DNA-binding domain in breast cancer case can be characterized by the artificial codes in information transmission, and to understand the correlation between various mutations in the gene and breast cancer prognosis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Patient characteristics</head><p>This study includes a total of 117 primary breast cancer patients with locally advanced (stage III) or distant metastasis (stage IV) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Berns et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bertheau et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Chrisanthar et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chrisanthar et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Geisler et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Geisler et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Langerød et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Powell et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Takahashi et al., 2000</ref>). Of these patients, 23 patients *To whom correspondence should be addressed. had missense point mutations affecting L2 loop (codons 163–195) of DNA-binding domain, 18 patients had missense point mutations affecting L3 loop (codons 236–251) of DNA-binding domain and 76 patients had wild-type. We selected patients with at least the following clinical data: TP53 mutation status affecting L2/L3 loops identified based on biopsy or surgery, TNM (tumor, node, metastasis) classification and/or histological stage and relapse-free survival and/or overall survival.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">The code structure of the p53 DNA-binding domain</head><p>Because the Galois Field GF(4) consists of four elements, 0, 1, and 2 such that 2 þ þ 1 ¼ 0, the four bases can be expressed in 24 combinations (four bases at each of four elements). We rewrite an important part of the nucleotide sequence encoding the DNA-binding domain by that of these four elements, and we make the error-correcting/detecting code by using an artificial code. The total length of such a code is multiples of three, and the length of the information symbols is multiples of two.4. Rewrite the encoded symbol sequence back into the encoded nucleotide sequence.</p><p>Artificial codes used for our study are linear codes, cyclic codes, BoseChaudhuri-Hocquenghem (BCH) codes, self-orthogonal codes and Iwadare codes. Let X be an amino acid sequence. We encoded the nucleotide sequence using a code C, and then we got the encoded amino acid sequences X C by the code C. If the code structure of the sequence X is the same as the structure of the code C, then X C ¼ X. Therefore, we compute the similarity between X and X C , denoted by rate of coincidence (RC) below, and we claim that this similarity becomes larger if the code structure of X is closer to that of C (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ohya and Sato, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Ohya and Volovich, 2011</ref>). The degree RC measuring the similarity between an artificial code of X C and the intrinsic code of amino acid sequence X before coding by C is defined by</p><formula>RC X, X C À Á ¼ 1 À a t 0 RC X, X C À Á 1 À Á ,</formula><p>where a is the numbers of sites for which two amino acid sequences differ from each other and t is the total number of sites compared. RC X, X C À Á is close to 0 for poorly related sequences, and RC X, X C À Á is close to 1 for<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>. Survival curves in the L2 loop. Kaplan–Meier survival curves in breast cancer patients stratified by mutation status in the L2 loop (left panels; A and C), and the RC values in the L2 loop (right panels; B and D) are shown: (A) Overall survival of patients with mutation in the L2 loop versus those with wild-type. (B) Overall survival of patients with the L2 loop that is close to the (33, 22)-BCH code versus those with the L2 loop that is far from that code. (C) Relapse-free survival of patients with mutation in the L2 loop versus those with wild-type. (D) Relapse free survival of patients with the L2 loop that is close to the (33, 22)-BCH code versus those with the L2 loop that is far from that code similar sequences. We call RC X, X C À Á the rate of coincidence (RC for short) for the code C. By calculating the RC for various codes, we can find a code structure characterizing the DNA-binding domain. If RC X, X C À Á for a code C is bigger than that of any other codes, then we can infer that the DNA-binding domain has the property that the code C owns.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A B C D</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Survival analysis</head><p>The Kaplan–Meier method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kaplan and Meier, 1958</ref>) was used to estimate the relapse-free survival rate and the overall survival rate of breast cancer patients with stage III or stage IV. The patients were stratified by mutation status in the L2 loop, the values of the RC in the L2 loop, mutation status in the L3 loop and the values of the RC in the L3 loop. The Wilcoxon test and the log-rank test were used to assess the difference between survival curves. For the two statistical tests, the P-values 50.05 were considered as statistically significant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>The Kaplan–Meier plots of breast cancer patients stratified by mutation status in the L2 loop are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1A</ref>and C. There was a statistically significant difference in the overall survival between the breast cancer patients with mutation in the L2 loop and those with wild-type (5-year overall survival: 44.9 versus 84.6%,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1A</ref>). In contrast, there was no significant difference in recurrence-free survival between two cases mentioned previously (P ¼ 0.137 for the Wilcoxon test, P ¼ 0.06 for the log-rank test,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1C</ref>). The Kaplan–Meier plots of breast cancer patients stratified by the RC values in the L2 loop are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1B</ref>and D. The overall survival and recurrence-free survival were statistically significantly worse in patients with the L2 loop that is close to the (33, 22)-BCH code than patients with the L2 loop that is far from that code (5-year overall survival: 0 versus 80.3%,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1B</ref>; 5-year recurrence-free survival: 0 versus 41.3%,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1D</ref>). In this analysis, we made a correspondence between the four bases and the elements in GF(4) as A ! 0, C ! 1, G ! a and T ! a 2 .<ref type="bibr">The</ref>A and C), and the RC values in the L3 loop (right panels; B and D) are shown: (A) Overall survival of patients with mutation in the L3 loop versus those with wild-type. (B) Overall survival of patients with the L3 loop that is close to the (24, 16)-BCH code versus those with the L3 loop that is far from that code. (C) Relapse-free survival of patients with mutation in the L3 loop versus those with wild-type. (D) Relapse-free survival of patients with the L3 loop that is close to the (6, 4)-BCH code versus those with the L3 loop that is far from that code loop are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>. There was no statistically significant difference in overall survival and recurrence-free survival between the patients with mutation in the L3 loop and those with wild-type (P ¼ 0.0574 for the log-rank test,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2A</ref>; P ¼ 0.277 for the Wilcoxon test, P ¼ 0.35 for the log-rank test,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2C</ref>). In contrast, there was a significant difference in the overall survival between the patients with the L3 loop that is close to the (24, 16)-BCH code and the patients with the L3 loop that is far from that code (5-year overall survival: 82 versus 25%,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2B</ref>). The generator polynomial of the (24, 16)-BCH code was GðxÞ ¼ x 8 þ x 6 þ x 4 þ x 2 þ , provided that the four bases were T! 0, G! 1, A! a and C! a 2. In addition, there was a statistically significant difference in the recurrence-free survival between the patients with the L3 loop that is close to the (6, 4)-BCH code and the patients with the L3 loop that is far from that code (5-year overall survival: 47.2 versus 25%,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2D</ref>). The generator polynomial of the (6, 4)BCH code was GðxÞ ¼ x 2 þ 1, provided that the four bases were G! 0, A! 1, T! a and C! a 2 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>The tumor-suppressor gene TP53 mutations are diverse in the central region encoding the DNA-binding domain. It has not been clear whether the prognostic significance for survival in breast cancer patients is the same for all types of mutations. Are there specific types of mutations carrying a worse prognosis? We studied the code structure of the DNA-binding domain of breast cancer patients by using various artificial codes in information transmission. In this study, we found a significant relation between the code structure of the DNA-binding domain and the breast cancer prognosis. Various types of mutations in the DNA-binding domain were classified by the code structure. We indicated that the prognostic significance of all types of mutations in the DNAbinding domain is not the same, and that the DNA-binding domain having a certain code structure is important for estimating the prognosis of breast cancer patients. We are convinced that the classification according to the code structure of the DNA-binding domain is useful for predicting patients who have a high mortality. Although novel TP53 mutations are continuously reported, the biological function is incompletely understood for many mutant p53 proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Berge et al., 2013</ref>). Our classification may be also useful for establishing effect of individual mutation on protein properties such as cell cycle arrest, apoptosis and senescence. Funding: Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research<ref type="bibr">[22740071]</ref>. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>1.</head><figDesc>Remove the third nucleotide of each codon, corresponding to the check symbol, and transform the remainder (information symbol) into the elements of the Galois Field. 2. Calculate the check symbols from the information symbols by means of the code rule. 3. Put the calculated check symbols into the corresponding position of the third nucleotide of codon.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Moreover, the breast cancer survival curves according to mutation status in the L3 loop and the RC values in the L3 A B C D</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Survival curves in the L3 loop. Kaplan–Meier survival curves in breast cancer patients stratified by mutation status in the L3 loop (left panels; A and C), and the RC values in the L3 loop (right panels; B and D) are shown: (A) Overall survival of patients with mutation in the L3 loop versus those with wild-type. (B) Overall survival of patients with the L3 loop that is close to the (24, 16)-BCH code versus those with the L3 loop that is far from that code. (C) Relapse-free survival of patients with mutation in the L3 loop versus those with wild-type. (D) Relapse-free survival of patients with the L3 loop that is close to the (6, 4)-BCH code versus those with the L3 loop that is far from that code</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">The code structure of the p53 DNA-binding domain at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">K.Sato et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional characterization of p53 mutants identified in breast cancers with suboptimal responses to anthracyclines or mitomycin</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Berge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1830" to="2790" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutations in residues of TP53 that directly contact DNA predict poor outcome in human primary breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Berns</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br. J. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1130" to="1136" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exquisite sensitivity of TP53 mutant and basal breast cancers to a dose-dense epirubicin-cyclophosphamide regimen</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Bertheau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">90</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When mutants gain new powers: news from the mutant p53 field</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Brosh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Rotter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="701" to="713" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">p53 gene mutations and steroid receptor status in breast cancer. Clinicopathologic correlations and prognostic assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Caleffi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2147" to="2156" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the length of programs for computing finite binary sequences: statistical considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Chaitin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CHEK2 mutations affecting kinase activity together with mutations in TP53 indicate a functional pathway associated with resistance to epirubicin in primary breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Chrisanthar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3062</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predictive and prognostic impact of TP53 mutations and MDM2 promoter genotype in primary breast cancer patients treated with epirubicin or paclitaxel</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Chrisanthar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19249</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of TP53 gene alterations and c-erbB-2 expression on the response to treatment with doxorubicin in locally advanced breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Geisler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2505" to="2512" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TP53 gene mutations predict the response to neoadjuvant treatment with 5-fluorouracil and mitomycin in locally advanced breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Geisler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5582" to="5588" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">p53 and survival in early onset breast cancer: analysis of gene mutations, loss of heterozygosity and protein accumulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Gentile</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1202" to="1207" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information Dynamics and Open Systems: Classical and Quantum Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Ingarden</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Dordrecht, The Netherlands</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonparametric estimation from incomplete observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Kaplan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Meier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="481" />
			<date type="published" when="1958" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prognostic significance of mutations in the p53 gene, particularly in the zinc-bindingdomains, in lymph node-and steroid receptor positive breast cancer patients. Austrian Breast Cancer Study Group</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Kucera</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="398" to="405" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TP53 mutation status and gene expression profiles are powerful prognostic markers of breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Langerød</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Breast Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">30</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deletion of 1p loci and microsatellite instability in colorectal polyps</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Lothe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Chromosomes Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Study of mutations in p53 tumour suppressor gene in human sporadic breast cancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Makwane</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Saxena</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Indian J. Clin. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutant p53 and genomic instability in a transgenic mouse model of breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Murphy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Rosen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncogene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1045" to="1051" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of information theory to study genome sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ohya</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Sato</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rep. Math. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="428" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mathematical Foundations of Quantum Information and Computation and Its Applications to Nano-and Bio-systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ohya</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Volovich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Dordrecht Heidelberg London ; New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The clinical value of somatic TP53 gene mutations in 1,794 patients with breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Olivier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1157" to="1167" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TP53 mutations in human cancers: origins, consequences, and clinical use</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Olivier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cold Spring Harb. Perspect. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TP53 mutations in human cancers: functional selection and impact on cancer prognosis and outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Petitjean</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncogene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2157" to="2165" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Somatic mutations in the p53 gene and prognosis in breast cancer: a meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Pharoah</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br. J. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1968" to="1973" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prognostic significance of mutations to different structural and functional regions of the p53 gene in breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Powell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent advances in p53 research and cancer treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Suzuki</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Matsubara</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biomed. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">978312</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinct prognostic values of p53 mutations and loss of estrogen receptor and their cumulative effect in primary breast cancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Takahashi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TP53 status and response to treatment in breast cancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Varna</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biomed. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutations in the DNA-binding codons of TP53, which are associated with decreased expression of TRAILreceptor-2, predict for poor survival in diffuse large B-cell lymphoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Young</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4396" to="4405" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>