
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Victor C11 library for protein representation and advanced manipulation</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Layla</forename>
								<surname>Hirsh</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biomedical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Padua</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Viale G. Colombo 3</addrLine>
									<postCode>35131</postCode>
									<settlement>Padova, Italy</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Pontificia Universidad Cató lica del Perú</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>San Miguel, 32 Lima</addrLine>
									<settlement>Perú</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Damiano</forename>
								<surname>Piovesan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biomedical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Padua</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Viale G. Colombo 3</addrLine>
									<postCode>35131</postCode>
									<settlement>Padova, Italy</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Manuel</forename>
								<surname>Giollo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biomedical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Padua</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Viale G. Colombo 3</addrLine>
									<postCode>35131</postCode>
									<settlement>Padova, Italy</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Information Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Padua</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Gradenigo 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>35121</postCode>
									<settlement>Padova</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Carlo</forename>
								<surname>Ferrari</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Information Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Padua</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Gradenigo 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>35121</postCode>
									<settlement>Padova</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Silvio</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C E</forename>
								<surname>Tosatto</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biomedical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Padua</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Viale G. Colombo 3</addrLine>
									<postCode>35131</postCode>
									<settlement>Padova, Italy</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Victor C11 library for protein representation and advanced manipulation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu773</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 19, 2014; revised on November 12, 2014; accepted on November 15, 2014</note>
					<note>Structural bioinformatics *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Contact: silvio.tosatto@unipd.it</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Protein sequence and structure representation and manipulation require dedicated software libraries to support methods of increasing complexity. Here, we describe the VIrtual Constrution TOol for pRoteins (Victor) Cþþ library, an open source platform dedicated to enabling inexperienced users to develop advanced tools and gathering contributions from the community. The provided application examples cover statistical energy potentials, profile–profile sequence alignments and ab initio loop modeling. Victor was used over the last 15 years in several publications and optimized for efficiency. It is provided as a GitHub repository with source files and unit tests, plus extensive online documentation, including a Wiki with help files and tutorials, examples and Doxygen documentation. Availability and implementation: The Cþþ library and online documentation, distributed under a GPL license are available from URL: http://protein.bio.unipd.it/victor/.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Structural bioinformatics methods require valid software libraries to represent and manipulate proteins efficiently. A number of widely used tools have been developed over the years to visualize proteins, e.g. Chimera (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Huang et al., 2014</ref>), Swiss-PdbViewer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Guex et al., 2009</ref>), MolIDE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Canutescu and Dunbrack, 2005</ref>) and VMD (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Humphrey et al., 1996</ref>) to name a few. Software libraries to manipulate proteins efficiently provide basic data representation and more advanced functionality with a different focus each. ESBTL (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Loriot et al., 2010</ref>) is mainly a Protein Data Bank (PDB) file parser. Biskit (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Grü nberg et al., 2007</ref>) additionally provides functionality for analysis of molecular dynamics simulations, while PTools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Saladin et al., 2009</ref>) focuses on molecular docking. OpenStructure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Biasini et al., 2010</ref>) places more attention on structure visualization and energy calculation. The latter is also supported by MSL (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Kulp et al., 2012</ref>) and Tinker (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Shi et al., 2013</ref>), while BALL (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Hildebrandt et al., 2010</ref>) in addition provides many advanced optimization algorithms.<ref type="bibr">Finally, StrBioLib (Chandonia, 2007</ref>) extracts sequence information from the protein structure and can be used as an interface to several available third-party tools. The critical assessment of techniques for protein structure prediction (CASP) series of experiments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Moult et al., 2014</ref>) demonstrates that structure prediction is increasingly becoming an engineering problem, where sophisticated methods have to be combined into extensive pipelines to provide state-of-the-art results (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Khoury et al., 2014</ref>). This has raised the barrier for entry into the field to a point where little new developments are possible, considering that most software libraries used in CASP are proprietary and not available as open source. Here, we propose the open-source VIrtual Constrution TOol for pRoteins (Victor) Cþþ library as a way to mitigate this problem. Victor is both an efficiently designed Cþþ library, able to manipulate protein structures with minimal computing time, and a collection of advanced components for protein sequence and structure manipulation. In particular, Victorprovides three sample applications: profile–profile sequence alignments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Wang and Dunbrack, 2004</ref>), statistical potentials (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Tosatto, 2005</ref>) and loop modelling (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Tosatto et al., 2002</ref>). Each of these three applications has been extensively described in the literature and is beyond the scope of this article. To the best of our knowledge, neither is available as an open-source Cþþ library yet. Profile–profile sequence alignments, in particular, have been widely used to improve target-template alignment in CASP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kryshtafovych et al., 2014</ref>). Victor is composed of &gt;60 000 lines of code and still expanding as it is used in the main author's teaching. It was developed inhouse over the last 15 years with the contribution of tens of developers and has reached a high level of maturity. Victor is released to provide a platform for contributions from the interested community. It provides extensive online material in the form of a Wiki with help files, tutorials, Doxygen documentation and a list of applications built using Victor can be accessed from the URL: http://protein.bio. unipd.it/victor/. The actual GitHub repository with Cþþ source files, a precompiled Ubuntu 64-bit version and unit tests are available from URL: https://github.com/BioComputingUP/Victor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Core library</head><p>The Victor Cþþ library currently contains two components for data representation and manipulation in separate directories: tools and Biopool. Tools provide basic manipulation methods, e.g. vector coordinates and file I/O. The core of the library is provided by the Biopool module, which defines all relevant data structures and algorithms to represent protein structures and manipulate them at a higher level of abstraction. The core data structures were carefully developed using design patterns (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Gamma et al., 1995</ref>), to provide an elegant and simple, yet powerful set of Cþþ classes. To allow the simple manipulation of protein structure through the more intuitive torsion angles, automating low-level geometric transformations, atom positions are coded both explicitly in 3D coordinates and as a position relative to the previous atom on a graph structure. This ensures consistency in the structure, while allowing the programmer to change the protein conformation rotating a torsion angle with a single line of code. Computational efficiency is guaranteed by updating the corresponding Cartesian coordinates only when necessary. All low-level geometrical transformations remain transparent to the user. Biopool is able to read properly all existing PDB files. Additional tools are also provided, such as protein secondary structure automatic assignment with an ad hoc implementation of the original DSSP algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kabsch and Sander, 1983</ref>). Extensive online documentation allows the interested programmer to learn how to manipulate the Biopool data structures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Applications</head><p>The Victor library provides three main examples to demonstrate the range of possible applications, which are included as separate subdirectories: Energy, Align and Lobo. Extensive documentation, including detailed tutorials, is provided online to allow users to become familiar with the software and build on existing knowledge. Energy contains everything that is necessary to develop statistical potentials to evaluate protein structures. Two sample implementations of published methods included in the library, FRST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Tosatto, 2005</ref>) and TAP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Tosatto and Battistutta, 2007</ref>), can serve as a guide to develop additional methods. Both are contained in the Energy subdirectory and functioning code is provided both to generate the statistical potential itself as well as to use it on a PDB structure to calculate the potential energy. The interested user can thus easily develop additional statistical potentials. The Align directory provides basic sequence alignment algorithms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Tosatto et al., 2006</ref>) augmented with secondary structure element (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Fontana et al., 2005</ref>). Many different profile–profile scoring schemes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Wang and Dunbrack, 2004</ref>) are implemented, which have been extensively used in CASP to detect remotely homologous protein sequences. Code is also provided for variable gap penalties with additional terms for sequence to structure fit (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Madhusudhan et al., 2006</ref>) and advanced weighting schemes such as PSIC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Sunyaev et al., 1999</ref>). Alignment parameters have been extensively benchmarked and the default parameters are optimized for performance. Last but not least, the Lobo directory contains an application of ab initio loop modeling using a fast divide and conquer algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Tosatto et al., 2002</ref>). This makes extensive use of the functions to construct novel amino acids and manipulate the protein structure locally, providing sample code for more complex structural manipulations. It can easily be extended for ab initio structure prediction in combination with statistical potentials as target function.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusions</head><p>The Victor library is an open source project devoted to the structural bioinformatics community. It provides a unique combination of methods for sequence and structure manipulation. Expansion is ongoing both through in-house development, as it is the basis for several more recent publications [e.g. RING (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Martin et al., 2011</ref>) and NeEMO (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Giollo et al., 2014)]</ref>, and as part of the author's teaching activities, which include software development projects for students. We hope that the Victor library will contribute towards an easier development of advanced methods for structural bioinformatics.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 1138 Bioinformatics, 31(7), 2015, 1138–1140 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btu773 Advance Access Publication Date: 19 November 2014 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>To the Francesco Lovo, Enrico Negri and several students for contributing to the Victor project over the years as well as to members of the BioComputing UP lab for insightful discussions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This project was funded by FIRB Futuro in Ricerca grant RBFR08ZSXY and University of Padua grant CPDR123473 to S.T.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict</head><p>of interest: none declared.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OpenStructure: a flexible software framework for computational structural biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Biasini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2626" to="2628" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MollDE: a homology modeling framework you can click with</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Canutescu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Dunbrack</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2914" to="2916" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">StrBioLib: a Java library for development of custom computational structural biology applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J.-M</forename>
				<surname>Chandonia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2018" to="2020" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The SSEA server for protein secondary structure alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Fontana</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="393" to="395" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Design Patterns: Elements of Reusable ObjectOriented Software</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Gamma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NeEMO: a method using residue interaction networks to improve prediction of protein stability upon mutation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Giollo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. 4</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biskit—a software platform for structural bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Grü Nberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="769" to="770" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automated comparative protein structure modeling with SWISS-MODEL and Swiss-PdbViewer: a historical perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Guex</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electrophoresis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="162" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BALL—biochemical algorithms library 1.3</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Hildebrandt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">531</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhancing UCSF Chimera through web services</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="478" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">VMD: visual molecular dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Humphrey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dictionary of protein secondary structure: pattern recognition of hydrogen-bonded and geometrical features</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Kabsch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Sander</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biopolymers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2577" to="2637" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WeFold: a coopetition for protein structure prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Khoury</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1850" to="1868" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CASP10 results compared to those of previous CASP experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Kryshtafovych</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="164" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural informatics, modeling, and design with an open-source molecular software Library (MSL)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Kulp</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1645" to="1661" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ESBTL: efficient PDB parser and data structure for the structural and geometric analysis of biological macromolecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Loriot</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1127" to="1128" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variable gap penalty for protein sequencestructure alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Madhusudhan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Eng. Des. Sel</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RING: networking interacting residues, evolutionary information and energetics in protein structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J M</forename>
				<surname>Martin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Critical assessment of methods of protein structure prediction (CASP)—round x</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Moult</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. 2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PTools: an opensource molecular docking library</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Saladin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The polarizable atomic multipole-based AMOEBA force field for proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Shi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Theory Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4046" to="4063" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PSIC: profile extraction from sequence alignments with position-specific counts of independent observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Sunyaev</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="387" to="394" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A divide and conquer approach to fast loop modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C E</forename>
				<surname>Tosatto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="286" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Align: a Cþþ class library and web server for rapid sequence alignment prototyping</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C E</forename>
				<surname>Tosatto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Drug Discov. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The victor/FRST function for model quality estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C E</forename>
				<surname>Tosatto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1316" to="1327" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TAP score: torsion angle propensity normalization applied to local protein structure evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C E</forename>
				<surname>Tosatto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Battistutta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">155</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scoring profile-to-profile sequence alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Dunbrack</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1612" to="1626" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>