
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:43+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression Topologically inferring risk-active pathways toward precise cancer classification by directed random walk</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wei</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150081</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Heilongjiang Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150050</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chunquan</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yanjun</forename>
								<surname>Xu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150081</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Haixiu</forename>
								<surname>Yang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150081</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Qianlan</forename>
								<surname>Yao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150081</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Junwei</forename>
								<surname>Han</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150081</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Desi</forename>
								<surname>Shang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150081</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chunlong</forename>
								<surname>Zhang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150081</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Fei</forename>
								<surname>Su</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150081</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xiaoxi</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Health Management Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Nanfang Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Southern Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510515</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yun</forename>
								<surname>Xiao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150081</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Fan</forename>
								<surname>Zhang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150081</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Meng</forename>
								<surname>Dai</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150081</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Health Management Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Nanfang Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Southern Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510515</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xia</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>lixia@hrbmu.edu.cn or dm42298@126.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150081</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression Topologically inferring risk-active pathways toward precise cancer classification by directed random walk</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2169" to="2177"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt373</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 4, 2013; revised on May 29, 2013; accepted on June 23, 2013</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Ziv Bar-Joseph Availability: DRW is freely available at http://210.46.85.180:8080/ DRWPClass/ Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The accurate prediction of disease status is a central challenge in clinical cancer research. Microarray-based gene bio-markers have been identified to predict outcome and outperform traditional clinical parameters. However, the robustness of the individual gene biomarkers is questioned because of their little reproducibility between different cohorts of patients. Substantial progress in treatment requires advances in methods to identify robust biomarkers. Several methods incorporating pathway information have been proposed to identify robust pathway markers and build classifiers at the level of functional categories rather than of individual genes. However, current methods consider the pathways as simple gene sets but ignore the pathway topological information, which is essential to infer a more robust pathway activity. Results: Here, we propose a directed random walk (DRW)-based method to infer the pathway activity. DRW evaluates the topological importance of each gene by capturing the structure information embedded in the directed pathway network. The strategy of weighting genes by their topological importance greatly improved the reprodu-cibility of pathway activities. Experiments on 18 cancer datasets showed that the proposed method yielded a more accurate and robust overall performance compared with several existing gene-based and pathway-based classification methods. The resulting risk-active pathways are more reliable in guiding therapeutic selection and the development of pathway-specific therapeutic strategies.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>One important challenge in clinical cancer research is the accurate prediction of disease states and responses to treatment, which guide the choice of optimal therapy for the patients. Microarraybased gene biomarkers have been identified to predict outcome and outperformed traditional clinical parameters (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Perez-Diez et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">van 't Veer et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Wang et al., 2005</ref>). However, the reproducibility of the individual gene biomarkers has been challenged (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Dupuy and Simon, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Ein-Dor et al., 2006</ref>). The prediction performance of the gene signatures discovered in one dataset often decreased drastically in an independent dataset for the same disease phenotype. The main cause of this discrepancy may include the cellular heterogeneity within tissues, the inherent genetic heterogeneity across patients and the measurement error in microarray platforms. Moreover, the small number of samples that are available to build a classifier makes the problem more difficult (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Ein-Dor et al., 2006</ref>). To address this problem, several methods have been proposed to find more robust biomarkers at the level of functional categories rather than of individual genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Guo et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kim et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lee et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Su et al., 2009</ref>). Because the gene products are well known to function coordinately by way of a functional module or signaling cascade, the high-level perturbed functional modules may be more consistent than individual genes. Thus, integrating the expressions of function-related genes and extracting classification features at the functional level may produce more reproducible biomarkers. The biomarkers at the functional level could alleviate the impact of heterogeneity across the tissues or samples and provide a better biological interpretation of the relationships between the disease and canonical pathways such as the Gene Ontology (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ashburner et al., 2000</ref>) and KEGG databases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kanehisa and Goto, 2000</ref>). A number of feature extraction methods have been used to integrate the expression value of the member genes in canonical pathways.<ref type="bibr">Guo et al.</ref>used the mean and median of the expression values of member genes to infer the pathway activity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Guo et al., 2005</ref>).<ref type="bibr">Bild et al.</ref>used the first principal component of the expression values of the member genes to infer the pathway activity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bild et al., 2006</ref>). In contrast, Lee et al. inferred the pathway activity by using only a subset of genes [conditionresponsive genes (<ref type="bibr">CORGs)]</ref>, whose combined expression delivers optimal discriminative power for the disease phenotype (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lee et al., 2008</ref>). Other approaches estimated the pathway activity based on probabilistic inference (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Efroni et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Su et al., 2009</ref>). The existing methods successfully incorporated the *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>y</head><p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. pathway information into the disease classification procedure and achieved better classification performance. However, all these methods used the pathways as simple gene sets and treated all genes in the pathway equally but ignored the structure information embedded in the pathway network. It has been reported that the 'hub' genes with high connectivity are usually critical to the functionality of the whole pathway (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Carter et al., 2004</ref>). The perturbation on a 'hub' gene may impact the pathway more greatly than that on a gene with little topological importance. However, the 'hub' genes tend to have low levels of change in gene expression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Lu et al., 2007</ref>). Their subtle but consistent changes could be easily overshadowed by differential non-hub genes, whose changes may be unstable across the samples. Thus, up-weighting the hub genes and downweighting the non-hub genes according to their topological importance may contribute to a more robust pathway activity. A few methods have been proposed to mine the topological information of the network. Gao et al. designed a pathway score based on all connected gene pairs for the pathway enrichment analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gao and Wang, 2007</ref>). Hung et al. improved the pathway enrichment analysis by weighting each gene based on the closest correlated neighbor genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Hung et al., 2010</ref>). Recently, undirected random walk was used to mine the topological information of the protein–protein interaction network and showed superiority in prioritizing candidate disease genes or pathways (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Can et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kohler et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Li and Patra, 2010</ref>). However, these topological information mining methods consider the edges in the network as undirected; thus, they may lose some important information when used in the directed pathway networks, such as the position of the genes and the type of interactions, which are essential to measure the topological importance of the genes. For example, the genes located in the upstream are more important because they influence other genes downstream, such as the insulin receptor in the insulin signaling pathway, whose inactivation may shut off the entire pathway. To capture the topological properties in directed network and infer a more robust pathway activity, a flexible pathway topological information mining method is required. In this work, we propose a directed random walk (DRW)based method (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>) to mine the topological information and infer the pathway activity. DRW is performed on a merged global pathway network and attempts to evaluate the topological importance of each gene according to all the aforementioned topological properties. The strategy of weighting genes by their topological importance effectively enhances the reproducibility of the pathway activities. We apply the DRW method to the classification of six types of cancers and show that it can produce higher accuracy and stronger robustness compared with several existing pathway-based approaches, both within single datasets and in different independent datasets. The resulting risk-active pathways are more reliable in predicting clinical outcome and guiding therapeutic selection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Datasets</head><p>A total of 18 microarray datasets were used in this study. All were downloaded from the GEO database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Edgar et al., 2002</ref>). Our analysis focused on eight datasets. They are GSE10072 for lung cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Landi et al., 2008</ref>), GSE13911 for stomach cancer (D'<ref type="bibr">Errico et al., 2009</ref>), GSE17856 for liver cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Tsuchiya et al., 2010</ref>), GSE5364 for thyroid cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Yu et al., 2008</ref>), GSE15641 and GSE17895 for kidney cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dalgliesh et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Jones et al., 2005</ref>) and GSE3494 and GSE1456 for breast cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Miller et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Pawitan et al., 2005</ref>). For breast cancer, patients who died because of breast cancer within 5 years were defined as the 'poor' prognostic group, and the remaining patients were defined as the 'good' prognostic group (patients with a survival time 55 years without any reported event were excluded.). Each dataset contains gene expression profiles for !22 tumor/poor samples and !16 normal/good samples. To evaluate classification performance on independent dataset, we collected 10 additional datasets for validation (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). The pathway information was obtained from the KEGG database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kanehisa and Goto, 2000</ref>). This collection contains 150 metabolic and 150 non-metabolic pathways. The interactions in KEGG were manually drawn by summarizing experimental evidence in published literature.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Constructing the global-directed pathway graph</head><p>We first converted each KEGG pathway into a directed graph using the SubpathwayMiner software package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Li et al., 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Li et al., , 2013</ref>). Then the 300 graphs were merged into a global-directed pathway graph, which covers 4113 nodes and 40 875 directed edges. Each node in the graph represents a gene, and each directed edge represents how genes interact and regulate each other. The direction of the edge is derived from the type of interaction between two genes, which is available from the KEGG. For example, if gene A activates (inhibits) gene B, then A points to B. The random walk (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Lovasz, 1996</ref>) on the pathway graph is similar to the] is the expression value vector (i.e. pathway activity) of pathway P j across all samples. The diagram on the right is the detailed illustration of DRWbased pathway activity inference. The global pathway network is constructed on 150 metabolic and 150 non-metabolic pathways. A virtual ground node is added to balance the weights of the genes in the network. W 0 is the initial weights of the genes. W 1 is the output weight vector. The inference of the pathway activity of pathway P j is presented as an example. The edge direction in the original pathway network P j is reversed when we merge the pathway P j into the global pathway network. The pathway activity a(P j ) of P j is the integrated expression value vector of the significantly differentially expressed genes in the pathway weighting by W 1 PageRank algorithm used by the Google search engine (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Brin and Page, 1998</ref>), but the direction of the random walk is opposite (a web page is important if other pages point to it, whereas a gene is important if it influences other genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Draghici et al., 2007</ref>). Thus, we reversed the direction of all edges on the global pathway graph (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). To perform random walk, two problems need to be solved. First, there are 938 dangling nodes (0 out-degree, such as the most upstream nodes in the pathway) on the directed pathway graph. The dangling nodes will absorb the weight of other nodes but never distribute their weight back to the graph. Besides, there are 396 nodes with 0 in-degree; they do not receive any weights from other nodes. This may be unsatisfactory from a biological perspective. To alleviate this problem, we introduced a virtual ground node connected to every node through bidirectional edges (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). Thus, the graph became strongly connected and consisted of 4113 þ 1 nodes and 40 875 þ 2 Â 4113 edges. We denoted the extended graph as G ¼ (V, E), where V is the set of nodes and E is the set of edges.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">DRW on the global-directed pathway graph</head><p>The DRW with restart stimulates a random walker that starts on a source node s (or a set of source nodes simultaneously). At every time step, the walker transitions from its current node to a randomly selected neighbor (based on edge weights) or goes back to source node s with probability r. Formally, the DRW with restart is defined as</p><formula>W tþ1 ¼ ð1 À rÞM T W t þ rW 0 ð1Þ</formula><p>where W t is a vector in which the i-th element holds the probability of being at node i at time step t, and M is the row-normalized adjacency matrix of the graph G. To start the random walk, the initial probability vector W 0 was constructed by assigning to each node (except for the ground node, whose initial probability was 0) its absolute t-test score, and normalized to a unit vector. The restart probability r was set as 0.7. W t converges to a unique steady state in the presence of the ground node (<ref type="bibr">Luët al., 2011</ref>). This was obtained by performing the iteration until the L 1-norm between W t and W tþ1 510-10. At the steady state, we evenly distributed the probability of the ground node back to all other nodes and obtained the final probability vector W 1. W 1 provided a measure of the topological importance of the genes in the global pathway graph and was used as the weight vector of genes at the step of pathway activity inference. Because we used the t-test scores as the initial probabilities, the magnitude of the t-test scores also contributed to weight adjustments. Thus, genes which are both topologically important and significantly differentially expressed will obtain higher weights.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Pathway activity inference</head><p>For each pathway, we calculated the t-test statistics of all member genes. Only those genes that are significantly differentially expressed (P50.05, see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S2</ref>for the corresponding fdr, Benjamin correction) are selected in constructing the pathway activity. Consider a pathway P j that contains n j differential genes {g 1 , g 2 ,. .. , g nj } after those genes that were not significantly differentially expressed in the training set have been removed. The pathway activity a T (P j ) of the pathway P j in the training dataset is calculated as follows:</p><formula>a T ðP j Þ ¼ X nj i¼1 W 1 ðg i ÞÁsgnðt score ðg i ÞÞ Á z T ðg i Þ ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi X nj i¼1 W 1 ðg i Þ ð Þ 2 q ð2Þ</formula><p>where W 1 (g i ) is the weight of gene g i , t score (g i ) is the t statistics of gene g i from a two-tailed t-test on expression values between two phenotypes, z T (g i ) is the normalized expression value vector of g i across the samples in the training dataset and sgn() is the sign function that returns À1 for negative numbers and þ1 for positive numbers. The pathway activity a V (P j ) of the pathway P j in the test dataset is given by</p><formula>a V ðP j Þ ¼ X nj i¼1 W 1 ðg i ÞÁsgnðt score ðg i ÞÞ Á z V ðg i Þ ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi X nj i¼1 W 1 ðg i Þ ð Þ 2 q</formula><p>where z V (g i ) is the normalized expression value vector of g i across the samples in the test dataset.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Reproducibility power</head><p>Yang et al. proposed that a pathway activity is reproducible if it provides similar discriminative power on the training-test pair datasets (<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Yang et al., 2012</ref>). The reproducibility power is given by</p><formula>C score ðNÞ ¼ 1 N X N i¼1 t score ðP i T Þ Á t score ðP i V Þ ð 3Þ</formula><p>where t score (P) is the t statistics of P from a two-tailed t-test on pathway activities between two phenotypes, P i T is the i-th pathway activity in descending order (ranked by absolute t-scores) in the training dataset, P i V is its corresponding pathway activity in the test dataset and N is the number of selected pathways. The reproducibility power reflects the discriminative power and the robustness of the pathway activity. For within-dataset experiments, the samples in a dataset were randomly divided into five subsets of equal size. Four of these subsets were used as the training dataset, whereas the remaining subset was used as the test set. Each subset was used in turn as the test set to evaluate the reproducibility. For unbiased evaluation, we repeated these experiments for 100 random partitions for the entire dataset. The averaged C score over 500 experiments was reported as the overall reproducibility performance. For cross-dataset experiments, the whole first dataset was used as the training dataset, and the second independent dataset was used as the test set.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">Classification evaluation</head><p>For within-dataset experiments, we randomly divided the dataset so that four-fifths of the samples were used as the training set, and the remaining one-fifth was used as the test set (5-fold cross-validation). To select the best pathway marker set for classification, we further split the training set into three equal-sized subsets. Two subsets were used as the marker evaluation dataset to build the classifier and rank the pathway markers, and one subset was used as the feature selection dataset for assessing which pathway marker set produced the best classification performance. To build the classifier, we calculated the t-test statistics of the pathway activities on the marker evaluation dataset and ranked the pathways by their P-values in increasing order. The top 50 pathways were used as the candidate features to build the logistic regression model (or classifiers based on other classification algorithms). We first constructed the classifier with the pathway ranked first. Then the pathways were added sequentially to train the logistic regression model, and the performance of the classifier was measured by evaluating its area under the receiver operating characteristics curve (AUC) on the feature selection dataset. The added pathway marker was kept in the feature set if the AUC increased and was removed otherwise. We repeated the above process for the top 50 pathway markers to optimize the classifier and obtained the best feature set. The performance of the optimized classifier was evaluated on the test set by using the pathway markers in the best feature set. Each subset of the training set was used in turn as feature selection dataset to optimize the classifier. Therefore, each training set generated three optimized classifiers and generated three AUCs on the corresponding test set. Each of the five subsets in the whole dataset was evaluated in turn as the test set. Thus, one partition generated 15 AUCs. For unbiased evaluation and to estimate the variation of the AUC, we repeated the above process 100 times. The mean AUC across 1500 classifiers was reported as the overall performance of the classification method. For cross-dataset experiments, the whole first dataset was used as the training set, and the second independent dataset was used as the test set. The first dataset was divided into five subsets of equal size. Four subsets were used as the marker evaluation dataset to train the classifier, and one subset was used as the feature selection dataset to optimize the constructed classifier and select the best feature set. We repeated this experiment by using each subset as the feature selection dataset in turn and evaluated the optimized classifier on the test set. One hundred random partitions of the training set were generated for building the classifier and feature selection. The averaged AUC on the test set over 500 classifiers was reported as the final performance measure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7">Other classification methods</head><p>For comparison with other pathway activity inference methods, we implemented four pathway-based classification methods, namely, the Mean and Median methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Guo et al., 2005</ref>), the Principle Component Analysis (PCA) method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bild et al., 2006</ref>) and the Pathway Activity inference using Condition-responsive genes (PAC) method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lee et al., 2008</ref>). The Mean and Median methods use the mean and median of the expression values of the member genes to infer the pathway activity. The PCA method uses the first principal component of the expressions of the member genes to represent the pathway activity. The PAC method performs a greedy search to identify CORGs and infers the pathway activity by using only the CORGs. We also compared the performance of a traditional gene-based classifier that uses individual genes as features (the Genes method). Additionally, we compared our method with another excellent gene-based method Reweighted Recursive Feature Elimination (RRFE) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Johannes et al., 2010</ref>) implemented in pathClass (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Johannes et al., 2011</ref>). RRFE also incorporates topological information to improve AUC as well as the reproducibility and interpretability of selected gene features.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>illustrates the overview of the DRW-based pathway activity inference method. DRW mines the topological information embedded in the global pathway network and weights the genes according to their topological importance. With these weights, we integrate the expression values of the differential member genes to topologically infer the activity for each pathway. The genes that are topologically important receive more weights and contribute more to pathway activity. Finally, the DRW method translates the gene profiles into pathway profiles. We applied the DRW method on the lung cancer dataset and inferred 245 pathway activities of lung cancer. The top 50 active pathways (ranked by absolute t-scores) are able to classify samples with no misclassifications by using two-way hierarchical clustering (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2A</ref>). The top 50 active pathways of seven other datasets also show good discriminative ability (Supplementary Figs S1–S7). The heat map in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2B</ref>depicts the –log (P-value) of 200 common active pathways from a two-tailed t-test on pathway activities between the two phenotypes in eight cancer datasets. It provides a snapshot of the active levels of the pathways for each cancer. A few cancer-related pathways show high active levels in all datasets, such as apoptosis, p53 signaling pathway and acute myeloid leukemia. Compared with kidney cancer, the pathway activities of breast cancer are less discriminative and consistent between two breast cancer datasets, confirming the molecular heterogeneity of breast cancer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Inferring pathway activity by DRW</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Pathway activities show high reproducibility</head><p>A major challenge in pathway activity inference is to find active pathways that have stronger discriminative power and robustness. We used the reproducibility power [Equation (3), see '<ref type="bibr">Materials and Methods' section]</ref>to evaluate the pathway activities. Greater reproducibility power indicates more discriminative power and stronger robustness of the pathway activity. We computed the reproducibility power of the active pathways and ranked the pathways according to their reproducibility power. The mean reproducibility power of the top pathways of five pathway activity inference methods, namely, the Mean and Median methods, the PCA method, the PAC method and the DRW method, was compared (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S8</ref>). Besides, we also evaluated the reproducibility power of the top single gene markers, which were chosen from the 4113 genes covered by the 300 pathways used in this study. The DRW-based pathway activities exhibited the greatest power to discriminate between tumor and normal samples for all eight datasets. They showed $1.5-fold increased reproducibility over the PAC-based pathway activities, $2-fold over individual gene markers and $10-fold improvement over pathway activities inferred by other methods, such as the Mean, Median and PCA methods. Another important measurement of the robustness of pathway activities is their reproducibility between independent datasets. We further analyzed the kidney and breast cancer datasets because two separate cohorts of patients were available for each cancer. The DRW method again obtained the largest reproducibility on average (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S9</ref>), further indicating the robustness of the DRW-based pathway activities. The Genes method performed worst in the 'Kidney-Germany-4USA' case (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S9A</ref>). This is because the most discriminative markers in the Kidney-Germany dataset were not highly discriminative in the Kidney-USA dataset, indicating that the gene markers were not robust. The PAC method showed a similar phenomenon in that the pathway markers extracted from the 'Kidney-Germany' dataset were not highly discriminative in the 'Kidney-USA' dataset.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Risk-active pathways improve cancer classification</head><p>To test the usefulness of pathway activities in discriminating between different disease phenotypes, we performed classification on eight cancer datasets. For a fair and effective comparison with other methods, we carried out within-dataset experiments similar to those used in<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lee et al. (2008)</ref>to evaluate the classificationperformance (see 'Materials and Methods' section). To reduce the effect of sensitivity in feature selection when comparing different pathway-based methods, we also used the top 50 pathway activities ranked by their P-values in increasing order as the candidate features for feature selection. The classifier was built by using the selected pathway activities based on logistic regression. The Mean, Median, PAC and PCA methods followed the same procedure. The results of pathClass (RRFE) were obtained by a 10-times repeated 5-fold cross-validation by using R-package pathClass. For the Genes method, the top 50 discriminative gene markers were chosen as the candidate features to keep the maximum number of features identical across all classification methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Su et al., 2009</ref>).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref>presents a summary of the AUC of the cross-validation experiments (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S10A</ref>shows the classification accuracy). The proposed DRW method obtained AUCs (accuracies) of 0.9996 (95.58%), 0.9820 (94.34%), 0.9602 (93.06%), 0.9029 (87.33%), 0.9961 (97.55%), 0.9496 (94.87%), 0.6776 (73.36%) and 0.6926 (82.21%) for eight cancer datasets, respectively, indicating that the DRW-based pathway markers were quite competent in discriminating between different disease phenotypes. The AUCs (accuracies) of the DRW method on the eight datasets were significantly greater than those of the PAC, Mean, Median, PCA and Genes methods at the 5% significance level<ref type="bibr">[</ref><ref type="bibr">respectively]</ref>. This indicates that the DRW method outperforms other methods not only in AUC but also in accuracy. The pathClass method also yielded favorable performance, but was slightly inferior to the DRW method. Of these eight datasets, the AUC of the DRW method was larger compared with pathClass in five datasets. Although the Genes method reached the highest AUC for kidney cancer, it did not perform well in five datasets, especially the thyroid and breast cancer datasets, suggesting that the individual gene markers are less stable than pathway markers. To evaluate the generalization ability of the classifier, we carried out cross-dataset experiments on the kidney and breast cancer datasets. One dataset was used as the training set and another independent dataset as the test set (see 'Materials and Methods' section). To estimate the variation of the AUC of pathClass on independent dataset, we also randomly divided the whole training dataset into five subsets of equal size. Each subset was removed in turn, and the remaining four subsets were used as the training set to build the classifier. Each classifier was then used to predict the class of samples in the independent test set. The aforementioned process was repeated 10 times to obtain the average AUC and the standard deviation.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref>shows the results of the cross-dataset experiments (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.  S10B</ref>shows the classification accuracy). The DRW method again outperformed other pathway inference methods, especially in the two kidney cancer datasets, which were detected on different microarray platforms. The AUC of the proposed method improved by 36.28, 20.14, 17.65, 35.67 and 37.30% in the 'Kidney-Germany-4USA' case and 5.13, 32.76, 27.72, 62.28 and 7.81% in the 'Kidney-USA-4Germany' case compared with the PAC, Mean, Median, PCA and Genes method. The pathClass also obtained good performance in the two kidney cancer datasets. A potential reason may be that both the DRW method and pathClass incorporate topological information to build the classifier. However, pathClass was inferior to the DRW method on average. The AUC of the DRW method was larger compared with pathClass in three of four paired training-test datasets. Compared with within-dataset experiments, although the PAC, Mean, Median and Genes methods showed good performances on the two kidney cancer datasets, respectively (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>), their performances decreased drastically in the independent datasets. This is not surprising if we consider the reproducibility power presented in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S9A</ref>. The DRW method showed consistent performance and strong generalization ability, indicating that the DRW-based pathway activities are less sensitive to different cohorts of patients and microarray platforms and are more reliable in predicting clinical outcome in practice. To further demonstrate the superior performance of DRW on independent dataset, we collected 10 additional datasets and performed cross-dataset experiments. Of the 10 experiments, the AUCs of DRW ranked first in six experiments (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). They were significantly greater than those of the PAC, Mean, Median, Genes and DRW-NR methods at the 5% significance level (Wilcoxon signed-rank test: P ¼ 0.0137, 0.0020, 0.0020, 0.0195, 0.0020, respectively). pathClass also obtained good performance, but it was inferior to DRW in seven experiments. In all, our DRW method outperformed all other methods on average. In addition, to show that the superior performance of our DRW method was not dependent on the chosen classificationalgorithm, we repeated the within-dataset and the cross-dataset experiments by using three additional classification algorithms: naı¨venaı¨ve Bayes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">John and Langley, 1995</ref>), LibLINEAR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Fan et al., 2008</ref>) and LibSVM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Chang and Lin, 2011</ref>). The results exhibited a similar tendency to that in logistic regression (Supplementary Figs S11–S13).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Robustness of risk-active pathways</head><p>The classification experiments showed that the DRW-based pathway activities had reliable predictive accuracy. The discriminative pathway activities that are frequently selected to build the classifier may reveal new, robust risk-active pathways for cancers. We provided the 20 most frequently selected risk-active pathways in Supplementary Table S3 (the genes used to infer these pathway activities are provided in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table  S4</ref>). Among these pathways, the regulation of actin cytoskeleton is identified as a risk-active pathway in most cancer datasets (<ref type="figure">Table 2</ref>). It has been reported that key proteins involved in the actin cytoskeleton, including WASP family proteins, Arp2/ 3 complex, LIM-kinase, cofilin and cortactin, are overexpressed in many cancers, such as breast (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Wang et al., 2004</ref>) and liver (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chuma et al., 2004</ref>). These proteins coordinately regulate the formation of invasive protrusions in tumor cells and generate the driving force for cancer cell migration, invasion and metastasis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Yamaguchi and Condeelis, 2007</ref>). Focal adhesion was identified in four datasets. This pathway functions in the link between the actin cytoskeleton and the extracellular matrix (ECM). The ECM-receptor interaction is the most frequently selected active pathway in the lung cancer dataset (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S3</ref>), suggesting its important role in lung cancer, consistent with the study by<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Cho et al. (Cho et al., 2011</ref>). These related pathways are all identified as risk-active pathways in multiple cancers, indicating their coactive effect on cancers. Besides, several widely studied pathways that are associated with cancer are identified as risk-active pathways in multiple cancers, such as pathways in cancer, MAPK, Wnt and calcium signaling pathway. Deregulated calcium signaling has been shown in many cancers and is used as a sensitive therapeutic target in some cancers, such as melanoma, lung cancer, prostate cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Haverstick et al., 2000</ref>) and so forth. Pathways specific to the phenotype of classification were identified. For example, ErbB signaling pathway was reported in the Breast-Uppsala dataset. From early studies of the prognostic indicator and therapeutic target of breast cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Hayes and Thor, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Wright et al., 1989</ref>) until recent reports on this topic (<ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Weigel and Dowsett, 2010</ref>), there is an agreement that ErbB2, a critical component involved in ErbB signaling pathway, plays an important role in breast cancer prognosis and therapy. Furthermore, HER2/ c-erbB-2 is highly associated with progression and metastasis of breast cancer via promotion of cancer's important processes, such as tumor cell motility and apoptosis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Johnson et al., 2010</ref>). In addition, calcium signaling pathway is the most frequently selected in both the Kidney-Germany and Breast-Uppsala datasets (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S3</ref>), suggesting that it may be a new biomarker for kidney and breast cancer. Tight junction pathway was associated with the occurrence and progression of lung cancer. Global gene expression analysis showed that the specific patterns of cell junction were implicatedin non–small cell lung cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kuner et al., 2009</ref>). Moreover, the disruption of tight junction has also been shown to be associated with lung cancer cell apoptosis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Zhang et al., 2011</ref>) and to play an important role in cancer metastasis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Martin and Jiang, 2009</ref>). The detailed evidence from previous reports concerning these risk pathways in the classification of each disease is provided in Supplementary Table S5. These risk-active pathways could be useful in cancer diagnosis and could provide novel hypotheses in cancer therapy.</p><formula>pathwayˇ— — — ˇ ˇ ˇ ˇ Focal adhesioňadhesioň — ˇ ˇ — ˇ — — Tight junctioňjunctioň — ˇ ˇ — — ˇ — PPAR signaling pathwayˇˇ pathwayˇ pathwayˇˇ — — — ˇ ˇ — MAPK signaling pathway — — — ˇ ˇ — ˇ ˇ E n d o c y t o s i s — — — ˇ — ˇ ˇ ˇ ECM-receptor interactioňinteractioň — ˇ ˇ — — — — Wnt signaling pathway — ˇ — ˇ — — ˇ — Axon guidance — ˇ ˇ ˇ — — — — Adherens junctioňˇˇjunctioň junctioňˇ junctioňˇˇ — — — — — a</formula><p>Cancer datasets: 1-Lung; 2-Stomach; 3-Liver; 4-Thyroid; 5-Kidney-Germany; 6-Kidney-USA; 7-Breast-Uppsala; 8-Breast-Stockholm.<ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>. A snapshot of the perturbed nodes in the calcium signaling pathway. A node is considered as disrupted if one of its member genes was altered (at the 5% significance level). The nodes marked with a star are disrupted in both datasets, whereas the nodes marked with a triangle symbol are disrupted in only one dataset that have less topological importance (e.g. GPCR, PTK, FAK2, IP3 3K) are down-weighted. Interestingly, most inconsistent genes (shown in bold italics in Supplementary Table S6) are down-weighted. For example, AGTR1, PTK2B and ITPKA are differentially expressed only in the Kidney-Germany dataset, whereas ADORA2A and GNA15 are differentially expressed only in the Kidney-USA dataset. The aforementioned phenomenon is in line with Lu et al.'s study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Lu et al., 2007</ref>); i.e. the hub genes (such as those residing in CALM) tend to exhibit low but consistent changes in gene expression. The highly differentially expressed genes may contribute greatly to the Genes method. For example, the most differential gene AGTR1 (P ¼ 4.70E-33) may be selected as a gene marker based on the Kidney-Germany dataset. However, it has little discriminative power (P ¼ 7.58E02) in the Kidney-USA dataset. Obviously, it will reduce the averaged reproducibility of the gene markers (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S9A</ref>) and thus the classification performance (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref>) between independent datasets. The inconsistent genes may also impact the pathway-based methods, which treat all genes in the pathway equally. Considering the instability of these genes between independent cohorts of patients, it is not hard to speculate about the deteriorated performance of most methods in cross-dataset experiments. The DRW method, however, could alleviate the impact of inconsistent genes by reducing their weights; thus, it is more stable than other methods. This further indicates the importance of incorporating pathway topological information in building a robust cancer classifier. DRW captures the topological properties of genes, including the position of the genes in the pathway, how many genes interact with the given gene and the type of interactions between them. Because we use the absolute t-test score as the initial probability in DRW, a gene connected to other differentially expressed genes may receive more weight. Thus, the differential hub genes exhibit an increased effect on the classifier. We reran the DRW method by deleting the top 'hub' genes to evaluate this influence. The genes were sorted in decreasing order according to out-degree (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S8</ref>). The top 2, 4, 6 and 8% of genes were deleted in turn. The results demonstrated that the AUC obtained by deleting 'hub' genes decreased to a greater extent compared with deleting randomly selected genes of the same number (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S16</ref>), confirming the importance of 'hub' genes. We further investigated the functional roles of the 'hub' genes (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S9</ref>). Transcription factors and membrane receptors comprised a high proportion (24.3 þ 10.2 ¼ 34.5%) of genes with out-degree (51 $ 100). This indicates that the influences of differential transcription factors and membrane receptors are enhanced by DRW if they connect to other differential genes and potentially serve as a driver of pathway activity to a certain extent. To test the influence of the directionality on the classifier, we evaluated the classification performance of a modified DRW algorithm (DRW-NR) that does not reverse the direction of the edges in the KEGG pathways. DRW-NR is inferior to DRW in almost all datasets (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). Also, the average standard deviations of AUCs of DRW-NR are $65.8% larger than that of DRW, indicating that DRW is more robust in predicting disease states. There is one parameter in the DRW algorithm: the restart probability r<ref type="bibr">[Equation (1)]</ref>. To investigate the performance of the DRW method for varying restart probabilities, we set r at 0.1, 0.3, 0.5, 0.7 and 0.9 and performed cross-dataset experiments based on logistic regression. The AUC and classification accuracy did not change much with the change in the value of restart probability r (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S17</ref>), which was in line with the results of<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Can et al. (2005)</ref>and Li and Patra(2010). The performance of the DRW method depends on the coverage and quality of the human pathway information. A more complete pathway topology could help to clarify the roles that the genes played in the pathway and weight the genes more precisely. With the rapid development of human interaction databases, we believe that having more complete biological pathway information will enable a more accurate prediction of disease status and provide a better guide for patient treatment.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Overview of the DRW-based pathway activity inference method. The gene profiles are translated into pathway profiles based on the DRW method. Row i of the gene profiles [z(g i )] is the expression value vector of gene g i across all samples. Row j of the pathway profiles [a(P j )] is the expression value vector (i.e. pathway activity) of pathway P j across all samples. The diagram on the right is the detailed illustration of DRWbased pathway activity inference. The global pathway network is constructed on 150 metabolic and 150 non-metabolic pathways. A virtual ground node is added to balance the weights of the genes in the network. W 0 is the initial weights of the genes. W 1 is the output weight vector. The inference of the pathway activity of pathway P j is presented as an example. The edge direction in the original pathway network P j is reversed when we merge the pathway P j into the global pathway network. The pathway activity a(P j ) of P j is the integrated expression value vector of the significantly differentially expressed genes in the pathway weighting by W 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Active levels of the pathway activities. (A) The top 50 active pathways of the lung cancer samples are clustered by complete linkage hierarchical clustering. (B) Heat map depicts the active levels of 200 common active pathways for each cancer</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Wilcoxon signed-rank test: P ¼ 0.0391 (0.0234), 0.0078 (0.0078), 0.0078 (0.0078), 0.0078 (0.0078) and 0.0391 (0.0391),</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Classification performances within datasets using logistic regression</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Classification performances cross-datasets using logistic regression</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1.</figDesc><table>Classification performance comparison on independent datasets 
Cancer 
Training set-4Test set 

DRW 

PAC 

Mean 

Median 

Genes 

pathClass 

DRW-NR a 

Lung 

GSE10072-4GSE19804 

0.9788 AE 

0.0063 

0.9400 AE 

0.0387 

0.9360 AE 

0.0213 

0.9401 AE 

0.0157 

0.9600 AE 

0.0143 

0.9714 AE 

0.0058 

0.9752 AE 

0.0271 

Lung 

GSE10072-4GSE19188 

0.9722 AE 

0.0053 

0.9348 AE 

0.0192 

0.9240 AE 

0.0261 

0.9332 AE 

0.0150 

0.9541 AE 

0.0175 

0.9745 AE 

0.0039 

0.9717 AE 

0.0057 

Stomach 

GSE13911-4GSE19826 

0.9258 AE 

0.0392 

0.8887 AE 

0.0360 

0.7754 AE 

0.0499 

0.8226 AE 

0.0439 

0.8827 AE 

0.0537 

0.8907 AE 

0.0514 

0.8872 AE 

0.0783 

Stomach 

GSE13911-4GSE38940 

0.7250 AE 

0.0707 

0.5702 AE 

0.0522 

0.5773 AE 

0.0119 

0.5391 AE 

0.0324 

0.6552 AE 

0.0933 

0.6657 AE 

0.0814 

0.7210 AE 

0.0831 

Liver 

GSE17856-4GSE14520_1 b 

0.9691 AE 

0.0148 

0.9505 AE 

0.0342 

0.9311 AE 

0.0150 

0.9245 AE 

0.0151 

0.8862 AE 

0.0774 

0.9555 AE 

0.1487 

0.9609 AE 

0.0235 

Liver 

GSE17856-4GSE14520_2 

0.9646 AE 

0.0274 

0.9547 AE 

0.0279 

0.9264 AE 

0.0113 

0.9235 AE 

0.0192 

0.8808 AE 

0.0724 

0.9791 AE 

0.0112 

0.9579 AE 

0.0466 

Thyroid 

GSE5364-4GSE33630 

0.9480 AE 

0.0462 

0.7762 AE 

0.0883 

0.6993 AE 

0.0441 

0.6963 AE 

0.0686 

0.9031 AE 

0.0667 

0.9456 AE 

0.0643 

0.9032 AE 

0.0879 

Thyroid 

GSE5364-4GSE29265 

0.9063 AE 

0.0606 

0.7806 AE 

0.1119 

0.7556 AE 

0.0325 

0.7447 AE 

0.0452 

0.7820 AE 

0.0635 

0.9020 AE 

0.0553 

0.8890 AE 

0.1151 

Kidney 

GSE17895-4GSE36895 

0.9874 AE 

0.0559 

0.9705 AE 

0.0688 

0.9009 AE 

0.0594 

0.9500 AE 

0.0333 

0.9882 AE 

0.0470 

0.9799 AE 

0.0760 

0.9637 AE 

0.0999 

Breast 

GSE3494-4GSE7390 

0.6035 AE 

0.0480 

0.6330 AE 

0.0430 

0.5142 AE 

0.0312 

0.5538 AE 

0.0382 

0.6238 AE 

0.0353 

0.6373 AE 

0.0309 

0.5954 AE 

0.0537 

Shown are the average AUC and the standard deviation. The evaluation was performed according to cross-dataset 

experiments. The AUC shown in bold is the best AUC for the corresponding paired training-test dataset. The 

DRW method outperformed all other methods on average. 

a 

DRW-NR: DRW algorithm does not reverse the direction of the edges in the KEGG pathways. 

b 

Roessler et al. 
provided tumor and paired non-tumor samples of patients from two independent cohorts in GSE14520. We used them as two independent test sets. </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. Risk-active pathways identified in multiple cancers</figDesc><table>Active pathway 
1 a 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 

Regulation of actin cytoskeletoňˇˇcytoskeletoň cytoskeletoňˇ cytoskeletoňˇˇ 
ˇ 
— 
ˇ 
ˇ 
ˇ 
Pathways in cancer 
— 
ˇ 
ˇ 
ˇ 
— 
ˇ 
ˇ 
ˇ 
Calcium signaling pathwayˇ— pathwayˇ </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">W.Liu et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Topologically inferring risk pathways at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> DISCUSSION Identifying reproducible disease biomarkers is important for clinical utility in diagnostic and prognostic applications. Pathway markers have been proven to be more reproducible than individual gene markers and provide better biological interpretation at the functional level (Guo et al., 2005; Kim et al., 2012; Lee et al., 2008; Su et al., 2009). Pathway markers are becoming a useful tool for discriminating the disease status toward clinical prediction and treatment. In this context, we proposed a novel DRW method for inference of reproducible pathway activities and robust disease classification. We showed that DRW-based pathway activities are more discriminative and consistent than individual gene markers and pathway activities inferred by other methods. Based on their superior reproducibility, we used the DRW-based pathway activities to build the classifier and tested the classification performance on eight datasets. The results showed that the AUCs and classification accuracies of the DRW method were significantly higher than those of the Genes method and other pathway-based methods, both within single datasets and in different independent datasets. The reliable performance of the DRW-based pathway activities could be attributed to the strategy of weighting genes according to their topological importance. By weighting the genes, the DRW method could amplify the signals of the key genes, whose variations in their expression levels may greatly impact the pathway but weaken the differential signals of the genes, which only appear somewhere downstream or does not affect the given pathway as much. Thus, the effectiveness of the topologically important genes associated with the phenotype of interest is up-weighted, whereas other genes that have little topological importance are weakened even if they are significantly differentially expressed. Therefore, the DRW method may alleviate the noise due to the heterogeneity of samples or the technical measurements, leading to more reproducible pathway activities. We take the calcium signaling pathway, which is the most frequently selected in the Kidney-Germany dataset, as an example for analysis. Figure 5 provides a snapshot of the perturbed nodes in the calcium signaling pathway (Supplementary Figs S14 and S15 show the perturbed nodes in each dataset, respectively). The topologically important genes located at the center of the pathway, such as those residing in CALM, PLCg, PLCb and PLCd, are up-weighted (Supplementary Table S6 and S7 provides the full gene list). For example, the weights of CALM member genes (CALM1, CALM2, CALM3, CALML3 and CALML5) exceed those of genes residing in GPCR (AGTR1, CYSLTR2, TACR3 and LHCGR), although the P-values of the latter genes are much smaller (P58.96E-13). In contrast, the member genes of nodes</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank all the research staff for their contributions to this project.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oncogenic pathway signatures in human cancers as a guide to targeted therapies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Bild</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">439</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="353" to="357" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The anatomy of a large-scale hypertextual web search engine</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Brin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Netw. ISDN Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of protein–protein interaction networks using random walks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Can</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 5th International Workshop on Bioinformatics</title>
		<meeting>the 5th International Workshop on Bioinformatics<address><addrLine>Chicago, Illinois</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="68" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene co-expression network topology provides a framework for molecular characterization of cellular state</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Carter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2242" to="2250" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LIBSVM: a library for support vector machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Chang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Trans. Intell. Syst. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology of interstitial lung diseases: integration of mRNA and microRNA expression changes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Cho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Med. Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overexpression of cortactin is involved in motility and metastasis of hepatocellular carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Chuma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Hepatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="629" to="636" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide expression profile of sporadic gastric cancers with microsatellite instability</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Errico</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="461" to="469" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic sequencing of renal carcinoma reveals inactivation of histone modifying genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Dalgliesh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">463</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="360" to="363" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systems biology approach for pathway level analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Draghici</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1537" to="1545" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Critical review of published microarray studies for cancer outcome and guidelines on statistical analysis and reporting</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Dupuy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Simon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Natl Cancer Inst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array data repository</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Edgar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of key processes underlying cancer phenotypes using biologic pathway analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Efroni</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">425</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thousands of samples are needed to generate a robust gene list for predicting outcome in cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Ein-Dor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5923" to="5928" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LIBLINEAR: a library for large linear classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Fan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mach. Learn. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1871" to="1874" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TAPPA: topological analysis of pathway phenotype association</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Gao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3100" to="3102" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards precise classification of cancers based on robust gene functional expression profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Guo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">58</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inhibition of human prostate cancer proliferation in vitro and in a mouse model by a compound synthesized to block Ca2þ entry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Haverstick</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1002" to="1008" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">) c-erbB-2 in breast cancer: development of a clinically useful marker</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Hayes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Thor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semin. Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="245" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of functional modules that correlate with phenotypic difference: the influence of network topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Hung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integration of pathway knowledge into a reweighted recursive feature elimination approach for risk stratification of cancer patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Johannes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2136" to="2144" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">pathClass: an R-package for integration of pathway knowledge into support vector machines for biomarker discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Johannes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1442" to="1443" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating continuous distributions in Bayesian classifiers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>John</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Langley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Eleventh Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the Eleventh Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence<address><addrLine>Montreál, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="338" to="345" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HER2/ErbB2-induced breast cancer cell migration and invasion require p120 catenin activation of Rac1 and Cdc42</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Johnson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">285</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29491" to="29501" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene signatures of progression and metastasis in renal cell cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5730" to="5739" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KEGG: kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kanehisa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Goto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathway-based classification of cancer subtypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Direct</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Walking the interactome for prioritization of candidate disease genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kohler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="949" to="958" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global gene expression analysis reveals specific patterns of cell junctions in non-small cell lung cancer subtypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Kuner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lung Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leaders in social networks, the delicious case</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Lu¨</forename>
				<surname>Lu¨</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21202</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression signature of cigarette smoking and its role in lung adenocarcinoma development and survival</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Landi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1651</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inferring pathway activity toward precise disease classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SubpathwayMiner: a software package for flexible identification of pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">131</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subpathway-GM: identification of metabolic subpathways via joint power of interesting genes and metabolites and their topologies within pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integration of multiple data sources to prioritize candidate genes using discounted rating system</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Patra</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Random walks on graphs: a survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Lovasz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In: Combinatorics, Paul Erdos is Eighty</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Já nos Bolyai Mathematical Society</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="398" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<publisher>Já nos Bolyai Mathematical Society</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hubs in biological interaction networks exhibit low changes in expression in experimental asthma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Lu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">98</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Loss of tight junction barrier function and its role in cancer metastasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Martin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Jiang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1788" to="872" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An expression signature for p53 status in human breast cancer predicts mutation status, transcriptional effects, and patient survival</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Miller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13550" to="13555" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression profiling spares early breast cancer patients from adjuvant therapy: derived and validated in two population-based cohorts</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Pawitan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Breast Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="953" to="964" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microarrays for cancer diagnosis and classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Perez-Diez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Exp. Med. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">593</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate and reliable cancer classification based on probabilistic inference of pathway activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Su</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8161</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression in nontumoral liver tissue and recurrencefree survival in hepatitis C virus-positive hepatocellular carcinoma Gene expression profiling predicts clinical outcome of breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Tsuchiya</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cancer Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">415</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="530" to="536" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification and testing of a gene expression signature of invasive carcinoma cells within primary mammary tumors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8585" to="8594" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene-expression profiles to predict distant metastasis of lymph-node-negative primary breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">365</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="679" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Current and emerging biomarkers in breast cancer: prognosis and prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Weigel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Dowsett</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocr. Relat. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expression of c-erbB-2 oncoprotein: a prognostic indicator in human breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Wright</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2087" to="2090" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulation of the actin cytoskeleton in cancer cell migration and invasion</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Condeelis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1773" to="642" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Core module biomarker identification with network exploration for breast cancer metastasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A precisely regulated gene expression cassette potently modulates metastasis and survival in multiple solid cancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Yu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydroxycamptothecin-loaded Fe3O4 nanoparticles induce human lung cancer cell apoptosis through caspase-8 pathway activation and disrupt tight junctions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1216" to="1222" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>