
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:43+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">TopoGSA: network topological gene set analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Enrico</forename>
								<surname>Glaab</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nottingham University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Jubilee Campus</addrLine>
									<settlement>Nottingham</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anaïs</forename>
								<surname>Baudot</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Structural Biology and Biocomputing Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNIO</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>Madrid</region>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Natalio</forename>
								<surname>Krasnogor</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nottingham University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Jubilee Campus</addrLine>
									<settlement>Nottingham</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>avalencia@cnio.es</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Structural Biology and Biocomputing Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNIO</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>Madrid</region>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">TopoGSA: network topological gene set analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1271" to="1272"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq131</idno>
					<note type="submission">Systems biology Advance Access publication March 24, 2010 Received on January 15, 2010; revised on March 4, 2010; accepted on March 19, 2010</note>
					<note>[13:05 13/4/2010 Bioinformatics-btq131.tex] Page: 1271 1271–1272 Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Availability: Freely available at http://www.infobiotics.net/topogsa Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>TopoGSA (Topology-based Gene Set Analysis) is a web-application dedicated to the computation and visualization of network topological properties for gene and protein sets in molecular interaction networks. Different topological characteristics, such as the centrality of nodes in the network or their tendency to form clusters, can be computed and compared with those of known cellular pathways and processes.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Functional genomic experiments provide researchers with a wealth of information delineating gene sets of biological interest. To interpret these lists of genes, common steps in a functional gene set analysis include the search for enrichment patterns [for a review, see (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abatangelo et al., 2009)]</ref>, e.g. to identify significant signalling pathways or protein domains, and text mining in the literature [see review by (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Krallinger et al., 2008)]</ref>. Another approach for the functional interpretation of gene sets is the analysis of molecular interactions in which the genes or their corresponding proteins are involved, in particular protein–protein interactions. In this context, some existing bioinformatics tools already allow users to map genes onto networks of interacting or functionally associated molecules to identify related genes and proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Jenssen et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Snel et al., 2000</ref>). However, to the best of the authors' knowledge, so far these tools do not take into account topological properties in interaction networks to analyse and compare gene sets. In this article, we introduce TopoGSA (Topology-based Gene Set Analysis), a web-tool to visualize and compare network topological properties of gene or protein sets mapped onto interaction networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">WORKFLOW AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Analysis of network topological properties</head><p>An analysis begins with the upload of a list of gene or protein identifiers (Ensembl IDs, HGNC symbols, etc.; see webpage for a complete list of supported formats). Alternatively, a microarray dataset can be used as input and differentially expressed genes will be extracted automatically using methods from a previously published online microarray analysis tool * To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors.</p><p>[arraymining.net (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Glaab et al., 2009)]</ref>. Moreover, the user can add labels to the uploaded identifiers to compare different subsets of genes (e.g. 'up-regulated' versus 'down-regulated' genes). After submitting the list of identifiers, the application maps them onto an interaction network (Section 4), and computes topological properties for the entire network, the uploaded gene/protein set and random sets of matched sizes. The available network topological properties are:</p><p>@BULLET The degree of a node (gene or protein) is the average number of edges (interactions) incident to this node.</p><p>@BULLET The local clustering coefficient quantifies the probability that the neighbours of a node are connected (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Watts and Strogatz, 1998</ref>). @BULLET The shortest path length (SPL) for two nodes v i and v j in an undirected, unweighted network is defined as the minimum number of edges that have to be traversed to reach v j from v i. We use the SPL as a centrality measure, computing the average SPL from each node of interest to all other nodes in the network.</p><p>@BULLET The node betweenness B(v) of a node v can be calculated from the number of shortest paths σ st from nodes s to t going through v:</p><formula>B(v) = s =v,s =t,v =t∈V σ st (v) σ st (1)</formula><p>@BULLET The eigenvector centrality measures the importance of network nodes by applying a centrality definition, in which the score of each node reciprocally depends on the scores of its neighbours. More precisely, the centrality scores are given by the entries of the dominant eigenvector of the network adjacency matrix (see<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bonacich et al., 2001</ref>, for a detailed discussion of this property). Furthermore, user-defined 2D and 3D representations can be displayed for each individual gene/protein in the dataset and plotted data points are interlinked with relevant entries in an online annotation database.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Comparison with known gene sets</head><p>The analysis of network topological properties of only a single gene/protein set does not lend itself to direct functional interpretation. However, TopoGSA enables the user to compare the properties of a dataset of interest with a multitude of predefined datasets corresponding to known functional processes from public databases. For the human species, these include signalling pathways [KEGG (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kanehisa et al., 2006</ref>), BioCarta (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Nishimura, 2001)]</ref>, Gene Ontology [Biological Process, Molecular Function and Cellular Component (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Ashburner et al., 2000)]</ref>and InterPro protein domains (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Apweiler et al., 2001</ref>). Summaries of network topological properties are provided for all gene/protein sets, and in the 2D and 3D plots different colours distinguish different datasets. Users can identify pathways and processes similar to the uploaded dataset visually, based on the plots or based on a tabular ranking using a numerical score to quantify the similarity across all topological properties. The similarity score is obtained by computing five ranks for each pathway/process set according to the absolute differences between each of its five median topological properties and the corresponding value for the uploaded dataset. The sum of ranks across all topological properties is then computed and normalized to a range between 0 and 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.Glaab et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">EXAMPLE ANALYSIS</head><p>It has been shown that proteins encoded by genes that are known to be mutated in cancer have a higher average node degree in interaction networks than other proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Jonsson et al., 2006</ref>). This observation is confirmed by a TopoGSA analysis of the complete set of genes currently known to be mutated in cancer<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[Futreal et al. (2004)</ref>, http://www.sanger.ac.uk/genetics/CGP/<ref type="bibr">Census]</ref>. The cancer genes are involved in more than twice as many interactions, on average, than matched-size random subsets of network nodes (with a difference of &gt;15 SDs for 10 random simulations). Furthermore, the analysis with TopoGSA reveals that the cancer genes are closer together in the network (in terms of their average pairwise shortest path distances) than random gene sets of matched sizes and occupy more central positions in the interaction network (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1a</ref>for details). The 3D plot displaying node betweenness, degree and SPL reveals in particular the tumour suppressor p53's (TP53) outstanding network topological properties. When comparing the network topological properties of the cancer proteins with pathways from the KEGG database, considering each individual pathway as a gene set (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>), the cancer proteins appear to have network properties comparable to several KEGG cellular processes and environmental information processing pathways [according to the KEGG-BRITE pathway hierarchy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kanehisa et al., 2006</ref>),<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>, purple and brown], whereas they clearly differ from metabolism-related pathways (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>, yellow). Interestingly, although the network topological properties of cancer genes are in agreement with their role in promoting cell division and inhibiting cell death (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Vogelstein and Kinzler, 2004</ref>), they differ from those of most disease-related KEGG pathways (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>, green).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>The network analysis and gene mapping was implemented in the programming language R and the web interface in PHP. To build a human protein interaction network, experimental data from five public databases<ref type="bibr">[MIPS (Mewes et al., 1999</ref>), DIP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Xenarios et al., 2000</ref>), BIND (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bader et al., 2001</ref>), HPRD (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Peri et al., 2004</ref>) and IntAct (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hermjakob et al., 2004)]</ref>were combined and filtered for binary interactions by removing entries with PSI-MI codes for detection methods that cannot verify direct binary interactions (these are evidence codes for co-immunoprecipitation or colocalization, for example; details on the used method definitions and PSI-MI codes can be found in the 'Datasets' section on the webpage). This filtering resulted in a network consisting of 9392 proteins and 38 857 interactions. Additionally, protein interaction networks for the model organisms yeast (Saccharomyces cerevisiae), fly (Drosophila melanogaster), worm (Caenorhabditis elegans) and plant (Arabidopsis thaliana) have been built using the same methodology as for the human network and the BioGRID database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Stark et al., 2006</ref>) as additional data source (see the help sections on the webpage for additional details on these networks). TopoGSA will be updated periodically twice per year to integrate newly available protein interaction data and reference gene sets. Moreover, users can upload their own networks. A video tutorial and instructions on how to use the web tool are available in the 'Tutorial' section on the webpage.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Example results produced with TopoGSA based on the cancer gene set by Futreal et al. (2004). (a) Topological properties can be computed and examined as visual (1) and tabular (2) outputs; (b) The gene set can be compared with a chosen reference database (here the KEGG database).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: Marie-Curie Early-Stage-Training programme (MESTCT-2004-007597); the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council (BB/F01855X/1); Spanish Ministry for Education and Science (BIO2007-66855); Juan de la Cierva post-doctoral fellowship (to A.B.). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from [13:05 13/4/2010 Bioinformatics-btq131.tex]</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative study of gene set enrichment methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Abatangelo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">275</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The InterPro database, an integrated documentation resource for protein families, domains and functional sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Apweiler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">37</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene Ontology: tool for the unification of biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BIND–the biomolecular interaction network database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Bader</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="242" to="245" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Eigenvector-like measures of centrality for asymmetric relations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Bonacich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soc. Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="201" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A census of human cancer genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Futreal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="183" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ArrayMining: a modular web-application for microarray analysis combining ensemble and consensus methods with cross-study normalization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Glaab</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">358</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IntAct: an open source molecular interaction database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Hermjakob</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="452" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A literature network of human genes for high-throughput analysis of gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Jenssen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global topological features of cancer proteins in the human interactome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Jonsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2291" to="2297" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From genomics to chemical genomics: new developments in KEGG</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kanehisa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="354" to="357" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linking genes to literature: text mining, information extraction, and retrieval applications for biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Krallinger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MIPS: a database for genomes and protein sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Mewes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Nishimura</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BioCarta. Biotech Softw. Internet Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human protein reference database as a discovery resource for proteomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Peri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">497</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">STRING: a web-server to retrieve and display the repeatedly occurring neighbourhood of a gene</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Snel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3442" to="3444" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioGRID: a general repository for interaction datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Stark</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">535</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancer genes and the pathways they control</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Vogelstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Kinzler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="789" to="799" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective dynamics of &apos;small-world&apos; networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Watts</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Strogatz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">393</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="440" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DIP: the database of interacting proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Xenarios</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>