
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:41+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression tRanslatome: an R/Bioconductor package to portray translational control</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Toma</forename>
								<surname>Tebaldi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Translational Genomics -Centre for Integrative Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Trento</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via delle Regole 101</addrLine>
									<postCode>38123</postCode>
									<settlement>Mattarello</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Erik</forename>
								<surname>Dassi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Translational Genomics -Centre for Integrative Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Trento</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via delle Regole 101</addrLine>
									<postCode>38123</postCode>
									<settlement>Mattarello</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Galena</forename>
								<surname>Kostoska</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Translational Genomics -Centre for Integrative Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Trento</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via delle Regole 101</addrLine>
									<postCode>38123</postCode>
									<settlement>Mattarello</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gabriella</forename>
								<surname>Viero</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNR –</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via alla Cascata 56/C</addrLine>
									<postCode>38123</postCode>
									<settlement>Povo</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Associate Editor: Inanc Birol</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alessandro</forename>
								<surname>Quattrone</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Translational Genomics -Centre for Integrative Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Trento</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via delle Regole 101</addrLine>
									<postCode>38123</postCode>
									<settlement>Mattarello</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression tRanslatome: an R/Bioconductor package to portray translational control</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="291"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt634</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 2, 2013; revised on October 10, 2013; accepted on October 29, 2013</note>
					<note>Contact: t.tebaldi@unitn.it Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>High-throughput technologies have led to an explosion of genomic data available for automated analysis. The consequent possibility to simultaneously sample multiple layers of variation along the gene expression flow requires computational methods integrating raw information from different &apos;-omics&apos;. It has been recently demonstrated that translational control is a widespread phenomenon, with profound and still underestimated regulation capabilities. Although detecting changes in the levels of total messenger RNAs (mRNAs; the transcrip-tome), of polysomally loaded mRNAs (the translatome) and of proteins (the proteome) is experimentally feasible in a high-throughput way, the integration of these levels is still far from being robustly approached. Here we introduce tRanslatome, a new R/Bioconductor package, which is a complete platform for the simultaneous pairwise analysis of transcriptome, translatome and proteome data. The package includes most of the available statistical methods developed for the analysis of high-throughput data, allowing the parallel comparison of differentially expressed genes and the corresponding differentially enriched biological themes. Notably, it also enables the prediction of translational regulatory elements on mRNA sequences. The utility of this tool is demonstrated with two case studies. Availability and implementation: tRanslatome is available in Bioconductor.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>High-throughput ('-omics') measurements of macromolecule variations in the cell offer the possibility to comprehensively understand how the cellular processes are regulated and to reveal how different layers of control are coordinated in producing a physiologically coherent response. These measurements are also invaluable to understand how the loss of this coordination contributes to disease origin. The establishment of highthroughput technologies and the consequent explosion of available data allow us to reach a 'systems' understanding of the variations in gene expression only when a parallel evolution of algorithms and data mining techniques is achieved. This eventually enables to suggest and prioritize potential mechanistic processes. Nonetheless, the integration of '-omics' data, ranging from epigenetic chromatin remodeling to the dynamics of transcription, translation and protein activities, still requires considerable experimental and computational developments. In this context, the low correlation observed between messenger RNA (mRNA) and protein levels is an unsolved issue (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Vogel and Marcotte, 2012</ref>). Recently we showed that the analysis of the translatome, an intermediate level between the transcriptome and the proteome formed by mRNAs engaged with polysomes, provides substantial and somewhat surprising new information (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Tebaldi et al., 2012</ref>). This and other examples (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Colman et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Schwanhaüsser et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Vogel et al., 2010</ref>) show how the integration of '-omics' data can provide a biologically relevant outcome. Here we present tRanslatome, a new Bioconductor package for the analysis of differential profiles coming from transcriptome, translatome and proteome studies. tRanslatome will help to study mRNA and protein variations in an exhaustive way, providing specific tools for the comparison of polysomal mRNA with total mRNA or protein data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">DESCRIPTION AND USAGE</head><p>tRanslatome is a complete platform for the analysis and pairwise comparison of two '-omics' levels implemented as a Bioconductor package. It is developed to compare translatome data with transcriptome and/or proteome data. A general overview of the functions offered by tRanslatome is given in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1A</ref>. The package is conceptually organized in three modules, described as follows:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">DEGs detection</head><p>The only input required by tRanslatome is an expression matrix containing either read counts (from next-generation sequencing data) or normalized signals (from microarray or proteome experiments). To select differentially expressed genes (DEGs), the package offers, in the same computational environment, the integrative analysis of established and emerging statistical methods: (i) DEseq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Anders and Huber, 2010</ref>) and edgeR *To whom correspondence should be addressed.This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which permits noncommercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Robinson et al., 2010</ref>), specifically implemented for the analysis of next-generation sequencing data; (ii) significance analysis of microarrays (SAM) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Tusher et al., 2001</ref>), developed for the analysis of microarray data; (iii) t-test, RankProd (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Breitling et al., 2004</ref>), linear models and moderated t-test (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Smyth, 2004</ref>), suitable to deal with general quantitative data; and (iv) methods dealing specifically with the comparison of translatome and transcriptome data, e.g. ANOTA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Larsson et al., 2011</ref>) and translational efficiency, derived from the ratio of polysomal and subpolysomal signals (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Powley et al., 2009</ref>) or the ratio of ribosome protected fragments and RNA-seq reads (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Ingolia et al., 2011</ref>). These techniques are described more exhaustively in the documentation and in the Supplementary Material. To study all the relevant differences arising from the two '-omics' levels, tRanslatome offers a variety of graphical outputs, helping the quality assessment and interpretation of the results. The minus-average plots aid the identification of intensity-dependent patterns, whereas the standard deviation plot can help the selection of the best method for DEGs identification (see Supplementary Figs 4 and 5). The graphics also include scatterplots, displaying changes in the expression of genes in terms of fold changes at both levels (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1B</ref>), and histograms, showing a detailed representation of all the DEGs classes (Supplementary Figs 2 and 3).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Gene Ontology enrichment comparison</head><p>One of the most frequent applications of the Gene Ontology (GO) is enrichment analysis, i.e. the identification of significantly overrepresented GO terms in a given gene set (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ashburner et al., 2000</ref>). tRanslatome includes the detection and comparison of GO terms, resuming information about cellular components, molecular functions and biological processes associated to DEGs detected from the two '-omics' levels. Multiple choices are offered for the overrepresentation test, which exploits the GO 'tree' structure by means of the Bioconductor package 'topGO': these choices can satisfy the need for either more general or more specific biological themes. To simplify the inspection of the results and to effectively represent the differences in the enrichment of ontological terms, the corresponding radar plots and heatmaps can be produced (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1C</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figs 7 and 8</ref>). tRanslatome also provides methods for a sensitive comparison of the similarity between enriched GO terms, including the semantic similarity scores (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Wang et al., 2007</ref>) between terms at each level, and the global similarity score between the two levels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Enrichment analysis of post-transcriptional regulatory elements</head><p>As tRanslatome focuses on the study of global translational controls, enrichment analysis of RNA binding proteins and microRNA binding sites or other RNA regulatory motifs (e.g. AU-rich elements) can be performed on the lists of DEGs. This analysis allows the user to identify possible regulatory factors responsible for the translational regulation of genes in the experiment under consideration (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1D</ref>). The list of genes regulated by each post-transcriptional element is obtained from therecently established Atlas of UTR Regulatory Activity (AURA) database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Dassi et al., 2012</ref>). The method computes a Fisher test P-value indicating whether binding sites for each regulator are significantly enriched in the DEGs lists. The annotations from AURA will be updated on every release of tRanslatome. Users can also specify a custom annotation file in place of the one provided by default.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>y</head><figDesc>Present address: Department of Information Engineering and Computer Science, University of Trento, via Sommarive 5, 38123 Povo (TN), Italy. zThe authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Outline of tRanslatome workflow and graphical outputs. (A) General overview of the three modules provided by tRanslatome. (B) Scatterplot of fold changes. Each gene is mapped according to the fold change in the transcriptome and the translatome. Different classes of DEGs are color labeled. The Spearman correlation coefficients are displayed for all genes and for all DEGs. (C) Radar plot of the top enriched GO biological process terms for the transcriptome and the translatome DEGs. (D) Heatmap of the top enriched post-transcriptional regulators for the transcriptome and the translatome DEGs. The color scale is based on the-log10 of the enrichment P-value, calculated with a Fisher test</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">T.Tebaldi et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> EXAMPLES A worked example, derived from data on differentiated versus undifferentiated human hepatocytes (Parent et al., 2007) is used to generate the panels contained in Figure 1. Detailed explanations of this example, along with a second example dealing with the comparison of the proteome and the transcriptome between two human cell lines (Stevens and Brown, 2013), are provided in the Supplementary Material. 4 CONCLUSION tRanslatome allows a user-friendly comparison and integration of data generated from two &apos;-omics&apos; measurements, empowering the discovery of regulatory mechanisms underlying the uncoupling processes among the transcriptome, the translatome and the proteome. Funding: This work is supported by the University and Scientific Research Services of the Autonomous Province of Trento. Conflicts of interest: none declared.</note>

			<note place="foot">tRanslatome at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Anders</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Huber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rank products: a simple, yet powerful, new method to detect differentially regulated genes in replicated microarray experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Breitling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEBS Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">573</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide analysis of host mRNA translation during hepatitis C virus infection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Colman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Virol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6668" to="6677" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AURA: Atlas of UTR Regulatory Activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Dassi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="144" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ribosome profiling of mouse embryonic stem cells reveals the complexity and dynamics of mammalian proteomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Ingolia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="789" to="802" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">anota: Analysis of differential translation in genome-wide studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Larsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1440" to="1441" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mammalian target of rapamycin activation impairs hepatocytic differentiation and targets genes moderating lipid homeostasis and hepatocellular growth</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Parent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4337" to="4345" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Translational reprogramming following UVB irradiation is mediated by DNA-PKcs and allows selective recruitment to the polysomes of mRNAs encoding DNA repair enzymes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Powley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1207" to="1220" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global quantification of mammalian gene expression control</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Schwanhaüsser</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">473</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="342" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linear models and empirical bayes methods for assessing differential expression in microarray experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Smyth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Appl. Genet. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In silico estimation of translation efficiency in human cell lines: potential evidence for widespread translational control</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Stevens</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Brown</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">57625</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Widespread uncoupling between transcriptome and translatome variations after a stimulus in mammalian cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Tebaldi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">220</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Significance analysis of microarrays applied to the ionizing radiation response</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Tusher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5116" to="5121" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Insights into the regulation of protein abundance from proteomic and transcriptomic analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Vogel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Marcotte</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequence signatures and mRNA concentration can explain two-thirds of protein abundance variation in a human cell line</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Vogel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">400</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new method to measure the semantic similarity of GO terms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Z</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1274" to="1281" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>