
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:37+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis VirVarSeq: a low-frequency virus variant detection pipeline for Illumina sequencing using adaptive base-calling accuracy filtering</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bie</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M P</forename>
								<surname>Verbist</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematical Modeling, Statistics and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Coupure Links 653, 2 Janssen R&amp;D</addrLine>
									<postCode>9000</postCode>
									<settlement>Gent</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Janssen Pharmaceutical Companies of Johnson &amp; Johnson</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Turnhoutseweg 30</addrLine>
									<postCode>2340</postCode>
									<settlement>Beerse</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kim</forename>
								<surname>Thys</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joke</forename>
								<surname>Reumers</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yves</forename>
								<surname>Wetzels</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Koen</forename>
								<surname>Van Der Borght</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Willem</forename>
								<surname>Talloen</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jeroen</forename>
								<surname>Aerssens</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lieven</forename>
								<surname>Clement</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Applied Mathematics, Informatics and Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Krijgslaan 281 S9</addrLine>
									<postCode>9000</postCode>
									<settlement>Gent</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Olivier</forename>
								<surname>Thas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematical Modeling, Statistics and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Coupure Links 653, 2 Janssen R&amp;D</addrLine>
									<postCode>9000</postCode>
									<settlement>Gent</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Janssen Pharmaceutical Companies of Johnson &amp; Johnson</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Turnhoutseweg 30</addrLine>
									<postCode>2340</postCode>
									<settlement>Beerse</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mathematics and Applied Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Wollongong</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Institute for Applied Statistics Research Australia (NIASRA)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2522</postCode>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Associate Editor: Inanc Birol</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis VirVarSeq: a low-frequency virus variant detection pipeline for Illumina sequencing using adaptive base-calling accuracy filtering</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="94" to="101"/>
							<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu587</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 4, 2014; revised on July 25, 2014; accepted on August 26, 2014</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Availability: The VirVarSeq is available, together with a user&apos;s guide and test data, at sourceforge: http://sourceforge.net/projects/virtools/?source=directory Contact: bie.verbist@ugent.be Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: In virology, massively parallel sequencing (MPS) opens many opportunities for studying viral quasi-species, e.g. in HIV-1-and HCV-infected patients. This is essential for understanding pathways to resistance, which can substantially improve treatment. Although MPS platforms allow in-depth characterization of sequence variation, their measurements still involve substantial technical noise. For Illumina sequencing, single base substitutions are the main error source and impede powerful assessment of low-frequency mutations. Fortunately, base calls are complemented with quality scores (Qs) that are useful for differentiating errors from the real low-frequency mutations. Results: A variant calling tool, Q-cpileup, is proposed, which exploits the Qs of nucleotides in a filtering strategy to increase specificity. The tool is imbedded in an open-source pipeline, VirVarSeq, which allows variant calling starting from fastq files. Using both plasmid mixtures and clinical samples, we show that Q-cpileup is able to reduce the number of false-positive findings. The filtering strategy is adaptive and provides an optimized threshold for individual samples in each sequencing run. Additionally, linkage information is kept between single-nucleotide polymorphisms as variants are called at the codon level. This enables virologists to have an immediate biological interpretation of the reported variants with respect to their antiviral drug responses. A comparison with existing SNP caller tools reveals that calling variants at the codon level with Q-cpileup results in an outstanding sensitivity while maintaining a good specificity for variants with frequencies down to 0.5%.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>RNA viruses such as HIV-1 and HCV exist in their host as complex populations composed of several closely related subgroups. They are referred to as quasi-species and originate from high and error-prone replication rates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Domingo et al., 2012</ref>). This heterogeneous mixture of genomes allows a viral population to rapidly adapt to changing environments. The fittest mutants outcompete the others, allowing the virus to develop resistance to antiviral therapy. The characterization of sequence variation within the viral population is key for understanding pathways to resistance, but the identification of low-frequency variants remains challenging (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Codoner et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Gianella et al., 2010</ref>). Until recently, the genetic diversity of a virus population could be assessed only through genotyping by Sanger sequencing, which provides information on only the most abundant viral variants. Massively parallel sequencing technologies allow for a more in-depth characterization of sequence variation, including low-frequency viral strains. However, their measurements still involve substantial technical noise, complicating the analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Beerenwinkel et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dohm et al., 2008</ref>). Pyrosequencing, commercialized by Roche 454, was the most common sequencing method for viral population sequencing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Beerenwinkel and Zagordi, 2011</ref>). The recent announcement by Roche to retract the 454 technology from the market by mid-2016 illustrates the pressing need to evaluate and implement alternative technologies. Recently Illumina's sequencing technique has strengthened its position in this field (Thys et al., Manuscript under review). Illumina also complements the sequenced nucleotides with quality scores (Qs) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ewing and Green, 1998</ref>) that reflect the basecalling substitution error probability. The 454 Qs, however, do not have such an intuitive interpretation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">De Beuf et al., 2012</ref>). Filtering based on Qs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Reumers et al., 2012</ref>) has already proven valuable to reduce false-positive findings. It often involves the use of a hard quality threshold. Unfortunately, this does not account for variation in quality between runs resulting in too stringent or too relaxed thresholds. Most variant calling tools focus on the detection of single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Macalalad et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wilm et al., 2012</ref>) or perform haplotype reconstruction (<ref type="bibr">Shirmer et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Zagordi et al., 2011</ref>). Haplotype assembly has *To whom correspondence should be addressed. its weakness in the detection of low-frequency variants (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Prosperi et al., 2013</ref>), whereas the latter is our main interest. Instead, we prefer to call variants within the read length to avoid challenges encountered in the haplotype reconstruction. On the other hand, linkage between the nucleotides is lost when calling variants at the SNP level. In this contribution, we introduce a novel strategy for calling variants at the codon level (nucleotide triplets), which facilitates immediate biological interpretations, particularly in virology applications where drug target regions are of interest. In this article, we present an innovative approach for variant calling at the codon level, named Q-cpileup, that reduces the number of false-positive findings by exploiting the Qs of the nucleotides generated by sequencing. Our thresholding strategy is adaptive to provide an optimized threshold for individual samples in each sequencing run. Q-cpileup is imbedded in a pipeline, called VirVarSeq, which starts from fastq files.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>Several samples were sequenced using Illumina's genome analyzer (GA) IIx according to manufacturing protocols (see Supplementary Material). The VirVarSeq pipeline proceeds as follows:</p><p>(1) The sequenced reads are aligned against a reference sequence using the Burrows–Wheeler aligner tool (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Li and Durbin, 2009</ref>).</p><formula>(2)</formula><p>Based on this alignment, a consensus sequence is defined.</p><p>(3) A realignment is performed against this consensus. This strategy of iterative mapping will increase coverage, especially in samples where the consensus strongly deviates from the reference (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>).</p><p>(4) After alignment, Q-cpileup is executed, which consists of a threestep analysis:</p><p>(a) In the first step, the Qs of the codons in the reading frame of interest are retrieved.</p><p>(b) Next, the threshold is determined dependent on the quality of the run.</p><p>(c) Finally, the filtered codon table is constructed. The VirVarSeq pipeline, which runs from fastq to the filtered codon table, is available at http://sourceforge.net/projects/virtools/?source=directory together with a user's guide (see Supplementary Material 2). All reads containing indel errors are removed before running Q-cpileup. It is hereby assumed that indels will result in non-viable virus. In some rare occasions, however, there might be an insertion mutation at the codon level, which can be investigated in a separate analysis (see indel Table Supplementary Material). Below, the different steps from Q-cpileup will be explained in more detail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Quality of codons</head><p>A pileup of read bases is generated using the alignments to a consensus sequence. In analogy with mpileup of samtools, for which the base-pair information at each reference position is described, cpileup describes the codon information at each amino acid position of the reference genome. For each position in the reference genome, the different codons are reported together with one Q for each codon. This requires that the Qs of the three nucleotides within a codon have to be summarized. A comparative analysis of different summarizations revealed that the weakest link, i.e. minimum Q of the three nucleotides in the codon, provided the best separation between low-and high-quality codons (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S2</ref>). This minimum Q represents the codon's nucleotide with the highest probability of being a sequencing error. A codon table is built based on the pileup where for each codon position of the reference the different codons within a sample are reported together with their frequency (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). The minimum Qs of the codons at a particular position are averaged to give a rough idea about the overall quality. However, the individual minimum Qs of the codons themselves is used in subsequent analyses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Q-intersection threshold</head><p>The distribution of the minimum Qs was checked and compared for one particular sample sequenced in two different runs and three different lanes reaching an average coverage of around 30 000 (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). The shape of the distributions can be approximated by a mixture distribution with three truncated normal components (see Supplementary Material for model selection and goodness of fit in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S3</ref>). Truncation is performed at the lower and upper ends of the Q range. The first mode represents a point probability at Q 2, which is the lowest Illumina Q. This is due to an artifact created by Illumina's base caller. Read ends with a segment of mostly low quality (Q15) are given a Q of 2. The second component distribution is a distribution of low Qs, reflecting the sequencing error distribution. Finally, the highest mode, close to 40, originates from a distribution of reliable calls. Note that the mixture of three normal components for the errors and reliable calls should be considered only as a working assumption and that neither trimming nor filtering of the data is required before fitting the mixture models. The expectation maximization (EM) algorithm of McLachlan (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">McLachlan and Jones, 1988</ref>) will be applied for fitting these normal mixture models. We have written an R-wrapper to run the original Fortran code of McLachlan, which is embedded in the pipeline VirVarSeq. The EM algorithm was initialized by setting the three modes at 2, 10 and 35 and the variances at 0.8 for the point probability and 40 for the other two distributions. The marginal error probability, the sum of mixing proportion of the distributions at 2 and 10, was set to 15%. The bulk of Qs was high, indicating a majority of reliable calls in the dataset (green distribution in<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). At the other end, a clear point probability at the Q of 2 was seen. The red distribution in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>corresponds to low-quality codons that are likely to be sequencing errors. There are several criteria to define a threshold for filtering the low-quality codons and for distinguishing between errors and reliableNotes. The different codons observed in a sample are counted at each codon position of the reference genome and their frequencies are calculated using the coverage at that particular position. The Qs are summarized by averaging the minimum Qs of the codons. Position: amino acid position of the reference. Ref: codon of the reference genome at a particular position. Codon: codon present in a sample at a particular position. Count: the number of times a particular codon occurs in the cpileup at a particular position. Coverage: the number of reads that fully cover a particular codon position. Frequency: Count/Coverage. Mean: Average of the minimum Qs of a particular codon at a particular position.</p><p>calls. An approach is chosen that is adaptive and robust. The intersection point of the two component distributions was used and is referred to as the Q-intersection threshold (QIT), which is indicated with vertical dashed lines in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. The distribution of the minimum Qs of the codons and hence the QIT varies between different runs for the same sample, confirming the need for an adaptive filtering strategy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Filtering of codon tables</head><p>Once the QIT is determined, an updated codon table can be constructed. All codons with a minimum Q below the threshold will be filtered from the analysis. The influence of trimming is negligible, as it mainly affects low-quality nucleotides, which are removed by the filter. The three-step analysis returns a codon table with different variants and their frequencies at each codon position of the reference, which is robust to sequencing errors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">HCV plasmid mixtures</head><p>To assess the filtering accuracy of Q-cpileup, we made use of two plasmids that carry HCV NS3 amino acids 1 to 181 and that differ at only two codon positions, 36 and 155. The two plasmids were mixed in four different proportions—1:10, 1:50, 1:100 and 1:200—and sequenced with average coverages of 96 211, 81 179, 95 590 and 74 820, respectively (see Supplementary Material for sample preparation; sequencing data are available at the European Nucleotide Archive, accession number PRJEB5028). A minor variant is defined as a codon that differs from the consensus. Hence, only two minor variants are expected at codon positions 36 [GTC (consensus) ! ATG] and 155 [CGG (consensus) ! AAA]; all others can be considered as false-positive findings. For each of the four sequenced mixes, the QIT was determined (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). Comparison of the number of variants when no filtering but trimming (QIT = 0) is applied and after Q-cpileup reveals that adaptive quality filtering can reduce the number of false-positive findings by 20–50% (third and fourth columns of<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). With Q-cpileup, no false-positive findings are reported with frequencies 41%, a reporting limit defined by Thys et al. (Manuscript under review). This is in strong contrast with the 7–12% FDR without filtering, for discoveries with frequencies 41%. Q-cpileup is able to reduce the number of falsepositive findings while the frequencies of the true minor variants (last columns of<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>) remain unaltered. The results for the mixing proportion of 1% are shown in more detail in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 2</ref>. A QIT of 19 was used for filtering in this sample (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 2a</ref>). In panel b, the codons equal to the consensus (called major variants) are investigated before (QIT = 0) and after filtering (QIT = 19). The plasmid data have only two real variants, meaning that the codons investigated here should have frequencies close to 100%. After applying Q-cpileup, the frequencies of the codons are indeed closer to 100, indicating again that the number of false-positive findings is reduced. The minor variants are compared in panel c. Without filtering, several minor variants are reported with frequencies above the reporting limit of 1%. Their frequencies are strongly reduced after filtering, while the estimates of the true minor variant frequencies remain (red triangles). This suggests again that Q filtering provides effective noise reduction while still retaining the reliable calls at low frequency.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 2c</ref>reveals that our new filtering method allows for lowering the reporting<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. Distribution of the minimum Qs of the codons present in an HCV sample, which was sequenced twice in the same run (run 1) but in different lanes (lanes 1 and 2), and which was sequenced yet another time in another run (run 2). The black line shows the overall fit of the mixture distribution, which consists of the blue, the red and the green component distributions. The blue and the red distributions correspond to codons that likely result from sequencing errors, and the green distribution represents reliable calls. The QIT is indicated with a vertical black dashed lineNotes: For each of four mixing proportions, the QIT is reported that was used for filtering. The number of reported codons, the false discovery rate for discoveries with frequency above 1% and the estimated frequencies of the true variants are compared before filtering is applied and after Q-cpileup. limit, although the discovery of true variants below 0.5% remains challenging.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Comparison with LoFreq, V-Phaser 2 and ShoRAH</head><p>The performance of Q-cpileup is compared with three other methodologies: LoFreq (v0.5.0) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wilm et al., 2012</ref>), V-phaser 2 (v2.0) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Macalalad et al., 2012</ref>) and ShoRAH (v0.8) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Zagordi et al., 2011</ref>). They were run in their default settings and using the previously described plasmid mixtures. With ShoRAH, we were unable to use the original bam file, as unresolvable problems (even after discussion with the developers) were encountered when extracting the reads from the desired region. Therefore, the ShoRAH results are based on a bam file with remapped reads against the reference region of interest. None of the existing methods calls variants immediately at the codon level. Hence, three SNP callers were chosen based on their capabilities for inferring diversity within viral populations. The two codon variant positions present in the mixtures differ at five nucleotide positions, which should be discovered by the SNP callers. The results are presented in the top part of<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>. None of the methods could discover the five SNPs at the 0.5% level, and only LoFreq could retrieve all SNPs present at 1%. Hence, LoFreq is the most sensitive SNP caller in this comparison, but it also detects some false-positive findings with frequency 41% (bottom rows of<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>). Comparison with<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>reveals that the sensitivity and specificity for discoveries 41% with Q-cpileup is outstanding. Especially its sensitivity is of utmost importance: the method is initially developed for finding resistance-associated mutations, and missing important variants might mislead further treatment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Clinical HCV sample and comparison with 454</head><p>Subsequently, Q-cpileup was applied on a clinical HCV sample (see Supplementary Material for sample preparation). The fit of the mixture distribution returned a QIT of 26 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3a</ref>). In<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3b</ref>, the frequencies of the codons before and after filtering were plotted on the log scale, which allows a better comparison of low-frequency variants. The frequencies of the variants that were removed after filtering were indicated in gray at the bottom. As the truth is unknown in clinical samples, one cannot reliably separate true variants from sequencing errors. However, one could compare the discovered variants with 454 sequencing results. As 454 sequencing chemistry is different, another error profile can be expected. Hence, variants that were not discovered with 454 are more likely to be Illumina sequencing errors (and vice versa) and are indicated with red triangles in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3b</ref>. A good correlation between the filtered and the unfiltered variant frequencies is observed above 1%. The variants that were not detected in the 454 experiment, likely to be false discoveries, drop in frequency after applying Q-cpileup. Hence, our approach seems to control the false discovery rate at a reasonable level up to variant frequencies of 0.5%. A lower coverage depth of the 454 experiment did not allow for comparing Illumina and 454 sequencing for frequencies 50.1%.</p><formula>(a) ( b)</formula><p>(c)In case of ShoRAH, the frequency is estimated from three overlapping windows, but often the SNP is only retrieved in two out of the three windows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Effect of inter-/intra-run variability on QIT</head><p>An equimolar pool of 42 clinical HCV samples was sequenced three times to investigate the variability in sequencing quality and hence the variability of the QIT. The 42 samples were sequenced twice within the same run (R1) but on two different lanes (L1 and L2), and they were all sequenced again in another run (R2 L3). For one of these samples, the mixture distribution of each of the three sequencing runs is shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. A clear difference in quality between the runs is observed, resulting in different QITs. Boxplots of the QITs of 42 samples for each of the sequencing runs show that the inter-run variability of the QIT is larger than the variability between lanes of the same run (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 4</ref>). First, the effect of the intra-run variability of the QITs on the final codon table was investigated. The number of reported codons with frequency 41% is plotted for both lanes in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure  5a</ref>. In all, 74% of the samples report at most one additional codon, depending on the lane on which it is sequenced. The maximum difference in reported number of codons is four. We further explored frequency differences for all codons. The distribution of the differences in frequency between the two lanes is plotted for each sample in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5b</ref>. Overall, the frequencies are similar with some deviations up to 3%. These maxima, however, are mainly originating from codons located in a GC-rich region, where a coverage drop is observed. The sample where the maximum absolute difference is observed (indicated in red) is investigated in detail in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5c</ref>.</p><p>The frequencies for all codons discovered on both lanes are plotted against each other on the log scale. No substantial differences can be observed at 41%. Finally, the maximum differences, for each of the 42 samples, are reported on a relative scale in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5d</ref>. The sizes of the dots are scaled according to the absolute frequency obtained in lane 1, which teaches us that most deviations occur for frequencies 450%. Overall, the reported variants and their frequencies are comparable on both lanes after applying Q-cpileup, despite slightly different QITs. This is in strong contrast with the raw data (see in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. S4</ref>). These raw data were only trimmed, which is partially based on Qs. Without Q-cpileup, the comparison of the samples sequenced on both lanes reveals that (i) the number of reported variants differs up to 16 variants, (ii) deviations of the frequencies go up to 6% and (iii) even for the variants with frequency 41%, some clear deviations between the two lanes can be observed. This suggests that Q-cpileup is able to reduce the number of false-positive findings while retaining the true signal, and that the adaptive approach is able to account for differences in quality between the lanes. In the next step, the inter-run variability of the QITs was investigated. The second run was a high-quality run with fewer errors (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1 comparing run 1</ref>lane 2 and run 2 lane 3). The overall good quality in run 2 makes the estimation of the error component of the mixture challenging and results in a large QIT. The effect of these high QITs on the final codon table was investigated. The number of reported variants, with frequency 41%, is again similar even after applying these high thresholds (<ref type="figure">Fig. 6a</ref>). In all, 83% of the samples report at most one additional variant, and only one sample reports four additional variants, which is again the maximum difference in reported number of variants. The distribution of the frequency differences remains small overall, but the maximum difference in frequency as well as the relative change for these maxima rises (<ref type="figure">Fig. 6b</ref>and d).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mixture distribution</head><p>PhredBut these maxima occur again at rather high frequencies. When focusing on a particular sample, high QITs seem to have no negative impact on the final codon table (<ref type="figure">Fig. 6c</ref>). Despite the questionable working assumption that the second component separates the error distribution from the distribution of the reliable calls, the resulting QITs provide reliable codon tables. Hence, our filtering approach seems robust to deviations from the working assumption. Q-cpileup is adaptive and thereby can cope with differences in quality between runs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Robustness of the method</head><p>Approximately 400 samples, from both HCV-and HIV-infected subjects, were sequenced in seven different runs and analyzed with Q-cpileup. Some examples of the HCV results are displayed in Figures 3 and 5. The sequenced amplicons of HCV samples cover GC-rich regions. It is known that Illumina is error prone in these regions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dohm et al., 2008</ref>). This is reflected in the distribution of the minimum Qs where more low values are observed than with amplicons of HIV samples for which no GC-rich regions were covered (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S5</ref>). It is especially in these GC-rich regions where you expect that false-positive findings exist with frequencies 41% as seen in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3b</ref>on the x-axis. When applying Q-cpileup, the frequencies of these false-positive findings could be reduced. In Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure S5</ref>, we illustrate that the proposed strategy also similarly reduces the noise for HIV samples. Although this new variant calling tool was primarily developed based on Illumina's GAIIx sequencing data, it can also be a valuable tool for other Illumina sequencing platforms, such as HiSeq. HiSeq uses the same sequencing-by-synthesis technique and suffers from the same error types (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Minoche et al., 2011</ref>). HiSeq data, analyzed with Q-cpileup, are presented in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S6</ref>. The tool, however, is not applicable for pyrosequencing techniques, such as Roche 454. Their Qs do not reflect substitution error probabilities but probabilities of calling homopolymers of particular length (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">De Beuf et al., 2012</ref>). For these types of data, the toolthe upper whiskers range roughly between 1% and 5% difference in reported codon frequency, depending on the run where the sample was sequenced. (c) Comparison of all codon frequencies on the log scale between the two runs for the sample where the maximum frequency difference is observed. The frequencies of variants that are absent in the other run are plotted in gray. (d) Relative change for codons with maximum absolute frequency difference is plotted for each sample and scaled according to the estimated frequency in condition 2. The relative change is calculated as<ref type="bibr">[</ref>/x 2 with x 1 and x 2 the codon frequencies for lane 1 and lane 2, respectively (sample with the maximum absolute difference in red). The sizes of the dots are scaled according to the estimated frequency in lane 1, indicating that most maximum differences occur at higher frequencies can, however, still generate a codon table, but no threshold determination or QIT-based filtering should be applied.</p><formula>(a) ( b) (c) (</formula><formula>(c) ( d)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>Many sequence variant identification tools have been described in literature to call variants at the SNP level. Most approaches are tailored to call SNPs in human resequencing projects (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Nielsen et al., 2011</ref>) where SNPs can be either heterologous (50%) or homologous (100%). However, in viral deep sequencing projects, the SNP frequency can vary between 100% and 0%, whereas SNPs present in 51% of the reads also may be of interest. Further, our main focus is the detection of drugresistant variants for which a specific drug-target region has to be investigated. Hence, it would be beneficial to report variants at the codon level per amino acid position to enable an immediate biological interpretation of the variants with respect to their antiviral drug responses. Variant calling tools used by the virologists in this research field are either not fully described in-house tools (Noguera-Julian et al., 2013) or build based on SNPs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Parameswaran et al., 2012</ref>) at the DNA or RNA level only. In the latter case, one needs to retrieve the linkage information between the neighboring nucleotides to deduce effects at the coded amino acid level. This process is not always straightforward. Some of the variant callers developed for viral population sequencing have add-on tools, like V-profiler (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Henn et al., 2012</ref>) for V-phaser (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Macalalad et al., 2012</ref>), to convert the list of SNPs to a list of codon variants. However, these are mainly developed for 454 data. None of the available tools reports the variants immediately at the codon level. Therefore, Q-cpileup was initially developed and imbedded in a pipeline. By taking the weakest link as a representative for the quality of the codon, the filtering remains at the individual nucleotide level but reporting is done at the codon level. The approach is adaptive to allow for differences in quality between the runs. The intersection point between the distributions of the errors and reliable calls is suggested as a threshold (QIT). However, other criteria could also be considered. For instance, the number of false discoveries can be controlled by defining the QIT as a certain quantile of the reliable call component distribution. By using the 5% quantile as a QIT, 5% of the codons, which are truly present in the population, are falsely considered as being errors. This statement relies heavily on the interpretation of the distributions as errors and reliable calls. However, the three-component mixture distribution should be considered only as a working assumption. Moreover, it is impossible to check the actual interpretation of the mixture distributions. Hence, the interpretation of the different components as error and reliable calls cannot always be warranted, particularly when low Qs are underrepresented. Therefore, we advise users to assess the distribution plots as diagnostic tools to critically judge whether the chosen threshold is acceptable and/or meaningful. Instead of applying hard filtering with a QIT, as suggested in this article, the posterior probabilities of the reliable call distribution could be used. The counts of a codon at a particular position can be weighted with these probabilities. By doing so, codons with a low Q will have a low contribution in the final frequency estimates. Hence, data are not filtered but weighted with the probabilities of being truly present in the reliable codon population. This method also relies on the interpretation of the different component distributions as error distribution and reliable call distribution. Importantly, we have shown that the filtering strategy using hard threshold QIT is robust to runs where the distributions deviate from the working assumption. The impact on the final codon table frequencies was minimal. Overall, our proposed filtering strategy controls the false-positive rate at reasonable levels with no false discoveries above a reporting limit of 1%. The noise is effectively reduced while retaining the reliable calls even at low frequency. This suggests that the reporting limit of detection at 1% could be lowered, although distinguishing true variants from error at 0.5% remains challenging. Depending on the risk one is willing to take to include a small number of false-positive findings, either one of the cutoffs can be used. More importantly, Q-cPileup shows a splendid sensitivity that could not be achieved by the SNP callers while maintaining a good specificity for variants with frequencies down to 0.5%. This sensitivity will allow further investigation of the reported variants above one of the cutoffs defined by the specificity to search for resistance-associated mutations, or in the next step to monitor drug resistance and guide treatment (Dierynck et al., submitted for publication). Currently, the clinical cutoff is not yet defined for minority drugresistant virus variants, and it is still a subject of open debate (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Schneider et al., 2014</ref>). Some studies have found no significant association between the presence of low-frequency variants and subsequent virological failure, whereas others report clear correlations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Vandenhende et al., 2014</ref>). The availability of methods that detect low-frequency variants at the codon level with high sensitivity and good specificity can help in defining the clinical benefit of low-frequency resistance testing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">CONCLUSION</head><p>A variant calling tool is proposed for identifying true variants at the codon level within a viral population using Illumina sequencing. The variants are filtered using base-calling Qs for reducing false-positive findings. The lowest Q of the three nucleotides of the codon is taken as representative for the codon. An adaptive strategy is developed to provide an optimized threshold for individual samples in each sequencing run. The intersection point of the component distributions of the mixture is suggested as a valuable threshold, QIT. Codons with a Q below this threshold are not reported. The robustness against deviations of the working assumption justifies the utilities of our method for low-and high-quality sequencing runs. It is shown that the generated filtered codon table is reporting far fewer false-positive findings compared with the codon table based on the raw data. Moreover, VirVarSeq has a superb sensitivity compared with existing SNP callers while maintaining a good specificity for codon variants with frequencies down to 0.5%. This suggests that the current reporting limit of detection at 1% can even be lowered. The tool is implemented in a userfriendly open-source pipeline, VirVarSeq, which allows virologists to call variants at the codon level starting from the fastq files.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. (a) Distribution of the minimum Qs of the codons present in the HCV plasmids mixed 1:100. The black line shows the overall fit of the mixture distribution, which consists of the blue, the red and the green component distributions. The blue and the red distributions correspond to codons that likely result from sequencing errors, and the green distribution represents reliable calls. The QIT (QIT = 19) is indicated with a vertical black dashed line. (b) Boxplot of the major variant frequencies when no filtering is applied (QIT = 0) and after Q-cpileup with QIT = 19. (c) Scatterplot of minor variants (frequencies before filtering (QIT = 0) on the x-axis and after Q-cpileup on the y-axis). The true minor variants at codon positions 36 and 155 are indicated with red triangles; all others can be regarded as false-positive findings. The 1% reporting limit is indicated with dotted lines</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. (a) Distribution of the minimum Qs of the codons present in an HCV clinical sample. The black line shows the overall fit of the mixture distribution, which consists of the blue, the red and the green component distributions. The blue and the red distributions correspond to codons that likely result from sequencing errors, and the green distribution represents reliable calls. The QIT is indicated with a vertical black dashed line. (b) Scatterplot of estimated codon frequencies before (QIT = 0) and after filtering (QIT = 26) on the x-axis and y-axis, respectively. The reporting limits of 1% and 0.5% are indicated with dashed lines and dotted lines, respectively. The codons that were not reported after Q-cpileup are indicated in gray at the bottom. Codons not detected with 454 sequencing were indicated with red triangles and are likely to be false-positive findings</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Boxplot of the QITs of 42 clinical samples for each of the sequencing runs denoted by run (R) and lane (L) to investigate inter-and intrarun variability. The black boxplots are part of the intra-run comparison, whereas the gray boxplot represents the QITs of the other run. The interrun variability is larger compared with the intra-run variability</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. Effect of the intra-run variability of the QITs on the final reported codon frequencies. (a) Plot of the number of codons with a frequency41% for the 42 samples sequenced on lane 1 (x-axis) and lane 2 (y-axis). The plotting symbols indicate the number of codons that differ between the two lanes. (b) Boxplots of differences in codon frequency between two lanes for each of the 42 samples. For each of the samples, 75% of the codons show differences in frequencies close to zero, whereas the upper whiskers range roughly between 0.5% and 3% difference in reported codon frequency, depending on the lane where the sample was sequenced. (c) Comparison of all codon frequencies on the log scale between two lanes for the sample where the maximum frequency difference is observed. The frequencies of codons not present in the other lane are plotted in gray. (d) Relative change for codons with maximum absolute difference plotted for each sample. The relative change is calculated as [x 1 – x 2 ]/x 2 with x 1 and x 2 the codon frequencies for lane 1 and lane 2, respectively (sample with the maximum absolute difference in red). The sizes of the dots are scaled according to the estimated frequency in lane 1, indicating that most maximum differences occur at higher frequencies</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Example of a frequency table at codon level</figDesc><table>Position 
Ref 
Codon 

Codon Count Coverage Frequency 
(%) 

Mean 
Q 

001 
GGG 
AGG 
167 18 966 
0.88 
35 
001 
GGG 
GTG 
83 18 966 
0.44 
16 
001 
GGG 
TGG 
15 18 966 
0.08 
33 
001 
GGG 
GGG 
18 693 18 966 
98.6 
37 
002 
CGT 
CAG 
461 19 217 
2.4 
30 
002 
CGT 
GGG 
20 19 217 
0.1 
5 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. HCV plasmids results for 181 codon positions sequenced with average depth of 87 000</figDesc><table>Mix 
QIT 
N 
Variants 
FDR (%) 
Freq Codon 36 (%) 
Freq Codon 155 (%) 

No filtering 
Q-cpileup 
No filtering 
Q-cpileup 
No filtering 
Q-cpileup 
No filtering 
Q-cpileup 

1:10 
20 
22 405 
10 583 
12 
0 
10.4 
11.6 
10.3 
11.6 
1:50 
20 
12 724 
10 488 
7 
0 
2.28 
2.37 
2.25 
2.37 
1:100 
19 
14 886 
10 631 
6 
0 
0.97 
1.00 
0.91 
0.95 
1:200 
19 
15 692 
10 813 
8 
0 
0.50 
0.49 
0.43 
0.45 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 3. Notes: The bottom rows of the table report the number of codons detected in the NS3 region which in theory should be 548 (543 WT + 5 SNPs). The number of false discoveries with frequencies above 1% is expressed using the false discovery rate calculated as the number of false discoveries with frequencies above 1% divided by the total number of discoveries with frequency above 1%.</figDesc><table>Frequency estimates of the five SNPs present in the mixture of 
plasmids with mixing proportions 1:200, 1:100 and 1:50 

SNP (WT) LoFreq 
V-Phaser 2 
ShoRAH 

1:200 1:100 1:50 1:200 1:100 1:50 1:200 1:100 1:50 

36 
A (G) 
/ 
1.03 2.41 0.59 1.06 2.37 / 
/ 
2.22 
T (T) 
G (C) 
0.54 1.01 2.38 / 
0.94 2.33 / 
/ 
2.22 
155 
A (C) 
0.66 1.03 2.16 / 
/ 
/ 
0.44 a 0.80 a 1.78 a 
A (G) 
0.48 0.91 2.10 0.52 1.04 2.11 0.44 a 0.80 a 1.78 a 
A( G ) 
/ 
0 . 8 9 2 . 0 5 0 . 4 8 / 
2 . 0 7 / 
/ 
1 . 2 8 
FDR (%) 
0.18 0.18 0.18 0 
0.18 0 
0 
0 
0 
N 
Variants 549 553 550 565 578 571 549 546 549 

a 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">VirVarSeq at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">B.M.P.Verbist et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors wish to thank the scientists at Janssen Pharmaceutica who collected and produced the data as well as Tobias Verbeke and Joris Meys who gave the necessary IT support. Herwig Van Marck is kindly acknowledged for the insightful discussions. The authors are grateful to Prof McLachlan and his team for providing the original Fortran code and for giving support to write the R-wrapper. Thanks to Osvaldo, developer of ShoRAH, who was always very helpful when problems were encountered while running ShoRAH.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Challenges and opportunities in estimating viral genetic diversity from next-generation sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Beerenwinkel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">329</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ultra-deep sequencing for the analysis of viral populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Beerenwinkel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Zagordi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Virol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="413" to="418" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Added value of deep sequencing relative to population sequencing in heavily pre-treated HIV-1-infected subjects</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Codoner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19461</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved base-calling and quality scores for 454 sequencing based on a Hurdle Poisson model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">De</forename>
				<surname>Beuf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">303</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deep sequencing of the HCV NS3/4A region confirms low prevalence of telaprevir-resistant variants both at baseline and end of study</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Dierynck</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Infect. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">210</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1871" to="1880" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Substantial biases in ultra-short read data sets from high-throughput DNA sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Dohm</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viral quasispecies evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Domingo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Base-calling of automated sequencer traces using phred. II. Error probabilities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Ewing</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Green</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="194" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minority variants of drug-resistant HIV</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Gianella</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Infect. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">202</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="657" to="666" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole genome deep sequencing of HIV-1 reveals the impact of early minor variants upon immune recognition during acute infection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Henn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS Pathog</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002529</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast and accurate short read alignment with BurrowsWheeler transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Durbin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1754" to="1760" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Highly sensitive and specific detection of rare variants in mixed viral populations from massively parallel sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Macalalad</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002417</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fitting mixture models to grouped and truncated data via the EM algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Mclachlan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="571" to="578" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of genomic high-throughput sequencing data generated on illumina HiSeq and genome analyzer systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Minoche</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genotype and SNP calling from next-generation sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Nielsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable HIV-1 integrase diversity during initial HIV-1 RNA decay suggests complete blockade of plasma HIV-1 replication by effective raltegravir-containing salvage therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Noguera-Julian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Virol. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">350</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide patterns of intrahuman dengue virus diversity reveal associations with Viral Phylogenetic Clade and Interhost Diversity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Parameswaran</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Virol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2152" to="2157" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Pt. 10</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empirical validation of viral quasispecies assembly algorithms: state-of-the-art and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C F</forename>
				<surname>Prosperi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2837</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimized filtering reduces the error rate in detecting genomic variants by short-read sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Reumers</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antiviral therapy of hepatitis C in 2014: Do we need resistance testing?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Schneider</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Antiviral Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Benchmarking of viral haplotype reconstruction programmes: an overview of the capacities and limitations of currently available programmes Brief</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Shirmer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating the use of the Illumina deep sequencing platform for the detection of minority variants in HIV and HCV</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Thys</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Virol. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Manuscript. under review</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevalence and evolution of low frequency HIV drug resistance mutations detected by ultra deep sequencing in patients experiencing first line antiretroviral therapy failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Vandenhende</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LoFreq: a sequence-quality aware, ultra-sensitive variant caller for uncovering cell-population heterogeneity from high-throughput sequencing datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Wilm</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11189" to="11201" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ShoRAH: estimating the genetic diversity of a mixed sample from next-generation sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Zagordi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>