
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">WATCLUST: a tool for improving the design of drugs based on protein-water interactions</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Elias</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Ló Pez</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departamento de Química Bioló gica</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Buenos Aires</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ciudad Universitaria, Pabelló n II, Ciudad de Buenos Aires</addrLine>
									<postCode>C1428EHA</postCode>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Juan</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Pablo</forename>
								<surname>Arcon</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departamento de Química Bioló gica</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Buenos Aires</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ciudad Universitaria, Pabelló n II, Ciudad de Buenos Aires</addrLine>
									<postCode>C1428EHA</postCode>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">INQUIMAE-CONICET</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ciudad Universitaria, Pabelló n II, Ciudad de Buenos Aires</addrLine>
									<postCode>C1428EHA</postCode>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Diego</forename>
								<forename type="middle">F</forename>
								<surname>Gauto</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">INQUIMAE-CONICET</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ciudad Universitaria, Pabelló n II, Ciudad de Buenos Aires</addrLine>
									<postCode>C1428EHA</postCode>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ariel</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Petruk</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">INQUIMAE-CONICET</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ciudad Universitaria, Pabelló n II, Ciudad de Buenos Aires</addrLine>
									<postCode>C1428EHA</postCode>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Carlos</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Modenutti</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departamento de Química Bioló gica</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Buenos Aires</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ciudad Universitaria, Pabelló n II, Ciudad de Buenos Aires</addrLine>
									<postCode>C1428EHA</postCode>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Victoria</forename>
								<forename type="middle">G</forename>
								<surname>Dumas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departamento de Química Bioló gica</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Buenos Aires</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ciudad Universitaria, Pabelló n II, Ciudad de Buenos Aires</addrLine>
									<postCode>C1428EHA</postCode>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Marcelo</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Marti</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departamento de Química Bioló gica</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Buenos Aires</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ciudad Universitaria, Pabelló n II, Ciudad de Buenos Aires</addrLine>
									<postCode>C1428EHA</postCode>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">INQUIMAE-CONICET</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ciudad Universitaria, Pabelló n II, Ciudad de Buenos Aires</addrLine>
									<postCode>C1428EHA</postCode>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Adrian</forename>
								<forename type="middle">G</forename>
								<surname>Turjanski</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departamento de Química Bioló gica</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Buenos Aires</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ciudad Universitaria, Pabelló n II, Ciudad de Buenos Aires</addrLine>
									<postCode>C1428EHA</postCode>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">INQUIMAE-CONICET</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ciudad Universitaria, Pabelló n II, Ciudad de Buenos Aires</addrLine>
									<postCode>C1428EHA</postCode>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">WATCLUST: a tool for improving the design of drugs based on protein-water interactions</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv411</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 31, 2015; revised on June 5, 2015; accepted on June 27, 2015</note>
					<note>Structural bioinformatics * To whom correspondence should be addressed † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Water molecules are key players for protein folding and function. On the protein surface , water is not placed randomly, but display instead a particular structure evidenced by the presence of specific water sites (WS). These WS can be derived and characterized using explicit water Molecular Dynamics simulations, providing useful information for ligand binding prediction and design. Here we present WATCLUST, a WS determination and analysis tool running on the VMD platform. The tool also allows direct transfer of the WS information to Autodock program to perform biased docking. Availability and implementation: The WATCLUST plugin and documentation are freely available at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Water molecules play an essential role in the structure/function of proteins, participating in enzymatic reaction mechanisms, ligand binding and release and proton/electron transfer processes, among others. Importantly, due to the shape and electrostatic potential of the protein surface, water molecules are not placed randomly and display instead a particular structure that can be characterized by the presence of hydration or water sites (WS). These sites are defined as confined space regions, adjacent to the protein surface, where the probability of finding a water molecule is higher than in the bulk solvent. They can be determined from explicit water Molecular Dynamics (MD) simulations (<ref type="bibr">Abel et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">De Beer et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Di Lella et al., 2007</ref>). Moreover, using the theoretical basis of the Inhomogeneous Fluid Solvation Theory (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Li and Lazaridis, 2012</ref>), WS can also be structurally and thermodynamically characterized. Once identified, they constitute a precious knowledge that can be used in several applications, such as analysis of protein-ligand and protein-protein complexes (<ref type="bibr">Abel et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Di Lella et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Forli and Olson, 2012</ref>), determination of hydration free energies of simple solutes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Huggins and Payne, 2013</ref>), small ligands uptake by heme proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bustamante et al., 2014</ref>) and, as shown by us and others, significant improvement of molecular docking results, both in terms of accuracy and selectivity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gauto et al., 2013</ref>). To date, there are few methods for WS detection and characterization. WaterMap (<ref type="bibr">Abel et al., 2008</ref>) is a grid based method part of the Schrodinger package which is not freely available. WATsite (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hu and Lill, 2014</ref>) is restricted to perform MD simulations only with GROMACS. Finally, there are other programs that do not require MD simulations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Guarnieri and Mezei, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Sanschagrin and Kuhn, 1998</ref>) or use alternative thermodynamic calculation methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Li and Lazaridis, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Nguyen et al., 2014</ref>). It should be noted that none of them allow to use the WS information directly in docking calculations. Extended application of MD simulations to understand protein function boosted the use of the open source graphical<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Morris et al., 2009</ref>), one of the most widely used open source docking programs, in order to perform WS biased docking (WSBD) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gauto et al., 2013</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>The method requires as input a set of snapshots derived from an explicit water MD trajectory. The strategy used to determine the WS is adapted from our previous works (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Di Lella et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Gauto et al., 2009</ref>). For each obtained WS the program computes the following parameters: (i) water finding probability (WFP), (ii) R 90 , (iii) WSprotein mean interaction energy (&lt; E wp &gt;), (iv) WS-water mean interaction energy (&lt; E ww &gt;), (v) mean total interaction energy with respect to bulk (DE int ) and finally, (vi) excess rotational (Sr) and translational (St) entropies. The resulting WS (or a selection of them) can then be used to define an Autodock grid map to perform a WSBD. See SI for details on WS determination, properties and WSBD. The usage and output will be only briefly described here. For further details and information on how to install the app see the tutorials and/or user guide available at the previously cited web page.</p><p>Step 1. Load Trajectory. The first step required by WATCLUST is to load in the VMD program an explicit water MD simulation set of snapshots. Previous works from our group show that 10–20 ns long MD simulations with c.a. 1000 snapshots are enough to provide converged results. Step 2. Determine WS. Once the trajectory is loaded, the WATCLUST plugin can be accessed in 'Extensions &gt; Analysis &gt; WATCLUST'. The plugin allows to select the parameters that define how and where the WS are to be determined. Briefly, a subgroup of residues can be selected to define the region where the WS will be computed, while a reference structure-frame (or a group of residues) for the alignment of all the trajectory snapshots is required. Proper alignment is important to obtain accurate results and several residue selections, e.g. only those in the binding site, should be tested. It is important to avoid the inclusion of residues with high mobility. Step 3. Analyze WS. WS can be characterized directly in VMD, colored according to WFP or R 90 and analyzed using all the capabilities of the VMD program. All the previously mentioned structural and thermodynamic parameters are reported in log files for each WS.</p><p>Step 4. Transfer WS data to Autodock. Once WS have been determined, they can be used to build modified Autodock grid maps to perform WSBD. To obtain the biased map, a conventional oxygen grid map should be loaded into VMD. After selection of the desired WS, the modified grid should be saved and used for docking calculations in the usual way.</p><p>As an example (see tutorials), in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1A</ref>we present WS found in the active site of AmpC beta-lactamase. The WS are shown superimposed to the structure of the HTC-AmpC complex. It is clearly seen how the best WS (i.e. with high WFP and low R 90 ) match the ligand oxygen groups interacting with the protein. Moreover, the comparative docking results between WSBD and the non-biased case (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1B</ref>) underscore the WSBD improved performance yielding a clear outlier (with significant higher cluster population and the best binding energy) in the population vs. DG plot, that nicely overlays (RMSD 1.72 A ˚ ) with the reference ligand.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1C</ref>shows the poses of the outlier results compared to the reference ligand for both docking methods. A final remark should be made concerning the use of WS as potential replacement sites in docking calculations. In some cases, water molecules strongly interacting with the protein are not replaced by the ligand, but instead act as bridges between the ligand and receptor, (Garcia<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Sosa and Mancera, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Garcia-Sosa, 2013</ref>) thus careful analysis of WS should be performed and their inclusion as part of the receptor must be evaluated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Conclusion</head><p>We present an application that works as a plugin under the widely used VMD program. Based on an explicit water MD simulation trajectory, it allows the characterization of the solvent structure through the identification and analysis of WS. The program features are a flexible definition of the WS finding algorithm, determination of each WS structural and thermodynamical parameters and visualization of results on VMD with all its functionality. The method is thus ideally suited for studies of the solvent structure on protein surfaces and cavities with a wide range of applications, such as (i) determination of WS in protein-ligand binding sites and (ii) proteinprotein interaction surfaces that evidence hydrophilic hot-spots, (iii) determination of water structure in water/ion channels and (iv) characterization of catalytic waters, among others. It also allows to build modified Autodock grid maps to perform WS biased docking calculations, which we have shown to give significantly better results when compared to conventional docking, especially for ligands having hydrophilic moieties (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gauto et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Modenutti et al., 2015</ref>). The only drawback is that the method relies on the presence of specific protein-water interactions, so it should not be used on large highly hydrophobic surfaces or regions with too high mobility.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by Agencia Nacional de Promoció n Científica y Tecnoló gica<ref type="bibr">[PICTO 2010</ref><ref type="bibr">2805</ref><ref type="bibr">, PICTOGSK 2012</ref>. Conflict of Interest: none declared.<ref type="bibr">Abel,R. et al. (2008)</ref>Role of the active-site solvent in the thermodynamics of factor Xa ligand binding. J. Am. Chem. Soc., 130, 2817–2831.Structure of the reference complex (PDB: 1XGJ) superimposed to the WS positions (red spheres). (B) Population vs. binding free energy plot obtained with conventional docking (black triangles) and WSBD (green squares). Values next to the dots represent the ligand RMSD between the predicted complex structure and the reference. (C) Structures for the predicted HTC orientation (ball and stick) compared to the reference ligand pose (cylinder)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>References</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Results for the redocking of HTC to E. coli AmpC beta-lactamase. (A) Structure of the reference complex (PDB: 1XGJ) superimposed to the WS positions (red spheres). (B) Population vs. binding free energy plot obtained with conventional docking (black triangles) and WSBD (green squares). Values next to the dots represent the ligand RMSD between the predicted complex structure and the reference. (C) Structures for the predicted HTC orientation (ball and stick) compared to the reference ligand pose (cylinder)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 3697 Bioinformatics, 31(22), 2015, 3697–3699 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv411 Advance Access Publication Date: 20 July 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table>and analysis interface known as Visual Molecular Dynamics (VMD, 
Humphrey et al., 1996) with more than 11 000 cites to date. 
However, VMD lacks a WS determination/analysis tool. 
WATCLUST fills this gap presenting an intuitive and user friendly 
tool to determine WS and their properties, available to all people in 
the structural bioinformatics field. Moreover, WATCLUST allows 
direct transfer of WS information to Autodock (</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ligand uptake modulation by internal water molecules and hydrophobic cavities in hemoglobins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Bustamante</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1234" to="1245" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of water molecules in computational drug design</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">De</forename>
				<surname>Beer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B A</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Top. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="66" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterization of the galectin-1 carbohydrate recognition domain in terms of solvent occupancy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Di</forename>
				<surname>Lella</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7360" to="7366" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A force field with discrete displaceable waters and desolvation entropy for hydrated ligand docking</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Forli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Olson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="623" to="638" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydration properties of ligands and drugs in protein binding sites: tightly-bound, bridging water molecules and their effects and consequences on molecular design strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Garcia-Sosa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1388" to="1405" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Free energy calculations of mutations involving a tightly bound water molecule and ligand substitutions in a ligand-protein complex</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Garcia-Sosa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Mancera</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Inf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="589" to="600" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Carbohydrate-binding proteins: dissecting ligand structures through solvent environment occupancy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Gauto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8717" to="8724" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solvent structure improves docking prediction in lectincarbohydrate complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Gauto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Glycobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simulated annealing of chemical potential: a general procedure for locating bound waters. Application to the study of the differential hydration propensities of the major and minor grooves of DNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Guarnieri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Mezei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8493" to="8494" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WATsite: hydration site prediction program with PyMOL interface</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Hu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Lill</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1255" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing the accuracy of inhomogeneous fluid solvation theory in predicting hydration free energies of simple solutes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Huggins</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Payne</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8232" to="8244" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">VMD—Visual Molecular Dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Humphrey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computing the thermodynamic contributions of interfacial water</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Lazaridis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<editor>Baron,R.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">819</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="393" to="404" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using crystallographic water properties for the analysis and prediction of lectin-carbohydrate complex structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Modenutti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Glycobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="196" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AutoDock4 and AutoDockTools4: Automated docking with selective receptor flexibility</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Morris</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2785" to="2791" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermodynamics of water in an enzyme active site: Grid-based hydration analysis of coagulation factor Xa</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Nguyen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Theory Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2769" to="2780" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cluster analysis of consensus water sites in thrombin and trypsin shows conservation between serine proteases and contributions to ligand specificity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Sanschagrin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Kuhn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2054" to="2064" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Ló Pez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>