
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:54+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Boolean network model of the FA/BRCA pathway</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfredo</forename>
								<surname>Rodríguez</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Investigación en Genética Humana</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratorio de Citogenética</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Instituto Nacional de Pediatría</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Posgrado en Ciencias Biológicas</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<surname>Sosa</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Investigación en Genética Humana</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratorio de Citogenética</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Instituto Nacional de Pediatría</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Leda</forename>
								<surname>Torres</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Investigación en Genética Humana</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratorio de Citogenética</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Instituto Nacional de Pediatría</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bertha</forename>
								<surname>Molina</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Investigación en Genética Humana</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratorio de Citogenética</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Instituto Nacional de Pediatría</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sara</forename>
								<surname>Frías</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Investigación en Genética Humana</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratorio de Citogenética</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Instituto Nacional de Pediatría</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Medicina Genómica</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Luis</forename>
								<surname>Mendoza</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>lmendoza@biomedicas.unam.mx</email>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Biología Molecular y Biotecnología</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Instituto de Investigaciones Biomédicas</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="MX">México</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Toxicología Ambiental and Instituto de Investigaciones Biomédicas</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Boolean network model of the FA/BRCA pathway</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="858" to="866"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts036</idno>
					<note type="submission">Systems biology Advance Access publication January 20, 2012 Received on September 1, 2011; revised on January 13, 2012; accepted on January 16, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: ES MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [14:53 13/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts036.tex] Page: 858 858–866 Associate Editor: Martin Bishop Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Fanconi anemia (FA) is a chromosomal instability syndrome originated by inherited mutations that impair the Fanconi Anemia/Breast Cancer (FA/BRCA) pathway, which is committed to the repair of DNA interstrand cross-links (ICLs). The disease displays increased spontaneous chromosomal aberrations and hypersensitivity to agents that create DNA interstrand cross-links. In spite of DNA damage, FA/BRCA-deficient cells are able to progress throughout the cell cycle, probably due to the activity of alternative DNA repair pathways, or due to defects in the checkpoints that monitor DNA integrity. Results: We propose a Boolean network model of the FA/BRCA pathway, Checkpoint proteins and some alternative DNA repair pathways. To our knowledge, this is the largest network model incorporating a DNA repair pathway. Our model is able to simulate the ICL repair process mediated by the FA/BRCA pathway, the activation of Checkpoint proteins observed by recurrent DNA damage, as well as the repair of DNA double-strand breaks and DNA adducts. We generated a series of simulations for mutants, some of which have never been reported and thus constitute predictions about the function of the FA/BRCA pathway. Finally, our model suggests alternative DNA repair pathways that become active whenever the FA/BRCA pathway is defective.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Fanconi anemia (FA) is a chromosomal instability syndrome characterized by bone marrow failure, congenital abnormalities and an increased risk to develop cancer (D'<ref type="bibr">Andrea, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">de Winter and Joenje, 2009</ref>). Cells of patients with FA display increased chromosomal aberrations, and are hypersensitive to agents that create DNA interstrand cross-links (ICLs) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Auerbach, 2009</ref>). The reported prevalence of FA ranges from 1 to 5 cases per one million persons, while the heterozygous carrier frequency is about one case per 300 persons (although the true frequency is probably higher), with a median age at diagnosis of 6.5–8 years (D'<ref type="bibr">Andrea, 2010</ref>). FA * To whom correspondence should be addressed. represents a suitable model to study human DNA repair mechanisms and it is gaining relevance because heterozygous carriers have a high risk of developing malignancies such as breast cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Neveling et al., 2009</ref>). FA is a genetically heterogeneous disease, caused by mutations in at least one of the 15 distinct genes, namely: FANCA, FANCB, FANCC, FANCD1/BRCA2, FANCD2, FANCE, FANCF, FANCG, FANCI, FANCJ/BRIP1/BACH1, FANCL, FANCM, FANCN/PALB2, FANCO/RAD51C and FANCP/SLX4. These genes are involved in the so-called Fanconi Anemia/Breast Cancer (FA/BRCA) pathway, dedicated to the repair of DNA ICLs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">de Winter and Joenje, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kim et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Vaz, 2010</ref>). Currently, there is no consensus regarding the precise nature of the FA/BRCA pathway, or the network of interactions established with other genes/proteins involved in FA. We hereby propose the regulatory network established among 20 protein complexes that include the aforementioned proteins of the FA/BRCA pathway. Moreover, this network includes nodes to describe the three types of DNA damage commonly observed in FA. We thereafter implement the FA/BRCA network as a discrete dynamical system and study its behavior. The modeling of regulatory networks of biological interest as discrete dynamical systems is a well-established methodology. Boolean networks, the simplest form of discrete dynamical systems, have been used to model a wide variety of processes such as the genetic control of floral morphogenesis in Arabidopsis thaliana (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Mendoza et al., 1999</ref>), the differentiation process of T-helper lymphocytes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Mendoza, 2006</ref>), the control of the mammalian cell cycle (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Fauré et al., 2006</ref>) and the surviving process of malignant cells in large granular lymphocyte leukemia (<ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Zhang et al., 2009a</ref>), to name a few examples. This type of approach is widely used to study the dynamical behaviour of regulatory networks because of its straightforwardness, robustness and compatibility with published qualitative data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chaves et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Christensen et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Davidich and Bornholdt, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Mendoza and Pardo, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Wu et al., 2009</ref>). There are some mathematical models that describe DNA repair, see, for example, Crooke and Parl (2010). However, to our knowledge, the model presented here is the first dynamical system proposed specifically for the FA/BRCA DNA repair pathway. This model is able to reproduce the ICLs repair process mediated by the FA/BRCA pathway, and the repair of double-strand breaks (DSBs) and DNA adducts (ADDs). In order to obtain a dynamical behavior that reproduces the experimental data, we propose the</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FA/BRCA pathway</head><p>existence of some interactions not reported in the experimental literature, and therefore they constitute predictions of our model. Specifically, we include the generation of DSBs during ICLs repair by alternative DNA endonucleases, even in FA/BRCA mutants. Second, we propose a rule that enables MRN to act in the absence of FA/BRCA and NHEJ pathways during an ICL-generated DSB repair process. Third, we propose that USP1 is regulated by the activity of FANCM. And fourth, we propose that the Checkpoint Recovery process (CHKREC) negatively regulates 17 nodes of the FA/BRCA pathway.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Reconstruction of FA/BRCA network</head><p>The experimental literature on FA was thoroughly analyzed, so as to reconstruct the connectivity among key components of the FA/BRCA pathway. Briefly, a DNA ICL is able to arrest the DNA synthesis process; the FANCM/FAAP24 protein complex (FANCM) recognizes the damage and recruits the FA core (FAcore) complex (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Gari et al., 2008</ref>). Then, the FAcore complex monoubiquitinates the FANCD2I complex (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kim et al., 2011</ref>), which in turn recruits endonucleases such as FAN1 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">MacKay et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Smogorzewska et al., 2010</ref>), XPF/ERCC1 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bhagwat et al., 2009</ref>) and MUS81/EME1 (MUS81) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hanada et al., 2006</ref>) to generate a DSB and a DNA adduct. The FA/BRCA proteins funnel the DSB to be repaired by the homologous recombination repair (HRR) pathway mediated by Breast Cancer 1 (BRCA1) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bekker-Jensen et al., 2006</ref>), FANCN (<ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Xia et al., 2007</ref>), FANCD1 (San<ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Filippo et al., 2006</ref>), FANCJ (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Gong et al., 2010</ref>) and the RAD51 complex (<ref type="bibr" target="#b45">San Filippo et al., 2006</ref>). The blockage of the DNA replication by the presence of an ADD can be bypassed with the help of the proliferation cell nuclear antigen (PCNA) and translesion synthesis (TLS) polymerases and then repaired by the nucleotide excision repair (NER) proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chang and Cimprich, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Garg et al., 2005</ref>). As a final step, the ubiquitin-specific protease 1 (USP1) protein inactivates the FAcore complex and PCNA proteins by deubiquitination, turning the signaling process off (Huang and D'<ref type="bibr">Andrea, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Niimi et al., 2008</ref>). Finally, it is important to note that the FA/BRCA pathway establishes a cross talk with the ataxia telangiectasia and Rad3-related (ATR) Checkpoint protein and its effector kinase, Checkpoint kinase 1 (CHK1), which are required for the activation of the FA/BRCA pathway and cell cycle arrest. The reader may find a more detailed explanation of the whole process in Supplementary Material. Our proposed network for the FA/BRCA pathway, shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>, Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S1</ref>and Supplementary Material (FA_BRCA_ network.pdf), incorporates DNA damage recognition proteins, DNA damage Checkpoint proteins and DNA repair effector proteins. At least 51, proteins were found to be relevant for the reconstruction of the network; however, some of these proteins act as functional complexes, and therefore they were collapsed into single functional nodes to facilitate the dynamical analysis. Furthermore, three nodes representing different types of DNA damage were included into the model, namely ICL, DSB and ADD. As a result, the network is made up of 28 nodes and 122 regulatory interactions, 80 of them positive and 42 negative (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). The regulatory rules of this network is presented in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. A detailed description of the information used to reconstruct the connectivity and the logical rules of such network can be found as Supplementary Material. Not all interactions of the FA/BRCA network, as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>, have been reported in the experimental literature or appear in specialized databases. Indeed, while our regulatory network includes some of the elements of the FA/BRCA pathway as included in the KEGG database, our network incorporates more nodes, specifically ATM, CHK1 CHK2 and some pathways like the non-homologous end joining. Because of this characteristic, our network is unique in incorporating a cross talk with alternative DNA repair pathways. Of the 122 regulatory interactions present in our model, 16 were included so as to obtain a dynamical behavior that reproduce the experimental data. These proposed regulatory interactions are divided into four groups. First, we included a positive interaction of XPF over DSB to ensure the generation of DSBs during ICL repair by the activity of alternative DNA endonucleases even in FA/BRCA-deficient cells. Second, we incorporated negative regulations of MRN from FANCD2I, KU, RAD51 and CHKREC, so that during the ICL-generated DSB repair process the MRN exonuclease acts only in the absence of FA/BRCA and NHEJ pathways. Third, we propose that USP1 is under positive control from FANCD1N, and under negative control from FANCM, to indicate that the USP1 deubiquitinating enzyme is directly or indirectly regulated by the presence of FANCD1/BRCA2, FANCN and FANCM. And fourth, we propose that CHKREC negatively regulates 11 nodes (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>,<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. S2</ref>). The selection of these 16 unreported interactions was based exclusively in the recovery of the known attractors for the wild type and the mutants. This was the minimal set of new interactions that we found consistent with the experimental data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">The FA/BRCA network as a discrete dynamical system</head><p>We modeled the reconstructed FA/BRCA pathway as a Boolean network, where each node is described by a variable x that takes the value of 0 or 1 to represent its inactive or active state of activation, respectively. The activation state of the whole network is then represented by a vector with the set of Boolean variables x 1 ,x 2 ,...,x n , where x i is the state of activation of the i-th node. The state of activation of each node changes in discrete time steps according to x i (t +1) = F i (x 1 (t),x 2 (t),...,x n (t)), where x 1 (t),x 2 (t),...,x n (t) is the state of the regulators of node x i at time t, and F i is a Boolean function, also called a logical rule, determining the state of node x i at the next time step. The specific Boolean functions for each node are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. These equations describe a deterministic dynamical system, with a total of 2 28 = 268435456 possible activation states. We exhaustively tested the dynamical behavior of the FA/BRCA network by starting the simulations from all possible initial conditions with BoolNet (<ref type="bibr">Müssel et al., 2010</ref>) under synchronous updating, until the system reached a stationary pattern of activation, also referred to as an attractor. Finally, to simulate loss-and gain-of-function mutants, the corresponding variable was fixed to 0 or 1, respectively. The file containing the FA/BRCA network in the BoolNet format is available as the Supplementary Material (FA_for_BoolNet.txt). Given the large number of possible activation states of the FA/BRCA network, it is computationally unfeasible to fully analyze its dynamical behavior using an asynchronous updating. However, it is instructive to compare certain key results under both synchronous and asynchronous updating. Therefore, the attractors of the wild type, FAcore null mutant, and FANCD1N null mutant models, were obtained by using BoolNet with asynchronous updating starting from 10 000 random initial states.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>A great proportion of FA cells in culture die when exposed to ICL inducing agents, such as mitomycin C (MMC) or diepoxybutane (DEB), due to severe DNA repair deficiencies. However, some cells survive exhibiting unrepaired DSBs and cytogenetic evidence of erroneous DNA repair such as radial exchange figures and a normal rate of sister chromatid exchanges (SCEs) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Latt et al., 1975</ref>). Our aim was to understand the mechanism by which FA cells use alternative DNA repair pathways when exposed to ICL-inducing agents. To accomplish this, we developed a Boolean network model of the FA/BRCA pathway, which incorporates the known interactions of FA proteins with other pathways that participate in the preservation of genome stability. The network has three nodes that can be used as input, so as to model different types of DNA damage signals thatactivate the DNA repair process, namely ICL, DSB and ADD. The reason to include these nodes in the network is that FA cells are highly sensitive to ICLs (D'<ref type="bibr">Andrea, 2010</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">The FA/BRCA network</head><p>The reconstructed FA/BRCA regulatory network (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>) and its associated logical functions (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>) integrate the vast majority of experimental knowledge about the FA/BRCA pathway and its interactions with other genes/proteins involved in FA. The resulting discrete dynamical system was exhaustively analyzed so as to obtain the attractors of the system, particularly when starting in the presence of the three types of DNA damage: ICLs, DSBs and ADDs, under wild type and mutant conditions. With the inclusion of some inferred, but not yet reported, interactions the model recovers the main known features of the wild type FA/BRCA pathway. Since, to our knowledge, there are no published reports about these interactions, they constitute veritable predictions of our model that require additional research in order to be validated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1">The generation of DSBs during ICL repair is assured by the activity of FA/BRCA pathway endonucleases</head><p>It has been reported that primary FA-C cells are not defective in the generation of DSBs during the initial steps of ICL repair (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Rothfuss and Grompe, 2004</ref>). Since the generation of DSBs during the processing of ICLs is not absolutely abolished in FA, then there must exist alternative endonucleases that become active even when the FA/BRCA pathway<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>is defective. A likely candidate is XPF/ERCC1 with 5 endonuclease activity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Kuraoka et al.,, 2000</ref>), which has a similar function to FAN1 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">MacKay et al., 2010</ref>). We hereby propose that the activity of this alternative endonuclease is promoted by MUS81 proteins, very probably in concert with the newly described SLX4 (FANCP) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Crossan et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kim et al., 2011</ref>). Alternatively, XPF/ERCC1 might be activated by a p53-dependent pathway. Under wild-type conditions, the activity of this alternative endonuclease must be inhibited in order to avoid a possible interference with the FA/BRCA pathway. In our model, this inhibition was accomplished by the activation of the FANCM or FANCD2I complexes in association with FAN1 (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. S3</ref>). This is an issue that deserves additional research because it does not exist information about any direct or indirect active inhibition of any endonuclease by the FA/BRCA proteins. Very likely, these alternative endonucleases are present as a secondary pathway whose effect becomes evident whenever the FA/BRCA pathway is defective.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">During the repair of an ICL-intermediate DSB the MRN exonuclease activity acts in the absence of FA/BRCA and NHEJ pathways</head><p>When a DSB is generated, proteins of different DNA repair pathways such as HRR and NHEJ surround the region of DNA damage. The co-localization of these proteins is considered as evidence of interaction between both DNA repair pathways (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bekker-Jensen et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kass and Jasin, 2010</ref>). Now, the MRN complex, a heterotrimeric complex with exonuclease activity, is able to process DSBs generating DNA overhangs that are funneled to the HRR process. In normal cells, the presence of the MRN complex is considered as essential for FANCD2 stability (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Roques et al., 2009</ref>); moreover, recent studies have suggested that FANCD2 also possesses exonuclease activity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Pace et al., 2010</ref>). Therefore, the exonuclease activity of the MRN complex may not be necessary when the FA/BRCA pathway functions properly. The same group also found that the KU70, a NHEJ protein, corrupts the DNA repair process and changes the DNA repair choice to the errorprone NHEJ pathway in FA cells. They also observed that the FANCA/KU70 double mutant is able to repair the DNA damage by the HRR pathway. Moreover, a series of reports have shown that cells deficient in the FA/BRCA pathway generate sister chromatid exchanges (SCEs) when treated with MMC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Latt et al., 1975;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Wilson et al., 2001</ref>). Now, as SCEs are considered a result of HRR with crossing-over, this could mean that FA cells are still able to perform HRR by a FA/BRCA-independent pathway. Interestingly, downstream FA/BRCA pathway mutant cells, such as RAD51 and FANCD1/BRCA2, are not able to generate SCEs when exposed to ICL-inducing agents (<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Sonoda et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Takata et al., 2001</ref>). Taking all the previous information into account, we believe that the MRN complex is a likely candidate to direct the HRR process in the absence of FA/BRCA and NHEJ proteins. According to this, the first mechanism to repair an ICL-intermediate DSB would be the HRR mediated by FA/BRCA and then the NHEJ proteins. If both these pathways are defective, the candidate to initiate an alternative</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.Rodríguez et al.</head><p>HRR and generate SCE would be the MRN complex. Our model proposes that KU70 in conjunction with the FANCD2I complex act inhibiting MRN (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. S4</ref>). Then, when the inhibitors are absent, the activation of ATM and the presence of a DSB is enough to activate MRN. This might explain why the DNA repair is improved in FANCA/KU70 double mutants (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Pace et al., 2010</ref>). Alternatively, a point of inhibition over MRN could be the activation of RAD51 and CHKREC, which would turn the activity of the MRN complex off. The USP1 deubiquitinating enzyme is directly or indirectly regulated by the presence of FANCM To date, it is known that the USP1 deubiquitinating protein is able to inactivate the FANCD2I complex (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Cohn et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Nijman et al., 2005</ref>) and TLS proteins (Huang and D'<ref type="bibr">Andrea, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Niimi et al., 2008</ref>), although it is not yet clear which is the mechanism that activates USP1 itself. In our model, the activation of USP1 cannot occur unless both the FANCD2I and FANCD1N complexes or TLS are active (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Fig. S5</ref>). Also, the activation of USP1 is restricted since it does not occur unless FANCM is turned off. This behavior ensures that the activity of the FA/BRCA pathway continues until the ICL has been processed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.3">The Checkpoint recovery process is critical for the FA/BRCA pathway regulation</head><p>We found that negative feedback mediated by the CHKREC is indispensable to obtain the experimentally observed behavior of the FA/BRCA network. In our model, we propose that CHKREC is able to inactivate 10 nodes; namely, MRN, BRCA, FANCD1N, RAD51, HRR, DNAPK, NHEJ, ATR, p53 and CHKREC itself. These 10 out of 17 regulatory interactions of CHKREC are not reported in the experimental literature, they are predictions of our model. It is important to mention that the CHKREC process includes several proteins able to inactivate key DNA repair and Checkpoint proteins allowing the progression of the cell cycle (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bartek and Lukas, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Carlessi et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Douglas et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fiscella et al., 1997</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Dynamics of the FA/BRCA boolean model</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Dynamics of the model in the absence of damage</head><p>The FA/BRCA network model has only one attractor, regardless of the initial state of the network, that we refer to as the cell cycle progression (CCP) attractor, characterized by a periodic oscillation between two network states (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 2</ref>, specifically the last two time periods in Panels A–C). This attractor is reached in an average of ∼10 time steps from its initial state (see the distribution of values in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6</ref>). Once in the CCP attractor all nodes are inactive, except for CHKREC that oscillates between the on and off states. This period-2 attractor can be interpreted biologically as the periodical transition in the cell cycle that starts with the activation of proteins that release the G 2 /M Checkpoint, which verifies the DNA integrity and allow the progression of the cell cycle. Once a new cell cycle starts, the CHKREC proteins turn off, only to be active again when the cell reaches the G 2 phase of a new cell cycle. Hence, the proteins involved in this cyclic behavior might include Cyclindependent kinases (Cdks), which have an active/inactive transitional behavior controlling the progression through the eukaryotic cell cycle (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bloom and Cross, 2007</ref>). Importantly, this period-2 attractor is also obtained if the network is studied with an asynchronous updating.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Dynamics of the model during DSB, ADD and ICL repair</head><p>The FA/BRCA network recovers the known order of activations leading to the repair of DSBs, ADDs and ICLs. Specifically, when a DSB is introduced in the model (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 2A</ref>), the network is able to repair it via the MRN-mediated HRR pathway (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kass and Jasin, 2010</ref>). Also, the simulation of an ADD (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 2B</ref>) causes the activation of the PCNATLS pathway (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chang and Cimprich, 2009</ref>), which repairs the ADD by the mediation of NER. Finally, the FA/BRCA network is able to describe the elimination of an ICL (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 2C</ref>) by way of the generation of DSB and ADD intermediates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">de Winter and Joenje, 2009</ref>). Moreover, the dynamics shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 2C</ref>also includes the recently described inhibition of FA proteins over NHEJ proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bunting et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Pace et al., 2010</ref>), as well as the activation of the Checkpoint proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bartek and Lukas, 2007</ref>). The cross talk among pathways generate negative feedback loops that create an homeostatic process in the recovering of the system after the DNA damage. In our model, the negative feedback mediated by CHKREC involves NHEJ, MRN, BRCA1, FANCD1N, RAD51, HRR, DNAPK, ATR, p53 and CHKREC itself. Once DNA damages have been eliminated, the network returns to its normal behavior, as represented by the CCP attractor. However, if by any reason the damage is constantly generated, for example by the persistentpresence of MMC or DEB, the network reaches attractors different from the CCP (see further).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.3">Dynamics of mutants of the FA/BRCA network</head><p>We used the FA/BRCA to study the effects of turning some nodes on or off permanently, thus simulating diverse physiological and mutant conditions. First, we simulated the permanent presence of DNA damage by leaving the ICL node always on. Such a constitutive activation pretends to represent the effect observed when there is a persistent presence of chemicals such as MMC or DEB.Biologically, this pattern might represent that the cell is performing a DNA repair process without progressing on the cell cycle. Because of this characteristic, we refer to this attractor as the cell cycle arrest (CCA) attractor. If the source of DNA damage is eliminated, i.e. the ICL node is permitted to become inactive, the cell cycle progresses as evidenced by the network reaching the CCP attractor (data not shown). Following the simulation of the repair of ICLs, DSBs and ADDs, we tested all possible single gain-and loss-of-function mutants and their dynamical behavior (Supplementary Material). Regarding null mutants on the FA/BRCA pathway, our model adequately describes the reported cellular phenotypes including the persistence of unrepaired DSBs, the activation of the NHEJ pathway, the activation of RAD51 in upstream mutants, the inability to activate RAD51 in downstream mutants and the correct activation of Checkpoint proteins that leads to an arrest in CCP. This last point is of relevance, since it argues in favor of a well-conserved G 2 /M Checkpoint function of FA/BRCA pathway in mutant cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Neveling et al., 2009</ref>). Interestingly, with the exception of the CHKREC null mutant, every null mutant recovers the CCP attractor, although some mutants also have additional attractors with larger basins (Supplementary Material). Most FA patients carry an alteration in the FANCA gene (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Auerbach, 2009</ref>), hence we hereby show the corresponding simulation, which is the constitutive null mutant of FAcore (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 4</ref>). The model of the mutant is able to repair the damage simulated by an ICL pulse, thus reaching the CCP attractor (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 4A</ref>, time steps 14–15). Noteworthy, the same attractor is recovered by using an asynchronous updating scheme. In this condition, our model A Bshows that the NHEJ pathway repaired the DSB generated as an intermediary. Furthermore, when a constant ICL damage was simulated in the FAcore null mutant, the model reaches a period-10 attractor (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 4B</ref>, time steps 23–32) somewhat similar to the CCA attractor (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 3</ref>). Interestingly, the model shows a difference in the mechanism of repair, depending on the persistence of the damage. With a single ICL pulse, the NHEJ pathway is the main route to repair the damage, whereas with a constant ICL stimulus there is a combined effort among the NHEJ and HRR paths. This is in marked contrast to the wild-type network, where the HRR—by mediation of the FA/BRCA proteins—is always the first option of repair. With an intact FA/BRCA pathway, the FAcore collaborates in the activation of the FAN1 endonuclease to generate the necessary DSBs to repair an ICL (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">MacKay et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Smogorzewska et al., 2010</ref>) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 2C</ref>). However, in FANCA patients the activity of FAcore does not exist, it is therefore instructive to analyze which DNA endonucleases are responsible for the generation of DSBs in this case. According to our model, in the absence of FAcore, the effect could be achieved by the activation of the FANCM protein and the MUS81 and XPF endonucleases (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 4</ref>), with the subsequent activation of FANCJBRCA1 and Checkpoint proteins, such as ATR and ATM kinases. At this point, an ADD and a DSB are generated, a normal TLS/NER process (part of the PCNATLS node) repairs the ADD, and then the NHEJ pathway or the MRN-mediated HRR could repair the DSB. Recent data have shown that a completely functional FA/BRCA pathway will block the NHEJ pathway (Pace<ref type="bibr">et al. et al., 2010</ref>); therefore in FAcore mutants, the KU proteins have the possibility to occupy the DSB and direct the DNA lesion to the NHEJ pathway. Additionally, this mechanism could explain the radial exchange figures seen in FA cell metaphases. The period-10 attractor observed due to a persistent ICL in FAcore null mutant includes the activation of the HRR pathway, mediated by MRN, BRCA1, ssDNARPA and RAD51 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 4B</ref>). This behaviour could explain the sister chromatid exchanges observed in upstream FA cells, as these SCEs are considered a result of HRR with crossingover (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Hirano et al., 2005</ref>). This, in turn, could mean that FA cells are still able to perform HRR by a FA/BRCA-independent pathway. Our model points to MRN as a candidate to direct the HRR process in the absence of some FA proteins. The simulation in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 4B</ref>shows that in FAcore null mutant is possible to observe that the activation of the Checkpoint proteins, namely ATR, ATM, CHK1, CHK2 and p53, is not impaired. This implies that the Checkpoint protein activation in the presence of DNA damage should be normal in FA cells, in concordance with experimental data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Heinrich et al., 1998</ref>). However, the simulation shows that the Checkpoint module turns off even when the DNA damage nodes are still active, which may explain the presence of unrepaired ICLs, DSBs and ADDs. We turn now our attention to a different mutant. It has been demonstrated the involvement of FANCD1/BRCA2 and FANCN/PALB2 in the development of breast cancer. These are molecules that act downstream of the FA/BRCA pathway in the DSB repair mediated by HRR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Xia et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Zhang et al., 2009b</ref>). Patients carrying FA/BRCA downstream null mutations, such as FANCD1/BRCA2 or FANCN/PALB2, are relatively rare and develop malignant solid tumors earlier in life than FA patients carrying FA/BRCA upstream null mutations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Neveling et al., 2009</ref>). This characteristic might be due to the inability to use alternative DNA repair pathways; in fact, cells from these patients are unable to perform sister chromatid exchanges (<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Sonoda et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Takata et al., 2001</ref>).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 5</ref>shows the simulations of the null mutation in FANCD1N. In<ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 5A</ref>, it can be observed that the attractor reached is characterized by the activation of the Checkpoint proteins with a concomitant absence of HRR and NHEJ activities. Moreover, such attractor is obtained with either synchronous or asynchronous updating schemes. Now,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 5B</ref>shows the attractor reached under persistent ICL damage. These activation patterns can be interpreted as resulting from an arrest in the cell cycle due to a lack of repair of the DNA damage. If true, this behavior could partially explain the scarcity of patients with mutations in either FANCD1/BRCA2 or FANCN/PALB2 genes. Clearly, those surviving patients presenting these mutations should present alternative mechanisms of DNA repair allowing them to survive. The clinical manifestations of FA patients are extremely variable, therefore it has been difficult to establish a clear genotype– phenotype correlation. Nonetheless, there are phenotypic differences when comparing patients with FAcore mutations against those who carry mutations in the downstream genes, as FANCN or FANCD1. Specially the later kind of patients die due to the development of Wilms Tumor or meduloblastome, which typically occur earlier than pancytopenia, and also have more severe congenital malformations. In our model, it is possible to find a clear difference between null mutants in upstream and downstream nodes. The upstream null mutant shows the activation of alternative DNA repair pathways, A Beventually leading to the system to the CCP attractor (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 4</ref>and Supplementary Material). In contrast, the simulations of downstream null mutant show the limited possibilities of DNA repair, leading the system principally to the CCA attractor (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Fig. 5</ref>and Supplementary Material). This implies that cells with downstream null mutations have clearly few possibilities of repair, thus eventually causing cell death. It is important to mention the scarcity of patients carrying mutations somewhere in downstream FA/BRCA, probably due to early cell demise concomitant with an irreversible arrest of CCP, as implied by the CCA attractor. We described in the previous paragraphs the simulation of some variants of the FA/BRCA network that reflect the mutations of certain type of patients, and the response of their cells to certain type of DNA damage, namely ICLs. The reader may refer to the Supplementary Material for an exhaustive presentation of the simulations for all possible single mutants of the FA/BRCA network.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.Rodríguez</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>We presented in this article the reconstruction of the FA/BRCA network, as well as its implementation as a discrete dynamical system, and its behavior under a number of simulated mutations and DNA damages. To our knowledge, this is the first network model incorporating this DNA repair pathway. We simulated with the model the dynamical behavior leading to alternative routes of DNA repair that might help explain the phenotype of cells obtained from patients with FA. Our simulations strongly suggest that the use of alternative DNA repair pathways help to safeguard the integrity of the genome, although the choice of pathway does not warrant a proper joining of damaged DNA. While we did not present a formal robustness analysis of the FA/BRCA network, the results shown here are suggestive of a robust system. The recovery of a small number of attractors, all of them with a clear qualitative biological interpretation, even under the systematic alteration of the network to represent lossand gain-of-function mutations imply that the network has a strong canalizing dynamical behavior. Moreover, 45 out of the possible 56</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FA/BRCA pathway</head><p>mutants conserved the wild-type attractor. Now, most simulations were performed using a synchronous update method, which is unrealistic from the biological point of view. However, we tested a number of key network variants, namely the wild type, the FAcore and the FANCD1N null mutants with both synchronous and asynchronous update schemes, obtaining exactly the same attractors. This invariability favors the interpretation that our results are robust, and are not completely determined by the updating methodology used. We are aware that these results are only suggestive about the robustness of the FA/BRCA network, and therefore the issue has to be further studied properly and systematically. Our model makes a number of very concrete, testable predictions in the form of trajectories and attractors reached under different circumstances. Testing these predictions in the laboratory can help in the understanding of the mechanisms behind the DNA repair process as mediated by the FA/BRCA pathway. Such knowledge has potential implications in the refinement of FA/BRCA and DNA repair related pathways, with the concomitant improvement in the treatment of patients with FA, with tumors with a FA phenotype, or even with chemo-resistant forms of cancer. The current model will be improved in the future in several ways. The incorporation of more nodes or interactions may refine the model so that it would explain the cellular behavior of rare complementation groups. Also, the analysis of the network as a stochastic dynamical system could generate information about the probability of cells to make use of alternative DNA repair mechanism, and thus improve the chance to survive to DNA damages. Finally, it is worth exploring the incorporation of interactions with apoptotic pathways, which are highly related to the DNA repair process.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: ES MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [14:53 13/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts036.tex] Page: 860 858–866 A.Rodríguez et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The FA/BRCA network. Rectangles represent proteins or protein complexes, pointed arrows are positive regulatory interactions, and dashed lines with blunt arrows are negative regulatory interactions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>.</head><figDesc>Boolean functions for the nodes in the FA/BRCA network Rules ICL ← ICL ∧ ¬ DSB FANCM ← ICL ∧ ¬ CHKREC FAcore ← FANCM ∧ (ATR ∨ ATM) ∧ ¬ CHKREC FANCD2I ← FAcore ∧ ((ATM ∨ ATR) ∨ (H2AX ∧ DSB)) ∧ ¬ USP1 MUS81 ← ICL FANCJBRCA1 ← (ICL ∨ ssDNARPA) ∧ (ATM ∨ ATR) XPF ← (MUS81 ∧ ¬ FANCM) ∨ (MUS81 ∧ p53 ∧ ¬ (FAcore ∧ FANCD2I ∧ FAN1)) FAN1 ← MUS81 ∧ FANCD2I ADD ← (ADD ∨ (MUS81 ∧ (FAN1 ∨ XPF))) ∧ ¬ PCNATLS DSB ← (DSB ∨ FAN1 ∨ XPF) ∧ ¬ (NHEJ ∨ HRR) PCNATLS ← (ADD ∨ (ADD ∧ FAcore)) ∧ ¬ (USP1 ∨ FAN1) MRN ← DSB ∧ ATM ∧ ¬ ((KU ∧ FANCD2I) ∨ RAD51 ∨ CHKREC) BRCA1 ← DSB ∧ (ATM ∨ CHK2 ∨ ATR) ∧ ¬ CHKREC ssDNARPA ← DSB ∧ ((FANCD2I ∧ FANCJBRCA1) ∨ MRN) ∧ ¬ (RAD51 ∨ KU) FANCD1N ← (ssDNARPA ∧ BRCA1) ∨ (FANCD2I ∧ ssDNARPA) ∧ ¬ CHKREC RAD51 ← ssDNARPA ∧ FANCD1N ∧ ¬ CHKREC HRR ← DSB ∧ RAD51 ∧ FANCD1N ∧ BRCA1 ∧ ¬ CHKREC USP1 ← ((FANCD1N ∧ FANCD2I) ∨ PCNATLS) ∧ ¬ FANCM KU ← DSB ∧ ¬ (MRN ∨ FANCD2I ∨ CHKREC) DNAPK ← (DSB ∧ KU) ∧ ¬ CHKREC NHEJ ← (DSB ∧ DNAPK ∧ XPF ∧ ¬ ((FANCJBRCA1 ∧ ssDNARPA) ∨ CHKREC)) ∨ ((DSB ∧ DNAPK ∧ KU) ∧ ¬ (ATM ∧ ATR)) ATR ← (ssDNARPA ∨ FANCM ∨ ATM) ∧ ¬ CHKREC ATM ← (ATR ∨ DSB) ∧ ¬ CHKREC p53 ← (((ATM ∧ CHK2) ∨ (ATR ∧ CHK1)) ∨ DNAPK) ∧ ¬ CHKREC CHK1 ← (ATM ∨ ATR ∨ DNAPK) ∧ ¬ CHKREC CHK2 ← (ATM ∨ ATR ∨ DNAPK) ∧ ¬ CHKREC H2AX ← DSB ∧ (ATM ∨ ATR ∨ DNAPK) ∧ ¬ CHKREC CHKREC ← ((PCNATLS ∨ NHEJ ∨ HRR) ∧ ¬ DSB) ∨ ((¬ ADD) ∧ (¬ ICL) ∧ (¬ DSB) ∧ ¬ CHKREC) References regarding the literature used for the inference of this rules can be found in the Supplementary Material.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: ES MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [14:53 13/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts036.tex] Page: 862 858–866</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Dynamical behavior of the FA/BRCA network, simulating the response to three different types of damage. (A) In a DSB damage, DNA is repaired by MRN-mediated HRR. (B) An ADD is repaired by PCNATLS. (C) An ICL is repaired by FA/BRCA pathway via the creation of intermediary DSB and ADD. Time steps in arbitrary units are indicated at the leftmost column. The period-2 attractor of the network is indicated in gray in the time column. Nodes are grouped into functional categories by shades of gray, and also by name at the topmost column.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Dynamical behavior of the FA/BRCA network simulating a persistent ICL damage. The period-10 attractor of the network is indicated in gray in the time column.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure3(</head><figDesc>time steps 11–20) shows that under such circumstances the network reaches a period-10 attractor characterized by the persistent activation of Checkpoint, FA/BRCA and HRR pathways.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Simulation of the network with a null mutation in FAcore. (A) A single ICL pulse. (B) A persistent ICL damage.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: ES MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [14:53 13/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts036.tex] Page: 864 858–866</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. Simulation of the network with a null mutation in FANCD1N. (A) A single ICL pulse. (B) A persistent ICL damage.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: ES MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [14:53 13/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts036.tex] Page: 865 858–866</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We want to thank Nathan Weinstein, Eugenio Azpeitia, as well as the anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments during the elaboration and correction of this manuscript.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fanconi anemia and its diagnosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Auerbach</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mutat. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">668</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA damage checkpoints: from initiation to recovery or adaptation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Bartek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Lukas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="245" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial organization of the mammalian genome surveillance machinery in response to DNA strand breaks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Bekker-Jensen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">173</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">XPF-ERCC1 participates in the Fanconi Anemia pathway of cross-link repair</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Bhagwat</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6427" to="6437" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple levels of cyclin specificity in cell-cycle control</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Bloom</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Cross</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">53BP1 inhibits homologous recombination in Brca1-deficient cells by blocking resection of DNA breaks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Bunting</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="243" to="254" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A protein phosphatase feedback mechanism regulates the basal phosphorylation of Chk2 kinase in the absence of DNA damage</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Carlessi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1803" to="1213" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA damage tolerance: when it&apos;s OK to make mistakes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Chang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Cimprich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="90" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robustness and fragility of Boolean models for genetic regulatory networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Chaves</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">235</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="449" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Albert systems-level insights into cellular regulation: inferring, analysing, and modelling intracellular networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Christensen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IET Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UAF1 is a subunit of multiple deubiquitinating enzyme complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Cohn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5343" to="5351" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A mathematical model for DNA damage and repair</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Crooke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Parl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Nucleic Acids</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">352603</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disruption of mouse Slx4, a regulator of structure-specific nucleases, phenocopies Fanconi anemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Crossan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Susceptibility pathways in Fanconi&apos;s Anemia and breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Andrea</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N. Engl. J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">362</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1909" to="1919" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Boolean network model predicts cell cycle sequence of fission yeast</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Davidich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Bornholdt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1672</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genetic and molecular basis of Fanconi anemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>De Winter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Joenje</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mutat. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">668</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein phosphatase 6 interacts with the DNA-dependent protein kinase catalytic subunit and dephosphorylates gamma-H2AX</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Douglas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1368" to="1381" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamical analysis of a generic Boolean model for the control of the mammalian cell cycle</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Fauré</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="124" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wip1, a novel human protein phosphatase that is induced in response to ionizing radiation in a p53-dependentmanner</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Fiscella</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6048" to="6053" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ubiquitinated proliferating cell nuclear antigen activates translation DNA polymerases eta and REV1</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Garg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Burgers</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18361" to="18366" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Remodeling of DNA replication structures by the branch point translocase FANCM</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Gari</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16107" to="16112" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BACH1/FANCJ acts with TopBP1 and participates early in DNA replication checkpoint control</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Gong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="438" to="446" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structure-specific endonuclease Mus81-Eme1 promotes conversion of interstrand DNA crosslinks into double-strands breaks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Hanada</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4921" to="4932" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA cross-linker-induced G 2 /M arrest in group C Fanconi anemia lymphoblasts reflects normal checkpoint function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Heinrich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="287" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional relationships of FANCC to homologous recombination, translesion synthesis, and BLM</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hirano</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="418" to="427" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulation of DNA repair by ubiquitylation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Andrea</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="323" to="334" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collaboration and competition between DNA doublestrand break repair pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Kass</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Jasin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEBS Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">584</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3703" to="3708" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expanded roles of the Fanconi anemia pathway in preserving genomic stability</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Kee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Andrea</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1680" to="1694" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cell cycle-dependent chromatin loading of the Fanconi anemia core complex by FANCM/FAAP24</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5215" to="5222" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutations of the SLX4 gene in Fanconi anemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Repair of an interstrand DNA cross-link initiated by ERCC1XPF repair/recombination nuclease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Kuraoka</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">275</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26632" to="26636" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Induction by alkylating agents of sister chromatid exchanges and chromatid breaks in Fanconi&apos;s anemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Latt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4066" to="4070" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of KIAA1018/FAN1, a DNA repair nuclease recruited to DNA damage by monoubiquitinated FANCD2</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Mackay</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A network model for the control of the differentiation process in Th cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Mendoza</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BioSystems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A robust model to describe the differentiation of T-helper cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Mendoza</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Pardo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theory Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="293" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic control of flower morphogenesis in Arabidopsis thaliana: a logical analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Mendoza</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="593" to="606" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BoolNet-an R package for generation, reconstruction and analysis of Boolean networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Müssel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1378" to="1380" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genotype-phenotype correlations in Fanconi anemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Neveling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mutat. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">668</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulation of proliferating cell nuclear antigen ubiquitination in mammalian cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Niimi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16125" to="16130" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The deubiquitinating enzyme USP1 regulates the Fanconi anemia pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M B</forename>
				<surname>Nijman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="339" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ku70 corrupts DNA repair in the absence of the Fanconi anemia pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Pace</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">329</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="223" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MRE11-RAD50-NBS1 is a critical regulator of FANCD2 stability and function during DNA double-strand break repair</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Roques</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2400" to="2413" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bioinformatics-bts036.tex] Page</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="66" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Rodríguez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Repair kinetics of genomic interstrand DNA crosslinks: evidence for DNA double-strand break-dependent activation of the Fanconi anemia/BRCA pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Rothfuss</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Grompe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recombination mediator and Rad51 targeting activities of a Human BRCA2 polypeptide</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">San</forename>
				<surname>Filippo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">281</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11649" to="11657" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A genetic screen identifies FAN1, a Fanconi anemiaassociated nuclease necessary for DNA interstrand crosslink repair</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Smogorzewska</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sister chromatid exchanges are mediated by homologous recombination in vertebrate cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Sonoda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5166" to="5169" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chromosome instability and defective recombinational repair in knockout mutants of the five Rad51 paralogs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Takata</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2858" to="2866" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutation of the RAD51C gene in a Fanconi anemia-like disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Vaz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="406" to="411" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The chinease hamster FANCG/XRCC9 mutant NM3 fails to express the monoubiquitinated form of the FANCD2 protein, is hypersensitive to a range of DNA damaging agents and exhibits a normal level of spontaneous chromatid exchange</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Wilson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Carcinogenesis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1939" to="1946" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A dynamic analysis of IRS-PKR signaling in liver cells: a discrete modeling approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8040</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fanconi anemia is associated with a defect in the BRCA2 partner PALB2</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Xia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network model of survival signaling in large granular lymphocyte leukemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16308" to="16313" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PALB2 links BRCA1 and BRCA2 in the DNA-damage response</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="524" to="529" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>