
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:31+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology A coherent feedforward loop design principle to sustain robustness of biological networks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Duc-Hau</forename>
								<surname>Le</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electrical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Ulsan</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>93 Daehak-ro, Nam-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>680-749</postCode>
									<settlement>Ulsan</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Water Resources University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>175 Tay Son, Dong Da</addrLine>
									<settlement>Hanoi</settlement>
									<country key="VN">Vietnam</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yung-Keun</forename>
								<surname>Kwon</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electrical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Ulsan</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>93 Daehak-ro, Nam-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>680-749</postCode>
									<settlement>Ulsan</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology A coherent feedforward loop design principle to sustain robustness of biological networks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="630" to="637"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt026</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 17, 2012; revised on December 26, 2012; accepted on January 12, 2013</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Contact: kwonyk@ulsan.ac.kr Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Many studies have investigated the relationship between structural properties and dynamic behaviors in biological networks. In particular, feedback loop (FBL) and feedforward loop (FFL) structures have received a great deal of attention. One interesting and common property of FBL and FFL structures is their coherency of coupling. However, the role of coherent FFLs in relation to network robustness is not fully known, whereas that of coherent FBLs has been well established. Results: To establish that coherent FFLs are abundant in biological networks, we examined gene regulatory and signaling networks and found that FFLs are ubiquitous, and are in a coherently coupled form. This result was also observed in the species-based signaling networks that are integrated from KEGG database. By using a random Boolean network model, we demonstrated that these coherent FFLs can improve network robustness against update-rule perturbations. In particular , we found that coherent FFLs increase robustness because these structures induce downstream nodes to be robust against update-rule perturbations. Therefore, coherent FFLs can be considered as a design principle of human signaling networks that improve network robustness against update-rule perturbations.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Cellular dynamics are largely controlled by various topological motifs included in large-scale biological networks, which are represented by a huge number of interactions among biological components, such as genes, proteins, miRNAs and other small molecules (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Klein et al., 2012</ref>). One of these topological motifs is a feedback loop (FBL) structure, and its effects on dynamics have been widely investigated. For example, it was shown that more robust networks tend to have larger numbers of positive FBLs and smaller numbers of negative FBLs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Kwon and Cho, 2008b</ref>), and the number of FBLs involving a node is positively correlated with the functional importance of the node (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kwon et al., 2007</ref>). It was also shown that two diseases are more likely to be comorbid if the genes associated with each disease are connected with FBLs of a relatively short length in a human signaling network (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Le and Kwon, 2011a</ref>). These observations were validated as a design principle of biological networks through extensive simulations based on computational models. In addition, the role of FBLs was also investigated in some specific biological processes. For example, interlinked fast and slow positive FBLs drive reliable cell decisions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Brandman et al., 2005</ref>), interlinked positive and negative FBLs sustain the robustness of biological oscillation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Tsai et al., 2008</ref>) and FBLs play important role in modulating p53 pathway in individual cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Harris and Levine, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lahav et al., 2004</ref>). Another well-known motif is the feedforward loop (FFL) structure that has also been investigated for its effects on network dynamics. For example, specific FFLs are needed for robust carbohydrate uptake in Escherichia coli (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kremling et al., 2008</ref>), as well as for adaptation to variations in the critical morphogen level where cell fate is switched (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Rodrigo and Elena, 2011</ref>). In addition, a simple FFL motif composed of three genes was capable of processing external signals robustly (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Macia et al., 2009</ref>), and the degree to which an FFL consisting of three positive transcriptional regulators was sensitive to primary level perturbation was related to the robustness (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hayot and Jayaprakash, 2005</ref>). One interesting structural property common to FBLs and FFLs is coherent coupling. When a pair of FBLs or FFLs of the same sign is coupled, this is called a coherent coupling (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>for an illustrative example). Some previous studies have shown that an individual coherent structure can play an important role in the dynamic behavior of biological networks. For example,<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Mangan et al. (2003)</ref>showed that a coherent FFL serves as a sign-sensitive delay element in transcription networks, and<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Kalir et al. (2005)</ref>showed that a coherent FFL prolongs flagella expression in Escherichia coli. On the other hand,<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Kim et al. (2008)</ref>showed that a coupled positive FBL enhances signal amplification and bi-stable characteristics, whereas a coupled negative FBL realize enhanced homeostasis. In particular, we note a previous study that showed that coherently coupled FBLs can be a design principle in a human signaling network, as they make the network more robust (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kwon and Cho, 2008a</ref>). This result led us to question about whether the coherent FFL is also an important design principle for robustness-related dynamics, like the coherent FBLs in biological networks. Thus, in this study, we investigate the relationship between robustness-related dynamics and the coherent FFL structure through extensive simulations. A biological network such as a gene regulatory or signaling network can be represented by computational models. Among them, the Boolean network model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Glass and Kauffman, 1973;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kauffman, 1993</ref>) can be used to analyze the *To whom correspondence should be addressed. complex dynamics of biological networks because it provides the most simplified representation for the network state (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bornholdt, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kauffman et al., 2003</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Kauffman et al., , 2004</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Kwon and Cho, 2008b</ref>; Le and Kwon, 2011a;<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Shmulevich et al., 2005</ref>). Thus, we used the Boolean network model for the dynamics analysis. Before examining how the dynamics are related to the coherent FFLs, we first showed that FFLs are ubiquitously found in gene regulatory and signaling networks and further, that they are more likely to form a coherent structure than randomly expected. In addition, we examined a large set of signaling networks of 1008 species integrated from the KEGG pathway database (<ref type="bibr">Kanehisa and Goto, 2000</ref>) and showed that there is a larger number of coherent FFLs than randomly expected in each of 1001 species. In other words, coherent FFLs are frequently observed motifs in biological networks. To unravel the role of these coherent FFLs, we examined the robustness against initial-state or update-rule perturbations through the Boolean network model. To this end, two groups of random networks were generated and classified according to the degree of coherency of the FFLs. Through extensive simulations, we observed that the networks with relatively high coherency of FFLs are more robust against update-rule perturbations than those with relatively low coherency of FFLs, whereas there is little difference between them in terms of robustness against initial-state perturbations. In addition, we found that coherent FFLs can make downstream nodes robust against update-rule perturbations, and this induces the difference in robustness against update-rule perturbations. In summary, coherent FFLs seem to be a design principle to efficiently sustain robust behavior against update-rule perturbations in biological networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Biological networks dataset</head><p>To investigate the distributions of coherent FFLs, we used four relatively small-scale gene regulatory networks and two large-scale signaling networks. In addition, we used the species-based signaling pathways in the KEGG database. Gene regulatory networks: We collected four gene regulatory networks based on the literature: (i) Arabidopsis morphogenesis regulatory network (AMRN) with 10 nodes and 22 links (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Mendoza et al., 1999</ref>); (ii) a yeast cell cycle network (YCCN) with 11 nodes and 34 links (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Li et al., 2004</ref>); (iii) a mammalian cell cycle network (MCCN) with 10 nodes and 34 links (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Faure et al., 2006</ref>); and (iv) Arabidopsis floral organ fate determination gene network (AFDN) with 15 nodes and 37 links (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Espinosa-Soto et al., 2004</ref>). All of these networks were shown to be robust against some external or internal perturbations. For instance, AMRN was shown to robustly control the process of flower development (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Mendoza et al., 1999</ref>). In addition, it was shown that AFDN has a robust developmental module (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Espinosa-Soto et al., 2004</ref>), and YCCN is robustly designed against mutations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Li et al., 2004</ref>). Signaling networks: Two large-scale signaling networks were collected based on the literature: (i) a human signaling network (HSN) including 1539 nodes and 4754 interactions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Cui et al., 2009</ref>) and (ii) a canonical signaling network (CSN) including 818 nodes and 1801 links (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kwon and Cho, 2008a</ref>). To analyze a large set of signaling networks, we collected signaling pathways from the KEGG (<ref type="bibr">Kanehisa and Goto, 2000</ref>), containing pathways of 1574 species. After extracting only the activation and inhibition interactions from the pathways and integrating them for each species, we ultimately found 1008 species containing at least one FFL of length 2 (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">A random Boolean network model</head><p>A Boolean network is represented by a directed graph G(V, A), where V is a set of Boolean variables, and A is a set of ordered pairs of the Boolean variables called directed links. Each v i 2 V has a value of 1 ('on') or 0 ('off'), which represents the possible states of the corresponding elements. For example, the values 1 and 0 represent the 'turn-on' and 'turn-off' statuses, respectively. A directed link (v i , v j , ) represents a positive (activating) or negative (inhibiting) relationship from v i to v j by setting to 1 or À1, respectively. The value of each variable v i at time t þ 1 is determined by the values of k i other variables v i1 , v i2 , :::, v ik i with a link to v i at time t by the Boolean update function f i : f0, 1g ki ! f0, 1g. All the variables are synchronously updated. Hence, the update rule can be written as v i ðt þ 1Þ ¼ f i ðv i1 ðtÞ, v i2 ðtÞ, :::, v ik i ðtÞÞ where we randomly select either a logical conjunction or disjunction in f i with a uniform probability distribution. For example, if a Boolean variable v has a positive relationship with v 1 , a negative relationship with v 2 , and a positive relationship with v 3 , then the conjunction and disjunction update rules are</p><formula>vðt þ 1Þ ¼ v 1 ðtÞ ^ v 2 ðtÞ ^ v 3 ðtÞ and vðt þ 1Þ ¼ v 1 ðtÞ _ v 2 ðtÞ _ v 3 ðtÞ,</formula><p>respectively. In the case of a conjunction, the value of v at time t þ 1 is 1 only if the values of v 1 , v 2 and v 3 at time t are 1, 0 and 1, respectively. Meanwhile, in the case of a disjunction, the value of v at time t þ 1 is 1 if at least one of the states of the clauses, v 1 (t), v 2 ðtÞ and v 3 (t) is 1. In previous studies, biological networks such as signaling and gene regulatory networks were successfully described with Boolean network models using only conjunction or disjunction update-rules (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Albert, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Faure et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Huang and Ingber, 2000</ref>;<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kwon and Cho, 2007</ref>). Many studies have been performed to elucidate the dynamic behaviors of biological networks. These dynamic behaviors include noise propagation and signaling sensitivity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Hornung and Barkai, 2008</ref>), robustness and fragility (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Kwon and Cho, 2008b</ref>) and cross-talk (<ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Siso-Nadal et al., 2009</ref>). In this study, we focus on converging dynamics. In particular, we address robustness against perturbations in terms of Boolean dynamics. Given a Boolean network G(V, A) with V ¼ {v 1 , v 2 ,. .. , v N }, a state of G is defined as a vector of values v 1 through v N. A state trajectory starts from an initial state and eventually converges to either a fixed-point or limit-cycle attractor. These attractors can represent diverse biological network behaviors such as multi-stability, homeostasis and oscillation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bhalla et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ferrell and Machleder, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Pomerening et al., 2003</ref>). Based on the definition of the attractor, we can introduce the notion of robustness in terms of converging dynamics. If a network sustains the convergedattractor against a perturbation, it is called robust against the perturbation. This concept has been widely used (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Ciliberti et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Huang et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kitano, 2004a, b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Li et al., 2004</ref>). Here, we considered two types of perturbations: an initial-state perturbation and an updating-rule perturbation. Given a Boolean network G(V, A), a set of update-rules F ¼ {f 1 , f 2 ,. .. , f N } and an initial state s ¼ [v 1 (0), v 2 (0),. .. , v N (0)] at t ¼ 0, an initial-state perturbation subject to a node v i 2V represents a situation in which s is mutated to s' ¼ [v 1 (0),. .. , 1-v i (0),. .. , v N (0)], i.e. the corresponding initial value is switched to v i ð0Þ [the negation of v i (0)]. An initial-state perturbation represents the abnormal (or malfunctioning) status of a protein or gene caused by a mutation. On the other hand, an update-rule perturbation subject to a node v i 2V involves a mutation where F is changed to F' ¼ {f 1 ,. .. , f i, ',. .. , f N }, where f i ' is the disjunction rule if f i is the conjunction rule and vice versa. The update-rule perturbation may represent a change of a relationship between nodes. For a set of considered initial states S, we now define the robustness of a node v i against the initial-state perturbation and the update-rule perturbation, denoted by s (v i ) and r (v i ), respectively, as follows:</p><formula>s ðv i Þ ¼ P s2S Iððs, G, FÞ ¼ ðs 0 , G, FÞÞ jSj and r ðv i Þ ¼ P s2S Iððs, G, FÞ ¼ ðs, G, F 0 ÞÞ jSj ;</formula><p>where (s, G, F) represents the attractor to which s will converge in a Boolean network G specified by the set of update-rules F, and I(condition) denotes an indicator function that returns 1 if the condition is true and 0 otherwise. In other words, s (v i ) and r (v i ) represent the probability with which a network sustains the converging attractor against the initial-state and update-rule perturbations, respectively. In addition, a node v whose s (v) or r (v) is 51 is called a nonrobust node against the initial-state or the update-rule perturbation. Furthermore, the robustness of a network G against the initial-state perturbation and the update-rule perturbation, denoted by s (G) and r (G), respectively, are defined as follows:</p><formula>s ðGÞ ¼ P v2V s ðvÞ jVj and r ðGÞ ¼ P v2V r ðvÞ jVj :</formula><p>In other words, the robustness of a network is computed by averaging the robustness of all nodes in the network. To perform extensive simulations over a number of random Boolean networks, we used two random network generation models: a Baraba´siBaraba´si– Albert model (BA;<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Barabasi and Albert, 1999</ref>), and a variant model (ER) of an Erdo 00 s–Re´nyiRe´nyi model (Erdo¨sErdo¨s and Re´nyi<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Re´nyi, 1959</ref>). These models have been widely used to discover design principles of biological networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kwon et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kwon and Cho, 2008a</ref>, b; Le and Kwon, 2011a, b) [refer to our previous study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Le and Kwon, 2011b</ref>) for pseudo-codes to calculate s (v), r (v), s (G), r (G) and to generate random networks based on BA and ER models].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Feedforward loops</head><p>A feedforward loop is an important motif in network dynamics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Dongsan et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Yang et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Zecca and Struhl, 2010</ref>). Given a network G(V, A), a sequence of nodes w 0 ! w 1 !. .. ! w L-1 ! w L is a simple path of length L(!1), if there exist links from w i-1 to w i [i.e. (w i-1 , w i )2A 8i ¼ 1, 2,. .. , L], with w j 6 ¼ w k for j, k2{0, 1,. .. , L}. The sign of a simple path is determined by the parity of the number of negative links involved. If the parity number is even or zero, the path is positive, otherwise, it is negative. When there are two or more simple paths from a source node (v i ) and a target node (v j ) without any common intermediate node between those paths except v i and v j , the set of the simple paths is called an FFL starting from v i and ending at v j. Furthermore, an FFL is coherent if all simple paths involved have the same sign, otherwise, it is incoherent. In this work, we only consider FFLs of length two (i.e. the paths connecting a source and a target node have length less than or equal to two). We also define NuFFL of G(V, E) as the number of FFLs found in the network. In other words, it represents the number of pairs of (v2G, w2G) such that there exists an FFL from v to w. Similarly, NuCoFFL and NuInCoFFL of G(V, E) represent the number of coherent and incoherent FFLs found in the network, respectively. In addition, NuCoFFL(v) and NuInCoFFL(v) for a node v2V denote the number of coherent and incoherent FFLs involving the node v, respectively. Let us consider an FFL consisting of M ( ! 2) different paths connecting a source (v i ) and a target node (v j ) of lengths L 1 , L 2 ,. .. , and L M. Assuming that a path is specified as being negative or positive independently and uniformly at random, the probability with which the FFL is coherent or incoherent is 2/2 M or (2 M À2)/2 M , respectively. Then, the randomly expected ratio of coherent FFLs in a network with N FFLs consisting of M 1 , M 2 ,. .. , M N paths can be defined as</p><formula>1 N P N i¼1 2 2 M i .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Ubiquitousness of FFLs and their coherency in real biological networks</head><p>We first examined how frequently FFLs are found in the real biological networks. To this end, we compared NuFFLs of the real biological networks with those of random networks generated by shuffling the direction and the sign of every interaction from the real biological networks. More specifically, for a given real biological network represented by G(V, A), a shuffled random network was obtained by replacing each interaction</p><formula>(v i , v j , )2A with one of (v i , v j , ), (v i , v j , À), (v j , v i , )</formula><p>and (v j , v i , À) uniformly at random. In this way, we generated 1000 shuffled random networks for each of the four gene-regulatory (AMRN, YCCN, MCCN and AFDN) and two signaling networks (HSN and CSN).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>shows that NuFFLs of HSN and AMRN are significantly larger than those of the shuffled random networks (using one-sample t-test, all P-values510 À7 ). Similar results were also observed for other signaling (CSN) and gene-regulatory (YCCN, MCCN and AFDN) networks (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). This indicates that FFLs are ubiquitous in real biological networks. Second, we examined how predominantly FFLs are coherently organized. To this end, we compared the ratio of NuCoFFL to NuFFL in two real biological networks, HSN and AMRN, with that in the shuffled random networks (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3</ref>). The ratio of both HSN and AMRN is significantly greater than that of the shuffled networks (using one-sample t-test, all P-values510 À196 ). In addition, the ratio of NuCoFFL to NuFFL in the real biological networks is larger than the randomly expected ratio of coherent FFLs (see Materials and Methods for the definition of the randomly expected ratio of coherent FFLs). Similar results are observed for other signaling (CSN) and gene-regulatory networks (YCCN, MCCN and AFDN) (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. S2</ref>). We further investigated degree of coherency of FFLs in 1008 species-based signaling networks integrated from the KEGG signaling pathway database (see Materials and Methods section). For each signaling network, we calculated the ratio of NuCoFFL to NuFFL and the randomly expected ratio of coherent FFLs (<ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>). Intriguingly, the ratio of NuCoFFL to NuFFL is greater than the randomly expected ratio in 1001 cases of signaling networks (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). Similar results were observed for individual pathways. For example, there were 100 pathways of Homo sapiens having at least one FFL of length 2, and the ratio of NuCoFFL to NuFFL was greater than the randomly expected ratio in all the pathways (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table S2</ref>).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref>shows the case of the Type II diabetes mellitus pathway in Homo sapiens, where a total of 116 different FFLs are found, and all of them are coherent. Therefore, coherent FFLs are more frequently found in real biological networks than randomly expected, and this raises the question of why coherent FFLs are so abundant in real biological networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Effect of an individual coherent FFL on robustness</head><p>Before investigating the effect of multiple coherent FFLs on network robustness, we examine the effect of an individual coherent FFL. Thus, we investigate the robustness against the initial-state and the update-rule perturbations in the Boolean networks consisting of only a single three-node FFL (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 6</ref>). There can be eight different networks that are classified into two groups of networks containing only a single coherent (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 6a</ref>) or incoherent FFL (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 6b</ref>), respectively. Then, the following two lemmas with respect to s (G) and r (G), respectively, can be proved. In both lemmas, all possible initial states are considered for robustness computation, and v S , v M and v T denote a source, a mediate and a target node in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref>, respectively. In addition, F ¼ {f S , f M , f T } represents the set of update rules for v S , v M and v T , respectively. LEMMA 1. Given a Boolean network G(V ¼ {v S , v M , v T }, A) consisting of a three-node FFL as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref>, s (G) is 2/3 for both coherent and incoherent FFL cases. In particular, v S is the unique nonrobust node.</p><p>(PROOF) Let us consider an arbitrary initial state s ¼ {v S (0), v M (0), v T (0)}2{0,1} 3. For convenience, v(s, t) represents the value of a node v at time t when the network is initialized with a state s.(i) When v S is perturbed, the perturbed initial state s' is set to {1Àv</p><formula>S (0), v M (0), v T (0)}. Then, v S (s, t)6 ¼v S (s', t</formula><p>) for t!0 and thus s (v S ) ¼ 0.</p><formula>(ii) When v M is perturbed, s' is set to {v S (0), 1Àv M (0), v T (0)}. Then, v S (s, t) ¼ v S (s', t) for t!0 and thus v M (s', 1) ¼ f M (v S (s', 0)) ¼ f M (v S (s, 0))¼ v M (s, 1). That is, v M (s, t) ¼ v M (s', t) for t ! 1. Similarly, v T (s', 2) ¼ f T (v S (s', 1), v M (s', 1)) ¼ f T (v S (s, 1), v M (s, 1)) ¼ v T (s, 2). That is, v T (s, t) ¼ v T (s', t) for t ! 2. Therefore, s (v M ) ¼ 1.</formula><p>(iii) When v T is perturbed, s' is set to {v</p><formula>S (0), v M (0), 1Àv T (0)}. It is trivial that v S (s, t) ¼ v S (s', t) and v M (s, t) ¼ v M (s', t) for t!0. Then, v T (s', 1) ¼ f T (v S (s', 0), v M (s', 0)) ¼ f T (v S (s, 0), v M (s, 0))¼ v T (s, 1). Thus, v T (s, t) ¼ v T (s', t) for t!1 and then s (v T ) ¼ 1. Note that (i), (ii), and</formula><p>(iii) hold for all types of networks shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref>. Therefore, s (G) is 2/3 and, in particular, v S is the unique nonrobust node.</p><formula>LEMMA 2. Given a Boolean network G(V ¼ {v S , v M , v T }, A</formula><p>) consisting of a three-node FFL as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref>, r (G) is 1 for coherent FFL cases whereas it is 2/3 for incoherent FFL cases. In particular, T is the unique nonrobust node for incoherent FFL cases.</p><p>(PROOF) For convenience, v(F, t) represents the value of node v at time t when the network is given with the set of update-rules F.</p><p>(i) When v S or v M is perturbed, the perturbed update rule F ' is set to {f</p><formula>S ', f M, , f T } or {f S , f M ', f T },</formula><formula>, r (v S ) ¼ 1 and r (v M ) ¼ 1.</formula><p>(ii) When v T is perturbed, the perturbed update rule F' is set to</p><formula>{f S , f M , f T '}. Then, v T (F', t) ¼ f T '(v S (f S , tÀ 1), v M (f M , tÀ1)) ¼ AB where A is v S (f S , tÀ1) or 1Àv S (f S , tÀ1</formula><p>), is the conjunction or disjunction function, and B is</p><formula>v M (f M , tÀ1) or 1Àv M (f M , tÀ1),</formula><p>respectively, for all t!1. Then, it is true that A ¼ B for coherent FFL cases but A6 ¼B for incoherent cases. In addition, we note that the outputs of the conjunction and the disjunction functions are same when the two inputs (A and B) are equivalent whereas they are different otherwise. Therefore, r (v T ) ¼ 1 for coherent FFL case whereas r (v T ) ¼ 0 for incoherent FFL case. From (i) and (ii), r (G) is 1 for coherent FFL cases whereas 2/3 for incoherent FFL cases. In particular, v T is the unique nonrobust node for incoherent FFL cases. These lemmas say that the robustness against the initial-state perturbation is 2/3 in all networks. In other words, there is no difference between the networks composed of a single coherent or incoherent FFL with respect to s (G). On the other hand, the robustness against the update-rule perturbation was 1 for the networks of a single coherent FFL, whereas it was 2/3 for the networks of a single incoherent FFL. Therefore, coherency of FFLs improved robustness against update-rule perturbations, but not against the initial-state perturbations. Moreover, it was found that the source node denoted by S in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref>was always a unique nonrobust node subject to initial-state perturbation in both the single coherent and incoherent FFL networks</p><formula>[i.e. s (v S ) ¼ 0 and s (v M ) ¼ s (v T ) ¼ 1 in all networks]</formula><p>. On the other hand, the target node denoted by T was a nonrobust node subject to update-rule perturbation in only the networks composed of a single incoherent FFL [i.</p><formula>e. r (v S ) ¼ r (v M ) ¼ 1 and r (v T ) ¼ 0]</formula><p>, whereas there was no nonrobust node in the networks of coherent FFLs<ref type="bibr">[</ref></p><formula>i.e. r (v S ) ¼ r (v M ) ¼ r (v T ) ¼ 1].</formula><p>This interesting result can be similarly observed in the case of four-node FFLs (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S3</ref>). More specifically, a network G consisting of only a single four-node FFL shows s (G) ¼ 3/4, since the source node (S) is always not robust. On the other hand, for the target node (T), r (v T ) ¼ 1 for every coherent FFL network (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S3a</ref>), but r (v T ) ¼ 0 for every incoherent FFL network (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S3b</ref>). From this result, we can infer that the network robustness against the perturbation subject to the upstream area is not controlled by the coherency of FFLs. However, the coherent FFLs can better sustain network robustness against the update-rule perturbation subject to the downstream area. '5' groups. We compared the average s (G) and r (G) between those two groups (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). As shown in the table, the robustness against the update-rule perturbation of '4' is significantly larger than that of '5' (using two-sample t-test, Pvalue50.01), whereas the difference between the two groups with respect to robustness against initial-state perturbations is not obvious (using two-sample t-test, P-value40.1). Similar results were observed for the random Boolean networks with different size and density (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S3</ref>). Therefore, more abundant coherent FFLs than randomly expected help a network to sustain robustness against update-rule perturbations, whereas they do not affect the robustness against the initial-state perturbations. This result is consistent with the observation inIn addition, we proved that a single coherent FFL better sustains robustness against update-rule perturbations subject to a target node than a single incoherent FFL, and this causes a robustness difference between the single coherent and incoherent FFLs. Therefore, we additionally investigated whether the robustness difference between '4' and '5' network groups, as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>, can be explained with the same reasoning. To this end, we classified every source or target node (v) included in the 10 000 random Boolean networks into 'Group1' if NuCoFFL(v)4NuInCoFFL(v) and into 'Group2' if NuCoFFL(v)5NuInCoFFL(v). Next, we compare average s (v) and r (v) between the two groups. As shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>, there was no difference between the two node groups of the source nodes with respect to average s (v) and r (v). For the target nodes, whereas there was no difference between the two node groups with respect to average s (v), the average r (v) of Group1 is significantly greater than that of Group2 (using two-sample ttest, all P-values510 À48 ). Similar results were observed for the random networks with different size and density (See Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S4</ref>). This result indicates that the coherent FFLs make a network more robust against the update-rule perturbation subject to target nodes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>In a recent study, Kwon and Cho (2008a) showed that FBLs have a tendency to be coherently coupled in human signaling networks, and these coherently coupled FBLs seem to be a design principle, as they enhance network robustness against initial-state perturbation. In this study, we extended this previous finding to the coherent FFL structure. We first observed that FFL is a ubiquitously found motif in human signaling networks, and it is likely to be coherently organized. Therefore, we investigated whether such a coherent FFL is correlated with robustness-related behavior of a network through simulations with random Boolean network models. We found that a single coherent FFL makes a network more robust against update-rule perturbation than a single incoherent FFL, whereas there is littleS, M and T represent a source, a mediate and a target node, respectively. With respect to the initial-state perturbation, s (G) is 2/3 for every network G in both (a) and (b). On the other hand, with respect to the update-rule perturbation, r (G) is 1 for every network G in (a), whereas r (G) is 2/3 for every network G in (b)</p><p>difference between these two types of FFLs with respect to initial-state perturbation. Interestingly, this difference is caused by difference in the robustness against update-rule perturbations that are subject to the target node of the FFLs. This phenomenon and reasoning held consistently for networks containing multiple FFLs. In summary, coherent FFLs can be a design principle of the human signaling networks in that they improve network robustness against update-rule perturbations. The findings in this article can help deepen understanding with regard to the dynamical role of coherent FFLs. For example, the structure of multiple coherent FFLs can be considered as a kind of redundancy engineering for biological robustness as observed in alternative regular pathways that aid competition and survival in changing environment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Pasek et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Zhu et al., 2012</ref>). In addition, the role of coherent FFLs found in this article is differentiated from those of incoherent FFLs exposed in the previous studies such as the fold-change detection in gene regulation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Goentoro et al., 2009</ref>), the stable biochemical adaption (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Ma et al., 2009</ref>), the precise gene expression programming (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Osella et al., 2011</ref>). Therefore, many other dynamics comparison between coherent and incoherent FFLs will be a good future study.A total of 10 000 random Boolean networks with jVj ¼ 30 and jAj ¼ 75 are generated by using ER and BA models individually, and all the source and target nodes are extracted. jSj is set to 100. 'Group1' and 'Group2' represent that the set of nodes where a node involves a larger or smaller number of coherent FFLs than that of incoherent FFLs, respectively. NA, Not Available.A total of 10 000 random Boolean networks with jVj ¼ 30 and jAj ¼ 75 are generated by using ER and BA models individually, and jSj is set to 100. Here, '4' or '5' represents that the set of random Boolean networks where the ratio of NuCoFFL to NuFFL observed in a network is larger or smaller than the randomly expected ratio of coherent FFLs, respectively.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. An illustrative example of coherent/incoherent FBL and FFL structures. When a pair of FBLs or FFLs of the same (different) sign is coupled, this is called a coherent (resp., incoherent) coupling</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. The ratio of NuCoFFL to NuFFL in the real biological networks and its distribution in the shuffled networks. (a) Results of HSN. The ratio of HSN (0.83) is significantly larger than the randomly expected ratio (0.422) and that of the shuffled networks. (The average and standard deviation of NuCoFFL/NuFFL are 0.625 and 0.008, respectively.) (b) Results of AMRN. The ratio of AMRN (0.667) is significantly larger than the randomly expected ratio (0.45) and that of the shuffled networks. (Average and standard deviation of NuCoFFL/NuFFL are 0.469 and 0.164, respectively.) In each subfigure, 1000 shuffled networks were generated</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Comparison of NuFFL between the real biological networks and the shuffled networks. (a) Results of HSN. NuFFL of HSN (4867) is significantly larger than that of the shuffled networks. (The average and standard deviation of NuFFL are 4485.29 and 76.4, respectively.) (b) Results of AMRN. NuFFL of AMRN (15) is significantly larger than that of the shuffled networks. (The average and standard deviation of NuFFL are 9.85 and 2.56, respectively.) In each subfigure, 1000 shuffled networks were generated</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><figDesc>Section 3.2 about the simple network consisting of a single FFL.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. Type II diabetes mellitus pathway in KEGG. In this pathway, there are a total of 116 FFLs of length 2, and every one is a coherent FFL. Arrow and bar links denote the activation and the inhibition interactions, respectively</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.6.</head><figDesc>Fig. 6. Robustness of a Boolean network consisting of only a single three-node FFL. (a) Four different networks consisting of a single coherent FFL. (b) Four different networks consisting of a single incoherent FFL. In the figure, S, M and T represent a source, a mediate and a target node, respectively. With respect to the initial-state perturbation, s (G) is 2/3 for every network G in both (a) and (b). On the other hand, with respect to the update-rule perturbation, r (G) is 1 for every network G in (a), whereas r (G) is 2/3 for every network G in (b)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: This research is funded by Vietnam National Foundation for Science and Technology Development (NAFOSTED) under grant number 102.03-2012.16. This research was supported by Basic Science Research Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology (2010-0010533 and 2012R1A1A2040357). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. Robustness comparisons between source/target node groups classified by the difference between the numbers of coherent and incoherent FFLs involved by the node</figDesc><table>Model 
Location 
Node group 
Number 
Average 
P-value 
Average 
P-value 
of nodes 
of nodes 
s (v) 
r (v) 

ER 
Source 
Group1 
4102 
0 
NA 
1 
NA 
Group2 
4523 
0 
1 
Target 
Group1 
4049 
1 
NA 
0.25575 
9.42 Â 10 À50 
Group2 
4419 
1 
0.14386 
BA 
Source 
Group1 
6195 
0 
NA 
1 
NA 
Group2 
7200 
0 
1 
Target 
Group1 
6344 
1 
NA 
0.2953 
3.44 Â 10 À49 
Group2 
7170 
1 
0.19585 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Effect of the multiple coherent FFLs on robustness in random Boolean networks</figDesc><table>Model 
Network group 
Number of networks 
Average 
P-value 
Average 
P-value 
s (G) 
r (G) 

ER 
4 
4804 
0.91282 
3.06 Â 10 À1 
0.43288 
2.12 Â 10 À5 
5 
4985 
0.91389 
0.42658 
BA 
4 
4881 
0.92394 
6.69 Â 10 À1 
0.52034 
5.63 Â 10 À3 
5 
5085 
0.92436 
0.51613 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">A coherent feedforward loop design principle at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">D.-H.Le and Y.-K.Kwon at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3">.3 Effect of multiple coherent FFLs on robustness in random Boolean networks Inspired by the observation of the effect of a simple motif composed of a single coherent FFL on network robustness, we hypothesized that multiple coherent FFLs in a network play an important role in sustaining robustness, in particular against the update rule perturbation. To confirm the hypothesis, we performed extensive simulations over many random Boolean networks. To this end, we generated two sets of 10 000 random Boolean networks with 30 nodes and 75 links (i.e. jVj ¼ 30 and jAj ¼ 75) using the ER and BA models, respectively (see Materials and Methods), and jSj is set to 100. Then, they were classified into two groups of networks according to the difference between the ratio of NuCoFFL to NuFFL () and the randomly expected ratio of coherent FFLs (), &apos;4&apos; and Fig. 4. Comparison of the ratio of NuCoFFL to NuFFL observed in the signaling networks integrated from KEGG and the randomly expected ratio of coherent FFLs. A point represents a result of a signaling network of one species, and the values of the y-axis and x-axis represent the ratio of NuCoFFL to NuFFL observed in the signaling networks and the randomly expected ratio of coherent FFLs, respectively. The former is larger than the latter in 1001 cases out of 1008 species</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Boolean modeling of genetic regulatory networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Albert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lect. Notes Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">650</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="481" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emergence of scaling in random networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Barabasi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Albert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">286</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="512" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MAP kinase phosphatase as a locus of flexibility in a mitogen-activated protein kinase signaling network</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Bhalla</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">297</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1018" to="1023" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology: Less is more in modeling large genetic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Bornholdt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">310</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interlinked fast and slow positive feedback loops drive reliable cell decisions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Brandman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">310</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="496" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robustness can evolve gradually in complex regulatory gene networks with varying topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Ciliberti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein evolution on a human signaling network</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Cui</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The biphasic behavior of incoherent feed-forward loops in biomolecular regulatory networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Dongsan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BioEssays</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1204" to="1211" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On random graphs, I</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Erdo¨serdo¨s</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Re´nyire´nyi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1959" />
			<publisher>Publicationes Mathematicae</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="297" />
			<pubPlace>Debrecen</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A gene regulatory network model for cell-fate determination during arabidopsis thaliana flower development that is robust and recovers experimental gene expression profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Espinosa-Soto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2923" to="2939" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamical analysis of a generic boolean model for the control of the mammalian cell cycle</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Faure</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="124" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The biochemical basis of an all-or-none cell fate switch in xenopus oocytes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Ferrell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Jr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Machleder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">280</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="895" to="898" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The logical analysis of continuous, non-linear biochemical control networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Glass</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Kauffman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The incoherent feedforward loop can provide fold-change detection in gene regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Goentoro</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="894" to="899" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The p53 pathway: positive and negative feedback loops</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Harris</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Levine</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncogene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2899" to="2908" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A feedforward loop motif in transcriptional regulation: induction and repression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Hayot</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Jayaprakash</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">234</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Noise propagation and signaling sensitivity in biological networks: A role for positive feedback</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Hornung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Barkai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cell fates as high-dimensional attractor states of a complex gene regulatory network</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shape-dependent control of cell growth, differentiation, and apoptosis: Switching between attractors in cell regulatory networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Ingber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp. Cell Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">261</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A coherent feed-forward loop with a SUM input function prolongs flagella expression in Escherichia coli KEGG: Kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kalir</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol. Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<editor>Goto,S.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Origins of Order: Self-organization and Selection in Evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kauffman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Random boolean network models and the yeast transcriptional network</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kauffman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. US A</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. US A</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14796" to="14799" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic networks with canalyzing Boolean rules are always stable</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kauffman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. US A</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. US A</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17102" to="17107" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coupled feedback loops form dynamic motifs of cellular networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="365" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biological robustness</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Kitano</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="826" to="837" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancer as a robust system: Implications for anticancer therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Kitano</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Natl. Rev. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural and dynamical analysis of biological networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Klein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Funct. Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="420" to="433" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A feed-forward loop guarantees robust behavior in Escherichia coli carbohydrate uptake</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Kremling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="704" to="710" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Boolean dynamics of biological networks with multiple coupled feedback loops</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Kwon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Cho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2975" to="2981" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coherent coupling of feedback loops: A design principle of cell signaling networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Kwon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Cho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1926" to="1932" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative analysis of robustness and fragility in biological networks based on feedback dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Kwon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Cho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="987" to="994" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigations into the relationship between feedback loops and functional importance of a signal transduction network based on Boolean network modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Kwon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">384</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamics of the p53-Mdm2 feedback loop in individual cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Lahav</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effects of feedback loops on disease comorbidity in human signaling networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Le</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Kwon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1113" to="1120" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NetDS: a Cytoscape plugin to analyze the robustness of dynamics and feedforward/feedback loop structures of biological networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Le</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Kwon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2767" to="2768" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The yeast cell-cycle network is robustly designed</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4781" to="4786" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining network topologies that can achieve biochemical adaptation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Ma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="760" to="773" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Specialized or flexible feed-forward loop motifs: A question of topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Macia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">84</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The coherent feedforward loop serves as a sign-sensitive delay element in transcription networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Mangan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">334</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="204" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic control of flower morphogenesis in Arabidopsis thaliana: A logical analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Mendoza</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="593" to="606" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of incoherent microrna-mediated feedforward loops in noise buffering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Osella</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of domain redundancy in genetic robustness against null mutations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Pasek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">362</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building a cell cycle oscillator: Hysteresis and bistability in the activation of Cdc2</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Pomerening</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="346" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural discrimination of robustness in transcriptional feedforward loops for pattern formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Rodrigo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Elena</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">16904</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Eukaryotic cells are dynamically ordered or critical but not chaotic</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Shmulevich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13439" to="13444" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross-talk between signaling pathways can generate robust oscillations in calcium and cAMP</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Siso-Nadal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7189</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust, tunable biological oscillations from interlinked positive and negative feedback loops</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y C</forename>
				<surname>Tsai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">321</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Feed-forward signaling of TNF-{alpha} and NF-{kappa}B via IKK-{beta} pathway contributes to insulin resistance and coronary arteriolar dysfunction in type 2 diabetic mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Phys. Heart Circ. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">296</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1850" to="1858" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A feed-forward circuit linking wingless, fat-dachsous signaling, and the Warts-hippo pathway to Drosophila wing growth</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Zecca</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Struhl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000386</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Engineering the robustness of industrial microbes through synthetic biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Zhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Microb</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="94" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>