
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:59+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A high-throughput framework to detect synapses in electron microscopy images</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Saket</forename>
								<surname>Navlakha</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Machine Learning Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Computer Science</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
								<surname>Suhan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alison</forename>
								<forename type="middle">L</forename>
								<surname>Barth</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Center for the Neural Basis of Cognition</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ziv</forename>
								<surname>Bar-Joseph</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Machine Learning Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Computer Science</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A high-throughput framework to detect synapses in electron microscopy images</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="17"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt222</idno>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS Availability: Code is available at http://www.cs.cmu.edu/ $saketn/detect_synapses/ Contact: zivbj@cs.cmu.edu</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Synaptic connections underlie learning and memory in the brain and are dynamically formed and eliminated during development and in response to stimuli. Quantifying changes in overall density and strength of synapses is an important prerequisite for studying con-nectivity and plasticity in these cases or in diseased conditions. Unfortunately, most techniques to detect such changes are either low-throughput (e.g. electrophysiology), prone to error and difficult to automate (e.g. standard electron microscopy) or too coarse (e.g. magnetic resonance imaging) to provide accurate and large-scale measurements. Results: To facilitate high-throughput analyses, we used a 50-year-old experimental technique to selectively stain for synapses in electron microscopy images, and we developed a machine-learning framework to automatically detect synapses in these images. To validate our method, we experimentally imaged brain tissue of the somatosensory cortex in six mice. We detected thousands of synapses in these images and demonstrate the accuracy of our approach using cross-validation with manually labeled data and by comparing against existing algorithms and against tools that process standard electron mi-croscopy images. We also used a semi-supervised algorithm that leverages unlabeled data to overcome sample heterogeneity and improve performance. Our algorithms are highly efficient and scalable and are freely available for others to use.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The mammalian brain can contain hundreds of millions of neurons, each with thousands of specialized connections called synapses that enable indirect communication between cells. Estimates for the number of synapses in the mammalian brain ranges into the trillions. Synapses are essential for the transfer of information across neuronal ensembles, and individual synapses can be modulated by patterns of incoming neural activity, a phenomenon thought to underlie learning and memory. Changes in the relative strength and number of synapses can be regulated by a myriad of factors, including developmental age (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Cowan et al., 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Huttenlocher and Dabholkar, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Stoneham et al., 2010</ref>), sensory experience (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Klintsova and Greenough, 1999</ref>), drug addiction (<ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Van den Oever et al., 2012</ref>), estrus cycle (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Cooke and Woolley, 2005</ref>) and brain pathology. For example, in a form of autism linked to mutation of the Fragile X gene, spine density in the neocortex is elevated (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hinton et al., 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Pfeiffer and Huber, 2009</ref>), a feature that has also been observed in mice carrying the same genetic mutation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Nimchinsky et al., 2001</ref>). Rett syndrome, another neurodevelopmental disorder, is characterized by smaller brain size caused by deficits in synaptogenesis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Glaze, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Johnston et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Na and Monteggia, 2011</ref>) that results in fewer spines. Similarly, in Alzheimer's disease and other dementias, cognitive deficits are associated with reduced synapse density in the hippocampus, a brain structure critical for learning (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Clare et al., 2010</ref>). Understanding how connectivity across neurons can change is thus an important question that drives contemporary neuroscience research. Because synapse distribution is a useful and diagnostic criterion to evaluate circuit function in learning and disease, there have been a variety of methods used to estimate synaptic connectivity or overall synapse numbers. Electrophysiological methods to estimate connectivity and the number of inputs per cell can be informative (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Lefort et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Yassin et al., 2010</ref>), but these approaches are low-throughput and can typically only capture tens or hundreds of connections in reasonable amounts of time (<ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Walz, 2007</ref>). MRI-based techniques can be used to study network function at the level of brain regions or voxels, but they do not provide enough spatial resolution to estimate neural connectivity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Sporns, 2010</ref>). Anatomically, synapse densities are measured via light-microscopy to identify specialized substructures called spines that stud the dendrites of neurons or using electron microscopy (EM) to identify ultrastructural features that correspond to pre-and post-synaptic elements. Traditional approaches have used cumbersome manual detection to count synapses in these images (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b53">White et al., 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Knott et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">da Costa et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Morshedi et al., 2009</ref>) and were thus constrained to small-scale measurements or required the use of specialized transgenic animals (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Feng et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kim et al., 2012</ref>) limiting their usage for studying plasticity and development in wild-type mice. Since the early 1990s, bioimage informatics has emerged as an important area in the analysis of biological images (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Peng, 2008</ref>). Imaging datasets are usually much larger than other highthroughput biological datasets (e.g. confocal microscopy data can range in the hundreds of gigabytes for a single imaging session). Accurately identifying elements of interest (molecules, cells, synapses, etc.) within these massive datasets requires the development of sophisticated and efficient computational models. This often involves a classification-based strategy in which a (small) manually labeled training set is used to learn a general model that can be used to analyze a larger collection of images automatically. The key computational challenges involve the reliability and speed at which the analysis is done, as well as dealing with the heterogeneity of biological structures and noise *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by-nc/3.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com present in each image. Electron microscopy data suffer particularly from these problems and often contain undesired variation in intensity and contrast within and across samples and preparations. This presents a major computational challenge because model parameters learned from one sample may not generalize to other samples. Although reconstruction and segmentation of conventional EM images has helped answer important questions about brain structure and function (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bock et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Denk et al., 2012</ref>), these approaches have yet to reach the point of full automation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Merchan-Perez et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Jain et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Cardona et al., 2012</ref>), which has limited their scale and accuracy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kreshuk et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Morales et al., 2011</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">APPROACH</head><p>To aid in identifying and quantifying synapses in EM images, we used a 50-year-old experimental technique (<ref type="bibr">Aghajanian, 1966, 1968</ref>) to selectively stain for synapses in any animal model (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1A</ref>). Unlike conventional EM, this protocol uses ethanolic phosphotungstic acid (EPTA) to pronounce electron opacity at synaptic sites by targeting specific proteins in contact zones. This technique typically leaves non-synaptic membranes (e.g. plasma membranes, neurotubules and vesicles) unstained, though considerable variation can exist from sample to sample. We dissected brain tissue in the mouse somatosensory cortex and performed EM experiments using the EPTA method. We used mice from different ages (P14, P17 and P75) and isolated the same cortical region in each animal to gauge variance in sample quality. To demonstrate the advantages of this protocol for large-scale synapse identification, we developed a machine-learning framework to detect synapses in these images in a high-throughput and fully-automated manner. We describe a two-step approach. First, we use a highly accurate first-pass filtration step to reduce the search space of possible synapses by 1–2 orders of magnitude, thereby significantly reducing false positives. Second, we train a classifier to recognize synapses using texture-and shape-based features extracted from small image patches around potential objects of interest. We show that our approach is highly accurate and that it outperforms correlation-based (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Roseman, 2004</ref>) techniques and an automated technique designed to detect synapses in conventional EM images (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Morales et al., 2011</ref>). To further improve classification and adjust for varying experimental conditions (different sample, different microscope, different person performing experiments, etc.), we developed a model that classifies synapses in images using both labeled and unlabeled data. This type of approach is known as semi-supervised learning (<ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Zhu, 2005</ref>), as it combines ideas from supervised learning (classification) and unsupervised learning (clustering). This technique can be used to build more robust classifiers in cases (such as ours) where large imaging datasets can easily be collected but where it is much harder to manually annotate these images. By integrating unlabeled data in the learning phase, a new sample can help fine-tune parameters of a model built from a previous sample, which can improve accuracy without requiring users to manually annotate images in the new sample. Indeed, we show that a classifier learned only on labeled data from our P14 samples and tested on our P75 samples performs worse than a semi-supervised classifier that also leverages unlabeled data from P75.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">METHODS</head><p>First, we describe the experiments we performed to gather and process mouse brain tissue for EM imaging with EPTA, and then we describe our machine-learning framework to automatically detect synapses in these images.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Experimental approach and data collected</head><p>We gathered tissue from the mouse somatosensory cortex because it is a well-characterized anatomical area in the cortex (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Fox, 2008</ref>) and thus serves as an important benchmark for the validity of our experimental approach. To prepare the tissue for EM analysis, we extracted, fixed (using 2.5% glutaraldehyde buffered with phosphate buffered saline) and sectioned 50-mm thick tissue from wild-type C57bl6 mice at ages P14, P17 and P75 with two animals per time point. This range of tissue was collected to determine whether our experimental procedure and subsequent computational analysis remained robust to natural variation in tissue samples within and across time points and to variation in the image acquisition process. Each mouse whisker is somatotopically mapped to a single neocortical column. To ensure that the same cortical region was identified in each sample, we applied a mitochondrial stain (cytochrome oxidase) to each section to visually identify layer 4 (called the barrel) of the D1 column/whisker. The barrel was extracted using a dissecting light microscope. Tissue was prepared for transmission electron microscopy in a series of steps. First, the tissue was washed with three changes (5 min each) of distilled water, followed by an incubation in 0.02% NaOH for 10 min. This latter step was absent from the original procedure of<ref type="bibr">Aghajanian (1966, 1968</ref>), but we found that it helped increase the contrast of synapses (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). Second, the tissue was dehydrated with an ascending series of EtOH (25, 50, 70, 80, 90 and 100%), followed by fixation with 1% phosphotungstic acid (PTA) in 100% EtOH. Third, a small amount,1. Reducing the search space of possible synapses via segmentation One popular technique to search for objects in an image is the sliding window approach (<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Szeliski, 2010)</ref>. In this approach, non-overlapping windows of a pre-defined size are slid across the image, and each window is classified as synapse-containing (positive) or not (negative). One drawback to this technique is that it can double-count synapses that lie in multiple windows or miss synapses that lie adjacent to each other. A more thorough approach is to use overlapping windows, but this greatly increases computational complexity when using large images, and subsequent post-processing steps still need to account for double-counting synapses. Further, this technique creates a large imbalance of negative-to-positive examples (windows), which may lead to many false positive predictions. To circumvent these problems, instead of using sliding windows, we apply a filtration step to reduce the number of windows to test by leveraging the fact that the experimental procedure outlined earlier in the text is designed specifically to stain synapses (there may be other biological structures, such as mitochondria and membranes, that also appear in the image, but rarely are there synapses that do not appear as dark). To avoid the challenge of selecting thresholds to segment the image (which may not generalize across samples owing to differences in intensity and enhancement), we adopt the contrast-limiting adaptive histogram equalization algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Zuiderveld, 1994</ref>). This method enhances the contrast of each window T in the image to approximately match a flattened histogram by mapping each pixel value v 2 ½0, 255 to its value in the cumulative distribution f(v) computed in T:</p><formula>fðvÞ ¼ 1 n X v i¼0 histðiÞ ¼ f ðv À 1Þ þ 1 n histðvÞ, ð1Þ</formula><p>where histðÁÞ represents the original histogram of the image and n is the number of pixels in the window. We also limit the enhancement by clipping the histogram at a scalar value of 0.20 before enhancement. The window is then rescaled to<ref type="bibr">[0,</ref><ref type="bibr">255]</ref>. The equalization is performed in each local window of the image, and then the windows are combined using bilinear interpolation to eliminate artificially induced boundaries. By only considering small windows of the image, this technique prevents the overamplification of noise or artifacts that only appear in localized regions of the image. Next, we binarize the equalized image using a single, sample-independent threshold, which was determined manually to be 10% (i.e. only the top 10% of pixels values are kept). The final segmentation is produced by computing connected components (segments) in the binary image. Compared with a non-overlapping sliding window approach that would produce roughly 300 windows to test per 1016 Â 1024-sized pixel image on average, our segmentation produces 25–35 candidate segments per image and an overall ratio of negative-to-positive examples of 9:1. We also allow for optional filtration of segments that are too small or too large to be synapses, as defined by the user. This step is only designed to produce segments and not to normalize the image, which we do separately later in the text. To validate that the segmentation step preserves synapses, we looked at two samples (P14 and P75) and manually checked what percentage of the first 100 synapses encountered were correctly segmented. We found that only 1% (1 in each sample) of the synapses were lost, and these were always due to two synapses touching each other, which caused them to be merged into a single segment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Using background cues to augment synapse identification One</head><p>key indicator to decide whether a candidate segment is a synapse is the physical context in which it lies. We consider a local 75 Â 75-pixel window around the centroid of each segment to capture information about the object and the neighborhood surrounding the object. This is important because elongated synapse-like segments may also appear within mitochondria, but such segments are always surrounded by an oval-like contour marking the boundary of the mitochondria, which can be a useful cue for classification. Similarly, dark circular spots in the nucleus may also be stained (see<ref type="figure">Fig. 1A</ref>), but their neighborhoods typically contain other such spots, which also serve as strong discriminators. These are not</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Handling experimental variation across samples The aforemen</head><p>tioned technique produces a set of windows (in which each candidate segment is embedded), but the actual pixel values within these windows may vary significantly from sample-to-sample and image-to-image.<ref type="figure">Figure 1B</ref>exemplifies the discrepancy that can exist across both negative and positive examples in the original images. These issues may be caused by a variety of factors (e.g. consistency of chemical reactions during sample preparation, age of the sample, skill of the experimenter, differential illumination in the microscope, etc.) that are extremely difficult to overcome experimentally and thus must be accounted for computationally. To reduce the effect of these differences, we normalize each candidate window W by computing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arbelaez et al., 2011</ref>):</p><formula>W 0 ¼ WxyÀðWÞ ðWÞ ,</formula><p>where W xy is the current value at pixel (x,y) and and are the mean and standard deviation of the pixel intensities in W.<ref type="figure">Figure 1B</ref>shows that this significantly reduces the variance across windows, which helps features dependent on pixel intensities to be compared in an equal setting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Adjusting for synapse heterogeneity Synapses in EM images may</head><p>be angled at any 2D orientation, which may add undesirable variation in training examples. To create a more invariant set of synapses, we applied the generalized Hough transformation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Duda and Hart, 1972</ref>) to automatically rotate the segment (within the candidate window) such that its major axis points vertically. Briefly, this is done by computing the Hough transform matrix H, where entry i,j of H corresponds to the number of points in the segment that fall along a line parameterized in polar coordinates as r i ¼ x cosð i Þ þ y sinð i Þ. We find the element ðr Ã , Ã Þ in H that corresponds to the (peak) line for which the most segment points lie. The corresponding Ã is used to compute the angle of rotation. We then cropped the image to 60 Â 60 pixels to remove the effects of the interpolation (this size is still large enough to fit almost all synapses). The outcome (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1B</ref>) shows much greater uniformity for both synapses and non-synaptic structures compared with the original images.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Supervised learning framework and features used to detect synapses</head><p>After the processing steps aforementioned, each image is reduced to a set of candidate segments defined by a (normalized and aligned) square window around the centroid of the segment. Next, we build an accurate and robust classifier to discriminate between positive (synapses) and negative candidates using texture-and shape-based features. Texture is a common cue used by humans when manually segmenting structures from electron micrographs, and its use has become popular in many image processing tasks today (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arbelaez et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Varma and Zisserman, 2003</ref>). In their seminal article, Leung and Malik (2001) defined texture by convolving an image with a bank of 48 Gaussian filters and used the filter responses at each image location to define a 'texton'. Textons were clustered and used to represent and classify images in a reduced dimension. Recently, more effective filter banks have been proposed to represent texture based on modeling joint distributions of intensity values over small and compact neighborhoods of the image (as opposed to the entire image), an approach we also adopt here. The maximum response (MR8) is one such technique that is derived from a set of 38 filters: 6 orientations Â 3 scalesÂ 2 oriented filters þ 2 isotropic filters. By recording only the maximum response across orientations, the number of responses is reduced to 8 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Varma and Zisserman, 2003</ref>). Each pixel is now represented as an 8D vector of responses at its (x, y) location. For each dimension d, we compute a normalized histogram with 17 bins (larger bin sizes yielded marginal gain in performance but increased computational complexity) composed of responses for d over all pixels in the window. Thus, the texture of the window is represented as a 8 Â 17-sized vector in R n. We used the default parameters for MR8 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Varma and Zisserman, 2003</ref>). Synapses also have a characteristic shape (typically long and elongated) that we also attempt to capture by extracting the following 10 shape descriptors for each segment. These features operate on the binary segment only (they ignore the intensity values of the pixels) and therefore contribute different information than texture alone.</p><p>(1) Area: the number of pixels in the segment.</p><p>(2) Perimeter: the number of pixels in the boundary of the segment.</p><p>(3) Major axis: the number of pixels constituting the major axis of the ellipse that has the same normalized second central moments (covariance) as the segment.</p><p>(4) Minor axis: same as above but for the minor axis of the ellipse.</p><p>(5) Orientation: the angle between the x-axis and the major axis of the ellipse.</p><p>(6) Eccentricity: the ratio of the distance between the foci of the ellipse and its major axis length.</p><p>(7) Convex area: the number of pixels in the convex hull of the segment.</p><p>(8) Solidity: the proportion of pixels in the convex hull that are also in the segment.</p><p>(9) Diameter: the diameter of the circle with the same area as the segment.</p><p>(10) Extent: the ratio of pixels in the segment to pixels in the smallest bounding box of the segment. The final feature we use is the histogram of oriented gradients (HoG) descriptor proposed by Dalal and Triggs (2005). We used nine orientation bins, cell and block sizes of 10 Â 10 and 6 Â 6, respectively, and a value of 0.2 for clipping the L2-norm. Intuitively, this 334D feature describes the appearance of an object by concatenating the distributions of intensity gradients (edge directions) in different subregions of the window. This descriptor has been shown to outperform other popular feature sets (e.g. PCA-SIFT and generalized Haar wavelets) in a variety of object detection tasks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Dalal and Triggs, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Skibbe et al., 2011</ref>). In total, each window is represented by a 480D feature vector in R n. All features are scaled to lie in<ref type="bibr">[0,</ref><ref type="bibr">1]</ref>. These features were then used to build a support vector machine (SVM) classifier (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chang and Lin, 2011</ref>) using a radial basis function kernel, and we performed a grid search to optimize parameters of the model. We also learned a Random Forest (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Breiman, 2001</ref>) classifier and an AdaBoost ensemble model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Freund and Schapire, 1995</ref>) using 100 trees/learners, respectively. An overview of the supervised algorithm is shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Semi-supervised learning</head><p>The supervised algorithm described earlier in the text only uses labeled data to train a classifier. We now show how unlabeled data can be used to further improve the classifier using co-training. The co-training algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Blum and Mitchell, 1998</ref>) assumes that features can be split into two different and fairly independent sets (in our case, texture and shape).<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Blum and Mitchell (1998)</ref>proved that for a classification problem with two such feature sets, the target concept can be learned based on a few labeled and many unlabeled examples, provided that the views are compatible and uncorrelated. The compatibility condition requires that all examples are identically labeled by the two classifiers (one for each of the feature sets). The uncorrelated condition means that for any pair of features, the two sets of features are independent, given the label. In real applications, these two conditions are rarely satisfied simultaneously. For example, in our task, compatibility may be hindered due to noise and imaging artifacts. Still, co-training has proven useful in several real-world applications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Zhu, 2005</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S.Navlakha et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>i12</head><p>In a co-training algorithm, two separate classifiers are trained with the labeled data using the two subfeature sets, respectively. Each classifier is applied to the unlabeled examples, and it outputs a list of positive (putative synapses) and negative examples, ranked by confidence of assignments. We consider all the predictions in each list above a given threshold and any example for which both independent classifiers agree on its label is added to the labeled dataset. We iterate this process once and then retrain a final single classifier using all features from the original set of labeled examples and the new (predicted) set of labeled examples obtained during this iterative process. In addition to our attempts to normalize each image, this approach provides another way to account for variability in never-before-seen samples without requiring explicit annotation, which can be cumbersome to obtain in practice.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Testing and comparing with other approaches</head><p>For experiments using supervised learning, we manually labeled 11% (59) of the 520 images from P14 and P75 distributed equally across each sample. To do so, we performed the first-pass segmentation described earlier in the text and labeled the resulting windows (segments) as positive or negative. A total of 230 synapses were identified (each showing a clear post-synaptic density and elongated shape) along with 2062 negative examples. The MR8, HoG and shape descriptors were extracted from each example and stored as a 480D feature vector. We performed 10-fold cross-validation and report precision, recall and area under the ROC and precision-recall curves. The confidence in each prediction was measured based on the distance from the test vector to the decision boundary in feature space (for SVM) and based on the proportion of tree agreements for the Random Forest classifier. For supervised learning, we did not use any unlabeled data. For the semi-supervised approach, we selected all the labeled images from one sample (sample A, e.g. P14) and trained two classifiers using texture and shape features, respectively. Each classifier was then applied to the % 90% of unlabeled images in sample B (P75), and all predictions in either the positive or negative set in which both classifiers agreed (i.e. both predicted the same label with confidence above a given threshold) were added to the training set. A new single classifier C 0 was then built using the known labeled examples from sample A as well as the highconfidence examples predicted by the co-trained classifiers. We also learned a baseline classifier C that was only trained on the known labels from sample A. Both classifiers were then tested for accuracy on the true labeled examples from sample B. We compared our supervised approach against a correlation-based technique (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Roseman, 2004</ref>) that classifies a test window W as synapsecontaining with respect to training set T if max i corrðW, T i Þ4t; i.e. if the correlation coefficient between W and any positive example in the training set is 4t, where t 2 ½0, 1. We also compare against Espina (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Morales et al., 2011</ref>), a tool designed to detect synapses in conventional EM images (see Supplementary Information).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Validating against conventional EM</head><p>One potential concern with using the EPTA method is that some synapses may be washed away alongside other non-synaptic structures. To validate the correctness of our experimental procedure, we tested whether EPTA-stained images preserve roughly the same density of synapses that appear in conventional EM images of the same region. First, we isolated tissue corresponding to the D2 barrel of the mouse somatosensory cortex at P75. In one hemisphere, we performed standard EM chemistry and in the other hemisphere, we applied our EPTA stain. We then asked an expert EM biologist (J.S.) and an expert neuroscientist (A.L.B.) to manually annotate 26 conventional EM images for high-and medium-confidence synapses, and we compared density ratios versus our automated algorithm on the EPTA-stained tissue.<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. Main steps of the supervised synapse-detection algorithm and corresponding pseudocode. High-contrast objects are automatically segmented using histogram equalization. Shape-based features are extracted from these objects, as well as texture-based features from a small window surrounding the object. A model is learned from these two features types and is used to classify synapses</p><formula>W = NormalizeWindow(I,S i ) 6: W = VerticalHoughTransform(W) 7: F text = ExtractTextureFeatures(W) 8: F hog = ExtractHoGFeatures(W) 9: F shape = ExtractShapeFeatures(S i ) 10</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detecting synapses in electron microscopy images</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>i13</head><p>EPTA appears to conserve synaptic density compared with conventional EM (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). In particular, the two experts found an average of 3.55 high and medium-confidence synapses per image within the conventional EM data versus 3.25 using the EPTA-stained images (an average difference of only 8%). We can even more closely approximate the number of high-confidence-only synapses by increasing the stringency of the classifier (a difference of51%). Because synaptic density may slightly vary according to pial depth of the specimen even within D2, some variation may be expected across hemispheres. If the EPTA stain were selectively staining for only asymmetric (excitatory) synapses and not symmetric (inhibitory) synapses, then we would expect a roughly 20% difference (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Micheva and Beaulieu, 1995</ref>) between the number of synapses counted using EPTA and conventional EM. However, the close correspondence between the two methods suggests that we may be capturing both. This further demonstrates the validity of the EPTA stain as synapse-preserving (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bloom and Aghajanian, 1966</ref>) and provides a way of choosing an appropriate threshold for classification.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Detecting synapses using supervised and semi-supervised learning</head><p>As aforementioned, we used texture-and shape-based features to train several different classifiers (SVM, Random Forest and AdaBoost). We next compared the performance of these classifiers as well as a template-matching algorithm previously suggested for this task (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Roseman, 2004</ref>) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>). The SVM trained on both texture and shape features (MR8, HoG and Shape) performed best with an accuracy ranging from 54.8 to 81.3% on the positive set and 99.6 to 96.8% on the negative set depending on the classifier threshold used. Specifically, the default threshold of 0.5 allowed us to recall 67.8% of the true synapses with a precision of 83.3% (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3B</ref>). This significantly outperformed all other classifiers, as well as the correlation-based template-matching algorithm. These results suggest that the EPTA stain facilitates the high-throughput and automated detection of synapses compared with conventional EM. Such a performance would enable the large-scale use of this method to study experience-dependent plasticity in the brain and to detect abnormal changes in synaptic density owing to neurological disorders.The shape descriptors by themselves worked well for identifying positive examples but predicted many false positives owing to similar contours in, for example, nucleus regions, which are better discriminated using texture. The HoG features especially benefited from the vertical alignment of the synapses (a 7–10% decrease in false negatives with similar false positives comparing classifiers trained with and without alignment). To further validate our classifier with respect to human annotation, we took 30 unlabeled images from our P14 sample and asked an independent party (a technician in the Barth lab familiar with the EPTA protocol) to manually annotate all high-confidence synapses. We then applied our supervised classifier to these images using the default classifier threshold of 0.5 and obtained an accuracy of 87.25% (89/102) on the set of positive predictions (66.6% recall) and 96.28% (1164/1209) on the negative predictions. These percentages are similar to those obtained using cross-validation. Next, we applied semi-supervised learning to detect synapses in new samples for which training data is not available (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). Here, we trained a single classifier C on one sample (either P14 or P75) and used co-training to learn another classifier C 0 using unlabeled examples from the other sample. We found that the accuracy of C 0 increases amongst the positive class by 8–12% and increases the AUC by 1–4% compared with the baseline classifier C (see Section 3). We varied the number of unlabeled examples to transfer into C 0 and found that using the top 0.5% of positive examples (with a corresponding number of negative examples to maintain the same ratio of positive-to-negative) improved accuracy but that including the top 1.5% led to loss in performance. To explore how semi-supervised learning can account for the variance between mice at the same age, we trained on positive and negative examples from one P75 mouse and used the examples from the other P75 mouse to test (and vice versa). The baseline without semi-supervised learning had an average precision-recall AUC of 68.89% (78.81 and 58.97% individually) and an average ROC AUC of 95.80% (98.48 and 93.12% individually). Then, we used co-training to train a new classifier and improved the average precision-recall AUC to 73.06% (82.45 and 63.66%) and the ROC AUC to 97.15% (98.78 and 95.52%). Both these results demonstrate the power of using semi-supervised learning on unlabeled data, which is often plentiful but ignored in bioimage applications. Our approach is also scalable and efficient: using unoptimized MATLAB code, we can process a single image in 3.4 s on a standard desktop machine using a single processor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Development changes in the mouse barrel cortex</head><p>Next, we used our method to study developmental changes in synapse density and size in a defined area of the mouse brain, the representation of a single specified (D1) whisker in layer 4 of somatosensory cortex. We performed additional experiments and imaged the D1 barrel in two P17 mice following the same<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4A</ref>). Further, we found that synapse density decreases in adults to about the same level as P14 (2.78 synapses per image at P75), which is also consistent with prior work on pruning (<ref type="bibr" target="#b52">White et al., 1997</ref>). Thus, our pipeline can be used to better understand the rates of developmental processes and can be used to define the precise timelines of their occurrence. Finally, to demonstrate the utility of the EPTA stain beyond simply detecting synapses, we used shape features to characterize the strength of each synapse based on its well-established correlation with spine size (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Lee et al., 2012</ref>). Modulation in synaptic strength is an important facet of neuroplasticity and development (<ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Wen and Barth, 2011</ref>) with larger contact areas likely to transmit more current to the post-synaptic neuron. We used our classifier-predicted synapses in all samples (P14, P17 and P75) and plotted the distribution of the perimeter of all synapses detected (larger perimeter ! larger size ! stronger synapse). Structurally similar synapses may appear to have different sizes when projected onto 2D because the image cross-sections may be taken at any angle. Exactly correcting for this bias would involve 3D reconstruction of synapses from stacks of EM images, which is a separate and interesting problem in its own right (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Jain et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kreshuk et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Merchan-Perez et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Morales et al., 2011</ref>). We found that the distribution of synapse size at all ages fits a log-normal distribution (P50:01 by Shapiro–Wilk and Anderson–Darling tests;<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4A</ref>), which is consistent with previous electrophysiological data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Song et al., 2005</ref>). We also observed that there was a significant shift in the distribution of synapse size toward the emergence of small synapses during the period of rapid increase in synapse density at P17, without a concomitant loss of large synapses within this short developmental time window (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4B</ref>). These data suggest that developmental processes may preferentially enable the addition of new synapses without necessarily augmenting the size of alreadyexisting synapses. The data analysis pipeline that we have established can thus be used to generate and test specific hypotheses about synapse growth and maturation in the developing neocortex in a high-throughput and statistically robust manner.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Synaptic density and strength are dynamically modulated in the brain and are important facets for understanding neural circuitry and function. Experience-dependent plasticity, circuit development and neuropathologies have all been linked to changes in the number and strength of synapses in the brain, and thus their characterization is a useful parameter to facilitate our understanding of network function. Although current experimental techniques for studying these conditions have many advantages [e.g. electrophysiology provides a wealth of data not extractable from images, and conventional EM can be used to resolve synapses to extract pre-and post-synaptic partners and thus potentially allow for reconstruction of microcircuits (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Denk et al., 2012)]</ref>, several interesting questions can also be answered by sampling from brain regions of interest over several conditions or time points and generating high-confidence large-scale statistics of synaptic structures present. But to do so requires both clarity in the data and robust algorithms to explore this data. We used an old experimental technique for selectively staining synapses in EM images. This technique does not require specialized animal models for enhancing synapses, and we validated it on new tissue of the mouse somatosensory cortex and against conventional EM. We collected 4800 images from three time points and developed a fully automated and high-throughput machine-learning framework that detected thousands of synapses in these images. We also used semi-supervised learning to learn models that can adapt to variability in new samples by leveraging unlabeled data. Such an approach is suitable for several other bioimage classification problems that also face issues of sample heterogeneity. Our approach is general and scalable enough to handle large datasets and is freely available for others to use. For future work, it would be a great interest to perform immunocytochemistry using EPTA against GABA and AMPA receptors to separately classify symmetric and asymmetric synapses. Accuracy could also be improved by detecting synapses in 3D, though this would require many more images and more sophisticated computational techniques that can automatically segment, align and reconstruct synapses across serial sections. The 2D sampling-based strategies (e.g. considering sections separated by 10 mm) may certainly miss synapses, but if the same procedure is applied to each sample at each time point, the relative number of synapses per image or unit area can still be compared in a fair manner. Further, to remove some biases in 2D analysis caused by larger synapses, previous works have proposed formulas to adjust counts based on the average size of synaptic profiles observed in the sample (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Coggeshall and Lekan, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Mayhew, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Huttenlocher and Dabholkar, 1997</ref>), which we can also use.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Histogram Equal.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Cross-validation accuracy of all methods. AUC of the ROC curve (top) and precision-recall curve (bottom) show that the SVM trained using both texture and shape descriptors outperforms all other methods</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Developmental changes and log-normal distribution of synaptic strength. (A) Histogram of synapse sizes (as measured by length of the perimeter of the synapse) from two P14 (blue), two P17 (red) and two P75 (green) samples. There is significant growth in number of synapses from P14 to P17, followed by pruning by adulthood (P75). Further, all three distributions closely approximate a log-normal curve, which matches electrophysiological data on synaptic connection strengths (Song et al., 2005). (B) Cumulative distribution of synapse sizes suggest a shift in synapse strength over time (P50:01, Kolmogorov–Smirnov test)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>1: I histeq = HistogramEqual(I) 2: S = FindCandidateSegments(I histeq ) 3: S = FilterSegments(S, min size, max size) 4: for all remaining segments S i ∈ S do 5:</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. EPTA-stained EM images preserve synapse density</figDesc><table>Technique 
Number of images 
Number of synapses 
Ratio 
Time 

Expert 1 (Standard EM, manual counting) 
0.77 min/image 
High confidence only 
26 
71 
2.73 AE 1.66 
High and medium confidence 
26 
88 
3.38 AE 1.90 
Expert 2 (Standard EM, manual counting) 
0.58 mins/image 
High confidence only 
24 
65 
2.71 AE 1.55 
High and medium confidence 
24 
89 
3.71 AE 1.85 
Algorithm (EPTA EM, automatic counting) 
0.06 mins/image 
Threshold ¼ 0.7 
275 
745 
2.71 AE 2.00 
Threshold ¼ 0.5 (default) 
275 
893 
3.25 AE 2.19 </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. Semi-supervised learning boosts cross-sample accuracy</figDesc><table>Train/Test 
Co-training 
Accuracy 
AUC 

Positive 
(%) 

Negative 
(%) 

Prec-recall 
(%) 

ROC 
(%) 

P75/P14 
No 
66.36 
98.20 
73.65 
96.91 
P75/P14 
Yes (0.5%) 
72.90 
98.60 
75.75 
97.14 
P75/P14 
Yes (1.5%) 
74.77 
96.91 
73.06 
96.65 
P14/P75 
No 
48.78 
98.96 
60.50 
90.38 
P14/P75 
Yes (0.5%) 
60.16 
98.21 
64.23 
92.89 
P14/P75 
Yes (1.5%) 
60.98 
97.55 
63.80 
92.83 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="7"> ml, of 95% ethanol, was added to each 1000 ml of PTA stain used, and the PTA was washed from the sample with two changes of 100% ethanol. Fourth, propylene oxide was used as a transitional solvent (the first change of propylene oxide was on ice), and then the specimen was infiltrated with Spurr embedding resin, which was polymerized at 60 C for 48 h. Finally, 100 nm sections were cut using a diamond knife on an ultramicrotome, which were picked up using 50 or 75 mesh copper grids. The specimen was observed using a transmission electron microscope, and images were taken digitally. We took roughly 130 images per animal (each image is of size 5 mm by 5 mm) covering a total surface area of $3000 mm 2 per sample and with a total of six samples (see Supplementary Information for additional details about image acquisition). Images were taken from a single plane, and therefore no correction was necessary to account for double-counting synapses across serially sectioned images. There was significant sampleto-sample variability in the images, but synapses were typically dark with most other biological structures washed away (Fig. 1A). In total, we collected 4800 images each containing between 0 and 12 synapses. The raw images were provided as input to the machine-learning algorithms described later in the text. 3.2 Strategies for effectively detecting synapses As described earlier in the text, electron microscopy images are inherently noisy owing to variations in the samples (e.g. different age), in the manual processing steps and in the image acquisition process. To overcome these issues, we developed a pipeline that uses object segmentation, background information, normalization and alignment to obtain a better feature set that can be used for effective classification. i10 S.Navlakha et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Note: We manually counted high and medium confidence synapses in 24–26 conventional EM images and used our algorithm to automatically count synapses in 275 EPTAstained EM images of the same region. Different classifier thresholds allow us to closely approximate the true number of synapses. S.Navlakha et al. i14 at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Note: We trained a classifier using images from one sample and tested it on images from another sample (first column). This was done without co-training as a baseline and with co-training using two thresholds for selecting the number of unlabeled examples to include (second column). The third and fourth columns show accuracy on the positive and negative classes, and the last two columns show the precisionrecall and ROC AUCs, respectively. Bold cells indicate best performance. Detecting synapses in electron microscopy images i15 at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental evaluation of support vector machine-based and correlation-based approaches to automatic particle selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Arbelaez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">175</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="328" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytochemistry of synapses: selective staining for electron microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Bloom</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Aghajanian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1575" to="1577" />
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fine structural and cytochemical analysis of the staining of synaptic junctions with phosphotungstic acid</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Bloom</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Aghajanian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Ultrastruct. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="361" to="375" />
			<date type="published" when="1968" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combining labeled and unlabeled data with co-training</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Blum</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Mitchell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 11th Annual Conference on Computational Learning Theory (COLT), COLT&apos; 98</title>
		<meeting>the 11th Annual Conference on Computational Learning Theory (COLT), COLT&apos; 98<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="100" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network anatomy and in vivo physiology of visual cortical neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Bock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">471</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Random forests</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Breiman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mach. Learn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Navlakha</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TrakEM2 software for neural circuit reconstruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Cardona</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">38011</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LIBSVM: A library for support vector machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C.-C</forename>
				<surname>Chang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C.-J</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Trans. Intell. Syst. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2727" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synapse loss in dementias</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Clare</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2083" to="2090" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Methods for determining numbers of cells and synapses: a case for more uniform standards of review</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Coggeshall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Lekan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comp. Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">364</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gonadal hormone modulation of dendrites in the mammalian CNS</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Cooke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Woolley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regressive events in neurogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Cowan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">225</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1258" to="1265" />
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic random sampling scheme optimized to detect the proportion of rare synapses in the neuropil</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Da Costa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">180</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="81" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Histograms of oriented gradients for human detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Dalal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Triggs</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)</title>
		<editor>Schmid,C., et al.</editor>
		<meeting>the International Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)<address><addrLine>Washington, DC, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="886" to="893" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inhibitory synaptogenesis in mouse somatosensory cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>De Felipe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cereb. Cortex</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="619" to="634" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural neurobiology: missing link to a mechanistic understanding of neural computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Denk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of the hough transformation to detect lines and curves in pictures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Duda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Hart</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="1972" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved synapse detection for mGRASP-assisted brain connectivity mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Feng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Barrel Cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Fox</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A decision-theoretic generalization of on-line learning and an application to boosting</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Freund</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Schapire</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Second European Conference on Computational Learning Theory (EuroCOLT</title>
		<meeting>the Second European Conference on Computational Learning Theory (EuroCOLT</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="37" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rett syndrome: of girls and mice–lessons for regression in autism</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Glaze</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ment. Retard Dev. Disabil. Res. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of neocortex in three males with the fragile X syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Hinton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Med. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="294" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regional differences in synaptogenesis in human cerebral cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Huttenlocher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Dabholkar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comp. Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">387</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Machines that learn to segment images: a crucial technology for connectomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Jain</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="653" to="666" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rett syndrome and neuronal development</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Johnston</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Child Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="759" to="763" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2012) mGRASP enables mapping mammalian synaptic connectivity with light microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="102" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synaptic plasticity in cortical systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Klintsova</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Greenough</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Formation of dendritic spines with GABAergic synapses induced by whisker stimulation in adult mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Knott</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automated detection and segmentation of synaptic contacts in nearly isotropic serial electron microscopy images</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Kreshuk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24899</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Examining form and function of dendritic spines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neural Plast</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">704103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The excitatory neuronal network of the c2 barrel column in mouse primary somatosensory cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Lefort</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representing and recognizing the visual appearance of materials using three-dimensional textons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Leung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Malik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Vision</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How to count synapses unbiasedly and efficiently at the ultrastructural level: proposal for a standard sampling and counting protocol</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Mayhew</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurocytol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="793" to="804" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Counting synapses using FIB/SEM microscopy: a true revolution for ultrastructural volume reconstruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Merchan-Perez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Neuroanat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An anatomical substrate for experience-dependent plasticity of the rat barrel field cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Micheva</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Beaulieu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11834" to="11838" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Espina: a tool for the automated segmentation and counting of synapses in large stacks of electron microscopy images</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Morales</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Neuroanat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased synapses in the medial prefrontal cortex are associated with repeated amphetamine administration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Morshedi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Synapse</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="135" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of MeCP2 in CNS development and function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Na</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Monteggia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Horm. Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="368" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Abnormal development of dendritic spines in FMR1 knock-out mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Nimchinsky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5139" to="5146" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bioimage informatics: a new area of engineering biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Peng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1827" to="1836" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The state of synapses in fragile X syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Pfeiffer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Huber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroscientist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="549" to="567" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FindEM–a fast, efficient program for automatic selection of particles from electron micrographs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Roseman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">145</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SHOG: spherical hog descriptors for rotation invariant 3d object detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Skibbe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 33rd International Conference on Pattern Recognition, DAGM&apos;11</title>
		<meeting>the 33rd International Conference on Pattern Recognition, DAGM&apos;11<address><addrLine>Berlin, Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="151" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Highly nonrandom features of synaptic connectivity in local cortical circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Song</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">68</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Networks of the Brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Sporns</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rules of engagement: factors that regulate activity-dependent synaptic plasticity during neural network development</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Stoneham</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">219</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Computer Vision: Algorithms and Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Szeliski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<publisher>SpringerVerlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, Inc, New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1st. edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The synaptic pathology of drug addiction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Van Den Oever</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Exp. Med. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">970</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="469" to="491" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Texture classification: are filter banks necessary?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Varma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Zisserman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2003 IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)</title>
		<meeting>the 2003 IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="691" to="699" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Patch-Clamp Analysis: Advanced Techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Walz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<publisher>Humana Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Neuromethods Series, Totowa, New Jersey, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Input-specific critical periods for experience-dependent plasticity in layer 2/3 pyramidal neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Wen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Barth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4456" to="4465" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of morphogenesis during the early postnatal period in PMBSF barrels of mouse SmI cortex with emphasis on barrel D4</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>White</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Somatosens. Mot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structure of the nervous system of the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>White</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">314</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="340" />
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An embedded subnetwork of highly active neurons in the neocortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Yassin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1043" to="1050" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semi-supervised learning literature survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Zhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Graphics Gems IV. Chapter Contrast Limited Adaptive Histogram Equalization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Zuiderveld</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<publisher>Academic Press Professional, Inc</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="474" to="485" />
			<pubPlace>San Diego, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Detecting synapses in electron microscopy images i17</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>