
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:40+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression A hidden Markov support vector machine framework incorporating profile geometry learning for identifying microbial RNA in tiling array data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wen-Han</forename>
								<surname>Yu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Forsyth Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Bioinformatics Graduate Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Boston University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02118</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hedda</forename>
								<surname>Høvik</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Oral Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oslo</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Oslo</settlement>
									<country key="NO">Norway</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Tsute</forename>
								<surname>Chen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Forsyth Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression A hidden Markov support vector machine framework incorporating profile geometry learning for identifying microbial RNA in tiling array data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1423" to="1430"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq162</idno>
					<note type="submission">Advance Access publication April 15, 2010 Received on 15 January 2010; revised on 22 March 2010; accepted on 9 April 2010</note>
					<note>[14:41 12/5/2010 Bioinformatics-btq162.tex] Page: 1423 1423–1430 Associate Editor: Ivo Hofacker</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: RNA expression signals detected by high-density genomic tiling microarrays contain comprehensive transcriptomic information of the target organism. Current methods for determining the RNA transcription units are still computation intense and lack the discriminative power. This article describes an efficient and accurate methodology to reveal complicated transcriptional architecture, including small regulatory RNAs, in microbial transcriptome profiles. Results: Normalized microarray data were first subject to support vector regression to estimate the profile tendency by reducing noise interruption. A hybrid supervised machine learning algorithm, hidden Markov support vector machines, was then used to classify the underlying state of each probe to &apos;expression&apos; or &apos;silence&apos; with the assumption that the consecutive state sequence was a heterogeneous Markov chain. For model construction, we introduced a profile geometry learning method to construct the feature vectors, which considered both intensity profiles and changes of intensities over the probe spacing. Also, a robust strategy was used to dynamically evaluate and select the training set based only on prior computer gene annotation. The algorithm performed better than other methods in accuracy on simulated data, especially for small expressed regions with lower (&lt;1) SNR (signal-to-noise ratio), hence more sensitive for detecting small RNAs. Availability and implementation: Detail implementation steps of the algorithm and the complete result of the transcriptome analysis for a microbial genome Porphyromonas gingivalis W83 can be viewed at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Current microarray manufacturing technology can synthesize millions of oligonucleotide probes in situ on a single microscopic glass slide. This great capacity of probes allows the design of genomic tiling microarrays containing probes covering both sense and antisense strands with a great frequency for most microbial genomes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Akama et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Selinger et al., 2000</ref>; * To whom correspondence should be addressed.<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Tjaden et al., 2002</ref>) as well as many eukaryotic genomes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bertone et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">David et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Kapranov et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Li et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Schadt et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Selinger et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Stolc et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Yamada et al., 2003</ref>). These high-density genomic tiling arrays can be used to detect the expression for all RNA species including protein coding RNAs and non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs). Although becoming popular, the data analysis for expression data obtained from the high-density tiling microarrays remains to be challenging. A fundamental task is how to precisely identify expression from noisy background. One common approach has been to segment the probe signals along the genomic coordinates. The assumption of this approach is that intensities within a transcript distribute as Gaussian noise. Thus, the breakpoints detected by the abrupt changes between two adjacent segments may represent the boundaries of the RNA transcripts. A segmentation algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bai and Perron, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Huber et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Picard et al., 2005</ref>) was developed to model the signal distribution that fitted Gaussian noise. Finding an optimal set of breakpoint locations that minimized the sum of squared residuals was accomplished by the dynamic programming algorithm with a fixed number of segments. However, it is not robust to estimate the total number of segments. Also, long computation time O(n 2 S) was required, where S is the number of segments and n is the genome size. For this,<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Huber et al. (2006)</ref>attempted to simplify the complexity of the algorithm with fixed maximum length l of segment and reduced the computation time to O(nlS). The determination of expression status for each segment relied, however, on a fixed cutoff value (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">David et al., 2006</ref>), which may overlook RNA with low expression level. A supervised learning algorithm using Hidden Markov Models (HMMs) has been introduced to directly distinguish transcribed and non-transcribed regions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Du et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Li et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Munch et al., 2006</ref>). This approach successfully incorporated validated biological knowledge into the model, instead of only considering the signal distribution that might be biased by noises or system errors. By given a training set, HMMs constructs a probabilistic model that connects the hidden states to the observables as well as to the adjacent states. Viterbi algorithm is then used to compute the most likely hidden state sequence. However, higher order HMMs are known to be a better model to describe the dependency between neighbors than typical first-order HMMs, although it has not been applied widely due to the complexity and computational demands. In addition, several limitations of the conventional HMMs havePage: 1424 1423–1430</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>W.-H.Yu et al.</head><p>been noted, such as that it typically trains a conditional probabilistic model rather than a discriminative hyperplane, and it lacks the power of processing highly dimensional feature vectors which represent the observed input sequence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Rabiner, 1989</ref>). A different classification algorithm, support vector machines (SVMs) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Cortes and Vapnik, 1995</ref>) providing a discriminative model, has been commonly used in various biological applications, such as the classification of the normal and cancer tissues from microarray expression data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Furey et al., 2000</ref>). SVMs are capable of finding a linear discriminative hyperplane for classification in a high-dimensional feature space, projected from the input object space by either linear or non-linear mapping via the kernel functions. However, the classification of individual object only estimates from the corresponding feature vectors. This approach is inappropriate for interpreting the transcriptome data directly because conditional dependency of the neighbors along the sequence needs to be considered as well. To take advantage of both learning algorithms, we implemented a novel discriminative algorithm 'hidden Markov support vector machines' (HM-SVMs). HM-SVMs combines HMMs and SVMs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Altun et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Joachims et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Zeller et al., 2008</ref>) and retains the Markov chain dependency structure between the hidden states as well as the efficiency of dynamic programming by Viterbi algorithm. Additional important components inherited from SVMs are also retained. The discriminative hyperplane is learned by kernel functions and determined by the maximum-margin principle with soft margin violation adjustment. At the same time, HM-SVMs show the capability to handle high-dimensional feature vectors and overlapping features. As a result, the input data of the HM-SVMs for feature vector construction can be readily extended through incorporating multiple experimental validated data.<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Zeller et al. (2008)</ref>implemented a similar SVM discriminative technique to analyze Arabidopsis thaliana tiling data. They modeled the exon– intron expression mechanism specific to the eukaryotes, which may not be suitable to the operon expression mechanism of the prokaryotes. In addition, recent tiling array probe design methods generate probe sets with unequal probe spacing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hovik and Chen, 2010</ref>), therefore a probabilistic model that considers both intensity profile and change of intensity across the probe location will be more adequate for describing the transcriptome profile detected with such probe design. In this study, we constructed a heterogeneous HMM model with profile geometry learning to include both intensity profile and positional changes. Together with normalization and dynamic training data screening, we present a comprehensive and robust methodology for predicting the occurrence of the transcription units across the genomic sequence on both strands from the tiling array expression data. We used this new method to study the architecture and dynamics of transcription activity of a model organism, Porphyromonas gingivalis W83, which is an important periodontal pathogen.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Experimental data</head><p>Microarrays used in this study were fabricated by Roche NimbleGen, Inc. (Madison, WI, USA) and each contained 385 000 unique 50mer sequences covering both sense and antisense strands of the entire genome of P.gingivalis W83 at a frequency of ca. one probe per 12 bases in average. Probe sequences were designed by using a dynamic genomic tiling array probe design pipeline (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hovik and Chen, 2010</ref>). The probe set can be downloaded from http://bioinformatics.forsyth.org/mtd. Total RNA and genomic DNA were extracted from P.gingivalis W83 grown on TSA sheep blood agar plates containing Hemin and Vitamin K (BAPHK) for 2 days in an anaerobic chamber at 37 @BULLET C (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Duncan et al., 1993</ref>), and were labeled with Label IT µArray Cy3 Labeling Kits (Mirus Bio LLC, Madison, WI, USA). Microarray hybridizations were performed at 42 @BULLET C for 16 h in the chamber with the Long Oligo hybridization buffer [80 mM Tris–HCl, pH 7.0, 8 mM ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA), 25% formamide, 5× SSC (75mM Trisodium Citrate, 750mM Sodium Chloride), 0.1% sodium dodecyl sulfate, 0.7 mg/ml salmon sperm DNA]. Post-hybridization procedures including array washing and signal acquisition were done according to Nimblegen's manufacturer protocol. Three biological replicates for both RNA and DNA samples were used for data analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Data normalization</head><p>Raw microarray intensities were adjusted with data from DNA reference arrays using the Bioconductor package 'tilingArray' under R statistical programming environment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Huber et al., 2006</ref>). A variety of factors affect the range of hybridization signals including different thermodynamic properties imposed by probe sequences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Royce et al., 2005</ref>), biases in labeling efficiency and the abundance of target sequences. The abundance of target molecule y ij can be modeled as,</p><formula>y ij = y ij −B i A i (1)</formula><p>where y ij is the observed intensity of i-th probe on the j-th array, B i is the unspecific background fluorescence and A i is the proportional factor specific to the abundance of y ij. The unknown parameters A i and B i were estimated directly or indirectly from the corresponding genomic DNA reference intensities. Non-specific background for B i was estimated from 80% of the probes with lowest intensities in the intergenic regions of the genome. The probe intensities with repeated sequences in the genome were regressed to the level equivalent to that of a single copy of the sequence. Between-array normalization (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Huber et al., 2002</ref>) included in the tilingArray package was used for adjusting systematic signal variations among the arrays and base 2 logarithm of probe intensities were scaled.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Signal noise reduction by support vector regression normalization</head><p>We applied SVMs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Cortes and Vapnik, 1995</ref>) to intensity regression implemented by the 'kernlab' package in R (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Karatzoglou et al., 2004</ref>). The SVMs is a kernel-based machine learning algorithm. It maps the input data x into a high-dimensional feature space H defined by a kernel function and then searches for a hyperplane, i.e. a linear relation f (x), among the data points in the feature space:</p><formula>f (x) =&lt; w,,(x) &gt; +b (2)</formula><p>where (x) is projection : x → H by the corresponding feature vector x ∈ R n ; w is the weight vector perpendicular to the hyperplane and weighting the corresponding dimension, and b ∈ R. The SVMs were developed to solve pattern classification (support vector classification) and regression problem [support vector regression (SVR)]. The SVR has been extensively implemented in studying financial time series prediction (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Huang et al., 2006</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1">The model</head><p>In this study, the model was learned by giving the input data, which in our case was the hybridization measurements {(x 1 ,</p><formula>y 1 ), (x 2 , y 2 )...(x i , y i )}</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HM-SVMs</head><p>Only the data points larger than the threshold of ±ε from the predicted linear function f (x) were subjected to the penalty. The complete optimization of SVR minimizes sum of the loss function and regularization item below:</p><formula>Minimize t(w,ξ) = C m i=1 (ξ i +ξ * i )+ 1 2 ||w|| 2 Subject to (&lt; w,,(x i ) &gt; +b)−y i ≤ ε−ξ i y i −(&lt; w,,(x i ) &gt; +b) ≤ ε−ξ * i ξ i ≥ 0, ξ * i ≥ 0, i = 1,2,...,m,</formula><formula>(4)</formula><p>where m is the number of total probes on the genome; C is the trade-off value, and ξ i and ξ * i are the corresponding positive and negative errors at the i-th probes, respectively. The epsilon tube around the decision line of f (x) was created by the loss function. Therefore, only the data points outside the tube area had impact on the final decision line and the degree of influence was determined by the distance to the decision line.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">RNA transcripts identification by HM-SVMs</head><p>HM-SVMs was used to decode transcribed (expressed) and non-transcribed (silent) regions from the complicated probe intensity profiles. This hybrid algorithm allowed labeling the hidden state of sequential data based on the model learned from a training dataset integrating with prior knowledge.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.1">The model</head><p>To refine the problem, the transcriptome data D from hybridization measurements consisting of probes x = (x 1 , x 2 , …, x m ,) are associated with the unknown hidden state sequence e = (e 1 , e 2 ,...,e m ) generated by an unknown model M. The feature vector V ≡ {x</p><formula>i = (v 1 , v 2 ,...,v n )}i = 1 ... m ∈ R n</formula><p>, where x i is i-th probe on the genome and v is one of n features, was constructed from D to characterize every probe. In order to predict the unknown state e over the sequence (i.e. expressed or silent states), we constructed a learning model M representing a true model M. The constraint data X ≡{(x i , e i )}∈ D, in which the hidden state sequence e constraint has been characterized by prior knowledge, were selected as a training dataset for algorithm modeling. A w-parameterized discriminative function F: X × E ∈ R was generated by maximizing Fover the response variable e constraint ∈ E for a specific input X :</p><formula>f (x) = argmaxF(X ,e constraint ;w) (5)</formula><p>The optimized function conjugated the pair of observation and hidden state sequences by a mapping , which extracted the features from observation/hidden state sequence pairs (x, e):</p><formula>F(X ,e constraint ;w) = &lt; w,,(x,e) &gt; (6)</formula><p>Suggested by the concept of HMM, the hidden state of probe intensity along the genome was considered as a Markov chain. Two types of the features that jointed input–output mapping were derived from the emission and transition matrices. The emission matrix combined attributes of the observation vectors with a specific hidden state. The transition matrix described the neighbor hidden states which depended on each other along the sequence. Therefore, the function F was rewritten as following:</p><formula>F(X ,e constraint ;w) = T i=1 σ,τ∈K [[e i−1 = σ ∧e i = τ]]+[[e i = τ]]ψ y (x i )</formula><formula>(7) where [[e i = τ]] ψ y (x i</formula><p>) represents combination of hidden states and observation in which ψ y (x i ) maps observation vector associated with the observation r from the i-th point in the sequence. In our case, ψ y (x i ) denotes the observed intensity y ∈ R at i-th probe in the sequence. And</p><formula>[[e i = τ]]</formula><p>shows an indicator function for the hidden state τ located at the i-th</p><formula>probe. [[e i−1 = σ ∧ e i = τ]]</formula><p>displays the dependencies of states σ, τ ∈ K at the (i−1)-th and i-th positions, where K denotes all possible states. In our case, K is either expressed or silent state. The equation mentioned above corresponds to first-order models, and higher order models can be generalized as well. F(X ,e constraint ;w) accumulates all extracted features along the sequence of length T. The maximum separation margin defined by the kernel function from the training data points in the feature space, which minimized errors of misclassification, was used to construct the discriminative function F. As described before, to solve possible non-separable data points, ξ slack variables and error cost C controlling the trade off were introduced to create a soft margin to allow margin violations. More detail HM-SVMs optimization combining the loss function with regularization item was described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Altun et al. (2003)</ref>. As a result, the hidden state sequence e was estimated by the function F, giving a complete test data with associated feature vector.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.2">Extraction of feature vector</head><p>We introduced a profile geometry learning method to construct feature vectors. In order to depict the profile terrain shaped by probe intensity and position, the feature vectors were composed of two terms including elevation and change of slopes. Given a search window (the range of the flanking regions of the current probe j)</p><formula>S = (x i , x i+1 ,...,x s</formula><p>) which represents the probe j, its feature vector can be written as</p><formula>V j ≡ {(f (ϕ) i,i+1 ,f (ϕ) i+1,i+2, …f (ϕ) s−1,s ), (z i , z i+1, …, z s )}. z i is</formula><p>the Z-score converted from the probe intensity under the assumption of the probe signals distributed by Gaussian. Therefore, Z-score normalizes the signals and presents the elevation of the terrain. f (ϕ) i,i+1 shows the score of jumping from probe x i to x i+1 as below:</p><formula>f (ϕ) i,i+1 = y i,i+1 x i,i+1 O(y) x E(y) x (8)</formula><p>where y and x showed the probe intensity and position. The first factor is the slope between probe x i , x i+1 ; the second was a weight which compared O(y) x (the observed y difference at the distance of x i and x i+1 ) to E(y) x (the expected y difference at the same distance). E(y) x can be estimated by averaging y calculated from all probe distances. Note that the probes were not equally distributed on genomic sequence. E(y) x is considered as signal noise due to distance change of the probe. Therefore, f (ϕ) i,i+1 presents the change of the slope between two probes on the profile terrain. The feature vector V was composed of an n×m matrix, where the row m represents total probes with n features. In contrast to the conventional HMM, the observed atomic data point was transformed to the numerical feature vector for SVM pattern recognition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.3">Hidden state assignment</head><p>In order to combine the observation of sequence Y represented by the feature vector V with the hidden state sequence e, each probe was assigned with one of following labels: expressed or silent state. The assigning criteria were initially based on the NCBI genome annotation data, which serves as a good starting systematic biological knowledge. The sequences were preliminarily labeled as expressed or silent state corresponding to coding and non-coding regions, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.4">The training set selection</head><p>To select the training set X , we used a comprehensive and objective scheme to determine subregions from the array data only based on genome annotation data. It has been known that &gt;90% of open reading frames (ORFs) were expressed in Escherichia coli (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Selinger et al., 2000</ref>). Under this assumption, first type of the subregions, which were restricted to the ORF, tRNA and rRNA regions identified by the annotation, was used as training data for learning the expressed state. For learning the silent states, second type of the subregions located at intergenic regions was extracted and 300 bp of the DNA sequence was trimmed from both 5 and 3 ends. The trimming was to remove potential ncRNA signals from the untranslated regions (UTRs) both upstream and downstream of ORFs. According to these criteria, 955 regions were selected. Different experimental conditions may influence the selection of the training set. Therefore, leaveone-out cross-validation was used to evaluate each member of the training set for different conditions. Those with accuracy predicted by cross validation lower than 0.9 were considered non-informative or misinformative, and were removed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.5">The post-processing</head><p>In the output, every probe was tagged with either expressed or silent state. Therefore, the boundaries of the segments</p><p>Page: 1426 1423–1430</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>W.-H.Yu et al.</head><p>were defined as the junctions between two regions of different states. In addition, to remove possible false segments, labels of segments consisting fewer than four probes were averted to the same states as the neighbors. In other words, we ignored the small RNA transcripts covered by fewer than four probes (ca. 50 bp in size). The source code of SVMhmm V3.10 written in C was downloaded from http://www.cs.cornell.edu/People/tj/svm_light/svm_hmm.html (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Joachims et al., 2009</ref>). The HM-SVMs algorithm was directly implemented in R and the input file for model learning and classification was formatted as described by the program. The results of transcriptome profile, algorithm classification and detail program scripts can be accessed on the website at http://bioinformatics.forsyth.org/mtd.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Strand-specific reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction</head><p>For standard reverse transcription–polymerase chain reaction (RT–PCR), the false positive PCR artifact was detected in the absence of added RT primer due to self-priming of RNA or non-specific small DNA or RNA contaminants in the RNA extraction, which acted as the primers for RT reaction. To avoid the artifacts, a DNA tag non-homologous to P.gingivalis W83 genomic sequence was added to the 5 end of the synthesized RTprimer for reverse transcription. After cDNA was synthesized, regular PCR was performed with the tag and a gene-specific oligo as the primer pair (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Purcell et al., 2006</ref>). Reverse transcription was initiated with 2 µg RNA and 20 pmol tagged primer. The procedures of RT–PCR followed Invitrogen SuperScript II's manual.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Data normalization and regression</head><p>To monitor the signal adjustments during different stages of data processing, we plotted the probe intensities along the genomic coordinate. Raw signal intensities were first adjusted using genomic DNA hybridization data as the reference.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1a</ref>shows the genomic DNA intensities on a region of genome. The probe intensities with repeated sequences which may mislead abundance of RNA molecules were regressed to a single copy level. Theoretically, every DNA signal based on single copy number should be of the same level. However, the result showed a much fluctuated intensity profile on the plot because of various factors. One major factor was oligonucleotide composition (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Royce et al., 2005</ref>), which directly affects the affinity between targets and probes. Another involved the labeling efficiency of the probe. In our study, the genomic DNA was labeled by covalently attaching fluorescent dye to a heteroatom on guanine residues, thus the efficiency of labeling depended on the nucleic acid composition of the probe. The fluctuated DNA hybridization profile was used to adjust the expression profiles so that the bias due to sequence composition can be eliminated.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1c</ref>shows the signal intensities adjusted by DNA reference signals and between-array normalization. Compared to<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1b</ref>, which plotted original RNA hybridization measurements on a base 2 logarithmic scale, the fluctuation of adjusted intensities was notably reduced within the expressed regions (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1c</ref>), but was amplified in the background regions. This can be confirmed by quantitative comparison of standard deviation of RNA raw data and normalization data in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. Also, the background noise in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1c</ref>shows a symmetric and stochastic distribution not similar to<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1b</ref>. Our explanation is that background intensities are mainly contributed by non-specific noises without perfectly matched RNA target binding. Thus, the background regions are not the suitable targets for the DNA normalization method. Despite of this caveat, two major advantages gained still justified the use of normalization with DNA signals. First, the difference between the positive and the background signals was enhanced, which increased the sensitivity for detecting low level of expressionand (e) the corresponding ORFs. The gray areas were selected as the positive signals for further quantitative evaluation of data processing performance as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. The green areas were visually determined as background noise and its quantitative evaluation can be seen in</p><formula>= (µ Q pos −µ Q neg )/σ Q r r∈pos,neg .</formula><p>signals.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>shows the difference of mean intensities between positive and background regions prior to and after normalization. Second, the normalized intensities within a transcript expressed a much condensed level and thus better represented the pattern profile of a RNA transcript. For this reason, SVR was applied to predict the local tendency from the scattered data distribution and eliminated the outliers. In<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1d</ref>and<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>, the noises presented by the standard deviations were significantly reduced in all regions after SVR adjustment. The moderation of SD mainly contributed to the improvement of signal-to-noise ratio (SNR), since the difference of positive and background signals did not change after normalization and SVR. To maintain the local tendency of the distribution, we empirically set the parameter σ to 5 × 10 4 , which could fit our highly non-linear data model and reduce the cross-validation error. The smaller the σ was, the much smoother the distribution became. But more informative intensities were lost and cross-validation error increased. Our major goal was to more accurately differentiate the transcript units (expressed signals) from the background (silent regions). The combination of DNA normalization and SVR enhanced the separation of positive signals from background noises.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2a</ref>–c compares the histograms of raw, normalized and SVR transformed intensities. For raw intensities, the majority of transcribed signals are located at levels just above the dominant background noises in accordance with a power-law distribution (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Royce et al., 2005</ref>). The mixed distribution obscured the recognition of the transcribed regions by the following algorithm. After adjustment by normalization and SVR, the data transformed to a bimodal-like distribution composed of a mixture of two Gaussian distributions. The lower dominant peak comprised the background signals and the right small one represented the transcript signals (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2b and c</ref>). The much-separated distributions between transcript and background signals improved the performance of the machine learning algorithm described next.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Performance measurement on simulated data</head><p>To compare the performance of our HM-SVMs and other methods, the synthetic dataset with four different sizes (10, 20, 30 and 40 K data points) simulating probe intensity distribution along the genomic coordination were constructed. Data points were randomlygenerated with Gaussian noise by fixing mean and SD (noise). Two hidden states (positive and background) were pre-assigned and the level of positive signals was controlled by SNR. To optimize the algorithm, several parameters were systematically explored in order to minimize misclassification rate on the simulated dataset, which included the cost of constraints violation C, precision value epsilon ε and the search window size s. Increasing the value of C expanded the cost of misclassified points and forced to create a more accurate model. The value of C was set as 170 in this study.Smaller precision value ε enhanced the prediction accuracy, but the computing time and memory usage increased. In this study ε was set at 0.5. The search window in size S was set at 5. Furthermore, we tested both directions of reading the sequential data points, HMSVMs generated exactly the same classification with simulated data. On four different sizes of simulated data, we measured performance of our HM-SVMs and two other methods—the segmentation method by<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Huber et al. (2006)</ref>and HMM-based method by<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Nicolas et al. (2009)</ref>. Since the level of SNR and the size of segment may influence the performance, we challenged the algorithms with various combinations of the two parameters. When the data represent gene expression level, the level of SNR corresponds to the amount of RNA. The size of segment suggests the length of RNA transcript. Some small regulatory RNAs may be found in small segments and operons consisting multiple cotranscribed genes may correspond to large segments. To access the performance of the three algorithms, accuracy and Youden's index (the difference of sensitivity and false positive rate) were calculated with different SNRs and segment sizes (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>). At low SNR (&lt;1.5), our algorithm outperformed other two methods in different segment sizes. The accuracy of our algorithm was equal or higher than that of other algorithms under all conditions. The accuracy decreased with lower SNR and larger segment size. This may be due to that some data points in segments with larger size and low SNR were classified as background. Comparison of Youden's index, our algorithm showed a better power to discriminate true positive and true negative. However, when SNR was lower (&lt;0.5), all algorithms showed poor Youden's indices, suggesting more false positive predictions. Overall, compared to the other two methods, our HM-SVMs showed higher discriminative power for classifying the underline states under all test conditions.We found a large number of transcripts containing potential novel ORFs in not yet annotated regions (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4a</ref>). Several cis-encoded antisense RNAs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Brantl, 2007</ref>) opposite to the location of the sense transcripts were also identified in many regions (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4b</ref>). Small ncRNAs which may be responsible for regulation of its antisense gene expression were also observed (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4c</ref>). The 5 and 3 UTR regions of the transcripts (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4d</ref>) may provide useful resource for studying post-transcriptional regulation. Furthermore, large transcription units were frequently found to contain several ORFs (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4e</ref>) and are the typical operons transcribed from the same promoters in bacterial cells.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Page: 1428 1423–1430</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>W.-H.Yu et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Benchmark comparison</head><p>The HM-SVMs algorithm used in this study is highly efficient in terms of computational time. The analysis of the single strand of P.gingivalis genomic tiling array expression profile (ca. 200 K data points) required less than 1 min of computation time and consumed only 120 Mb system memory on a single core 2.3 MHz Intel-based computer. For the same analysis on the same computer platform, the segmentation algorithm published by<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Huber et al. (2006)</ref>took more than 16 h [parameters: maximum segment length l = 2500 (25 kbp) and maximum segment number<ref type="bibr">K = 1900]</ref>and the method implementing HMM framework (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Nicolas et al., 2009</ref>) took more than 6 h (with the parameter hidden state K set at 100). Clearly, the HM-SVMs based algorithm reported here is much more efficient compared to other algorithms used for transcriptome profile analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Predicted transcripts validated by RT–PCR</head><p>To validate the novel transcripts and transcriptional architectures by the HM-SVMs algorithm, a total of 36 regions predicted by HMSVMs as either expression or silence were subjected to experimental verification by RT–PCR. Of 15 selected expressed regions by HM-SVMs, 13 showed positive RT–PCR signals, indicating the presence of RNA. Of 21 selected silent regions, 18 showed no sign of RT–PCR product, thus confirming the lack of RNA in these regions. By calculating hypergeometric distribution probability of classification from both experiment and computer, it suggested that the prediction of the algorithm significantly matched the results of the experiment (P-value &lt;0.05). Moreover 7 of total 15 predicted expressed regions confirmed by RT–PCR are novel RNAs that have never been described before. Of three regions which were predicted as silent but showed positive RT–PCR signals, the intensities in these regions were very close to the background noises (SNR ≈ 0.01) and thus the expression patterns were masked or disrupted by the background. Localized and better background correction algorithm may be needed in order to increase the accuracy for the prediction of the low intensity area.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>A comprehensive method combining multiple innovative algorithms was devised and used for transcriptome profile analysis. This method starts with raw data normalization using DNA reference array to Page: 1430 1423–1430</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>W.-H.Yu et al.</head><p>estimate probe-specific scaling and background parameters and to adjust probe intensity accordingly. SVR algorithm, a regression model preserving the local tendency of the profile, was then used to minimize the noises caused by the stochastic measurement error. Normalized and smoothed profile data were then subjected to expression status prediction using heterogeneous HM-SVMs, which incorporates profile geometry learning and transforms the hybridization signals into the high-dimensional feature vector for the discriminative model training. Viterbi algorithm was then used to decode the most likely underlying sequential states, considering the dependencies on the neighboring states. The performance was evaluated with the simulated data and our HM-SVM outperformed two other algorithms designed for similar purpose. The HM-SVMs algorithm has the flexibility of combining different types of validated biological information in learning the feature vector for constructing the predicting function. We believe this method will be a great addition to the current methods available for transcriptome profile analysis. Furthermore, this method can also be applied to the analysis of other types of time serial data, such as CGH, ChIP-on-chip and RNA-sequencing data for predicting hidden states of the data points.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>[14:41 12/5/2010 Bioinformatics-btq162.tex]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Intensity profiles of tiling microarray data at various stages of data processing. Log 2 probe intensities (y-axis) from a range of 90-kbp of the genome on the sense strand of the sequence were plotted on the genome coordinates (x-axis). The plots are (a) signal intensities of DNA reference array, (b) RNA raw intensities from microarray, (c) signal intensities after normalization, (d) after adjustment by SVR and (e) the corresponding ORFs. The gray areas were selected as the positive signals for further quantitative evaluation of data processing performance as shown in Table 1. The green areas were visually determined as background noise and its quantitative evaluation can be seen in Table 1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Histogram of frequency intensity distribution at different stages of data processing. (a) RNA raw intensities from microarray; (b) RNA intensities after normalization; (c) RNA intensities after adjustment by SVR; and (d) component distributions combining the background noise distribution (purple area) and positive signal distribution (orange area) from the predicted HM-SVMs results.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. The performance versus different SNRs and segment sizes among three algorithms—HM-SVMs, HMM and Segmentation (shown in blue, green and red lines, respectively). The bar denotes the 95% confidence level for each data point.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Examples of transcription prediction made by HM-SVMs. Normalized log intensities (y-axis) of the probes were plotted against the actual probe coordination of the genome (x-axis). The data predicted with the 'expressed' states were colored in red and green on the sense and antisense genomic sequences, respectively; data with 'silent' states were colored in pink and light green on the sense and antisense, respectively. Computer predicted ORFs were shown in red and green boxes on the sense and antisense strand, respectively. Putative boundaries of the transcripts were indicated as vertical gray lines. Several different types of RNA transcripts (exemplified by arrowheads) categorized are as follows: (a) novel RNA transcripts, (b) antisense RNAs, (c) non-coding small RNAs, (d) putative 5 UTR region and (e) potential operon containing multiple ORFs.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>, where x i is the probe genomic coordination and y i the normalized intensity. To perform regression, SVR uses a different loss function compared to common SVMs called ε-insensitive loss function:</figDesc><table>|y−f (x)|= 


0, 
if |y−f (x)| &lt;ε 
|y−f (x)| &lt;ε otherwise 
(3) Page: 1425 1423–1430 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1.</figDesc><table>Page: 1427 1423–1430 

HM-SVMs 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Quantitative assessment of different steps of data processing by signal to noise ratio (SNR) a</figDesc><table>Type 
Start (bp) 
Stop (bp) 
RNA raw intensities 
Normalization 
SVR 

Mean 
SD 
SNR 
Mean 
SD 
SNR 
Mean 
SD 
SNR 

Positive 
189 800 
194 400 
9.7 
0.66 

6.99 

4.8 
0.50 

6.85 

4.8 
0.36 

9.96 

Positive 
218 300 
223 000 
14.1 
0.98 
7.7 
0.47 
7.6 
0.29 
Positive 
216 550 
217 650 
12.4 
0.60 
8.1 
0.62 
8.1 
0.47 
Positive 
224 200 
230 400 
10.5 
0.93 
5.5 
0.63 
5.5 
0.53 
Background 
181 700 
189 000 
7.4 
0.34 
2.0 
0.67 
2.1 
0.37 
Background 
194 500 
197 650 
7.5 
0.46 
2.1 
0.76 
2.2 
0.60 
Background 
238 400 
242 300 
7.3 
0.38 
2.0 
0.72 
2.0 
0.38 
Background 
244 500 
251 000 
7.6 
0.49 
2.2 
0.80 
2.3 
0.48 

a SNR was calculated as the following where µ 

Q 

pos defines the mean of all positive intensities within 2.5–97.5% quantiles of total, and σ 

Q 

r r∈pos,neg indicates the mean of the SDs 
from both positive and negative signals within the same quantiles. SNR </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org 1423 at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3">.3 Identification of transcription units by HM-SVMs We applied this algorithm to the analysis of the transcriptome profile for P.gingivalis W83. The selected training data for model learning consisted of pairs of input and output objects. The input was the feature vector, based on the distribution of probe intensity expression level described above, and the output was desired hidden states (expressed or silent) retrieved from NCBI genome annotation data. Additionally, any other system-wide experimental data can also be incorporated into the feature vector to enhance the discriminating ability of SVMs. The strategy of training set selection described in the methods was to extract the most informative regions by removing those that may be undergoing post-transcriptional modifications or transcription regulations. The probes in the selected regions were tagged with confident hidden states and were used in the learning of the discriminative function F. In addition, we included leave-oneout cross-validation to evaluate each member of the training set, and the one with non-informative or misinformative was eliminated. This annotation-based selecting strategy was objective but may include false labeling, which can be alleviated by implementing a soft margin created by the error cost C and the slack variable ξ in the discriminative function F. The distributions of probe intensities associated with both expressed and silent states from HM-SVMs results were plotted in Figure 2d. Degrees of separation of these two distributions showed that HM-SVMs were able to recognize the patterns from both states and to discriminate them correctly. Notably, there was an overlap between the two distributions, suggesting that the decision of classification was determined by corresponding feature vector, which was highly related to local tendency (subsequent dependency), instead of by a simple cutoff. Therefore, the algorithm could recognize the complex pattern of the expression profile and make a decision on the expression state intelligently. Examples of transcription profile analysis using HM-SVMs were shown in Figure 4. The figure shows that the algorithm was able to correctly distinguish the expressed transcripts from background noises consistent to the annotated genes and intergenic regions, respectively. Several types of RNA transcripts were classified by comparing the HM-SVMs results with the genome annotation. Examples of different types of RNAs were shown in Figure 4.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank Dr Mark Kon at Boston University for valuable comments on the writing of the manuscript.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole-genome tiling array analysis of Mycobacterium leprae RNA reveals high expression of pseudogenes and noncoding regions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Akama</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bacteriol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3321" to="3327" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hidden Markov support vector machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Altun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Twentieth International Conference on Machine Learning</title>
		<meeting>the Twentieth International Conference on Machine Learning<address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computation and analysis of multiple structural change models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Bai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Perron</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Econometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global identification of human transcribed sequences with genome tiling arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Bertone</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">306</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2242" to="2246" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulatory mechanisms employed by cis-encoded antisense RNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Brantl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Support-vector networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Cortes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Vapnik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mach. Learn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="297" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A high-resolution map of transcription in the yeast genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>David</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5320" to="5325" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A supervised hidden Markov model framework for efficiently segmenting tiling array data in transcriptional and chIP-chip experiments: systematically incorporating validated biological knowledge</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Du</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3016" to="3024" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactions of Porphyromonas gingivalis with epithelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Duncan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infect. Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2260" to="2265" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Support vector machine classification and validation of cancer tissue samples using microarray expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Furey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="906" to="914" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic probe selection for studying microbial transcriptome with high-density genomic tiling microarrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Hovik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">82</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Local support vector regression for financial time series prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Joint Conference on Neural Networks. Sheraton Vancouver Wall Centre Hotel</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Vancouver, BC, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1622" to="1627" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variance stabilization applied to microarray data calibration and to the quantification of differential expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Huber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcript mapping with high-density oligonucleotide tiling arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Huber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1963" to="1970" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cutting-plane training of structural SVMs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Joachims</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mach. Learn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale transcriptional activity in chromosomes 21 and 22</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Kapranov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">296</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="916" to="919" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kernlab–an S4 package for kernel methods in R</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Karatzoglou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stat. Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A hidden Markov model for analyzing ChIP-chip experiments on genome tiling arrays and its application to p53 binding sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="274" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global identification and characterization of transcriptionally active regions in the rice genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">294</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A hidden Markov model approach for determining expression from genomic tiling micro arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Munch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">239</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptional landscape estimation from tiling array data using a model of signal shift and drift</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Nicolas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2341" to="2347" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A statistical approach for array CGH data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Picard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strand-specific, real-time RT-PCR assays for quantification of genomic and positive-sense RNAs of the fish rhabdovirus, Infectious hematopoietic necrosis virus</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Purcell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Virol. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A tutorial on hidden Markov models and selected applications in speech recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Rabiner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<meeting>. IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="286" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Issues in the analysis of oligonucleotide tiling microarrays for transcript mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Royce</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="475" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comprehensive transcript index of the human genome generated using microarrays and computational approaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Schadt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">73</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA expression analysis using a 30 base pair resolution Escherichia coli genome array</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Selinger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1262" to="1268" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A gene expression map for the euchromatic genome of Drosophila melanogaster</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Stolc</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">306</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="655" to="660" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptome analysis of Escherichia coli using high-density oligonucleotide probe arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Tjaden</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3732" to="3738" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empirical analysis of transcriptional activity in the Arabidopsis genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Yamada</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">302</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="842" to="846" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcript normalization and segmentation of tiling array data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Zeller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pac. Symp. Biocomput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="538" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>