
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:40+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics A mathematical model describing the mechanical kinetics of kinesin stepping</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hamidreza</forename>
								<surname>Khataee</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">School of Information and Communication Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Gold Coast Campus</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Griffith University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4222</postCode>
									<region>QLD</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alan</forename>
								<surname>Wee-</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">School of Information and Communication Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Gold Coast Campus</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Griffith University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4222</postCode>
									<region>QLD</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chung</forename>
								<surname>Liew</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>liew@griffith.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">School of Information and Communication Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Gold Coast Campus</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Griffith University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4222</postCode>
									<region>QLD</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics A mathematical model describing the mechanical kinetics of kinesin stepping</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="353" to="359"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt698</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 19, 2013; revised on November 3, 2013; accepted on November 24, 2013</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Availability and implementation: The code for this work is written in Visual C# and is available by request from the authors. Contact: a.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Kinesin is a smart motor protein that steps processively forward and backward along microtubules (MTs). The mechanical kinetics of kinesin affecting its stepping behavior is not fully understood. Here, we propose a mathematical model to study the mechanical kinetics of forward and backward stepping of kinesin motor based on the four-state discrete stochastic model of the motor. Results: Results show that the probabilities of forward and backward stepping can be modeled using the mean probabilities of forward and backward kinetic transitions, respectively. We show that the backward stepping of kinesin motor starts when the probability of adenosine diphosphate (ADP) binding to the motor is much higher than that of adenosine triphosphate (ATP) binding. Furthermore, our results indicate that the backward stepping is related to both ATP hydrolysis and synthesis with rate limiting factor being ATP synthesis. Low rate of ATP synthesis under high backward loads above 10 pN is also suggested as a reason for the detachment of kinesin motor from MT in the kinetic state MTÁKinesinÁADPÁP i .</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Kinesin-1, which will be referred to as kinesin hereafter, is a twoheaded motor protein that advances unidirectionally along a microtubule (MT) in discrete 8.2 nm steps (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Clancy et al., 2011</ref>) by walking in an asymmetric hand-over-hand fashion (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Yildiz et al., 2004</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Yildiz et al., , 2008</ref>). Kinesin can processively step forward and backward along an MT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Carter and Cross, 2005</ref>), taking approximately 100 steps before detaching from the MT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Clancy et al., 2011</ref>). Experimental investigation of kinesin processivity has revealed that kinesin can undergo discrete steps in the presence of fuel, i.e. adenosine triphosphate (ATP), or in the absence of ATP, if external load is applied to the motor (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Yildiz et al., 2008</ref>). The significance of studying the mechanical kinetics underlying stepping of kinesin motor becomes apparent when considering the important roles the motor plays ranging from human diseases to synthetic nanotechnological applications and the development of novel active nanodevices. Molecular biology have revealed critical roles of kinesin motor in brain wiring and formation, neuronal survival, higher brain function and control of central nervous system (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hirokawa et al., 2010</ref>). It is also evident that the impairment of these functions of kinesin motor would contribute to neuronal disease pathogenesis, such as Alzheimer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Stokin et al., 2005</ref>) and hereditary spastic paraplegia (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Ebbing et al., 2008</ref>), and other diseases such as cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Yu and Feng, 2010</ref>). Kinesin stepping can also exert localized forces on nanostructures. This force can be exploited in nanorobotics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Hess, 2006</ref>). Thus, engineers have commenced to invent synthetic nanodevices powered by kinesin motor that have unique potentials for use in medical diagnostics as well as engineering applications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Fischer et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Goodman et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Hess, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Kumar et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Sanchez et al., 2012</ref>). However, precise temporal and spatial control of such nanodevices is a challenging problem because of the stochastic motion, high complexity and small size of kinesin (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Khataee and Ibrahim, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Khataee et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Wang and Manesh, 2010</ref>). Even though the biophysical properties of kinesin motor have been widely studied, yet little is known about how the mechanical kinetics of kinesin affect its stepping behavior in the complex cellular environment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Verhey et al., 2011</ref>). Better understanding of the mechanical kinetics of kinesin stepping may translate into the development of molecular-targeted therapy for various human diseases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hirokawa et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Yu and Feng, 2010</ref>) and precise motion control for artificial nanomotors with a wide variety of missions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Wang and Manesh, 2010</ref>). Mathematical modeling can be used to not only conceptualize and characterize kinesin behavior under different experimental settings, but also to make predictions for novel applications. One major theoretical approach for the modeling of kinesin motor motion is based on a multistate discrete stochastic model and the assumption that a single stepping of the motor involves passing through a sequence of discrete kinetic states connected by reversible transition rates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Fisher and Kolomeisky, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kolomeisky and Fisher, 2007</ref>). Here, we mathematically model and analyze the mechanical kinetics of ATP-driven stepping behavior of kinesin motor over a discrete stochastic model at various forward (negative) and backward (positive) loads and ATP concentrations (<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>) at room temperature (forward and backward steps are taken toward the plus and minus ends of MT, respectively). We show that our mathematical model can be used to analyze, conceptualize and predict forward and backward stepping of kinesin motor in different situations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Mathematical model</head><p>For kinesin's processive movement, the simplest discrete stochastic model reported by<ref type="bibr">Fisher</ref>single stepping cycle of the motor as passing through a sequence of four kinetic states where state (i) may transit to states (i þ 1) and (i À 1) with forward and backward transition rates u i and w i , i ¼ 0, 1, 2, 3, respectively:</p><formula>0 ð Þ ! u0 w1 1 ð Þ ! u1 w2 2 ð Þ ! u2 w3 3 ð Þ ! u3 w0 0 ð Þ d 0 ! j j d 1 !j d 2 !j d 3 !j</formula><p>In this discrete stochastic model, the intermediate kinetic states of the model are denoted as MÁK, MÁKÁATP, MÁKÁADPÁP i and MÁKÁADP, respectively, where MÁK designates MT-kinesin complex and ADPÁP i complex stands for the products of ATP hydrolysis: adenosine diphosphate (ADP) and inorganic phosphate (P i ). The d i represents the substep length for the center of force of kinesin along MT, where the total step size is d ¼ (d 0 þ d 1 þ d 2 þ d 3 ). It has been shown that the rates of transitions between kinetic states are influenced by the temperature T (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Leibler and Huse, 1993</ref>) and external load F (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Fisher and Kolomeisky, 2001</ref>) as:<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kolomeisky and Fisher, 2007</ref>). The parameter values of Equations (1) and (2) summarized in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>as well as the parameter values of<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref></p><formula>u ðFÞ i ¼ u ð0Þ i exp À þ</formula><formula>u ð0Þ 0 ¼ k 0 ½ATP ð 3Þ w ð0Þ 0 ¼ k 0 0 ATP ½  ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 1 þ ATP ½  c0 2 q ð4Þ</formula><p>where k 0 ¼ 1.8 mM À1 s À1 , k' 0 ¼ 0.225 mM À1 s À1 and c 0 ¼ 16 mM. The four-state discrete stochastic model asserts that forward stepping of kinesin motor is associated with ATP hydrolysis, whereas backward stepping could give rise to ATP synthesis. Our mathematical model indicates that the backward stepping of kinesin motor is related to both ATP hydrolysis and synthesis. In discussing backward stepping under high backward loads,<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Carter and Cross (2005)</ref>stated that backward stepping is unlikely to result in ATP synthesis. However,<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Fisher et al. (2005)</ref>remarked that the experimental observations in Carter and Cross (2005) rest on a misconception of the significance of dwell times before forward and backward stepping, and asserted that backward stepping could result in ATP synthesis. In addition,<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Yildiz et al. (2008)</ref>have shown that kinesin motor can step in the direction of the applied external load in the absence of ATP due to the strain on the kinesin head generated by the external load. Although the external load was able to trigger stepping in the absence of ATP, our work focuses on the ATP-driven stepping of kinesin motor and we study the effect of<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>and loads on the forward and backward stepping.<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>is considered as a factor that affects the motor velocity at various loads (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Schnitzer et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Visscher et al., 1999</ref>) and thus, it affects the mean waiting time over kinetic states modeled in this work. In several recent works,<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>is proposed as a mean for temporal control of synthetic nanodevices powered by kinesin motor (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Dinu et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Wang and Manesh, 2010</ref>). Equations (1)</p><p>and</p><p>(2) show that the rates of forward and backward transitions change under different loads,<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>and temperatures. We expect this rate change to change the probabilities of triggering these transitions, as well as the mean waiting time and the probability distribution over each kinetic states. We define the probabilities of forward and backward transitions in terms of the forward and backward transition rates as follows:</p><formula>Pðu i Þ ¼ u ðFÞ i u ðFÞ i þ w ðFÞ i ð5Þ Pðw i Þ ¼ w ðFÞ i u ðFÞ i þ w ðFÞ i ð6Þ</formula><p>where i ¼ 0, 1, 2, 3. Using the forward and backward transition rates, the mean waiting time in kinetic state s i (i ¼ 0, 1, 2, 3) can be defined as follows:</p><formula>tðs i Þ ¼ 1 u ðFÞ i þ w ðFÞ i ð7Þ</formula><p>Equation (7) defines the mean waiting time over the four kinetic states of kinesin motor during forward and backward stepping processes. We also define the stationary distribution of probability over each kinetic states of kinesin motor using the Hill's diagram method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kurka and Dvorak, 1982</ref>), where a kinetic state change diagram is represented as a graph. Let G be a connected and directed graph with vertex set V(G) and edge set E(G), which represent kinetic states and transitions of the fourstate discrete stochastic model of kinesin motor, respectively. The edge weights of G correspond to transition rates of the discrete</p><formula>PðvÞ ¼ P v P total ð8Þ where P v ¼ P { Q D j D</formula><p>is a directional diagram of v} is the sum of products of all directional diagrams of vertex v; Q D ¼ Q {e(m, n)j{m, n}2V(D)} is the product of edge weights of a directional diagram D; e(m, n) is the edge weight between vertices m and n; and P total is the sum of all P v. D is defined as a directional diagram of a vertex v if for any vertex x2V(D) and x 6 ¼ v, there is exactly one path from x to v. Collectively, the mathematical model of the mechanical kinetics of stepping behavior of kinesin motor protein shows the behavior of the motor changes in response to changes in the environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Analysis and discussion</head><p>Experimental determinations reported the stall force of kinesin motor as a load ranging between 5–7.5 pN (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Carter and Cross, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Nishiyama et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Visscher et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Yildiz et al., 2008</ref>). It was observed in Carter and Cross (2005) and Nishiyama et al. (2002) that (i) below stall, forward stepping of kinesin motor is dominant, (ii) at stall, the forward and backward stepping are equally likely and (iii) above stall, backward stepping is more frequent. To model the probabilities of forward and backward stepping of kinesin motor, we define the mean probabilities of forward and backward kinetic transitions as follows:</p><formula>PðuÞ ¼ X 3 i¼0 Pðu i Þ 4 ð9Þ PðwÞ ¼ X 3 i¼0 Pðw i Þ 4 ð10Þ</formula><p>where P(u i ) and P(w i ) are the probabilities of forward and backward transitions given by Equations (5) and (6).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1A</ref>–C shows the mean probabilities of forward and backward kinetic transitions at loads over the range À10 pN F 32 pN. We define load F ¼ À10 pN as the supremum forward load where at this point and beyond, PðuÞ 40.99 and PðwÞ 50.01. Similarly, the supremum backward load is defined at load F ¼ 32 pN where at this point and beyond, PðwÞ 40.99 and PðuÞ 50.01. From<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1A</ref>–C, we observe that with increasing load from forward to backward, the mean forward transition probability PðuÞ decreases from almost 1 and intersects with the mean backward transition probability PðwÞ at load between 7–8 pN, beyond which PðwÞ becomes dominant. Therefore, the stall force (F stall ) of kinesin motor can be obtained by solving equation PðuÞ ¼ PðwÞ at various<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>. Our results show an almost constant and<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>independent stall force of F stall $ 7.3 pN, in agreement with the experimentally measured stall force between 5–7.5 pN (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Carter and Cross, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Nishiyama et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Visscher et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Yildiz et al., 2008</ref>). These results are also consistent with the experimental observations that stall force of kinesin motor is independent of<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>(<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Carter and Cross, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Clancy et al., 2011</ref>). Our obtained F stall also agrees with the experimental results of<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Nishiyama et al. (2002)</ref>in which the probabilities of forward and backward stepping intersect at load around 7–8 pN.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1A</ref>–C also indicates that the mean probabilities of forward and backward transitions are almost<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>independent. This is consistent with the observed<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>independent but load dependent probabilities of forward and backward stepping by<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Nishiyama et al. (2002)</ref>. It was reported that under forward loads of À 15 pN F À2 pN only forward stepping was observed (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Carter and Cross, 2005</ref>), but with increasing backward loads the probability of observing backward stepping increases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Nishiyama et al., 2002</ref>). These experimental observations agreed with our results in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1A</ref>–C as over the forward load ranging from À10 pN F À2 pN, PðuÞ 40.98 and PðwÞ 50.02, whereas with increasing backward load the probability PðwÞ increases. In addition, our calculations show that at loads over the range 0 F 8 pN and at various<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>, PðuÞ decreases from40.95 to $ 0.48 (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1A–C</ref>). This is in good agreement with the reported probabilities for forward stepping of 1 and 0.5 at the respective loads of F ¼ 0 pN and F ¼ 8 pN by<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Taniguchi et al. (2005)</ref>. These agreements of our model with experimental findings indicate that the probabilities of forward and backward stepping of kinesin motor can be modeled well using the mean probabilities of forward and backward transitions defined in Equations (9) and</p><p>(10), respectively. To further analyze the probabilities of forward and backward stepping of kinesin motor using kinetic transitions, we separately examine the probabilities of forward and backward kinetic transitions given by Equations (5) and (6) (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1D</ref>–F).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1D</ref>–F shows that with increasing load from high forward to backward loads at all<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>, P(w 0 ) is the first backward probability function that intersects its corresponding forward probability function P(u 0 ). As only transition rates u ðFÞ 0 and w ðFÞ 0 are<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>dependent, the minimum load at which P(u 0 ) intersects with P(w 0 ) at<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>¼ 5 mM is F ¼ 1.987 pN (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1D</ref>). At<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>¼ 100 mM and<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>¼ 2 mM, the crossover load points of P(u 0 ) and P(w 0 ) are found to be at F ¼ 2.754 pN and F ¼ 4.034 pN, respectively (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1E</ref>and F). These results indicate that at limiting<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>the probability of forward stepping is almost equal to 1 when the applied load is 51.987 pN because at loads F51.987 pN all the probabilities P(u i ) are greater than P(w i ), i ¼ 0, 1, 2, 3 (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1D</ref>). Similarly, at high<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>almost all steps are made in the forward direction when the applied load is 54.034 pN (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1F</ref>). This is in good agreement with the experimental observations of Nishiyama et al. (2002) that at loads lower than 4 pN the probability of forward stepping is almost equal to 1. In analyzing the probabilities of<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>independent kinetic transitions, we explore their respective forward and backward kinetic transitions. Equation (1) is capable of showing that with increasing load from high forward to backward, u ðFÞ 2 and u ðFÞ 3 rates fall equally, as they have the same parameters (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>), whereas they are lower than the decreasing u ðFÞ 1 , indicating that the rate limiting step of the ATPase cycle is P i or ADP release in the presence of MTs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Higuchi et al., 1997</ref>). However, w ðFÞ 2 rises with a rate much smaller than w ðFÞ 3 because w ð0Þ 2 ¼ 1.6 s À1 is small compared with w ð0Þ 3 ¼ 40 s À1 , meaning that P i binding rate is faster than the ATP synthesis rate, as reported by<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hackney (2005)</ref>. Thus, according to Equation (5), due to low rate of ATP synthesis, i.e. w ðFÞ 2 , the probability of P i release dominates the probability of ADP release, i.e. P(u 2 ) ! P(u 3 ), with a large difference. The low probability of ADP release agrees with the results of Hackney in<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Hackney (1988</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hackney ( , 2005</ref>) where they observed that the rate limiting factor of ATPase activity of kinesin motor is the ADP release. Also, as w ðFÞ 3 is equal to w ðFÞ 1 , P(u 1 ) falls between P(u 2 ) and P(u 3 ), indicating that P i release is at least as fast as ATP hydrolysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hackney, 2005</ref>). Similarly, the slow rise of w ðFÞ 2 leads to lowering the rise of P(w 2 ) in comparison with P(w3), confirming that P i binding rate is faster than the ATP synthesis rate (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hackney, 2005</ref>). P(w 1 ) ! P(w 2 ) also indicates that the rate of ATP dissociation is higher than that of ATP synthesis, as w ðFÞ 1 ! w ðFÞ 2. The forward and backward stepping processes of kinesin motor start from kinetic state '0' by the forward and backward transitions rates u ðFÞ 0 and w ðFÞ 0 , respectively. As forward stepping of kinesin motor switch to backward at loads F4F stall , we examine P(u 0 ) and P(w 0 ) at F ¼ F stall. Our calculations show that P(w 0 )40.97 and P(u 0 )50.03 at load range F4F stall. This result implies that the backward stepping of kinesin motor starts when the probability of ADP binding to the motor is much higher than that of ATP binding. The crossover load points of probabilities of<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>independent kinetic transitions are also calculated at loads:</p><formula>(i) F ¼ 6.515 pN for P(u 3 ) and P(w 3 ), (ii) F ¼ 8.795 pN for P(u 1 ) and P(w 1 ) and</formula><p>(iii) F ¼ 17.102 pN for P(u 2 ) and P(w 2 ). However, we are not able to relate these crossover load points with the available experimental data because in current experiments,<ref type="bibr">[ADP]</ref>and<ref type="bibr">[P i ]</ref>are not separately measured (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Fisher and Kolomeisky, 2001</ref>). The result obtained by separately examining the probabilities of<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>independent kinetic transitions illustrates that the probability of ATP hydrolysis, P(u 1 ), is higher than that of ATP synthesis, P(w 2 ), at loads F stall 5F513 pN. At this load range,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1A</ref>–C indicates that the backward stepping of the kinesin motor is more probable than forward stepping. This result suggests that the backward stepping of kinesin motor is related to ATP hydrolysis as experimentally observed in<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Carter and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Cross (2005) and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Nishiyama et al. (2002)</ref>. What gives rise to the<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>dependent detachment of kinesin from MT? Equation (7) enables us to model the mean waiting time over the four kinetic states of kinesin motor during forward and backward stepping processes at different<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>and loads (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2</ref>). The results show that at<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>¼ 5 mM and low loads the mean waiting time in kinetic state '0' is greater than that of other states and peaks at a maximum of 0.1055 s at F ¼ 1.148 pN in comparison with a maximum of 0.0063 s at F ¼ 2 pN and<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>¼ 100 mM (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2A</ref>and B). These results are consistent with experimental findings as at limiting<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>, kinesin is paused at MÁK kinetic state, waiting for ATP binding (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Clancy et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hackney, 1994</ref>). It has been observed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Schnitzer et al. (2000)</ref>that at limiting<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>the probability of detachment of kinesin motor from MT in kinetic state '0' increases with the increase in the duration of this state, whereas at high<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>the probability of detachment from kinetic state '0' diminishes. Our results in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2A</ref>and B indicate that the load points that maximize tðs 0 Þ are close to the crossover load points of P(u 0 ) and P(w 0 ) at<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>¼ 5 mM and 100 mM. Thus, these results indicate that at low<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>the probability of detachment from kinetic state '0' is the highest when the probabilities of ATP and ADP binding to the motor are close.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2C</ref>also shows that at high<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>, the ATP binding rate rises, which leads to a reduction in the duration of kinetic state '0' and an increase in the durations of kinetic states '2' and '3'. This agrees with the findings of<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Schnitzer et al. (2000)</ref>that at high<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>the probability of detachment from kinetic state '0' diminishes. Accordingly, our results suggest states '2' and '3' as the most probable kinetic states for the detachment of kinesin motor from MT at high<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>and low loads, in agreement with the reported kinetic states for the detachment of kinesin from MT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hackney, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Schliwa, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Seitz and Surrey, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Yajima et al., 2002</ref>). The detachment of kinesin motor from MT under high backward</p><formula>, P(u i ) and P(w i ) where i ¼ 0, 1, 2, 3</formula><p>loads has been observed more commonly at loads 410 pN, F detach 410 pN (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Carter and Cross, 2005</ref>). Therefore, our results in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2A</ref>–C show that at high backward loads 410 pN and all<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>the mean waiting time in kinetic states '2' and '3' is greater than that of other kinetic states. These results suggest states '2' and '3' as the first and second most probable kinetic states for the detachment of kinesin motor from MT at loads410 pN, in agreement with the reported kinetic states for the detachment of kinesin from MT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Schliwa, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Seitz and Surrey, 2006</ref>). To explain the higher durations of kinetic states '2' and '3', we analyze their respective forward and backward kinetic transitions. As we discussed in analyzing the probabilities of<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>Equation (7), the slow rise of ATP synthesis rate, i.e. w ðFÞ 2 , is the reason that tðs 2 Þ attains its maximum at higher loads and at a time that is higher than that of tðs 3 Þ .<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2A</ref>–C indicates F ¼ 10.946 pN as the load point that the mean waiting time in kinetic state '2' is the highest, tðs 2 Þ ¼ 0.0046 s for all<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>, due to the slow rise of w ðFÞ 2. This implies that at high backward loads F4F stall the rate limiting factor of kinesin's backward stepping is ATP synthesis, w ðFÞ 2. To compare the duration of kinetic state '2' with that of other kinetic states at load F ¼ 10.946 pN, we compute the ratio of tðs 2 Þ ¼ 0.0046 s to tðs i Þ using Equation (7), where i ¼ 0, 1, 3 (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>).<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>shows that the duration of kinetic state '2' is at least 63 times greater than that of kinetic state '0' at load F ¼ 10.946 pN and<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>¼ 5 mM. With increasing<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>, the duration of kinetic state '0' decreases, which leads to a rise in the ratio of tðs 2 Þ to tðs 0 Þ . As the forward and backward kinetic transitions of states '1' and '3' are<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>independent, the ratio of the duration of kinetic state '2' to those of kinetic states '1' and '3' at load F ¼ 10.946 pN are constant, at 5.067 and 4.200, respectively (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). Hence, in accordance with the observations of<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Schnitzer et al. (2000)</ref>, our results in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>suggest F ¼ 10.946 pN as the load point where the probability of detachment of kinesin motor from MT in kinetic state '2' is the highest. This is consistent with the common detachment load F detach 410 pN observed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Carter and Cross (2005</ref>). As we showed that at loads F stall 5F F detach the long mean waiting time in kinetic state '2' is due to the low transition rate w ðFÞ 2 , this low rate of ATP synthesis can be proposed as a reason for the detachment of kinesin motor from MT in kinetic state '2'. Furthermore,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2A</ref>–C shows that at loads F410.946 pN the mean waiting time in state '2' decreases because of the fast rise of ATP synthesis rate, w ðFÞ 2. Thus, based on these results, it can be deduced that with an increase in the rate of ATP synthesis at high backward loads F4F stall , the long duration of being in kinetic state '2' would decrease, which leads to the reduction of the detachment probability of kinesin motor from MT. The rise of ATP synthesis rate may lead to increase in the velocity of backward stepping of kinesin motor under high backward loads. These results and the results obtained by separately examining the probabilities of<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>independent kinetic transitions (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1D-F</ref>) conclude that the backward stepping of kinesin motor is related to both ATP synthesis and hydrolysis. The duration of state '2' decreases to almost 0 at loads F ! 32 pN as inthis load range the rate of ATP synthesis, w ðFÞ 2 , is at least 93 times greater than the rate of P i release, u ðFÞ 2. Obviously, the duration of kinetic states in the forward and backward stepping processes of kinesin motor should agree with the stationary distribution of probability in these states. According to Equation (8), to compute the stationary distribution of probability over kinetic states, it is required to obtain the directional diagrams of the states. We derive the directional diagrams of four kinetic states using the definition of directional diagram given in the previous Section (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 3</ref>). For example,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 3A</ref>shows four directional diagrams of kinetic state '0', which result in four products and their sum as</p><formula>follows: Y 0 ¼ w 3 w 2 w 1 , u 1 u 2 u 3 , u 2 u 3 w 1 , u 3 w 2 w 1 f g ð 11Þ X 0 ¼ w 3 w 2 w 1 þ u 1 u 2 u 3 þ u 2 u 3 w 1 þ u 3 w 2 w 1 ð Þ ð 12Þ Similarly, Q i and P i , where i ¼ 1</formula><p>, 2, 3, are obtained from<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 3B</ref>–D, respectively. P total is the sum of all 16 products obtained from four states:</p><formula>X total ¼ X 0 þ X 1 þ X 2 þ X 3 ð13Þ</formula><p>Therefore, we define the distribution of probability over kinetic states s i (i ¼ 0, 1, 2, 3) as follows:</p><formula>Pðs 0 Þ ¼ w 3 w 2 w 1 þ u 1 u 2 u 3 þ u 2 u 3 w 1 þ u 3 w 2 w 1 P total ð14Þ Pðs 1 Þ ¼ u 0 w 3 w 2 þ w 0 w 3 w 2 þ u 0 u 2 u 3 þ u 3 u 0 w 2 P total ð15Þ Pðs 2 Þ ¼ u 0 u 1 w 3 þ u 3 u 0 u 1 þ w 1 w 0 w 3 þ u 1 w 0 w 3 P total ð16Þ Pðs 3 Þ ¼ u 0 u 1 u 2 þ w 2 w 1 w 0 þ u 2 w 1 w 0 þ u 1 u 2 w 0 P total ð17Þ</formula><p>where u i and w i (i ¼ 0, 1, 2, 3) are computed by Equations</p><p>(1) and</p><p>(2). Using Equations (14)–(17), the distribution of probability over the four kinetic states is plotted in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref>and shows a similar pattern to the mean waiting time over these states in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2</ref>. As it can be seen from<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4A</ref>, at low<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>and low loads the distribution of probability in kinetic state '0' is the highest. This is consistent with the obtained results of the mean waiting time over kinetic state '0' and confirms that at limiting<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>kinesin mainly stays in kinetic state '0' and waits for ATP binding (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Clancy et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hackney, 1994</ref>).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4A</ref>and B shows that the distribution of probability in kinetic state '0' peaks at maximum points of 0.93 and 0.43 at loads F ¼ 1.987 pN and F ¼ 2.754 pN, respectively, coincide with the crossoverare depicted as u i and w i , respectively, where i ¼ 0, 1, 2, 3 load points of P(u 0 ) and P(w 0 ) at<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>¼ 5 mM and 100 mM. These results imply that the probability of observing kinesin motor in kinetic state '0' will be the highest when the probabilities of ATP and ADP binding to the motor are equal, i.e. P(u 0 ) ¼ P(w 0 ). This also confirms our earlier results about the duration over kinetic state '0'. At high<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>and low loads, the plot shows that the distribution of probability in kinetic states '2' and '3' becomes dominant (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4C</ref>), in agreement with the obtained results of the durations of kinetic states '2' and '3' in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2C</ref>. It is also seen from<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4A</ref>–C that at high backward loads 410 pN and at all<ref type="bibr">[ATP]</ref>, the distribution of probability in kinetic states '2' and '3' is greater than that of other kinetic states. This suggests '2' and '3' as the first and second most probable kinetic states that kinesin motor stays at loads 410 pN, in agreement with the obtained results of the durations of these kinetic states and the reported kinetic states for the detachment of kinesin from MT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Schliwa, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Seitz and Surrey, 2006</ref>). The high distribution of probability in kinetic state '2' at high loads F stall 5F F detach confirms the long duration of this state due to the low rate of ATP synthesis.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>dependent rates presented in Equations (3) and (4) have been estimated by Fisher and Kolomeisky (2001) through regression on the experimental data of Block et al. in Schnitzer et al. (2000) and Visscher et al. (1999) at room temperature:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Probabilities of kinetic transitions versus load at different [ATP]. (A–C) Mean probabilities of forward and backward kinetic transitions, PðuÞ and PðwÞ . (D–F) Probabilities of the forward and backward transitions, P(u i ) and P(w i ) where i ¼ 0, 1, 2, 3</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. The mean waiting time over the four kinetic states, tðs i Þ where i ¼ 0, 1, 2, 3, versus load at different [ATP]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Distribution of probability over the four kinetic states, P(s i ) where i ¼ 0, 1, 2, 3, versus load at different [ATP]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Directional diagrams of kinetic states '0'–'3' depicted in parts (A–D), respectively. For clarity, the transitions rates u ðFÞ i and w ðFÞ i</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: Griffith University International Postgraduate Research Scholarship and the Australian Postgraduate Award Scholarship. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>and Kolomeisky (2001) defines a *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Estimated parameters of forward and backward transition rate equations (Fisher and Kolomeisky, 2001)</figDesc><table>State i 
u ð0Þ 
i (s À1 ) 
w ð0Þ 
i (s À1 ) 
þ 

i 

À 

i 

0 
— 
— 
0.120 
0.430 
1 
580 
40 
0.020 
0.130 
2 
290 
1.6 
0.020 
0.130 
3 
290 
40 
0.020 
0.130 </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2.</figDesc><table>Ratio of tðs 2 Þ 


to tðs i Þ 


at F ¼ 10.946 pN, where i ¼ 0, 1, 3 

ATP (mM) 
tðs 2 Þ 


/ tðs i Þ 



i ¼ 0 
i ¼ 1 
i ¼ 3 

5 
63.654 
5.067 
4.200 
100 
541.704 
5.067 
4.200 
2000 
2599.708 
5.067 
4.200 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">H.Khataee and A.Wee-Chung Liew at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Mathematics of mechanical kinetics of kinesin at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanics of the kinesin step</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Carter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Cross</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">435</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="308" to="312" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A universal pathway for kinesin stepping</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Clancy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1020" to="1027" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cellular motors for molecular manufacturing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Z</forename>
				<surname>Dinu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anat. Record</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">290</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1203" to="1212" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of spastic paraplegia mutations in KIF5A kinesin on transport activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Ebbing</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mol. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1245" to="1252" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinesin crouches to sprint but resists pushing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Fisher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16209" to="16214" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simple mechanochemistry describes the dynamics of kinesin molecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Fisher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Kolomeisky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7748" to="7753" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A smart dust biosensor powered by kinesin motors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Fischer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Nanotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="162" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Engineered, harnessed, and hijacked: synthetic uses for cytoskeletal systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Goodman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="644" to="652" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinesin ATPase: rate-limiting ADP release</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hackney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6314" to="6318" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence for alternating head catalysis by kinesin during microtubule-stimulated ATP hydrolysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hackney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 91</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 91</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6865" to="6869" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathway of ADP-stimulated ADP release and dissociation of tethered kinesin from microtubules. Implications for the extent of processivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hackney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4437" to="4446" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The tethered motor domain of a kinesin-microtubule complex catalyzes reversible synthesis of bound ATP</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hackney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18338" to="18343" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward devices powered by biomolecular motors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Hess</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">312</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="860" to="861" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Engineering applications of biomolecular motors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Hess</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Biomed. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="429" to="450" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetics of force generation by single kinesin molecules activated by laser photolysis of caged ATP</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Higuchi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4395" to="4400" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular motors in neurons: transport mechanisms and roles in brain function, development, and disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Hirokawa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="610" to="638" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modelling of internal architecture of kinesin nanomotor as a machine language</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Khataee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Ibrahim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IET Nanobiotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flexible autonomous behaviors of kinesin and muscle myosin bio-nanorobots</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Khataee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Industr. Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5116" to="5123" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular motors: a theorist&apos;s perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Kolomeisky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Fisher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Phys. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="675" to="695" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Magnetic capture from blood rescues molecular motor function in diagnostic nanodevices</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kumar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Nanobiotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Markov chain methods in enzyme kinetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Kurka</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Dvorak</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Porters versus rowers: a unified stochastic model of motor proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Leibler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Huse</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1357" to="1368" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemomechanical coupling of the forward and backward steps of single kinesin molecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nishiyama</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="790" to="797" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spontaneous motion in hierarchically assembled active matter</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Sanchez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">491</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="434" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Molecular Motors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Schliwa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<publisher>Wiley-VCH</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">257</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Weinheim, Germany</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Force production by single kinesin motors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Schnitzer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="718" to="723" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Processive movement of single kinesins on crowded microtubules visualized using quantum dots</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Seitz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Surrey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Axonopathy and transport deficits early in the pathogenesis of Alzheimer&apos;s diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Stokin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">307</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1282" to="1288" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entropy rectifies the Brownian steps of kinesin</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Taniguchi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="342" to="347" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinesin assembly and movement in cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Verhey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Biophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="288" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single kinesin molecules studied with a molecular force clamp</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Visscher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">400</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="189" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motion control at the nanoscale</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Manesh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Small</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="338" to="345" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct long-term observation of kinesin processivity at low load</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Yajima</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="306" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinesin walks hand-over-hand</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Yildiz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">303</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="676" to="678" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intramolecular strain coordinates kinesin stepping behavior along microtubules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Yildiz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1030" to="1041" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of kinesin family proteins in tumorigenesis and progression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Yu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Feng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5150" to="5160" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>