
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:46+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A profile-based method for identifying func-tional divergence of orthologous genes in bac-terial genomes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nicole</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Wheeler</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>nicole.wheeler@pg.canterbury.ac.nz, lars.barquist@uni-wuerzburg.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Canterbury</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Christchurch</settlement>
									<region>New Zealand</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Biomolecular Interac-tion Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Canterbury</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Christchurch</settlement>
									<region>New Zealand</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lars</forename>
								<surname>Barquist</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Molecular Infection Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Wuerzburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Wuerzburg, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">¶</forename>
								<forename type="middle">*</forename>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Robert</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Kingsley</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Food Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Norwich Research Park</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hinxton</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Paul</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Gardner</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Canterbury</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Christchurch</settlement>
									<region>New Zealand</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Biomolecular Interac-tion Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Canterbury</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Christchurch</settlement>
									<region>New Zealand</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Bio-protection Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Canter-bury</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Christchurch</settlement>
									<region>New Zealand</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A profile-based method for identifying func-tional divergence of orthologous genes in bac-terial genomes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Sequence analysis ¶ These authors contributed equally to this work. *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Availability: A program implementing DBS for pairwise genome comparisons is freely available at: https://github.com/UCanCompBio/deltaBS. Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Next generation sequencing technologies have provided us with a wealth of information on genetic variation, but predicting the functional significance of this variation is a difficult task. While many comparative genomics studies have focused on gene flux and large scale changes, relatively little attention has been paid to quantifying the effects of single nucleotide polymorphisms and indels on protein function, particularly in bacterial genomics. Results: We present a hidden Markov model based approach we call delta-bitscore (DBS) for identifying orthologous proteins that have diverged at the amino acid sequence level in a way that is likely to impact biological function. We benchmark this approach with several widely used datasets and apply it to a proof-of-concept study of orthologous proteomes in an investigation of host adaptation in Salmonella enterica. We highlight the value of the method in identifying functional divergence of genes, and suggest that this tool may be a better approach than the commonly used dN/dS metric for identifying functionally significant genetic changes occurring in recently diverged organisms.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Genome sequencing technologies allow us to explore the wealth of genetic variation between and within species, and as these technologies advance this data is becoming progressively cheaper, faster, and easier to produce (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Loman et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Koren and Phillippy, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Loman and Pallen, 2015</ref>). However, analysis of the functional impact of genetic variation has lagged behind, and has largely focused on the presence or absence of macroscopic features such as particular genes, genomic islands, or plasmids. Comparative sequence analyses have become common, and exploration of genetic variation between closely-related organisms has provided key insights into bacterial evolution (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Croucher and Didelot, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bryant et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Barquist and Vogel, 2015</ref>). In particular, the analysis of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) has been a tremendous boon to the study of bacterial populations, allowing for the construction of phylogenetic trees which provide information on disease transmission and adaptation at scales ranging from global pandemics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Mutreja et al., 2011</ref>) to outbreaks within single hospital wards (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Harris et al., 2013</ref>). Still, the functional analysis of these SNPs, insertions, and Associate Editor: Dr. Inanc Birol © The Author(s) 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. deletions within protein sequences remains difficult, and often relies on inappropriate tools such as dN/dS. How then can the significance of fine-scale genetic variation be quantified and prioritized for investigation? Recent studies have shown that even single SNPs can have dramatic effects on major phenotypes such as host tropism (<ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Viana et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Yue et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Singletary et al., 2016</ref>). Studies of pathogen adaptation, for example the adaptation of Pseudomonas aeruginosa to the cystic fibrosis lung (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Marvig et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Jorth et al., 2015</ref>) or of Salmonella enterica to immunocompromised populations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Feasey et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Okoro et al., 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Okoro et al., , 2015</ref>), often result in findings of hundreds to thousands of SNPs and small indels in coding regions. Genome-wide association studies provide one method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Chewapreecha et al., 2014</ref>) for interpreting this variation, however the clonal nature of many pathogens can make such study designs difficult if not impossible to pursue and require large sample sizes to be effective. The development of fast and accurate ways to assess the functional impact of variation between strains and prioritize coding variants for follow-up work is an important step in extracting meaning from comparative analyses.</p><p>Our strategy uses a profile HMM-based approach. Profile HMMs are probabilistic models of multiple sequence alignments. For each column in the alignment they capture information on the expected frequency of occurrence of different amino acids, insertions, and deletions. We can then use this information to compute a score, which we call deltabitscore (DBS) for reasons explained below, that quantifies the divergence of two protein sequences with respect to the conservation patterns captured by the profile HMM. Our key assumption in this is that variation in positions conserved across a protein family are more likely to affect protein function than variation in less conserved positions. Similar assumptions have had success in a number of applications such as the prediction of tRNA pseudogenes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lowe and Eddy, 1997</ref>) and protein folds (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Marks et al., 2012</ref>). Our approach is unique in both the simplicity of the measure used, and its flexibility, making it well suited to comparative genomic applications. We demonstrate that our method is effective using several commonly used protein mutagenesis datasets, particularly when used with automatically constructed protein alignments. We provide an example of a comparative genomic analysis, by applying our approach to a whole proteome analysis of a well-studied case of host adaptation in Salmonella enterica serovars Enteritidis and Gallinarum, using a purpose built collection of HMMs. We additionally show these results generalize to other host-adapted salmonellae. Finally, we compare our method to a popular estimate of selection, dN/dS, and find that the two measures are only weakly correlated. This adds to the evidence that dN/dS is not an appropriate measure for inferring selection for gene function within bacterial populations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Benchmarking</head><p>In order to test the ability of profile HMMs to identify loss-of-function mutations we used three independent datasets from protein mutagenesis studies on HIV-1 protease (336 sequences) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Loeb et al., 1989</ref>), E. coli Lac I (4041 sequences) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Markiewicz et al., 1994</ref>), and phage lysozyme (2015 sequences) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Rennell et al., 1991</ref>). In these experiments, residues in the protein were systematically mutated and the impact of these mutations on protein function was quantified. The data were downloaded from the SIFT website (http://sift.bii.a-star.edu.sg/) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kumar et al., 2009</ref>). For binary classification of mutants, proteins with a classification of " + " were termed functional mutants and " +-" , "-+ " , and "-" were termed loss of function mutants. We tested two different reference HMM sets: curated HMMs from the Pfam database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Punta et al., 2012</ref>), and automatically constructed HMMs built using a range of residue identity cutoff values. We also compared these results to predictions made by the PROVEAN, SIFT and Mutation Assessor methods. PROVEAN results were downloaded pre-computed from their website. Otherwise, all methods were tested using their default settings. Exclusion of positions in the protein with low coverage in the SIFT database have only a marginal effect on SIFT performance (0.7 to 0.71 AUC in lysozyme dataset), and results in loss of data, so we use all sequence variants in our analysis. In order to evaluate the accuracy of each method we computed the 'Area Above the Curve' (AAC) for a series of Relative Cost Curve (RCC) plots (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Montvida and Klawonn, 2014</ref>). These values range between one and zero with an AAC equal to one indicating a perfect prediction tool across the range of relative costs tested. The Biocomb package (www.cran.rproject.org/package=Biocomb) was used with default relative costs unless otherwise specified to calculate AAC scores, and the ROCR package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Sing et al., 2005</ref>) was used to calculate other performance metrics, which can be found in Supplementary Table 1. For the construction of custom HMMs, query sequences were searched against the Uniref90 database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Suzek et al., 2015</ref>) using a single iteration of jackhmmer. Pairwise sequence identity was calculated as the number of matches between sequence pairs, divided by total length of the alignment after the removal of gap-gap columns. HMMs were built using hmmbuild, and DBS was calculated using hmmsearch, subtracting the bitscore value for the variant sequence from the bitscore value for the wild type sequence. jackhmmer, hmmbuild and hmmsearch are part of the HMMER3 package (version 3.1b2). Protein HMMs were built using a range of sequence identity cutoffs in order to determine the optimal range for performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Proteome analysis</head><p>We have designed this approach with whole proteome analyses in mind, so as a proof-of-concept, we applied the approach to the study of host adaptation in Salmonella enterica, using S. Enteritidis and S. Gallinarum as a specific example. For a summary of the workflow of this portion of the analysis, see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. Genomes for Salmonella Enteritidis str. P125109 (AM933172.1) and Salmonella Gallinarum str. 287/91 (AM933173.1) were retrieved. Custom gene models were constructed by searching each S. Enteritidis protein coding gene against the Uniref90 database. Profiles were built using sequences showing 40% or greater sequence identity to the original query protein.</p><p>In order to assess whether models built from a small number of sequences performed well, we tested the performance of models using proteins from the humsavar database (http://www.uniprot.org/docs/humsavar), which catalogs human polymorphisms and disease variants for a wide range of proteins which have different levels of representation in Uniprot90, and therefore result in profile models built from varying numbers of sequences. We built custom models for each protein in the database, then separated the models into classes based on both number of sequences and effective sequence number. We then computed AUC values for predictions made on variant data from each class. Results from this test can be found in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table 2</ref>. We saw no classes where custom models performed worse than Pfam models, so we did not filter models built from few sequences. We did, however, use Pfam models for those proteins with no homologs in Uniref90 rather than build a model from the query sequence, as we felt this could bias results towards the reference species. To assess the quality of our analysis, we wished to compare our results to those of Nuccio and Bäumler (2014), so we used the ortholog calls provided in their supplementary material. Genes represented by a custom model were scored using the appropriate model (n=3154), all others were scored using Pfam domain models. hmmsearch was used for scoring. If hits to multiple Pfam models occurred, any overlapping hits were competed based on E-value. Orthologs with incompatible Pfam domain architectures (n=32) were excluded from scoring, but counted as hypothetically attenuated coding sequences (HACs) in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2A</ref>if they involved a loss of domain in one serovar. We anticipate that the variance of delta-bitscores will increase with evolutionary distance, so rather than establish a fixed scoring cutoff for HACs, we identify loss-of-function mutations using an empirical distribution. We set a score threshold at which 2.5% of genes on the least dispersed side of the distribution would be called as HACs. If the two bacteria show an equal rate of protein function loss, this would result in 5% of orthologous proteins being called as HACs, however if one proteome shows a greater degree of functional degradation, this will result in a greater proportion of orthologs being classified as HACs.</p><p>Functional classification was performed using pathways from the KEGG database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kanehisa et al., 2016</ref>). We grouped genes into four categories: those present in a pathway but with no ortholog in the other serovar; genes identified as hypothetically disrupted coding sequences (HDCs) by<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Nuccio and Bäumler (2014)</ref>; genes identified by our DBS method as HACs, but not as HDCs; and finally genes not identified as nonfunctional by either method. dN/dS values were calculated using PAML (<ref type="bibr">Yang, 1997</ref>), and for the comparison of DBS and dN/dS, genes were filtered for those with dN&gt;0 and dS&gt;0.0001. Correlations between measures were computed using a Spearman's rho statistic (R package cor).As a comparison, we used DBS in two distinct ways. In the first, we calculated DBS scores based on alignments to curated Pfam domains (<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Punta et al., 2012</ref>). In the second, we constructed profile-HMMs containing sequences of varying minimal sequence identity. These two approaches to model construction capture distinct forms of information: Pfam domains are designed to capture maximal sequence diversity, and focus on deeply conserved domains within protein sequences. Additionally, many families are manually curated, and the alignment of known functional regions, such as active sites, may have been improved in some cases. Our custom profiles capture full length protein sequences. This means that the functions of sequences captured by custom models may be narrower than those captured by Pfam, and additionally will capture linker regions between conserved domains, which may nevertheless be functionally important.</p><p>Our benchmark showed that custom HMMs built at 40% identity outperformed other methods in terms of area above the relative cost curve (AAC) and maximum Matthew's correlation coefficient, with the exception of the superior performance of SIFT and PROVEAN on the HIV protease data (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1A</ref>, and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>). DBS using Pfam models had the best specificity across all datasets tested, but at the expense of sensitivity (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1B</ref>, Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>). This suggests that Pfam models are indeed capturing ancient features of protein families, and may be useful in cases where a low false-positive rate is desired at the expense of potentially missing variants. Our custom models meanwhile appeared to perform optimally with a 40% identity cutoff (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1A</ref>, C). Interestingly, 40% sequence identity has previously been proposed as a rule of thumb identity cutoff for the transfer of enzyme annotations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Addou et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Tian and Skolnick, 2003</ref>), indicating that this cutoff may reflect a common point of functional divergence in protein families.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">DBS identifies pathways associated with host range restriction in Salmonella Gallinarum</head><p>We have established that DBS can detect functionally relevant mutations. To explore the utility of this approach in a comparative genomics context, we developed a tool that takes whole proteome files as input, builds custom HMMs where applicable and uses Pfam HMMs to score the remaining genes, in order to identify functionally significant variation between two proteomes. Using this tool, we compared the proteomes of two closely related Salmonella enterica serovars that have expe-rienced contrasting selective pressures leading to host-restriction for one of them. Host-restriction is a common phenomenon in highly adapted invasive pathogens, often characterized by genomic features such as the proliferation of transposable elements and the degradation of substantial fractions of coding sequences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Moran and Plague, 2004</ref>; Goodhead and Darby, 2015). Within Salmonella enterica such restriction events have occurred independently multiple times in various hosts from broad host-range ancestors. Salmonella enterica serovar Enteritidis is a broad host-range pathogen, capable of infecting humans, cattle, rodents and a variety of birds, while the closely related serovar Gallinarum is restricted to infecting galliforme birds (<ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Rabsch et al., 2002</ref>). S. Gallinarum and S. Enteritidis have recently evolved from a common ancestor, however the S. Gallinarum genome has undergone extensive degradation since divergence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Thomson et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Langridge et al., 2015</ref>). In addition to being restricted to a narrow host range, S. Gallinarum has lost motility and causes a systemic, typhoid-like infection in birds, unlike Enteritidis which usually causes a self-limiting gastroenteritis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Thomson et al., 2008</ref>). A recent analysis of pseudogenes within this and other invasive Salmonella lineages identified signatures of host-restriction, characterized particularly by the loss of metabolic genes required for survival in the intestine (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Langridge et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Nuccio and Bäumler, 2014</ref>). Both of these analyses involved the manual comparison of coding sequences to identify mutations that would result in frameshifts or truncated proteins. We expect DBS to add an additional layer of information to such an analysis, identifying genes which have shifted in or lost function due to non-synonymous mutations or small indels occurring since the restriction event, but have not yet succumbed to obvious disruption events such as large truncations, frameshifts, or complete deletions. As shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2A</ref>, our loss-of-function predictions included many genes not identified as hypothetically disrupted coding sequences (HDCs) by manual inspection (Nuccio and Bäumler, 2014).We examined the concurrence between our loss of function calls and those made by Nuccio and Bäumler. Of 252 HDCs identified in S. Gallinarum but not in S. Enteritidis from the previous study, 148 of these were also classified as HACs by DBS, and a further 6 as HACs due to a loss of a domain in the S. Gallinarum copy of the gene (61% total agreement). Of the 104 disagreements, 28 genes had a DBS score below the threshold, and 70 were excluded from scoring analysis for having incompatible domain architectures (n=14) or no hits for either protein sequence to the Pfam database or any of our custom models (n=56). Of these 56, over half were fewer than 150 amino acids long, often due to extreme truncations or early frameshifts (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table 3</ref>). Of the 28 low scoring variants, many involved short truncations, alternate starts or indels of &lt;10 amino acids. The remainder involved S. Gallinarum pseudogenes that had no hits to custom models or Pfam domains in the truncated region. In many cases our models showed low sequence conservation and gaps in the regions affected by mutation. As expected, the distribution of DBS values centers around zero (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure  2B</ref>), showing that most orthologous gene pairs differ from the modeled sequence constraints to a similar degree. The distribution of DBS values shows an enrichment for positive DBS (exact binomial test, P = 2.18 e35), indicating greater divergence from the profile models for protein coding genes from S. Gallinarum when compared to S. Enteritidis. While some of these positive DBS values may indicate functional divergence rather than pseudogenization, extreme DBS values predominantly correspond to truncations, indels and mutations in highly conserved sites, so we assume that in these cases the ancestral function has been lost. To look at these hypothetically attenuated coding sequences (HACs) in a functional context, we grouped genes into functional categories based on their annotation in the KEGG database. Not only does S. Gallinarum have fewer genes than S. Enteritidis for most of the functional categories we considered (data not shown), but it also has a greater number of HACs across these groupings (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2A</ref>). Previous work that found the presence of non-ancestral pseudogenes in S. Enteritidis was limited while S. Gallinarum had accumulated a large number of pseudogenes since divergence is consistent with our results (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Langridge et al., 2015</ref>). In our analysis we found a number of results which are in agreement with previously published findings. Degradation of genes involved in chemotaxis is consistent with a loss of motility in this strain, and previously identified degradation of chemotaxis genes in other host adapted strains (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kingsley et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">McClelland et al., 2004</ref>). Fimbriae are also thought to be important for host colonisation by Salmonella, and we found high DBS values for bcfA, bcfC and stfG. Pseudogenization of other genes in these operons have already been identified in S. Gallinarum (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Foley et al., 2013</ref>). We found a number of HACs in genes involved in the utilization of nutrients derived from the inflamed host gut environment colonized by gastrointestinal serovars of Salmonella (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Nuccio and Bäumler, 2014</ref>) (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table 5</ref>). This is consistent with the recent adaptation of S. Gallinarum from an ancestral gastrointestinal pathogen to an extra-intestinal environment. Among the most highly ranked genes were representatives of the cbi, pdu, and eut operons, previously identified as central pathways subject to gene decay in S. Gallinarum (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Langridge et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Nuccio and Bäumler, 2014</ref>). A complete table of DBS values for orthologous genes can be found in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table 6</ref>.</p><p>These findings demonstrate that DBS provides an additional layer of information about gene function in addition to gene deletion when investigating serovars that have recently diverged. As time since divergence increases we expect that non-functional genes will be deleted and the ratio of non-functional and deleted genes will change. We anticipate that our method will be most useful in comparisons of organisms which have recently diverged, as it offers an opportunity to identify loss-of-function mutations that occur as an immediate response to a new environment and restricted population size, before deletion of entire genes occurs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kuo and Ochman, 2010</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">DBS does not correlate strongly with dN/dS</head><p>In comparing genome sequences, we have focused on identifying functionally significant variation, whereas a common approach is to classify genes from an evolutionary point of view, i.e. to identify genes are under negative selection, positive selection or that are evolving neutrally. A commonly used measure of selection is dN/dS (ω), which compares the rate of nonsynonymous changes in protein-coding sequences to the rate of synonymous changes to classify genes as either negative selection (ω &lt; 1), positive selection (ω &gt; 1) or neutrally evolving (ω ≈ 1) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Yang and Bielawski, 2000</ref>). While dN/dS is an inappropriate metric to use in comparing bacteria at the strain level (<ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Rocha et al., 2006</ref>), the metric is nevertheless used in similar situations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Roumagnac et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Fleischmann et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Holden et al., 2004</ref>), so we compared the results of the commonly used PAML program and DBS. In comparing the results from the two approaches, one of the most striking results is that there is little correlation between DBS and both dN/dS (R ≈0.17) and dN (R ≈0.18). Of the genes with high DBS and low dN/dS, most of these can be attributed to insertions and deletions, which are ignored by dN/dS but can have significant impacts on the functioning of a protein. Genes with low DBS and high dN/dS tend to carry a small number of nonsynonymous changes, most of which are between chemically similar residues, and a smaller number of synonymous mutations.To test whether a positively skewed DBS distribution was a common feature of host adaptation in Salmonella, we performed DBS analysis on three broad host range and three host-adapted Salmonella serovars. Rather than performing many pairwise comparisons to call HACs, for this analysis we compared bitscores for each gene to the median gene bitscore of the six strains. We found that host-restricted serovars showed a greater number of HACs than generalist serovars across all strains tested (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3A</ref>). We previously observed a similar phenomenon in host-restricted strains of S. Typhimurium (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kingsley et al., 2013</ref>). We observed a striking similarity in the score distributions of generalist strains, and in host-adapted strains (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>), with the generalist scores being lower overall than the host restricted scores. It is interesting to note that most of the separation in scores occurs at DBS values below our cutoff value for HAC classification (DBS = 8.2, Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>, top panel). Based on our benchmarking, if these proteins were tested in vitro many of them would show differences in function, but whether these differences relate to differences in intracellular and environmental conditions shaping the sequence requirements for these proteins or whether they relate to true declines in function is difficult to assess without experimental validation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.7">DBS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Discussion</head><p>We have described a surprisingly simple method for identifying functional divergence in orthologous proteins, including analysis of both point mutations and indel events. Despite the simplicity of the DBS measure, its accuracy is similar to state-of-the-art methods for predicting the functional impact of sequence variants. While curated Pfam models were less sensitive, they have a high specificity at conservative scoring thresholds (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>, Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>). The workflow for using such models is simpler (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure  1</ref>), and may be more appropriate for investigations where a low falsepositive rate is more important than detection of all loss-of-function mutations. In addition, while construction of custom models can be timeconsuming to run on a desktop computer, Pfam annotation can be performed rapidly. Because other methods for estimating the impact of sequence variation, such as SIFT, PROVEAN and MutationAssessor, require the user to specify mutations individually, broad scale comparative proteome analysis such as this is difficult and time-intensive to perform, and not all methods are able to score indels or more than one mutation in the same sequence. Both DBS approaches scale to whole proteome analysis with minimal user involvement (see Github page for pipelines), and were able to detect additional loss of function mutations that were missed by previous studies focused on protein truncations and frameshifts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.8">DBS for the study of bacterial adaptation</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. (A) Area above the relative cost curve (AAC) values for different analysis methods using three mutagenesis benchmarking datasets: phage lysozyme, LacI and HIV protease. The performance for each model across a range of sequence identity cutoffs is shown, as well as AAC values for the individual methods. AAC of 1.0 indicates perfect performance.; (B) Distribution of delta-bitscores for E. coli LacI using custom model analysis; (C) Distribution of delta-bitscores for E. coli LacI using Pfam model analysis.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. The results of a DBS comparison of the proteomes of S. Enteritidis (a generalist infectious agent) and S. Gallinarum (a host-restricted infectious agent). (A) The functional changes in orthologous protein-coding genes of S. Enteritidis and S. Gallinarum have been grouped into functional categories using the KEGG pathways database. Genes included in the pathway that have no ortholog in the other serovar are indicated in the darkest colour, followed by genes previously identified as hypothetically disrupted coding sequences (HDCs), then genes with significant DBS values that had not already been identified as HDCs. We refer to these as hypothetically attenuated coding sequences (HACs); (B) The distribution of delta-bitscores for orthologous genes showing non-synonymous changes in S. Enteritidis and S. Gallinarum. A symmetrical empirical distribution of scores generated by mirroring the least dispersed side is shown in red, the cutoff values we use to establish significance are shown as dashed lines. A skewed distribution implies excess functional changes in one lineage; (C) A plot of the dN/dS score and corresponding DBS is shown for each orthologous S. Enteritidis and S. Gallinarum gene.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>reveals trends of gene degradation across hostadapted Salmonella</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Counts of hypothetically attenuated coding sequences (HACs) for each serovar, identified as the most extreme deviations from the median bitscore across strains for each gene. The generalist serovars are coloured in dark grey, host-restricted serovars are coloured in light grey.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Yang,H. et al. (2014) Genome-Scale Metabolic Network Validation of Shewanella oneidensis Using Transposon Insertion Frequency Analysis. PLoS Comput. Biol., 10, e1003848. Yang,Z. (1997) PAML: a program package for phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood. Comput. Appl. Biosci., 13, 555–556. Yue,M. et al. (2015) Allelic variation contributes to bacterial host specificity. Nat. Commun., 6, 8754.</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">In our investigation of multiple S. enterica isolates, for all orthologous groups with a gene present in S. Enteritidis, scores were collated, and if individual scores were significantly different to the median score for all isolates, we identified these proteins as HACs. Significant difference was calculated in a similar way to the pairwise comparisons, with the score corresponding to the most extreme 2.5% of delta-bitscores on the least dispersed side of an empirical distribution being used as the cutoff. 3 Results 3.3 The delta-bitscore measure Alignment of a protein sequence to a profile HMM produces a bitscore value, which is the log odds ratio for this sequence under the profile HMM compared to a random null model, and serves as an indication of protein family membership. In subtracting the bitscore of one protein or domain from that of another, we produce a measure of the divergence between the two proteins, taking into consideration conservation patterns captured by the protein family model. We define delta-bitscore using the following equation: DBS = x ref-x var Where DBS is delta-bitscore and, xref and xvar are bitscores for reference and variant sequences derived from alignments to the same profile HMM. Highly conserved positions in a model alignment contribute more to bitscores than poorly conserved positions, meaning that unexpected mutations or indels in conserved sites are given a greater penalty than mutations in variable sites. In addition, the replacement of residues with chemically and structurally similar residues is generally scored more favourably than mutation to dissimilar residues. Multiple functionally neutral changes are likely to result in individual contributions to the bitscore that are small in magnitude and that cancel out over the length of the protein, while functionally significant change in a protein will likely produce one or more position-specific values of high magnitude that have a greater impact on overall DBS for the sequence. We first introduced this measure as part of studies of Salmonella adaptation to an wild avian host (Kingsley et al., 2013), and during within-host evolution of a hypermutator strain of Salmonella Enteritidis in an immunocompromised patient (Klemm et al., 2016), and elaborate upon it here. The Supplementary Text contains further discussion of this measure and comparisons with related measures derived from profile HMMs (Clifford et al., 2004; Shihab et al., 2013; Liu et al., 2015). 3.4 DBS is predictive of protein functional status Evaluating the performance of different methods for the quantification of the effects of sequence variation is challenging. For the case of human variation, some datasets exist, however given the limited amount of data available on functional protein variants care must be taken to avoid circularity in training and testing (Boulesteix, 2010; Grimm et al., 2015). While we have not comprehensively benchmarked DBS on human data sets given our focus on prokaryotic variation, we found it is competitive with other untrained methods (Supplementary Figures 3,4), despite its simplicity. In the case of bacterial variation we are not aware of wellcharacterized collections of protein variants. Rather, to test our method we compared its performance to a selection of methods on three large scale protein mutagenesis datasets (Kumar et al., 2009) (Figure 1A, Supplementary Figure 2 shows AUC values for the same analysis). A number of methods have been designed for predicting the impact of sequence variation on the function of non-human proteins, and we compare our measure to three competitive methods here (Grimm et al., 2015). These include: PROVEAN, which uses a BLAST-based approach to score sequence variants using closely related sequences (Choi et al., 2012); the SIFT algorithm which uses position-specific scoring matrices based on sequence homology and known patterns of common amino acid substitutions to predict the functional consequences of non-synonymous single nucleotide polymorphisms (nsSNPs) (Kumar et al., 2009); and MutationAssessor which computes both the conservation and specificity of residues within protein subfamilies to assess the impact of a mutation (Reva et al., 2011). at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Large scale genomic studies of bacterial pathogens have revealed striking similarities in evolutionary patterns in diverse pathogenic and symbiotic lineages. While adaptation to a new environment may involve the acquisition of new fitness determinants and rare, beneficial mutations, niche adaptation is also frequently accompanied by widespread loss-offunction mutations, particularly in pathogenic and symbiotic lineages. These loss-of-function mutations are likely generated through a number of distinct processes (Moran, 2002), including neutral or slightly deleterious stochastic loss due to reductions in effective population size, neutral loss of genes no longer required in the new environment, and adaptive loss (Hottes et al., 2013). DBS presents an opportunity to mine the genomes of bacteria adapting to new environments for these loss of function mutations, which may tell us as much about bacteria&apos;s adaptation to new environments as the acquisition of new genes. Comparative approaches based on pseudogene analysis have identified consistent signatures of adaptation in a number of bacterial pathogens, including Yersinia (Reuter et al., 2014; McNally et al., 2016), E. coli and Shigella (Monk et al., 2013; Feng et al., 2011), and Salmonella (Langridge et al., 2015; Nuccio and Bäumler, 2014). Our analysis of Salmonella genomes has shown that DBS is consistent with these previous studies, while providing additional sensitivity to detect non-functional or functionally divergent protein variants that may have been missed by pseudogene analyses (Kingsley et al., 2013). 3.9 DBS as a more appropriate alternative to dN/dS for studying evolution across short time scales While dN/dS can be a powerful approach to identifying genes under positive selection across long time scales, on shorter timescales it has been shown to be inaccurate, due to the lag in the removal of slightly deleterious mutations This leads to high dN/dS ratios being commonplace in comparisons of closely related strains, suggesting positive or relaxed selection where there is none (Rocha et al., 2006). Other studies have shown that dN/dS can provide inaccurate, even contradictory, results depending on the structure of the population being sampled (Kryazhimskiy and Plotkin, 2008). In spite of this, dN/dS is still commonly used in comparisons of closely related bacteria. Due to the unreliability of dN/dS measures at short evolutionary timescales and the inability of dN/dS based methods to score indels, we propose that DBS is a more suitable analysis tool for the study of functional divergence in recently diverged strains. In contrast, we would advise caution in the use of DBS on more divergent organisms, with careful consideration of the effects of sequence divergence on bitscore. Over time each lineage could accumulate mutations that affect protein function in different ways, but have the same degree of impact on bitscore, leading to a net DBS near zero. This does not necessarily indicate preservation of function and may instead indicate equal divergence from ancestral function. We have not examined the performance of DBS on deeply diverged lineages, partly for lack of data. Our observation that DBS performs optimally when reference alignments are in the 40 percent.identity range suggests sequences more divergent than this may be outside the range where can DBS provide meaningful information, but this will require additional investigation to establish. 3.10 Concluding remark We anticipate that this approach will be a useful addition to traditional comparative genomics workflows. It provides an effective method for scoring the functional potential of the overwhelming numbers of nonsynonymous variants that can distinguish closely related bacteria, allowing better prioritisation for further experimental investigation.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We would like to thank Fatemeh Ashari Ghomi for her contributions, and Sean Eddy for his clarification of some technical aspects of the HMMER3 software.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Domain-based and family-specific sequence identity thresholds increase the levels of reliable protein function transfer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Addou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">387</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="416" to="430" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approaches to querying bacterial genomes with transposon-insertion sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Barquist</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RNA Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1161" to="1169" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accelerating Discovery and Functional Analysis of Small RNAs with New Technologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Barquist</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Vogel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="394" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Over-optimism in bioinformatics research</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A.-L</forename>
				<surname>Boulesteix</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="439" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing insights into the mechanisms of evolution of bacterial pathogens from whole-genome sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Bryant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Future Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1283" to="1296" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive identification of single nucleotide polymorphisms associated with beta-lactam resistance within pneumococcal mosaic genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Chewapreecha</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1004547</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting the functional effect of amino acid substitutions and indels</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Choi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">46688</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale analysis of non-synonymous coding region single nucleotide polymorphisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Clifford</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1006" to="1014" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The application of genomics to tracing bacterial pathogen transmission</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Croucher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Didelot</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accelerated Profile HMM Searches</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Eddy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002195</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Invasive non-typhoidal salmonella disease: an emerging and neglected tropical disease in Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Feasey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">379</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2489" to="2499" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene decay in Shigella as an incipient stage of hostadaptation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Feng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">27754</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole-Genome Comparison of Mycobacterium tuberculosis Clinical and Laboratory Strains</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Fleischmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bacteriol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">184</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5479" to="5490" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Salmonella pathogenicity and host adaptation in chickenassociated serovars</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Foley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="582" to="607" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Taking the pseudo out of pseudogenes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Goodhead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Darby</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evaluation of tools used to predict the impact of missense variants is hindered by two types of circularity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Grimm</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mutat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="523" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole-genome sequencing for analysis of an outbreak of meticillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus: a descriptive study</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Harris</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet Infect. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Complete genomes of two clinical Staphylococcus aureus strains: evidence for the rapid evolution of virulence and drug resistance</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T G</forename>
				<surname>Holden</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9786" to="9791" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bacterial adaptation through loss of function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Hottes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003617</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regional Isolation Drives Bacterial Diversification within Cystic Fibrosis Lungs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Jorth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Host Microbe</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="319" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KEGG as a reference resource for gene and protein annotation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kanehisa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome and transcriptome adaptation accompanying emergence of the definitive type 2 host-restricted Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium pathovar</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Kingsley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MBio</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="565" to="578" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emergence of host-adapted Salmonella Enteritidis through rapid evolution in an immunocompromised host</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Klemm</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Microbiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15023</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">One chromosome, one contig: complete microbial genomes from long-read sequencing and assembly</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Koren</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Phillippy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The population genetics of dN/dS</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kryazhimskiy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Plotkin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting the effects of coding non-synonymous variants on protein function using the SIFT algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Kumar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1073" to="1081" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The extinction dynamics of bacterial pseudogenes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C.-H</forename>
				<surname>Kuo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Ochman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patterns of genome evolution that have accompanied host adaptation in Salmonella</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Langridge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="863" to="868" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HMMvar-func: a new method for predicting the functional outcome of genetic variants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">351</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Complete mutagenesis of the HIV-1 protease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Loeb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">340</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="400" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-throughput bacterial genome sequencing: an embarrassment of choice, a world of opportunity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Loman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="599" to="606" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Twenty years of bacterial genome sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Loman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Pallen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="787" to="794" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">tRNAscan-SE: a program for improved detection of transfer RNA genes in genomic sequence</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Lowe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Eddy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="955" to="964" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic studies of the lac repressor. XIV. Analysis of 4000 altered Escherichia coli lac repressors reveals essential and nonessential residues, as well as&apos; spacers&apos; which do not require a specific sequence</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Markiewicz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">240</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="421" to="433" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein structure prediction from sequence variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Marks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1072" to="1080" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convergent evolution and adaptation of Pseudomonas aeruginosa within patients with cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Marvig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of genome degradation in Paratyphi A and Typhi, human-restricted serovars of Salmonella enterica that cause typhoid</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Mcclelland</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1268" to="1274" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Add, stir and reduce&apos;: Yersinia spp. as model bacteria for pathogen evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Mcnally</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-scale metabolic reconstructions of multiple Escherichia coli strains highlight strain-specific adaptations to nutritional environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Monk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20338" to="20343" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relative cost curves: An alternative to AUC and an extension to 3-class problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Montvida</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Klawonn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Kybernetika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="647" to="660" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microbial minimalism: genome reduction in bacterial pathogens</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Moran</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="583" to="586" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic changes following host restriction in bacteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Moran</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Plague</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="627" to="633" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence for several waves of global transmission in the seventh cholera pandemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Mutreja</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">477</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="465" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reliabilities of identifying positive selection by the branch-site and the site-prediction methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nozawa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6700" to="6705" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative analysis of Salmonella genomes identifies a metabolic network for escalating growth in the inflamed gut</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S.-P</forename>
				<surname>Nuccio</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Bäumler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MBio</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="929" to="943" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intracontinental spread of human invasive Salmonella Typhimurium pathovariants in sub-Saharan Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Okoro</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1215" to="1221" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Signatures of adaptation in human invasive Salmonella Typhimurium ST313 populations from sub-Saharan Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Okoro</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Negl. Trop. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3611</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Pfam protein families database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Punta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Salmonella enterica serotype Typhimurium and its hostadapted variants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Rabsch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infect. Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2249" to="2255" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic mutation of bacteriophage T4 lysozyme</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Rennell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">222</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="88" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parallel independent evolution of pathogenicity within the genus Yersinia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Reuter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6768" to="6773" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting the functional impact of protein mutations: application to cancer genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Reva</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">118</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Salmonella uses energy taxis to benefit from intestinal inflammation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Rivera-Chávez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Pathog</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003267</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparisons of dN/dS are time dependent for closely related bacterial genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P C</forename>
				<surname>Rocha</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">239</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="226" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolutionary history of Salmonella typhi</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Roumagnac</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">314</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1301" to="1304" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting the functional, molecular, and phenotypic consequences of amino acid substitutions using hidden Markov models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Shihab</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mutat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Loss of Multicellular Behavior in Epidemic African Nontyphoidal Salmonella enterica Serovar Typhimurium ST313 Strain D23580</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Singletary</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MBio</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ROCR: visualizing classifier performance in R</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Sing</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3940" to="3941" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UniRef clusters: a comprehensive and scalable alternative for improving sequence similarity searches</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Suzek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="926" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative genome analysis of Salmonella Enteritidis PT4 and Salmonella Gallinarum 287/91 provides insights into evolutionary and host adaptation pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Thomson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1624" to="1637" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How well is enzyme function conserved as a function of pairwise sequence identity?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Tian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Skolnick</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">333</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="863" to="882" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A single natural nucleotide mutation alters bacterial pathogen host tropism</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Viana</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical methods for detecting molecular adaptation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Bielawski</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="496" to="503" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>