
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:41+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression A statistical framework for Illumina DNA methylation arrays</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">. 22 2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pei</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Fen</forename>
								<surname>Kuan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<settlement>Chapel Hill</settlement>
									<region>NC</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sijian</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics and Medical Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Wisconsin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>53792</postCode>
									<settlement>Madison</settlement>
									<region>WI</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xin</forename>
								<surname>Zhou</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Haitao</forename>
								<surname>Chu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Minnesota</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>55455</postCode>
									<settlement>Minneapolis</settlement>
									<region>MN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression A statistical framework for Illumina DNA methylation arrays</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2849" to="2855"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">. 22 2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq553</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 18, 2010; revised on September 9, 2010; accepted on September 23, 2010</note>
					<note>[12:04 19/10/2010 Bioinformatics-btq553.tex] Page: 2849 2849–2855 Associate Editor: Martin Bishop http://www.unc.edu/∼pfkuan/LumiWCluster Contact: pfkuan@bios.unc.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The Illumina BeadArray is a popular platform for profiling DNA methylation, an important epigenetic event associated with gene silencing and chromosomal instability. However, current approaches rely on an arbitrary detection P-value cutoff for excluding probes and samples from subsequent analysis as a quality control step, which results in missing observations and information loss. It is desirable to have an approach that incorporates the whole data, but accounts for the different quality of individual observations. Results: We first investigate and propose a statistical framework for removing the source of biases in Illumina Methylation BeadArray based on several positive control samples. We then introduce a weighted model-based clustering called LumiWCluster for Illumina BeadArray that weights each observation according to the detection P-values systematically and avoids discarding subsets of the data. LumiWCluster allows for discovery of distinct methylation patterns and automatic selection of informative CpG loci. We demonstrate the advantages of LumiWCluster on two publicly available Illumina GoldenGate Methylation datasets (ovarian cancer and hepatocellular carcinoma). Availability: R package LumiWCluster can be downloaded from</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>DNA methylation is an important epigenetic modification and plays critical roles in transcriptional regulation, chromosomal stability, genomic imprinting and X-inactivation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Rakyan et al., 2008</ref>). Numerous literatures have established the influence of DNA methylation in transcriptional aberrations in human diseases including various types of cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Esteller, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Irizarry et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Koga et al., 2009</ref>). DNA methylation occurs in cytosines of CpG dinucleotides in human in a non-random fashion across the genome. In particular, CpG-rich regions (known as CpG islands) are usually hypomethylated, whereas repetitive genomic sequences are hypermethylated in normal cells. Over the past decade, there has been vast research in studying alterations of * To whom correspondence should be addressed. DNA methylation in cancer. A general observed trend of perturbed DNA methylation includes hypomethylation of oncogenes and hypermethylation of tumor suppressor genes, leading to genomic instability and tumorigenesis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Esteller, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Irizarry et al., 2009</ref>). Several platforms are available for DNA methylation profiling that includes high-throughput arrays and more recently, the nextgeneration sequencing instruments. The experimental approaches in high-throughput array-based methylation include bisulfite conversion-based methods, restriction enzyme-based methods and immunoprecipitation-based methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Down et al., 2008</ref>). A popular robust methylation profiling platform via bisulfite conversion is the Illumina GoldenGate and Infinium Methylation Assays based on the BeadArray technology. This technology utilizes 3 µm silica beads which are replicated ∼30 times on the array and has emerged as an attractive platform for genotyping, expression and methylation analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dunning et al., 2008b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Lynch et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Xie et al., 2009</ref>). This technology requires less sample input but produces high-quality data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dunning et al., 2008b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Xie et al., 2009</ref>), thereby reducing the cost of array experiments. The increasing popularity of Illumina BeadArray technology is apparent given the numerous scientific publications since 2008. However, there is only a handful of statistical framework for analyzing Illumina BeadArray gene expression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dunning et al., 2008b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wong et al., 2008</ref>), and limited work is available for methylation array counterpart (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Lynch et al., 2009</ref>). Existing work for gene expression BeadArray falls into the categories of data preprocessing and differential expression detection. This includes background correction methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dunning et al., 2008b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Xie et al., 2009</ref>), variance-stabilizing techniques (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Dunning et al., 2008a</ref>) and modified test statistics for differential gene expression in Illumina BeadArray (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wong et al., 2008</ref>). Most of the framework for gene expression analysis is based on the assumption that the majority of the genes are not differentially expressed. In contrast, many sites are expected to be methylated (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Irizarry et al., 2008</ref>), and therefore the assumptions in gene expression are not applicable to methylation experiments. The goal of our article is to provide a statistical framework for arraybased methylation profiling on Illumina BeadArray technology, by studying the source of biases and the data-generating mechanism of Illumina methylation assays. Specifically, we propose a model for correcting the source of biases in Illumina Methylation BeadArray and introduce a weighted model-based approach for clustering the methylation profiles. The framework of our weighted model-based clustering can also be directly applied to other Illumina BeadArray platforms, e.g. gene expression BeadChip, because it does not rely on the assumption that most beads are from the null distribution of no differential expression. In the next section, we describe the<ref type="bibr">[12:04 19/10/2010 Bioinformatics-btq553.tex]</ref>Page: 2850 2849–2855</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P.F.Kuan et al.</head><p>methylation data structure and introduce our proposed statistical framework.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MOTIVATION</head><p>Methylation levels in Illumina methylation assays are quantified by the beta value using the ratio of intensities between methylated (M) and unmethylated (U) alleles. Specifically, beta = max(M,0) max(M,0)+max(U,0)+100 where M and U are the red and green dyes, respectively, for the GoldenGate and VeraCode Methylation assays, whereas for Infinium assay, M and U are signals A and B (produced by two different bead types and reported in the same color), respectively. The constant 100 is to regularize beta when both M and U values are small (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bibikova et al., 2006</ref>). The beta values are continuous and range from 0 (unmethylated) to 1 (completely methylated). Each locus reports an average beta value obtained from the average of M's and U's across approximately 30 bead replicates, and individual beadlevel measurements are not readily available (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dunning et al., 2008b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wong et al., 2008</ref>). A standard summary output from BeadStudio (Illumina software to process raw intensities) includes four columns for each sample, i.e. (1) average beta, (2) average M, (3) average U and (4) detection P-values, for each locus. Therefore, our proposed framework will be based on the average beta values for convenience. The detection P-value reported by BeadStudio can be used as a quality control measure of probe performance. The detection P-value is defined as 1−P-value computed from the background model characterizing the chance that the signal was distinguishable from negative controls (Supplementary Materials). Standard protocol by Illumina recommends excluding probes that have a detection P-value greater than an arbitrary cutoff of 0.05. On the other hand,<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Marsit et al. (2009)</ref>excluded samples that consist of ≥25% observations with detection P-values ≥ 1×10 −5 , as well as probes (CpG loci) with median detection P-values &gt;0.05, whereas Hernandez<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Vargas et al. (2010)</ref>excluded probes with detection P-values &gt;0.01 in &gt;10% of the samples. In Section 3.2, we will introduce a modeling framework that avoids arbitrary choice of detection P-value threshold. We will now explore and illustrate the source of biases present in Illumina Methylation BeadArray based on the data generated by the Thomas-Conway Lab at UNC-Chapel Hill. The methylation experiment is performed on the GoldenGate Cancer Panel I methylation panel, which interrogates 1505 CpG loci/probes associated with 803 cancer-related genes (tumor suppressor genes, oncogenes, genes involved in DNA repair, cell-cycle control, differentiation, apoptosis, X-linked and imprinted genes) where 28.6% contain one CpG site per gene, 57.3% contain two CpG sites and 14.1% have three or more sites (<ref type="bibr">Illumina, 2006</ref>). The probe length varies between 41 bp and 59 bp with median 50 bp, whereas the number of CG dinucleotides for each probe varies between 1 and 7. A pair of allele-specific oligonucleotide (ASO) and locusspecific oligonucleotide (LSO) measures the methylation level of a specific CG dinucleotide for a probe under the assumption that flanking CG dinucleotides within the same probe exhibit similar methylation status. In other words, the observed methylation level for the measured CG dinucleotide should not be affected by the number of flanking CG dinucleotides. To investigate the potentialsource of biases in Illumina Methylation assays, we utilize six positive control samples from our dataset, in which all the cytosines in CG dinucleotides are expected to be methylated and any deviation from methylated status indicates the presence of technical biases. We apply quantile normalization to these six positive control samples.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figures 1 and 2</ref>compare the pairwise correlations among these positive controls before and after normalization, respectively. Both plots show the high correlations among the positive controls, with improvement after normalization. In addition, array-based technology are known to be affected by the sequence and thermodynamic properties, e.g. melting temperature and GC content in protein–DNA binding and gene expression experiments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dunning et al., 2008b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Wei et al., 2008</ref>). In<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref>, we plot the quantile normalized average beta values pooled from all positive controls against probe length, number of CG dinucleotides within each probe, melting temperature and GC content. Individual plots for each positive control sample are given in Supplementary Materials. Melting temperature is computed according to<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Wei et al. (2008)</ref>, whereas GC content is the percentage of C and G nucleotides for a given probe. As evident from<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref>,the observed methylation level is influenced by the sequence and thermodynamics properties of the probes. Sequence length bias in methylation array is also observed in<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Lynch et al. (2009)</ref>. Since melting temperature is a function of GC content and sequence length, and GC content is highly correlated with the number of CG dinucleotides, our modeling framework will incorporate sequence length and GC content. In gene expression and protein–DNA binding arrays, GC content exhibits increasing trend with intensities due to the three hydrogen bonds compared with two hydrogen bonds in AT pairs. However, the decreasing trend observed in methylation arrays can be attributed to the loss of efficiency in binding for a probe with more CG dinucleotides, because the CG dinucleotides within a probe are expected to have similar methylation status. Although CG dinucleotides yield a more straightforward interpretation, we choose GC content which has more distinct values for better function approximation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Estimating L j and GC j biases</head><p>For notational brevity, we denote the average beta value and detection P-value for each locus j, j = 1,...,p and sample i, i = 1,...,n as β ij and p ij , respectively. Let L j and GC j denote the probe length and GC content for locus j, respectively. Since β ij ∈ (0,1), beta distribution arises as a natural distribution for modeling the observed β ij (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Houseman et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Siegmund et al., 2004</ref>). However, maximum likelihood estimation of the unknown parameters (α, β) in a beta distribution does not have a closed form and relies on numerical methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ji et al., 2005</ref>). In this article, we consider an alternative for modeling β ij via a logit transformation,</p><formula>y ij = log β ij 1−β ij ∈ R</formula><p>To avoid a logit tranformation of β = 0, we add an = 10 −4 to β as</p><formula>β = max( ¯ M,,) max( ¯ M,,)+max( ¯ U,,)+100</formula><p>where ¯ M and ¯ U are the average M and U values across ∼30 replicates as mentioned in Section 2. We modelwhere s ij is the true methylation level and h 1 , h 2 characterize the bias arising from sequence length and GC content. We estimate h 1 , h 2 from the positive control sample instead of treatment sample itself. This is to safeguard against removing actual methylation signals due to the potential confounding effect with GC content, i.e. hypomethylation in CpG islands (CG-rich regions) of normal cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Esteller, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Irizarry et al., 2008</ref>). Letunder the constraints (1) α 1 = 44α 2 ,</p><formula>y ij = s ij +h 1 (L j )+h 2 (GC j ) A B C D</formula><formula>h 1 (L j ) = α 1 I(L</formula><formula>(2) α 3 = 57α 2 , (3) γ 1 = 0.4γ 2 and</formula><p>(4) γ 3 = 0.8γ 2 for continuity at the knots. That is, we model h 1 and h 2 as piecewise constant + linear + constant. The knots are chosen so that the number of observations in {L j &lt; 44} and {L j ≥ 57} are comparable with the number of observations in {L j = n} for n = 44,...,56 as well as to avoid over (under)estimation for large (small) L j , and vice versa for GC j. In<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref>, we plot the correctedˆβcorrectedˆ correctedˆβ ij against the attributes, wherê</p><formula>wherê β ij = exp(y ij − ˆ h 1 (L j )− ˆ h 2 (GC j )) 1+exp(y ij − ˆ h 1 (L j )− ˆ h 2 (GC j ))</formula><p>for the positive control. As evident from this figure, the bias of these four attributes are reduced substantially.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">A weighted model-based approach</head><p>One of the most common applications of DNA methylation is in identifying subgroups with distinct methylation patterns (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Christensen et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Houseman et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Marsit et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Shen et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Siegmund et al., 2004</ref>) via unsupervised clustering techniques. Numerous clustering methods have been developed, including non-parametric (e.g. agglomerative hierarchical clustering) and model-based approaches. Modelbased clustering assumes that the data is generated from a finite mixture model, in which each mixture component corresponds to a cluster. It has emerged as a popular technique and allows for statistical inference (e.g. selecting number of clusters and estimating membership probability) to be carried out (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Fraley and Raftery, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Siegmund et al., 2004</ref>). We let</p><formula>y i = (y i1 ,...</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P.F.Kuan et al.</head><p>distributions. Specifically,</p><formula>y i ∼ K k=1 π k f k , K k=1 π k = 1, f k ∼ N (µ k +h 1 (L)+h 2 (GC),, k ), k ∈{1,...,K}</formula><p>where h 1 , h 2 are pre-estimated from positive control samples as shown in Section 3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Define˜yDefine˜ Define˜y ij</head><formula>= y ij − ˆ h 1 (L j )− ˆ h 2 (GC j ) ∼ K k=1 π k ˜ f k = K k=1 π k N (µ k ,, k ). Let θ k = (π k ,µ k ,, k )</formula><p>be the unknown parameters. The mixture model log-likelihood function for the whole data is given by</p><formula>L = n i=1 log K k=1 π k ˜ f k (˜ y i ;θ k )</formula><p>As pointed out in Section 2, standard preprocessing steps for Illumina methylation assays include a quality control of probe measurements by excluding probes that have detection P-values (p ij ) larger than an arbitrary cutoff. This step results in missing observations and information loss by discarding a subset of probes. To avoid using a hard threshold for quality assessment, we would like to assign a weight for each sample which reflects its quality rather than discarding a sample completely from the analysis. We introduce an alternative model-based clustering on a weighted likelihoodbased approach. The objective of a weighted likelihood function is to assign a different weight to each sample, in which samples with higher weights have more influence in estimating the mixture parameters for cluster structure inference. The weighted mixture model log-likelihood function is given by</p><formula>L W = n i=1 w i log K k=1 π k ˜ f k (˜ y i ;θ k )</formula><p>where w i is the weight of sample i. Without loss of generality, we assume, where Q3 is the third quartile. Weighted model-based clustering has been shown to outperform the non-weighted method in both simulations and real datasets from remote sensing images in geology (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Richards et al., 2009</ref>). In addition,<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Seo et al. (2004)</ref>showed that detection P-values weighting in computing Pearson's correlation coefficient improved the performance of expression profiling in Affymetrix microarrays. The mixture modeling framework can be recast in an expectation–maximization (EM) framework for estimating the unknown parameters θ k. We introduce z ik to be the unobserved indicator latent variable taking value 1 if sample i belongs to cluster k and 0 otherwise. The complete weighted log-likelihood function is</p><formula>L CW = n i=1 K k=1 w i z ik [logπ k +log( ˜ f k (˜ y i ;θ k ))]</formula><p>In clustering DNA methylation profiles for identifying subgroups among the n samples, we are faced with the well-known 'large p, small n' problem. One strategy is to apply dimension reduction, e.g. principal component analysis (PCA) to the p loci, followed by clustering on the reduced space. However, treating dimension reduction and clustering as two separate steps may destroy the cluster structure in the data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Raftery, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wang and Zhu, 2008</ref>). Moreover, each PCA is a linear combination of all CpG loci, and does not allow for automatic selection of important CpG loci. Therefore, our goal is to incorporate a variable selection in model-based clustering approach, which identifies important CpG loci (variable selection) and subgroups among the n samples (clustering) simultaneously based on a penalized criterion (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Pan and Shen, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wang and Zhu, 2008</ref>). We consider a penalized complete weighted log-likelihood to achieve the goal:</p><formula>L PCW = n i=1 K k=1 w i z ik [logπ k +log( ˜ f k (˜ y i ;θ k ))]−J() (1)</formula><p>where ={µ kj ,k = 1,...,K;j = 1,...,p} and J() is a penalty function. Several choices of penalty functions are available, e.g. Pan and<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Shen (2007)</ref>proposed an L 1-norm penalty function which takes the form J(</p><formula>) = K k=1 p j=1 |µ kj |.</formula><p>As pointed out by<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wang and Zhu (2008)</ref>, however, there is a natural group structure among µ kj 's, i.e. for each j, we can treat µ kj , k = 1,...,K as a group since they are associated with the same CpG locus. The L 1-norm penalty function ignores this group structure and treats µ kj individually. As a result, it tends to keep many unimportant loci in the model. To circumvent this problem, Wang and Zhu (2008) proposed a penalty function that incorporates group information and shrinks µ kj 's more effectively. In addition, some loci have large detection P-values across all samples and are unreliable. Therefore, we would like to impose heavier penalty on these loci. We achieve this by introducing g j to be weight of locus j, where larger g j values indicate more reliable probes. One possible choice is g</p><formula>j = median i (logp ij )/ p j=1 median i (logp ij ) ∈ (0,1</formula><p>) (here we take median across samples, cf. w i : median across loci). We generalize the proposed penalty function by<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wang and Zhu (2008)</ref>by including the detection P-values as follows:</p><formula>J() = p j=1 γ j g j max k (| ˜ µ kj | α ) +λ K k=1 p j=1 |θ kj | | ˜ µ kj | α where µ kj = γ j θ kj , ˜ µ kj 's</formula><p>are the unpenalized estimates of cluster means and α is a non-negative tuning parameter. Under this penalty function, loci with large detection P-values will be assigned a higher penalty, and are more likely to be excluded in the variable selection. λ is a tuning parameter that controls the sparsity, i.e. small (large) λ results in the selection of more (fewer) CpG loci. Additional details on the proposed penalty function are given in Supplementary Materials. We further assume that k = = diag(σ 2 1 ,...,σ 2 p ) as in<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wang and Zhu (2008)</ref>. That is, the covariance matrices are the same across different clusters and are diagonal, a common assumption for a high dimension and small sample size problem. Further theoretical justifications for adopting the diagonal structure of the covariance matrix are provided by<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bickel and Levina (2004)</ref>. At the t iteration of the EM algorithm, the E-step computesˆz computesˆ computesˆz</p><formula>(t) ik = ˆ π (t−1) k ˜ f (t−1) k (˜ y i ; ˆ θ (t−1) k ) K c=1ˆπc=1ˆ c=1ˆπ (t−1) c ˜ f (t−1) c (˜ y i ; ˆ θ (t−1) k ) for i = 1</formula><p>,...,n and k = 1,...,K. The M-step involves maximizing Equation (1) with respect to (π k , µ kj ,σ 2 j ). Following the derivations in<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wang and Zhu (2008)</ref>with modifications to incorporate the weights</p><formula>w i , g j and that n i=1 w i = 1, ˆ π (t) k = n i=1 w i ˆ z (t−1) ik , ˆ σ 2(t) j = K k=1 n i=1 w i ˆ z (t−1) ik (˜ y ij − ˆ µ (t) kj ) 2 ,</formula><p>The estimates for γ j and θ kj are not trivial, since the penalty function is singular at the origin point. However, similar to the derivation in Wang and Zhu (2008), we can update estimates of γ j and θ kj iteratively by the following explicit formula, which makes our method easy to implement in practice:</p><formula>ˆ γ j = I (∃k,θ kj =0) K k=1 ξ k µ 0 kjˆθ kjˆ kjˆθ kj K k=1 ξ k − ˆ σ 2 j g j max k (| ˜ µ kj | α ) K k=1 ξ k + ˆ θ kj = I (γ j &gt;0) sign(µ 0 kj ) |µ 0 kj | γ j − λ ˆ σ 2 j | ˜ µ kj | α γ 2 j n i=1 w i ˆ z ik + where ξ k = n i=1 w i ˆ z ikˆθikˆ ikˆθ 2 kj and µ 0 kj = n i=1 w i ˆ z ik˜yik˜ ik˜y i n i=1 w i ˆ z ik . The E</formula><formula>BIC = −2n n i=1 w i log K k=1ˆπ k=1ˆ k=1ˆπ k ˜ f k (˜ y i ; ˆ θ k )</formula><p>+Plogn</p><p>where P is the total number of non-zero estimates inˆµinˆ inˆµ kj , ˆ σ 2 j andˆπandˆ andˆπ k. The first term is the right-hand side is exactly the regular −2 n i=1 loglik when w i = 1/n, ∀i. We name our method LumiWCluster (IlLumina W eighted modelbased Clustering).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">DNA methylation studies in ovarian cancer</head><p>We illustrate our proposed method on the ovarian epithelial carcinoma tumors and cell lines methylation dataset from<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Houshdaran et al. (2009)</ref>. In<ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>, we show the presence of sequence bias on the positive control sample in this dataset. The observed pattern in consistent with our six positive control samples (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>). Using the estimated h 1 and h 2 from our six positive controls, we adjust for the observed bias in the ovarian methylation dataset. Although h 1 and h 2 are estimated from an independent source of data, we show that the effect of sequence bias is reduced significantly for the ovarian methylation dataset (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6</ref>). This ovarian cancer dataset consists of 27 primary tumors (15 serous, 9 endometrioid and 3 clear cell) and 15 cell lines. By applying our proposed weighted clustering approach (LumiWCluster) to this dataset, the optimal number of clusters chosen is K = 4. Details are provided in Supplementary Materials. We also compare the clustering results from Gaussian mixture model without penalty and weights, i.e. J(</p><formula>) = 0, w i = 1/n ∀i, g j = 1/p ∀j.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">DNA methylation studies in HCV-cirrhosis</head><p>Our next example is on a data set measuring DNA methylation of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Archer et al., 2010</ref>) from Illumina GoldenGate Methylation BeadArray. This data set consists of 20 samples from HCC with cirrhosis and 20 normal liver tissues. Similar to Section 4.1, we compare the clustering results from LumiWCluster, GMM-nopenalty, Mclust, k-means and PAM on the normalized data (corrected for sequence length and GC content biases). LumiWCluster selects K = 2, whereas the rest of the methods select K = 3 as the optimal number of clusters. LumiWCluster automatically shrinks 639 CpG to zero and results in perfect separation between the C and N samples. However, the other methods contain misclassification of these samples (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). In Supplementary Materials, we also provide the clustering results for the other methods by fixing K = 2. Unlike LumiWCluster, these methods still misclassify the two different types of samples. Next, we run GMM-nopenalty on the subset of CpG loci selected by LumiWCluster [referred to as 'GMM-nopenalty (with subset of CpGs selected by LumiWCluster)' in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref><ref type="bibr">]</ref>. Interestingly, the optimal number of clusters is chosen to be 2 and results in perfect classification. This highlights that LumiWCluster is able to select informative CpG loci that differentiate cirrhosis from normal tissues. To further illustrate the advantage of LumiWCluster in selecting important CpG loci, we carry out the non-parametric Wilcoxon ranksum test for comparing cirrhosis and normal group samples on each of these 1505 CpG loci. The P-values are adjusted using the false discovery rate (FDR) control (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995</ref>). At FDR of 0.05, 597 loci are significant, of which 578 overlap with the 866 loci selected by LumiWCluster. This shows that LumiWCluster is able to retain statistically significant loci. As a comparison, 19 CpG loci have median detection P &gt; 0.05 and will be excluded using the filtering criterion in<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Marsit et al. (2009)</ref>. Among these 19 loci, 15 of them were shrunk to 0 by LumiWCluster.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7A</ref>and B shows the distribution of the β values for two CpG loci that were not shrunk to 0, which appear to be informative in differentiating HCC with cirrhosis from normal liver tissues. We also include two CpG loci that have median detection P &gt;0.05 and were shrunk to 0 by LumiWCluster (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 7C and D</ref>). This again demonstrates the ability of LumiWCluster in selecting informative CpGs which can differentiate the two groups despite being completely unsupervised.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A B C D</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">DISCUSSION</head><p>The delineation of DNA methylation patterns is important in understanding how these epigenetic changes might lead to aberrant expression patterns and disease (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Laird, 2010</ref>). Advancements in biotechnology have enabled high-throughput profiling of DNA methylation, including the Illumina GoldenGate and Infinium BeadArray via bisulphite conversion. These platforms are robust, highly reproducible and require less starting materials. In the first part of this study, we illustrated the source of biases present in Illumina Methylation arrays and proposed a model for correcting these biases. A common approach in analyzing Illumina Methylation data includes omitting CpG loci and samples that exhibit detection P-values larger than an arbitrary cutoff. This hard thresholding step often results in missing observations and information loss by discarding a subset of probes. We proposed a weighted model-based approach called LumiWCluster that weights each CpG locus/sample by its detection P-values for clustering DNA methylation profiles. In this article, we set the weights as the median detection P-values across samples (or CpG loci) which appears to perform well in the two case studies. Optimal selection of weight functions is beyond the scope of this article and will be an interesting future research direction.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Pair plots of the six positive controls before normalization. Upper panel prints the pairwise correlation coefficient.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Pair plots of the six positive controls after quantile normalization. Upper panel prints the pairwise correlation coefficient.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. The effects of (A) sequence length, (B) number of CG dinucleotides, (C) melting temperature and (D) GC content bias. Gray line is the lowess approximation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. The effects of (A) sequence length, (B) number of CG dinucleotides, (C) melting temperature and (D) GC content bias after correction. Gray line is the lowess approximation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><figDesc>The optimal number of clusters chosen is K = 3. We refer to this model as GMM-nopenalty. This model is a special case of Mclust by Fraley and Raftery (2002). Mclust is a non-penalized standard modelbased clustering which allows for different functional forms of the covariance matrices, where all CpG loci are retained in the resulting clustering. We also include the clustering results from A B C D</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig.6.</head><figDesc>Fig. 6. The effects of (A) sequence length, (B) number of CG dinucleotides, (C) melting temperature and (D) GC content bias after correction on positive control of Houshdaran et al. (2009). Gray line is the lowess approximation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig.7.</head><figDesc>Fig. 7. (A, B) Distribution of β values for three CpGs which are omitted by the criterion in Marsit et al. (2009), but are not shrunk to zero in our weighted model-based clustering. (C, D) Example of CpGs which are omitted by the criterion in Marsit et al. (2009) and are shrunk to zero in our weighted modelbased clustering. The numbers printed in the parenthesis are the adjusted P-values.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>j &lt; 44)+α 2 L j I(44 ≤ L j &lt; 57) +α 3 I(L j ≥ 57) h 2 (GC j ) = γ 1 I(GC j &lt; 0.4)+γ 2 GC j I(0.4 ≤ GC j &lt; 0.8) +γ 3 I(GC j ≥ 0.8)</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>,y ip ) T to be a vector of logit-transformed beta values for sample i. We assume that y i is generated from a mixture of K multivariate normal</figDesc><table>Page: 2852 2849–2855 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>n i=1 w i = 1. The detection P-values arise as a natural weight function, since samples with large detection P-values are less reliable. A possible choice of weight function is w i = median j (logp ij )/ n i=1 median i (logp ij ) ∈ (0,1). Note that the criteria in Marsit et al. (2009) which excluded samples that consist of ≥25% observations with detection P-values ≥ 1× 10 −5 is a special case by defining w i = I[Q3 j (p ij ) &lt; 1×10 −5 ]/ n i=1 I[Q3 j (p ij ) &lt; 1×10 −5 ]</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><figDesc>step and M-step are iterated till convergence. and the number of clusters K by minimizing the Bayesian information criterion (BIC). To account for the weights w i in the likelihood functions in which n i=1 w i = 1, we define a modified BIC as follows:</figDesc><table>Page: 2853 2849–2855 

Model for DNA methylation array 

A 
B 

C 
D 

Fig. 5. The effects of (A) sequence length, (B) number of CG dinucleotides, 
(C) melting temperature and (D) GC content bias on positive control of 
Houshdaran et al. (2009). Gray line is the lowess approximation. 

As in Pan and Shen (2007) and Wang and Zhu (2008), we choose the 
tuning parameter λ </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1.</figDesc><table>Clustering result for the ovarian cancer data 

Cluster 
LumiWCluster 
GMM-nopenalty 
Mclust 

1 
15CL 
15CL 
15CL 
2 
1CC, 2E, 9S 
1CC, 2E, 9S 
1CC, 2E, 9S 
3 
2CC, 5E, 3S 
2CC, 7E, 6S 
2CC, 5E, 3S 
4 
2E, 3S 
– 
2E, 3S 

Cluster 
k-means 
PAM </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2.</figDesc><table>Clustering result for the HCC-cirrhosis data 

Cluster LumiWCluster GMM-nopenalty Mclust 

1 
20C 
17C 
17C 
2 
20N 
11N 
11N 
3 
– 
3C, 9N 
3C, 9N 

Cluster k-means 
PAM 
GMM-nopenalty 
(with subset of CpGs 
selected by LumiWCluster) 

1 
17C 
17C 
20C 
2 
11N 
11N 
20N 
3 
3C, 9N 
3C, 9N 
– 

C, HCC with cirrhosis samples; N, normal liver tissues. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org 2849 at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> 15CL, 1CC, 2E 9S 13CL, 1CC, 2E, 9S 2 2CC, 7E, 6S 2CL, 2CC, 7E, 6S CC, clear cell; CL, cell lines; E, endometrioid; S, serous. Mclust, k-means and PAM (partitioning around medoids, a more robust version of k-means) (Kaufman and Rousseeuw, 1990) which identify K = 4, 2 and 2 as the optimal number of clusters, respectively. The optimal number of clusters chosen by k-means and PAM is based on the &apos;silhouette&apos; criterion (Rousseeuwl, 1987). As shown in Table 1, k-means and PAM are unable to separate cell lines from primary tumors; whereas LumiWCluster, GMMnopenalty and Mclust yield comparable cluster membership, where cell lines are separated from primary tumors, but there are some mixing among the three tumor subtypes. However, an advantage of LumiWCluster is that it automatically shrinks 554 CpG loci to 0, which implies that these loci do not contribute to the clustering. This refines the set of CpG loci which are important in the resulting cluster structure. These 554 CpG loci include the eight sites which have median detection P &gt; 0.05 and are excluded using the filtering criterion in Marsit et al. (2009). We also demonstrate that the ability of LumiWCluster in selecting important CpGs yields tighter clusters in Supplementary Materials. In addition, LumiWCluster results in smaller BIC compared with GMM-nopenalty and Mclust, indicating a better model fit. We provide additional information on the advantages of incorporating the detection P-values in our proposed clustering approach in Supplementary Materials.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank Drs Nancy Thomas, Kathleen Conway and Sharon Edmiston for providing the control samples and the reviewers for valuable comments. Funding: NCI (grants 5-P30-CA16086-34 and 1R21CA13436801A1 to P.K. and H.C., in parts); Susan G. Komen Foundation (grant KG081397 to P.K. and H.C., in parts).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of Interest: none declared.</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Model for DNA methylation array</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1210</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>btq553. .tex]</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2855" to="2849" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-throughput assessment of CpG site methylation for distinguishing between HCV-cirrhosis and HCV-associated hepatocellular carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Archer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Genet. Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">283</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="349" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Benjamini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Hochberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-throughput DNA methylation profiling using universal bead arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Bibikova</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="383" to="393" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some theory for Fisher&apos;s linear discriminant function, &quot; naive Bayes&quot;, and some alternatives when there are many more variables than observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Bickel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Levina</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bernoulli</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="989" to="1010" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aging and environmental exposures alter tissue-specific DNA methylation dependent upon CpG island context</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Christensen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000602</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Bayesian deconvolution strategy for immunoprecipitation based DNA methylome analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Down</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spike-in validation of an Illumina-specific variancestabilizing transformation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Dunning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Res. Notes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical issues in the analysis of Illumina data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Dunning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">85</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancer epigenomics: DNA methylomes and histone-modifications maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Esteller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="286" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model-based clustering, discriminant analysis, and density estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Fraley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Raftery</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="611" to="631" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hepatocellular carcinoma displays distinct DNA methylation signatures with potential as clinical predictors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Hernandez-Vargas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9749</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model-based clustering of DNA methylation array data: a recursive-partitioning algorithm for high-dimensional data arising as a mixture of beta distribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Houseman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">365</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA methylation profiles of ovarian epithelial carcinoma tumors and cell lines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Houshdaran</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9359</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GoldenGate methylation cancer panel I</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Illumina</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive high-throughput arrays for relative methylation (CHARM)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Irizarry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="780" to="790" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human colon cancer methylome shows similar hypo-and hypermethylation at conserved tissue-specific CpG island shores</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Irizarry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Applications of beta-mixture models in bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Ji</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2118" to="2122" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Finding Groups in Data: An Introduction to Cluster Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Kaufman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Rousseeuw</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<publisher>Wiley-Interscience</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide screen of promoter methylation identifies novel markers in melanoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Koga</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1462" to="1470" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Principles and challenges of genome-wide DNA methylation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Laird</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Considerations for processing and analysis of Goldengate-based two-colour illumina platforms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Lynch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Methods Med. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="452" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epigenetic profiling reveals etiologically distinct patterns of DNA methylation in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Marsit</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Carcinogenesis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="416" to="422" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Penalized model-based clustering with application to variable selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Pan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Shen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mach. Learn. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1145" to="1164" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Discussion of Bayesian clustering with variable selection and transformation selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Raftery</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="271" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated resource for genome-wide identification and analysis of human tissue-specific differential methylated regions (tDMRs)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Rakyan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1518" to="1529" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Weighted model-based clustering for remote sensing image analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Richards</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Geosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Silhouettes: a graphical aid to the interpretation and validation of cluster analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Rousseeuwl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Appl. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactively optimizing signal-to-noise ratios in expression profiling, project-specific algorithm selection and detection p-value weighting in Affymetrix microarrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Seo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinfomatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2534" to="2544" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrative clustering of multiple genomic data types using a joint latent variable model with application to breast and lung cancer subtype analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Shen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2906" to="2912" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of cluster analysis methods using DNA methylation data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Siegmund</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1896" to="1904" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variable selection for model-based high dimensional clustering and its application to microarray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Zhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="440" to="448" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study of the relationships between oligonucleotide properties and hybridization signal intensities from NimbleGen microarray datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Wei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2926" to="2938" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the necessity of different statistical treatment for Illumina BeadChip and Affymetrix GeneChip data and its significance for biological interpretation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Wong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Direct</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical methods of background correction for Illumina BeadArray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Xie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="751" to="757" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>