
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:52+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A time-varying group sparse additive model for genome-wide association studies of dynamic complex traits</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Micol</forename>
								<surname>Marchetti-Bowick</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Machine Learning Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Junming</forename>
								<surname>Yin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Management Information Systems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Arizona</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tucson</settlement>
									<region>AZ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Judie</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Howrylak</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Penn State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</addrLine>
									<settlement>Hershey</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eric</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Xing</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Machine Learning Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A time-varying group sparse additive model for genome-wide association studies of dynamic complex traits</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw347</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on September 22, 2015; revised on May 24, 2016; accepted on May 27, 2016</note>
					<note>Genome analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: John Hancock Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Despite the widespread popularity of genome-wide association studies (GWAS) for genetic mapping of complex traits, most existing GWAS methodologies are still limited to the use of static phenotypes measured at a single time point. In this work, we propose a new method for association mapping that considers dynamic phenotypes measured at a sequence of time points. Our approach relies on the use of Time-Varying Group Sparse Additive Models (TV-GroupSpAM) for high-dimensional, functional regression. Results: This new model detects a sparse set of genomic loci that are associated with trait dynamics , and demonstrates increased statistical power over existing methods. We evaluate our method via experiments on synthetic data and perform a proof-of-concept analysis for detecting single nucleotide polymorphisms associated with two phenotypes used to assess asthma severity: forced vital capacity, a sensitive measure of airway obstruction and bronchodilator response, which measures lung response to bronchodilator drugs. Availability and Implementation: Source code for TV-GroupSpAM freely available for download at http://sydney.edu.au/science/biology/meep/softwarel.
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The goal of genome-wide association studies (GWAS) is to analyze a large set of genetic markers that span the entire genome in order to identify loci that are associated with a phenotype of interest. Over the past decade, GWAS has been used to successfully identify genetic variants that are associated with numerous diseases and complex traits, ranging from breast cancer to blood pressure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hindorff et al., 2015</ref>). However, a significant challenge in performing GWAS is that the studies are often vastly under-powered due to the high dimensionality of the feature set relative to the small number of human samples available. Traditional GWAS methodologies test each variant independently for association with the phenotype, and use a stringent significance threshold to adjust for multiple hypothesis testing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Clarke et al., 2011</ref>). Although this approach works well for traits that depend on strong effects from a few loci, it is less suitable for complex, polygenic traits that are influenced by weak effects from many different genetic variants. More recently, a significant body of work has emerged on penalized regression approaches for GWAS that capture the joint effects of all markers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Li et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Wu et al., 2009</ref>). The majority of these methods model the phenotype as a weighted sum of the genotype values at each locus, and use a regularization penalty such as the ' 1 norm to identify a sparse set of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) that are predictive of the trait. Although this technique helps to reduce overfitting and detect fewer spurious SNP-trait associations, the lack of statistical power to identify true associations persists. Here we aim to further boost the statistical power of GWAS by proposing a new model that leverages dynamic trait data, in which a particular trait is measured in each individual repeatedly over time, as depicted in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1a</ref>. Such datasets are often generated by longitudinal studies that follow participants over the course of months, years, or even decades. Though broadly available, dynamic trait datasets are frequently underutilized by practitioners who ignore the temporal information. We believe that leveraging time-sequential trait measurements in GWAS can lead to greater statistical power for association mapping. To illustrate this concept, consider the hypothetical patterns of SNP influence on the phenotype shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1b</ref>. As in traditional GWAS, an association between a SNP and the phenotype exists if the three SNP genotypes (which we denote AA, Aa and aa) have differential effects on the trait. In the first example, the effects of the three SNP genotypes only differ in the t 2 ½0:5; 1 time interval. A static method that uses data from an arbitrarily chosen time point or simply treats the time series as i.i.d. samples could easily miss this association, whereas a dynamic method that considers the entire dataset would detect it. The second example shows a SNP in which the difference between the effects of the three genotypes is small but consistent over time. Although this signal could be too weak to be interpreted as a significant association in the static case, it gets much stronger once evidence from the entire time series is considered. The longitudinal data setting is challenging because traits are measured at irregularly spaced time points over subject-specific intervals. One approach that has been proposed for performing GWAS of dynamic traits, called functional GWAS, or fGWAS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Das et al., 2011</ref>), constructs a separate model to estimate the smooth, time-varying influence of each SNP on the phenotype. Once the mean effects have been estimated for each genotype at each time point, a hypothesis test is performed to determine whether the SNP has any additive or dominant effect on the trait. Although the use of dynamic trait data gives fGWAS more statistical power than a standard hypothesis test on static data, the principal drawback of this method is that it is inappropriate for modeling complex traits that arise from interactions between genetic effects at different loci. A related approach extends the fGWAS framework to model multiple SNPs at once using a Bayesian group lasso framework (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Li et al., 2015</ref>). Although this approach seems promising, it is severely limited by its very slow MCMC inference procedure. There are a number of other methods that have been developed for dynamic trait GWAS, including<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Yang et al. (2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">), Furlotte et al. (2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">), Das et al. (2013</ref>, and Li and Sillanp€ a€ a (2013). However, the majority of them either perform single-locus analysis (as in fGWAS) or fail to learn an explicit, interpretable representation of the dynamic effects of the genetic variants at each locus. The notable exception to this is fGWAS with Bayesian group lasso, which we directly compare to our approach in a later section. In this work, we introduce a new penalized multivariate regression approach for GWAS of dynamic quantitative traits, in which the phenotype is modeled as a sum of nonparametric, time-varying SNP effects. We call this Time-Varying Group Sparse Additive Models, or TV-GroupSpAM. Our method is based on GroupSpAM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Yin et al., 2012</ref>), a non-parametric regression model with a groupstructured penalty over the input features, which we extend to capture the dynamic effects of SNPs. This model has three major advantages over existing approaches: (i) we leverage dynamic trait data; (ii) we model the contribution of each SNP to the phenotype as a smooth function of time, and explicitly learn these influence patterns; (iii) we model the combined effects of multiple SNPs on the phenotype and select a sparse subset that participate in the model, thereby identifying meaningful SNP-trait associations. We show that TV-GroupSpAM exhibits desirable empirical advantages over baseline methods on both simulated and real datasets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Approach</head><p>In this section, we first introduce a time-varying additive model for dynamic complex traits that captures the underlying patterns of genetic effects. We then apply a group sparse regularization scheme to this model in order to impose bias useful for discovering a sparse set of markers that influence the phenotype in a longitudinal setting. Finally, we provide an efficient algorithm for parameter estimation, and thereby association mapping, under our model. Notation. Let X ij 2 f0; 1; 2g : i ¼ 1;. .. ; n ; j ¼ 1;. .. ; p denote the genotype of individual i at SNP locus j, where n and p denote the number of individuals and SNPs, respectively. Let Y is 2 R : i ¼ 1;. .. ; n ; s ¼ 1;. .. ; m denote the phenotype value of individual i at the sth time point. Note that the exact time readings for different individuals at their sth time point may be different, i.e. the measurements are not necessarily time-aligned. We therefore introduce an explicit time variable T is 2 R þ to capture the time reading for individual i at the sth time point, and define Y is YðT is Þ as a stochastic process that captures the trait values at each time point. In what follows, we will useTwo synthetic examples of time-dependent patterns of SNP influence on the trait that would be difficult to detect with a static model uppercase letters X, Y, T to denote random variables and lowercase letters x, y, t to denote their instantiated values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Time-varying additive model</head><p>We consider the following time-varying additive model with scalar input variables X 1 ;. .. ; X p and functional response variable Y(T): YðTÞ ¼ f 0 ðTÞ þ X p j¼1 f j ðT; X j Þ þ xðTÞ</p><formula>(1)</formula><p>Here Y(T), which represents the trait value at time T, is decomposed into three terms: f 0 ðTÞ is an intercept term that represents the non-genetic influence on the phenotype at time T; f j ðT; X j Þ represents the genetic effect of marker j with genotype X j at time T; xðTÞ is the noise term that models the random fluctuation of the underlying process. Since X j is a categorical variable, each bivariate component function f j can be represented more simply as a set of three univariate functions of time, given by f j ¼ ff 0 j ; f 1 j ; f 2 j g. We can subsequently define f j ðT;</p><formula>X j Þ ¼ P g f g j ðTÞ IfX j ¼ gg where f g j ðÁÞ ¼ f j ðÁ; X j ¼</formula><p>gÞ. Next we simplify our notation by expanding each X j into a set of three binary indicator variables such that X g j ¼ 1 () X j ¼ g. This allows us to rewrite the model in the following form.</p><formula>YðTÞ ¼ f 0 ðTÞ þ X p j¼1 X 2 g¼0 f g j ðTÞ X g j þ xðTÞ (2)</formula><p>Note that the indicator variable X g j selects a single function among the set ff 0 j ; f 1 j ; f 2 j g for each SNP. In the data setting, since each observation is subject to measurement error, we assume Y is ¼ Y i ðT is Þ þ is where is $ N ð0; r 2 Þ. It follows from the model defined in (2) that the observed phenotypic values satisfy</p><formula>y is ¼ f 0 ðt is Þ þ X p j¼1 X 2 g¼0 f g</formula><p>j ðt is Þ x g ij þ xðt is Þ þ is</p><formula>(3)</formula><p>for subjects i ¼ 1;. .. ; n and measurements s ¼ 1;. .. ; m. In the remainder of this article, we assume that the residual errors e is ¼ xðt is Þ þ is are i.i.d. across both subjects and measurements, though an alternative approach would be to impose an autocorrelation structure on xðTÞ to capture the temporal pattern of the underlying longitudinal process (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Das et al., 2011</ref>; Li and Sillanp€ a€ a, 2013). In the model specified above, our only assumption about the genetic effects ff 0 j ; f 1 j ; f 2 j : j ¼ 1;. .. ; pg is that they are smooth functions of time. A well-established approach to estimate nonparametric functions in additive models (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hastie and Tibshirani, 1990</ref>) is to minimize the expected squared error loss:</p><formula>hðf Þ ¼ E YðTÞ À f 0 ðTÞ À X p j¼1 X 2 g¼0 f g j ðTÞ X g j " # 2 (4)</formula><p>where the expectation is calculated with respect to the distributions over SNP genotypes ðX 1 ;. .. ; X p Þ, time T, and phenotypic value Y. In the sample setting, this translates to minimizing</p><formula>b hðf Þ ¼ X n i¼1 X m s¼1 y is À f 0 ðt is Þ À X p j¼1 X p g¼0 f g j ðt is Þ x g ij ! 2 (5)</formula><p>subject to a set of smoothness constraints. We go into detail about how to estimate the parameters of this model in Section 2.3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Group sparse regularization</head><p>In a typical genome-wide association study, though a large number of markers are assayed, it is believed that only a small subset of them have a real effect on the trait of interest. This assumption motivates us to impose sparsity at the level of the SNPs X 1 ;. .. ; X p in the time-varying additive model of (2), such that the effects of many of these variables are zero. To achieve this, we apply a groupsparsity-inducing penalty that leads to shrinkage on the estimated effect of each locus as a whole, including the component functions for all genotypes and their values at all time points. Specifically, we employ a group norm penalty over the component functions in which each group consists of the three functions ff 0 j ; f 1 j ; f 2 j g that correspond to a particular marker X j. To construct this group penalty, we use the ' 1;2 norm first introduced in the context of the group lasso (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Yuan and Lin, 2006</ref>). The new empirical objective function for our model is given by</p><formula>b hðf Þ þ k X p j¼1 ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi X 2 g¼0 jjf g j jj 2 2 v u u t (6)</formula><p>and is again subject to a set of smoothness constraints. Here k &gt; 0 is a tunable regularization parameter that controls the amount of sparsity in the model, and the squared ' 2 norm over f g j is defined as</p><formula>jjf g j jj 2 2 ¼ X n i¼1 X m s¼1 f g j ðt is Þ 2 x g ij (7)</formula><p>The penalty term in (6) induces sparsity at the level of groups by encouraging each set of functions ff 0 j ; f 1 j ; f 2 j g to be set exactly to zero, which implies that the corresponding marker X j has no effect whatsoever on the phenotype at any time point. In what follows, we will refer to the model defined by the objective function in (6) as a Time-Varying Group Sparse Additive Model (TV-GroupSpAM). This model is based on both the Group Sparse Additive Model of<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Yin et al. (2012)</ref>, in which a group sparse regularization penalty is applied to a standard additive model, and the Time-Varying Additive Model of<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Zhang et al. (2013)</ref>, in which an unpenalized additive model is used to regress a functional response on scalar covariates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Optimization algorithm</head><p>To estimate the parameters of the TV-GroupSpAM model, we use a block coordinate descent algorithm in which we optimize the objective with respect to a particular group of functions at once while all remaining functions are kept fixed. Before presenting a complete algorithm for the regularized model, we first describe how to estimate the simpler, unpenalized model introduced in Section 2.1. Given the loss function of (4), some algebra shows that the optimal solution for f g j satisfies the following conditional expectation for each genetic marker j ¼ 1;. .. ; p and each genotype value g 2 f0; 1; 2g.</p><formula>f g j ðTÞ ¼ E YðTÞ À f 0 ðTÞ À X k6 ¼j X ' f ' k ðTÞ X ' k j T; X j ¼ g 2 4 3 5 (8)</formula><p>It has been well established in the statistics literature that a scatterplot smoother matrix can be viewed as a natural estimate of the conditional expected value (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hastie and Tibshirani, 1990</ref>). To evaluate (8) in the sample setting, we therefore replace the conditional expectation operator E½ Á j T; X j ¼ g by left multiplication with an n-by-n smoother matrix S g j ¼ fS g j ½a; bg, which is defined as S g j ½a; b / K h ðjt ðaÞ À t ðbÞ jÞ if x ðaÞ j ¼ g and x ðbÞ j ¼ g S g j ½a; b ¼ 0 otherwise where (a, b) is a pair of data points, each corresponding to a particular individual i and time point s, and K h is a smoothing kernel function with bandwidth h. An alternative way to think about S g j is as the element-wise product of a smoother matrix for T, in which entry (a, b) is proportional to K h ðjt ðaÞ À t ðbÞ jÞ, and an indicator matrix for X j ¼ g, in which entry (a, b) is given by Ifx ðaÞ j ¼ x ðbÞ j ¼ gg. This makes intuitive sense because we want to estimate a smooth function over time for each genotype value of each SNP. Thus, to learn each function f g j for a particular SNP j and a particular genotype g, we only want to consider data points for which the genotype at SNP j is g and we want to smooth over time. The empirical estimate of f g j will be a vector b f g j 2 R nm whose entries correspond to smoothed estimates of the effect of marker j with genotype g on the phenotype at each of the observed time points. Note that the entries of this vector corresponding to samples with genotype 6 ¼ g for SNP j will be set to zero because the function is not applicable to those samples. In practice, we drop these dummy entries at the end to obtain our final function estimates. We calculate these estimates using the empirical formula for (8),</p><formula>b f g j ¼ S g j y À b f 0 À X k6 ¼j X ' b f ' k Ifx k ¼ 'g ! (9)</formula><p>where y is the vector of concatenated trait values for each sample, and x k is the corresponding vector of genotypes at SNP k for each sample. Here a sample is a measurement for a specific individual i at a specific time point s. Cycling though SNPs and genotypes and applying the update rule of (9) leads to a variant of the well-known backfitting algorithm. We refer the readers to Hastie and<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Tibshirani (1990)</ref>for details about smoothing and backfitting. Finally, in order to optimize the penalized objective given in (6), we adapt the block coordinate descent and thresholding algorithms from<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Yin et al. (2012)</ref>to our setting. The complete optimization routine is shown in Algorithm 1. After smoothing the partial residual at each iteration, we perform a thresholding step by estimating the group norm b w j and using it to determine whether the group of functions b f j should be set to zero. If not, we re-estimate the function values by iteratively solving a fixed point equation. We note that Step 9 of our algorithm runs more efficiently than the corresponding step of the thresholding algorithm presented in Yin et al.</p><p>(2012) because we do not need to perform a matrix inversion on each iteration. This property results from the fact that within a particular group of function estimates, each one covers a disjoint set of observations, which simplifies the update equation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Simulation study</head><p>In order to illustrate the utility of our method, we perform several experiments on synthetic data. We generate data according to the following procedure. First we construct a set of realistic genotypes X ij by randomly subsampling individuals and SNPs from the real asthma dataset that we analyze in the next section. Next we independently sample time points T is $ Unifð0; 1Þ and measurement errors is $ N ð0; 1Þ. We select a subset of SNPs that will have nonzero contribution to the phenotype by placing their functions in an active set A ff 1 ;. .. ; f p g. We then construct the active functions by sampling their values from a diverse set of predefined influence patterns that exhibit a variety of trait penetrance models (including additive, multiplicative, dominant, and recessive) and interact differently with time (including some static patterns for balance). All functions not in the active set, including the intercept term, are defined such that f ðtÞ ¼ 0 8 t. Finally, we generate phenotype values y is according to the model defined in (3). To test the robustness of our model, we generate data according to two slightly different variants of (3). In the first setting, we uphold our original assumption that the residual errors are completely uncorrelated by independently generating x is $ N ð0; r 2 Þ. In the second setting, we invalidate this assumption and introduce strong correlation among the errors across time by jointly generating ðx i1 ;. .. ; x im Þ $ N ð0; RÞ. In all of our experiments, we fix the number of samples at n ¼ 100 and the number of time points at m ¼ 10. Then, to evaluate our approach in a broad range of settings, we vary the total number of SNPs over p 2 f50; 100; 200; 500; 1000; 2000; 5000g, which covers both the p n and p&gt; n cases, and vary the size of the active set over jAj 2 f5; 10; 20g. We compare our method against several baselines, including single-marker hypothesis testing (using the Wald test), group lasso (where each group consists of the 3 genotype indicators for one SNP), fGWAS, and BGL-fGWAS. We used several software packages to run these methods: the PLINK toolkit (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Purcell, 2009</ref>) for the Wald test, the SLEP Matlab package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Liu et al., 2009</ref>) for lasso and group lasso, and the fGWAS2 R package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wang and Li, 2012</ref>) for fGWAS and BGL-fGWAS. To run the static data methods (hypothesis test and group lasso), we summarize the phenotype values by averaging across time. To evaluate performance, we calculate the maximum power attained by each method at a fixed false discovery rate. In order to</p><formula>¼ S 0 ðy À P k P ' b f ' k Ifx k ¼</formula><p>'gÞ 5: for j ¼ 1;. .. ; p do 6: compute partial residual:calculate this metric, we first generate a ranked list of the top jAj SNPs identified by each method. For the Wald test and fGWAS, this is given by the SNPs with the smallest p-values. For the penalized regression methods, we test a series of values of the regularization parameter, k, and select the one that yields approximately the desired number of SNPs. We then rank these SNPs according to their fitted model weights or norms. Given this list, we select a cutoff point that yields the largest set of SNPs such that FDR is below 0.2, and we calculate the power at this threshold. The results of our experiments are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 2</ref>. Our results indicate that TV-GroupSpAM far outperforms all of the baseline methods in every setting. In many cases, the three dynamic methods are able to detect at least twice as many true associations as the static methods. This underscores the value of leveraging longitudinal data to boost statistical power. The results show that TV-GroupSpAM outperforms fGWAS even when the residual errors are correlated, despite the fact that our model assumes independent errors while fGWAS does not. These results demonstrate that TV-GroupSpAM performs well under many different conditions and is robust to noise.</p><formula>b R j ¼ y À b f 0 À X k6 ¼j X ' b f ' k Ifx k ¼ '</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Genome-wide association study of asthma</head><p>Next we use TV-GroupSpAM to perform a genome-wide association analysis of asthma traits. We look for associations between SNPs and two quantitative phenotypes frequently used to assess asthma severity: the forced vital capacity (FVC), a sensitive measure of airway obstruction, and bronchodilator response (BDR), which measures lung response to bronchodilator drugs. For this analysis, we use data from the CAMP longitudinal study of childhood asthma (Childhood Asthma Management Program Research<ref type="bibr">Group et al., 1999</ref>) with n ¼ 552 subjects genotyped at p ¼ 510 540 SNPs from across all 22 autosomal chromosomes. After preprocessing, in which we removed subjects with missing data and SNPs with minor allele frequency below 0.05, we were left with n ¼ 465 and p ¼ 509 299.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Average Precision-Recall Curves</head><p>WaldTest GroupLasso fGWAS BGLfGWAS TvGroupSpam<ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>. Comparison of precision-recall curves of TV-GroupSpAM to baseline methods shows that our approach has an average AUCPR of 0.87 60.01, which is much higher than the most competitive baseline, BGL-fGWAS, which has an average AUCPR 0.59 6 0</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>.02</head><p>In order to control for non-genetic effects, we incorporated several static covariates into our model, including: sex, race, the age of onset of asthma, the clinic where the patient's traits were measured, and the treatment or control group to which the patient was assigned in the clinical trial associated with the CAMP study. For computational efficiency, we first used our approach to filter out a relatively small set of SNPs to include in the final analysis for each phenotype. To do this, we split the dataset into 100 subsets, each containing $5000 SNPs, and ran TV-GroupSpAM separately on each set. We regulated the model sparsity by using a binary search procedure to identify a value of k that selected between 90 and 110 SNPs from each subset, following the example of<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Wu et al. (2009)</ref>. This yielded a filtered set of 10 118 SNPs for the FVC model and 9621 SNPs for the BDR model.<ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>shows the model weight (an indicator of significance) of every SNP that was selected in the filtering step for each phenotype. Next we fit a new global model for each trait using only these selected SNPs, and chose a value of k that yielded approximately 50 SNPs with nonzero effect on the phenotype (yielding 48 for FVC and 51 for BDR). Finally, we refit the model on just these selected SNPs with no regularization penalty, and use the estimated group functional norms to determine the effect size of each SNP. The complete sets of selected SNPs identified for each trait are listed in Supplementary Tables S1 and S2. Note that the FVC effect sizes are much higher in magnitude than the BDR effect sizes because the FVC phenotype is measured in different units than the BDR phenotype. In order to analyze the validity of our results, we identified all genes located within 500 Kb of each SNP and then determined whether any of the genetic loci or nearby genes are known to be associated with asthma or asthma-related functions in the existing literature. Because asthma is a disease characterized by inflammation and constriction of the airways of the lungs, we specifically searched for genes that have been linked to lung function or inflammatory response. Furthermore, since asthma is partly driven by a series of interactions between vascular endothelial cells and leukocytes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bijanzadeh et al., 2011</ref>), we also searched for genes involved in functions of the vascular system or the immune system, particularly those in pathways involving T-helper 2 (Th2) cells, which play a central role in the pathogenesis of asthma (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Ober and Yao, 2011</ref>). We list a curated subset of the SNPs selected in the FVC and BDR models in Tables 1 and 2, along with the nearby genes that can be linked to asthma. Our model was able to identify several genetic loci that have a well-established connection to asthma. For example, SNP rs6116189 on chromosome 20 is located near the ADAM33 gene, which has been implicated in asthma by several independent studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Ober and Hoffjan, 2006</ref>). In addition, SNP rs1450118 on chromosome 3 is located near IL1RAP, a gene that produces the Interleukin 1 receptor accessory protein and plays an important role in asthma (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Ober and Yao, 2011</ref>). Finally, the locus on chromosome 7 at 139.3 Mb is particularly interesting because it was selected in both the FVC and BDR models. This SNP is located near the TBXAS1 gene, which has been linked to asthma (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Oh et al., 2011</ref>). We plot some examples of the estimated time-varying effects of SNPs selected in our FVC and BDR models in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 6</ref>. Finally, in order to evaluate the sensitivity of TV-GroupSpAM to noise in the data, we returned to the two filtered sets of $10 000 SNPs each and reran the final selection step on multiple 90% subsamples of the data, then analyzed the stability of the set of selected SNPs. Because the stability naturally varies with the total number of SNPs being selected, we ran our algorithm on each subsample for a fixed set of k values such that the fraction of selected SNPs ranged from 0.5% to nearly 100%. We then calculated the average stability for a particular value of k as the average pairwise overlap among the selected SNPs divided by the average number of SNPs selected across all subsamples. We plot the stability as a function of the average percentage of SNPs selected in<ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>, with the shaded region showing the standard deviation. These results indicate that the stability of the FVC model when selecting 0.47% of SNPs (48 out of 10 118) is 32% and the stability of the BDR model when selecting 0.53% of SNPs (51 out of 9621) is 39%.<ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>. Manhattan plots of the model weights for each SNP that was selected in the FVC model (left) and BDR model (right) during the filtering stageshows that our approach runs much faster than both fGWAS and BGLfGWAS. We were unable to run fGWAS for p &gt; 1000 or BGL-fGWAS for p &gt; 200 due to time constraints</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Discussion</head><p>In this work, we propose a new approach to GWAS that bridges the gap between existing penalized regression methods, such as the lasso and group lasso, and dynamic trait methods, such as fGWAS. Our approach uses penalized regression to identify a sparse set of SNPs that jointly influence a dynamic trait. This is a challenging task for several reasons: first, we must contend with high-dimensional data, which necessitates that we regularize the model to perform variable selection; second, we do not know the true underlying model by which each SNP acts on the phenotype, and therefore we must avoid making parametric assumptions about these patterns; third, we assume that SNP effects vary smoothly over time, which means that we cannot apply a standard multi-task regression model that treats the time series as a set of unordered traits. Although TV-GroupSpAM achieves significantly better performance on synthetic data than existing methods, there are still certain challenging aspects of genome-wide association mapping that are not addressed by this approach. One of these is the task of rare variant detection. Although our method is robust to detecting spurious effects from rare variants, we are also not able to detect true effects from rare variants with high power. This is due to the lack of data available for the aa genotype in SNPs with very low minor allelegrowth factor b1; has pro-inflammatory as well as anti-inflammatory properties, and has been linked to asthma and airway remodeling (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Nagpal et al., 2005</ref>) CYP2A6, CYP2A7, RAB4B, MIA, EGLND—genes located in a known COPD locus (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bossé, 2012</ref>A time-varying group sparse additive model for GWASfrequency; because we estimate a separate effect function for each SNP genotype, we are unable to accurately estimate f aa when there are very few data points corresponding to this genotype. Modifying TV-GroupSpAM to more accurately detect the effects of rare variants would be an interesting direction for future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health<ref type="bibr">[</ref></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. GWAS has greater statistical power when dynamic traits are used. (a) A toy dataset illustrating the difference between static and dynamic traits. (b) Two synthetic examples of time-dependent patterns of SNP influence on the trait that would be difficult to detect with a static model</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Algorithm1.</head><figDesc>Block Coordinate Descent for TV-GroupSpAM 1: inputs: genotypes x 1 ;. .. ; x p , time points t, trait values y 2: initialize b f 0 ¼ 0 and b f g j ¼ 0 for j ¼ 1;. .. ; p and g 2 f0; 1; 2g 3: repeat 4: update intercept term: b f 0</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><figDesc>To obtain a more complete picture of the performance of each method, we plot the precision-recall curves obtained by varying the number of SNPs selected by each method from 0 to p. The average precision-recall curves obtained by averaging results over 20 datasets for the most challenging synthetic data setting (p ¼ 200, jAj ¼ 20, correlated errors) are shown in Figure 3. We also report the area under the precision recall curve (AUCPR) for BGL-fGWAS and TV-GroupSpAM. Our approach outperforms the most competitive baseline by a significant margin. Lastly, we compare the run times of the three dynamic trait methods for different values of p, and show the results in Figure 4. For p ¼ 200, TV-GroupSpAM ran in 12 minutes, fGWAS ran in 69 minutes, and BGL-fGWAS ran in 20 hours. These results show that our method is by far the most computationally efficient.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Comparison of TV-GroupSpAM to baseline methods shows that our approach achieves greater power for a fixed false discovery rate (FDR 0.2). The results are averaged over 20 random synthetic datasets for each setting, and the shaded region denotes the standard error</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Comparison of the running time of TV-GroupSpAM to baseline methods shows that our approach runs much faster than both fGWAS and BGLfGWAS. We were unable to run fGWAS for p &gt; 1000 or BGL-fGWAS for p &gt; 200 due to time constraints</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><figDesc>ADAM33—disintegrin and metalloproteinase domain-containing protein 33; has been implicated in asthma by several independent studies (Ober and Hoffjan, 2006; Van Eerdewegh et al., 2002)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><figDesc>this enzyme converts prostaglandin H2 to prostaglandin E2, a lipid inflammatory mediator that acts in the lung (Liu et al., 2012) rs11069178 12 117.9 Mb 0.6869 NOS1—nitric oxide synthase 1; nitric oxide levels are elevated in the air exhaled by asthmatics; NOS1 has been linked to a higher risk of asthma (Gao et al., 2000)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig.6.</head><figDesc>Fig. 6. Examples of estimated dynamic SNP effects. The top row shows four SNPs from the FVC model. The bottom row shows four SNPs from the BDR model</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><figDesc>grant numbers R01-GM093156, P30-DA035778]. Micol Marchetti-Bowick is partly supported by a National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship [under grant number DGE-1252522]. Junming Yin is partly supported by a Ray and Stephanie Lane Research Fellowship from CMU and a research award from the Center for Management Innovations in Health Care at the Eller College of Management. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. Selected SNPs associated with BDR</figDesc><table>SNP 
Chrom Location 
Effect size Nearby genes linked to asthma 

rs7766818 
6 
46.8 Mb 
0.0088 
GPR116—probable G protein-coupled receptor 116; plays a critical role in lung surfactant homeo-
stasis (Yang et al., 2013) 
TNFRSF21—tumor necrosis factor receptor superfamily member 21; plays a central role in regulat-
ing immune response and airway inflammation in mice (Venkataraman et al., 2006) 
rs12524603 
6 
159.8 Mb 
0.0075 
SOD2—superoxide dismutase 2, mitochondrial; plays a role in oxidative stress, and has been 
linked to bronchial hyperresponsiveness and COPD (Siedlinski et al., 2009) 
rs13239058 
7 
139.3 Mb 
0.0079 
TBXAS1—see Table 1 above 
rs10519096 
15 
59.1 Mb 
0.0086 
ADAM10—disintegrin and metalloproteinase domain-containing protein 10; plays an important 
role in immunoglobulin E dependent lung inflammation (Mathews et al., 2011) 
rs8111845 
19 
41.6 Mb 
0.0066 
TGFB1—transforming </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Selected SNPs associated with FVC</figDesc><table>SNP 
Chrom Location 
Effect size Nearby genes linked to asthma 

rs6442021 
3 
46.7 Mb 
1.5303 
CCR1, CCR2, CCR3, CCR5—chemokine receptors in the CC family; CCR2 is a receptor for a 
protein that plays a role in several inflammatory diseases, and has been directly linked to 
asthma (Batra and Ghosh, 2009); CCR3 may play a role in airway inflammation (NCBI, 2005) 
PRSS42, PRSS46, PRSS45, PRSS50—trypsin-like serine proteases; tryptases are known to cause 
bronchoconstriction and have been implicated in asthma (Zhang and Timmerman, 1997) 
rs2062583 
3 
56.9 Mb 
1.0074 
IL17RD—interleukin 17 receptor D; IL-17 is a pro-inflammatory cytokine produced by Th17 
cells that plays a role in multiple inflammatory diseases, including asthma (Manni et al., 2014) 
rs1450118 
3 
190.4 Mb 
0.9027 
IL1RAP—interleukin 1 receptor accessory protein; enables the binding of IL-33 to its receptor 
encoded by IL1RL1, which has been repeatedly linked to asthma (Ober and Yao, 2011) 
rs3801148 
7 
139.3 Mb 
0.8538 
TBXAS1—thromboxane A synthase; this enzyme converts prostaglandin H2 to thromboxane A2, 
a lipid that constricts smooth respiratory muscle (Oh et al., 2011) 
rs914978 
9 
132.3 Mb 
1.0631 
PTGES—prostaglandin E synthase; </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">M.Marchetti-Bowick et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic contribution of chemokine receptor 2 (CCR2) polymorphisms towards increased serum total IgE levels in Indian asthmatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Batra</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Ghosh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="168" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An understanding of the genetic basis of asthma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Bijanzadeh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Indian J. Med. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">149</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Updates on the COPD gene list Childhood Asthma Management Program Research Group The childhood asthma management program (CAMP) design, rationale, and methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Bossé</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Chronic Obstruct. Pulmon. Dis. Control. Clin. Trials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>et. al.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basic statistical analysis in genetic case-control studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Clarke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A dynamic model for genome-wide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Das</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="629" to="639" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic semiparametric bayesian models for genetic mapping of complex trait with irregular longitudinal data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Das</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="523" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust estimation of experimentwise p values applied to a genome scan of multiple asthma traits identifies a new region of significant linkage on chromosome 20q13</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Ferreira</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1075" to="1085" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide association mapping with longitudinal data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Furlotte</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="463" to="471" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variants of NOS1, NOS2, and NOS3 genes in asthmatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Gao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemical and Biophys. Res. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">267</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="761" to="763" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Generalized Additive Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Hastie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Tibshirani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A catalog of published genome-wide association studies. Available at: www.genome.gov/gwastudies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Hindorff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The bayesian lasso for genome-wide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="516" to="523" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Bayesian group lasso for nonparametric varying-coefficient models with application to functional genome-wide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Appl. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="640" to="664" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A bayesian nonparametric approach for mapping dynamic quantitative traits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Sillanp€ A€ A</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">194</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="997" to="1016" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic variants in PLCB4/PLCB1 as susceptibility loci for coronary artery aneurysm formation in Kawasaki disease in Han Chinese in Taiwan</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14762</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">SLEP: Sparse Learning with Efficient Projections. Arizona State University Available at: http://www.yelab.net/software</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prostaglandin E2 deficiency uncovers a dominant role for thromboxane A2 in house dust mite-induced allergic pulmonary inflammation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12692" to="12697" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A tale of two cytokines: Il-17 and IL-22 in asthma and infection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Manni</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp. Rev. Respir. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A potential new target for asthma therapy: a disintegrin and metalloprotease 10 (ADAM10) involvement in murine experimental asthma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Mathews</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Allergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1193" to="1200" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TGFb1 haplotypes and asthma in Indian populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Nagpal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Allergy Clin. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="533" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Entrez Gene Database Available at</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Ncbi</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asthma genetics 2006: the long and winding road to gene discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Ober</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hoffjan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="100" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genetics of asthma and allergic disease: a 21st century perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Ober</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Yao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">242</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association analysis of thromboxane A synthase 1 gene polymorphisms with aspirin intolerance in asthmatic patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Oh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacogenomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="363" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">PLINK 1.07 Available at</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Purcell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Superoxide dismutases, lung function and bronchial responsiveness in a general population</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Siedlinski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. Respir. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="986" to="992" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association of the ADAM33 gene with asthma and bronchial hyperresponsiveness</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Van Eerdewegh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">418</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="426" to="430" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Death receptor-6 regulates the development of pulmonary eosinophilia and airway inflammation in a mouse model of asthma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Venkataraman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunol. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>fGWAS2. . Available at</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide association analysis by lasso penalized logistic regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="714" to="721" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonparametric functional mapping of quantitative trait loci</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Essential regulation of lung surfactant homeostasis by the orphan G protein-coupled receptor GPR116</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1457" to="1464" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Group sparse additive models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Yin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 29th International Conference on Machine Learning</title>
		<meeting>the 29th International Conference on Machine Learning</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="871" to="878" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PLC/CAMK IV-NF-jb involved in the receptor for advanced glycation end products mediated signaling pathway in human endothelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>You</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Endocrinol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">320</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model selection and estimation in regression with grouped variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Yuan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Stat. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mast cell tryptase and asthma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Timmerman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mediators Inflamm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="317" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time-varying additive models for longitudinal data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="983" to="998" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Average stability of the FVC model (left) and BDR model (right) for different fractions of selected SNPs. Shaded region denotes the standard deviation. Vertical dashed line indicates the fraction of the filtered SNPs that we selected in our final analysis that yielded 48 SNPs for FVC and 51 SNPs for BDR</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Fig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>