
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:59+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis ALEA: a toolbox for allele-specific epigenomics analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hamid</forename>
								<surname>Younesy</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<country>Canada&apos;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computing Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Graphics Usability and Visualization Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Simon Fraser University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>V5A 1S6</postCode>
									<settlement>Burnaby</settlement>
									<region>British Columbia</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Torsten</forename>
								<surname>Mö Ller</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computing Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Graphics Usability and Visualization Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Simon Fraser University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>V5A 1S6</postCode>
									<settlement>Burnaby</settlement>
									<region>British Columbia</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Visualization and Data Analysis Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Vienna</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>A-1090</postCode>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alireza</forename>
								<surname>Heravi-Moussavi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<country>Canada&apos;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename>
								<forename type="middle">B</forename>
								<surname>Cheng</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Francisco</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine>
									<postCode>94143</postCode>
									<region>California</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
								<forename type="middle">F</forename>
								<surname>Costello</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Brain Tumor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Francisco</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine>
									<postCode>94158</postCode>
									<settlement>Helen</settlement>
									<region>California</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matthew</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Lorincz</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medical Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Life Sciences Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of British Columbia</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>V6T 1Z3</postCode>
									<settlement>Vancouver</settlement>
									<region>British Columbia</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mohammad</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Karimi</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>mkarimi1@interchange.ubc.ca or sjones@bcgsc.ca</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<country>Canada&apos;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medical Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Life Sciences Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of British Columbia</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>V6T 1Z3</postCode>
									<settlement>Vancouver</settlement>
									<region>British Columbia</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Steven</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J M</forename>
								<surname>Jones</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<country>Canada&apos;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Michael Smith Genome Sciences Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">BC Cancer Agency</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>V5Z 4S6</postCode>
									<settlement>Vancouver</settlement>
									<region>British Columbia</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis ALEA: a toolbox for allele-specific epigenomics analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1172" to="1174"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt744</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 21, 2013; revised on November 25, 2013; accepted on December 9, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Michael Brudno Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The assessment of expression and epigenomic status using sequen-cing based methods provides an unprecedented opportunity to identify and correlate allelic differences with epigenomic status. We present ALEA, a computational toolbox for allele-specific epigenomics analysis, which incorporates allelic variation data within existing resources , allowing for the identification of significant associations between epigenetic modifications and specific allelic variants in human and mouse cells. ALEA provides a customizable pipeline of command line tools for allele-specific analysis of next-generation sequencing data (ChIP-seq, RNA-seq, etc.) that takes the raw sequencing data and produces separate allelic tracks ready to be viewed on genome browsers. The pipeline has been validated using human and hybrid mouse ChIP-seq and RNA-seq data. Availability: The package, test data and usage instructions are available online at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Each diploid cell consists of two near-identical copies of the genome. Despite the similarity of these paternally and maternally contributed genomes, they differ in certain genomic loci due to heterozygous variants such as single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), indels and structural variations, which can be used to find allele-specific (AS) epigenetic variations. AS events may occur everywhere, including regions devoid of heterozygous variants. However, computational tools can only focus on heterozygous loci where the allelic differences are distinguishable. AlleleSeq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Rozowsky et al., 2011</ref>) is a computational pipeline for phasing heterozygous variants from trio (father, mother and child) data, constructing diploid personal genome and aligning short sequencing reads to maternal and paternal genomes. iASeq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Wei et al., 2012</ref>) uses a machine-learning approach to find the allelic imbalance by jointly analyzing multiple ChIP-seq datasets and by improving the AS inference using correlations among them. Allim (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Pandey et al., 2013</ref>) is a more recent AS tool for RNA-seq analysis of F1 individuals that generates a polymorphism-aware diploid reference genome from trio genomic and/or transcriptomic sequences, and corrects the residual mapping bias when measuring the allelic expression imbalance. What limits application of these tools for AS epigenomics studies is that the majority of genomic datasets are generated from single patient samples, which do not include genomic data from the parents of the patients. Also, it is not always practical or desirable to sequence multiple epigenomic marks for each patient as required by iASeq. To address these limitations, we developed a new pipeline, ALEA, for AS epigenomics analysis. ALEA takes advantage of the available genomic resources for human (The 1000 Genomes Project Consortium) and mouse (The Mouse Genomes Project) to reconstruct diploid in silico genomes for human or hybrid mice under study. Then, for each accompanying ChIP-seq or RNAseq dataset, ALEA generates two wiggle track format files from short reads aligned differentially to each haplotype.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>ALEA consists of the following four modules for which the processes, the input and output files and their formats are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1.</ref>A. Genotype phasing: For human samples, genotypes are typically called from whole genome-sequencing short reads accompanying the epigenomic dataset under AS study. SHAPEIT2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Delaneau et al., 2013</ref>) is then used to phase genotypes using the publicly available reference panel of haplotypes, provided by the 1000 Genomes project (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">McVean et al., 2012</ref>). We then use the phased haplotypes together with the original unphased variant files in the Variant Call Format (VCF) to create a phased variant file with two haplotypes containing homozygous and phased heterozygous SNPs and indels (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1a</ref>). For mouse datasets, ALEA accepts epigenomic marks from F1 hybrid offspring whose parents are among the 17 inbred strains available from the Mouse Genomes Project (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Keane et al., 2011</ref>). *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Diploid personal</head><p>genome reconstruction: The output of the phasing module, the phased variant file, together with the reference genome is fed into the second module (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1b</ref>) in which haplotype regions are reconstructed from the individual haplotypes. Two in silico genomes are created to be used for the optimal identification of chromosomal or AS effects. For mouse, the two in silico genomes represent the parental haplotypes, whereas for human the two genomes will essentially be a mosaic of the parental haplotypes due to the unlikeliness of true long-range phasing. The homozygous SNPs and indels do not need phasing, and they are simply assigned to both parental genomes. Although the homozygous variants are not informative for AS analyses, they may be included to investigate specific epigenomic signatures between individuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Haplotype-specific read alignment: This module aligns short</head><p>sequencing reads to the in silico genomes constructed by the previous module and detects reads that are uniquely aligned only to one of the two genomes (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1c</ref>). Thus, all reads aligned to multiple locations of either haplotypes or aligned uniquely to both haplotypes are filtered out and only AS reads mapping to the regions containing heterozygous SNPs are detected. We provide two methods to detect the AS reads:</p><p>(i) aligning the reads to a concatenated parental genome and (ii) aligning the reads to each parental genome separately. Details and comparison of the two methods are included in the Section 1 of the Supplementary Material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Projection to</head><p>reference genome: The fourth module (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1d</ref>) generates two haplotype-specific track files from mapped reads and projects them back to the reference genome. Owing to the existence of indels in the construction of parental in silico genomes, the coordinates of the tracks are skewed when compared with the reference genome. However, most visualization tools work based on alignment to reference genomes. Using an index created with the in silico genomes, ALEA maps the tracks back to the reference genome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">EVALUATION</head><p>We used known imprinted genes to validate our AS method for both human and mouse, as these regions are known to show allelic differences in both expression and specific histone marks. We used our AS pipeline on human skin fibroblast RNA-seq and H3K36me3 ChIP-seq datasets generated from the same individual. These data are available for download under the Gene Expression Omnibus accession numbers GSM751277 and GSM817238. Having advance access to unpublished whole genome-sequencing data for this individual, we called and phased the genotype, reconstructed in silico genomes and generated separate read profiles for each haplotype for RNA-seq and H3K36me3 data.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2a</ref>shows the monoallelic H3K36me3 enrichment of expressed alleles in selected humanimprinted genes. A similar approach was also applied to a recently published dataset for mouse trophoblast cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Calabrese et al., 2012</ref>), including RNA-seq and H3K36me3 ChIP-seq data derived from crosses between CAST/EiJ (Cast) and C57BL/6J (B6) mice. As we expected, H3K36me3 enriches the gene body of active genes and correlates with expression level of selected imprinted genes in a monoallelic manner (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2b</ref>). The details of the quantitative analysis and validation of haplotype-specific wiggle track format files for human and mouse are described in the Section 2 of the Supplementary Material. reference genome (.fasta)<ref type="bibr">[ALEA]</ref>Construct in silico genomes<ref type="bibr">[Aligner+ SAMTools]</ref>Align to in silico genomeThe tracks show opposite haplotype-specific RNA-seq and H3K36me3 read profiles for IGF2 and PLAGL1 versus RTL1 in human skin fibroblast, consistent with the fact that IGF2 and PLAGL1 have different imprinting status compared with RTL1. (b) Slc38a4 (Mirg)-imprinted gene is paternally (maternally) expressed in mouse trophoblast cells. The SNP-poor regions are devoid of reads as expected</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. AS epigenomics analysis pipeline: (a) genotype phasing, (b) constructing diploid genome, (c) finding haplotype-specific short reads and (d) projecting the haplotypic read profiles to reference genome</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Viewing haplotype-specific read tracks in the WashU epigenome browser using the same scale for both haplotypes in each gene reveals that AS H3K36me3 enrichment and RNA-seq expression in selected imprinted genes are correlated. (a) The tracks show opposite haplotype-specific RNA-seq and H3K36me3 read profiles for IGF2 and PLAGL1 versus RTL1 in human skin fibroblast, consistent with the fact that IGF2 and PLAGL1 have different imprinting status compared with RTL1. (b) Slc38a4 (Mirg)-imprinted gene is paternally (maternally) expressed in mouse trophoblast cells. The SNP-poor regions are devoid of reads as expected</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">H.Younesy et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Site-specific silencing of regulatory elements as a mechanism of X inactivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Calabrese</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">151</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="951" to="963" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved whole-chromosome phasing for disease and population genetic studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Delaneau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Meth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mouse genomic variation and its effect on phenotypes and gene regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Keane</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">477</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="294" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated map of genetic variation from 1,092 human genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Mcvean</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">491</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Allelic imbalance metre (Allim), a new tool for measuring allele-specific gene expression with RNA-seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Pandey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ecol. Resour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="740" to="745" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AlleleSeq: analysis of allele-specific expression and binding in a network framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Rozowsky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">iASeq: integrative analysis of allele-specificity of protein-DNA interactions in multiple ChIP-seq datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">681</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>