
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:29+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free detection of local similarity among viral and bacterial genomes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mirjana</forename>
								<surname>Domazet-Lošo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Evolutionary Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max-Planck-Institute for Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>24306</postCode>
									<settlement>Plön</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bernhard</forename>
								<surname>Haubold</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Evolutionary Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max-Planck-Institute for Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>24306</postCode>
									<settlement>Plön</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alex</forename>
								<surname>Bateman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Applied Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Electrical Engineering and Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Zagreb</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Zagreb</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free detection of local similarity among viral and bacterial genomes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1466" to="1472"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr176</idno>
					<note type="submission">Genome analysis Advance Access publication April 6, 2011 Received on February 16, 2011; revised on March 11, 2011; accepted on March 30, 2011</note>
					<note>[15:09 12/5/2011 Bioinformatics-btr176.tex] Page: 1466 1466–1472 Croatia Associate Editor: Availability: alfy is written in standard C and its source code is available under the GNU General Public License from The software package also includes documentation and example data. Contact: haubold@evolbio.mpg.de Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Bacterial and viral genomes are often affected by horizontal gene transfer observable as abrupt switching in local homology. In addition to the resulting mosaic genome structure, they frequently contain regions not found in close relatives, which may play a role in virulence mechanisms. Due to this connection to medical microbiology, there are numerous methods available to detect horizontal gene transfer. However, these are usually aimed at individual genes and viral genomes rather than the much larger bacterial genomes. Here, we propose an efficient alignment-free approach to describe the mosaic structure of viral and bacterial genomes, including their unique regions. Results: Our method is based on the lengths of exact matches between pairs of sequences. Long matches indicate close homology, short matches more distant homology or none at all. These exact match lengths can be looked up efficiently using an enhanced suffix array. Our program implementing this approach, alfy (ALignment-Free local homologY), efficiently and accurately detects the recombination break points in simulated DNA sequences and among recombinant HIV-1 strains. We also apply alfy to Escherichia coli genomes where we detect new evidence for the hypothesis that strains pathogenic in poultry can infect humans.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>In contrast to most eukaryotes, viruses and bacteria reproduce asexually. Nevertheless, their genomes are littered with evidence of occasional and localized recombination, usually referred to as 'horizontal gene transfer'. Horizontal gene transfer is observable as an abrupt change in homology along an alignment of two or more sequences. The importance of horizontal gene transfer for the evolution of immune evasion and antibiotic resistance of pathogenic * To whom correspondence should be addressed. microbes has been known for decades (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Maynard Smith et al., 1991</ref>). Correspondingly, there has been and still is a lot of interest in devising computer programs to automate the detection of mosaic gene or genome structure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Langille et al., 2010</ref>). Most of the current methods for annotating mosaic genome structure are based on alignments and target viral genomes or individual bacterial genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Kosakovsky Pond et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Westesson and Holmes, 2009</ref>). These methods are highly accurate but tend to be too slow for the analysis of whole bacterial genomes. Recently,<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Didelot et al. (2010)</ref>expanded their original Monte Carlo Markov Chain method for inferring recombination rates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Didelot and Falush, 2007</ref>) by also localizing the recombination events in alignments of whole bacterial genomes. However, even given such an alignment, the computational burden of their, again, highly accurate coalescent-based method is considerable. If speed is of concern, dramatic improvements are possible by simplifying or eliminating altogether any explicit model under which inference is made, and in addition by not basing the analysis on a full multiple sequence alignment.<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Rozanov et al. (2004)</ref>provide a web-based genotyping tool for viral genomes hosted by the NCBI. Their algorithm essentially consists of sliding a window across the query sequence and blasting the windows against the set of subject sequences to determine the closest homologs across the query. An even more radical departure from model-and alignmentbased treatment of mosaic genome structure is the alignment-free method for HIV typing proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al. (2007)</ref>. Alignmentfree methods of sequence comparison tend to be very fast, albeit less accurate than alignment-based sequence comparison (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Reinert et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Vinga and Almeida, 2003</ref>). Best known among the alignmentfree approaches are those based on k-word composition, which is also what<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al. (2007)</ref>have used. Here all substrings of length k are counted in the two sequences compared and a distance between the vectors of word counts is defined. Unfortunately, it is difficult to convert distances between word count vectors to true evolutionary distances. We have recently developed two methods that start from the lengths of exact matches between pairs of sequences and convert these to substitutions per site (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Haubold et al., 2011</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Haubold et al., , 2009</ref>). The advantage of this approach is that exact match lengths can be looked up efficiently using suffix trees implemented as their more recent abstractions known as enhanced suffix arrays (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Abouelhoda et al., 2002</ref>) and compressed suffix arrays (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ferragina et al., 2008</ref>). In this article, we use exact match lengths between a query and a potentially large set of subject sequences to solve a specialized,Page: 1467 1466–1472</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sequence similarity</head><p>but frequently occurring problem in sequence analysis: at each position in the query sequence, we wish to determine which subject sequence—if any—is most closely related to the query. This closest neighbors problem is common in microbiology and correspondingly we apply our method to the genomes of HIV and Escherichia coli. The most prevalent form of HIV is the M group of HIV-1, which is divided into eight subtypes (A, B, C, D, F, G, H, J) based on the sequence of their 9 and 10 kb genomes. However, recombination between these subtypes in multiply infected individuals leads to the emergence of new forms of the virus. Accurate detection of the origin of individual HIV-1 genome segments has clinical implications and the development of software to automate this procedure has received corresponding attention (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Kosakovsky Pond et al., 2009</ref>). Closely related strains of bacteria form 'pan-genomes' consisting of a common core and a variable part that is horizontally mobile (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Tettelin et al., 2005</ref>). One example for such a group is E.coli, which has a genome size ranging from 4.6 to 5.7 MB. This taxon comprises commensal strains as well as strains that are pathogenic in humans and homeothermic animals. An important question concerning E.coli is to what extend strains that are pathogens of live stock might cause infections in humans (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Johnson et al., 2007</ref>). In the following sections, we first describe our alignment-free method for determining local homology. We test this method through simulations and then use it to classify HIV-1 recombinant strains and to compare E.coli genomes. When comparing the E.coli genomes, we not only look for switches in local homology indicative of horizontal gene transfer, but also for regions with no close homolog among the subject sequences. Investigation of these 'private' genomic regions leads us to the detection of new evidence for the long-held suspicion that animal E.coli pathogens can also infect humans (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Johnson et al., 2007</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>Given a query DNA sequence, Q, and a set of subject DNA sequences, S ={S 1 ,...,S n }, we wish to determine the subject sequences that Q is most closely related to at every position p in Q. For instance, in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1A</ref>Q<ref type="bibr">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr">2]</ref>=TA matches S 3<ref type="bibr">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr">2]</ref>and Q<ref type="bibr">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr">4]</ref>matches S 2<ref type="bibr">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr">2]</ref>. We therefore say that Q<ref type="bibr">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr">2]</ref>is most closely related to S 3 and Q<ref type="bibr">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr">4]</ref>is most closely related to S 2. In this section, we describe a simplified version of our algorithm to locally annotate Q. The algorithm we actually implemented is detailed in Algorithm S1 of the Supplementary Material. When comparing Q to a specific subject, S i , we denote by h i,p the length of the shortest prefix of the query suffix Q<ref type="bibr">[p,|Q|]</ref>that starts at position p and is absent from S i. We follow our previous convention of calling these shortest absent prefixes shustrings for SHortest Unique subSTRINGS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Haubold and Wiehe, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Haubold et al., 2005</ref>). The length of the longest shustring starting at Q<ref type="bibr">[p]</ref>when compared to all subject sequences is H p = max 1≤i≤n h i,p. Notice that H p is bounded by the query length: H p ≤|Q|−p+1. For our example sequences in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1A</ref>h 1,1 =|T|=1; h 2,1 =|T|=1; h 3,1 =|TAG|=3; and H 1 = max{1,1,3}=3. The set of subject sequences that induce the longest shustring at Q<ref type="bibr">[p]</ref>is</p><formula>S p ={S i ∈ S|h i,p = H p }</formula><p>. For our example, sequences in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1A</ref>S 1 ={S 3 }. To determine which segment of Q is most closely related to which subject sequence, we compute all values of H p and S p. This is done by constructing a generalized suffix tree consisting of the query and all subject sequences (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.1B</ref>). We assume that at every branch node v i of this tree we can look up the length of the concatenated labels along the path from the root to v i , that is, the string depth of v i. For example, the string depth of v 3 in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1B</ref>is 2. This generalized suffix tree is traversed once, and whenever a leaf node w = (Q,p) is encountered, H p is computed as one plus the string depth ofthe lowest common ancestor node of w and any leaf node referring to a subject sequence (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1C</ref>). Moreover, S p is the set of subject sequences in the subtree rooted on that lowest common ancestor. Given the table of H p and S p values in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1C</ref>, we next cover Q with contiguous intervals of closest neighbors. Such closest neighbors intervals have the form (<ref type="bibr">[lb,rb]</ref>,S ,h), where lb and rb are the left and right borders, S = S lb , and h = H lb. The intervals are constructed by traversing the array H 1 ,H 2 ,...,H |Q| and whenever H p &gt; H p−1 , we do two things:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A</head><p>(1) close the current closest neighbors interval by setting rb ← p−1 and S ← S lb ;</p><p>(2) open a new closest neighbors interval with lb ← p and h ← H p .</p><p>For our example in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1C</ref>, this procedure results in the detection of the two closest neighbors intervals (<ref type="bibr">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr">2]</ref>,{S 3 },3) and (<ref type="bibr">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr">5]</ref>,{S 2 },3). Finally, the closest neighbors intervals are summarized into larger regions of similarity. This is done using a sliding window approach: for each subject sequence referred to by the closest neighbors intervals within a window, the shustring lengths are summed and the one or more subject sequences with the greatest sum are designated the closest neighbors of Q at the given position.<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Haubold et al. (2009)</ref>derived the null distribution of shustring lengths as a function of the number of mismatches between pairs of sequences. In the limit of 0.75 mismatches per site this corresponds to the distribution of shustring lengths expected by chance alone. We can therefore also identify query regions without close homologs among the subject set. Such regions are characterized as having an average shustring length that is less than the maximal shustring length expected by chance alone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Implementation</head><p>The procedure for finding closest neighbors intervals can easily be generalized to more than one query sequence and this is the version that we have implemented. However, when dealing with large datasets the auxiliary table of H p and S p values would impose a substantial memory overhead. So instead of explicitly constructing this table, we directly build the set of closest</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>M.Domazet-Lošo and B.Haubold</head><p>neighbors intervals during suffix tree traversal. This yields a much more memory efficient implementation, and by keeping the closest neighbors as an ordered binary tree the concomitant cost in runtime is minimal (Algorithm S1). The final program is called alfy for ALignment-Free local homologY and is written in standard C. The suffix tree was implemented as an enhanced suffix array (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Abouelhoda et al., 2002</ref>) using the suffix array library distributed by Manzini and Ferragina (2002).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Runtime analysis</head><p>alfy determines closest homologs in three phases: it begins by constructing an enhanced suffix array of all m query and n subject sequences. This array is then traversed to compute the list of closest neighbors intervals. Finally, the list of closest neighbors intervals is subjected to sliding window analysis to produce the desired annotation of the query. Suffix array construction for m query and n subject sequences of length L ideally takes time O((m+n)L). Insertion of a single interval node in an interval tree takes O(logL); the construction of one tree per query sequence thus takes a total of O(mLlogL) time. Traversal of m interval trees takes time O(mL). Therefore, the whole procedure takes time O((m+n)L +mLlogL +mL). Notice that if a single query is compared to a large number of subjects, that is, m = 1 and n logL, the run time approaches O(nL).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Phylogeny reconstruction</head><p>Pairwise substitution rates were estimated from whole E.coli genomes using the program kr (Domazet<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Lošo and Haubold, 2009</ref>). The substitution rates were clustered using the neighbor joining algorithm implemented in the program neighbor, which is part of the software package PHYLIP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Felsenstein, 1989</ref>). Trees were midpoint-rooted using retree and drawn using drawgram, which are also part of PHYLIP.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>In the following sections, we first apply alfy to simulated and then to empirical data to explore the efficiency and accuracy of the program.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Runtime and memory consumption</head><p>We simulated sequence samples consisting of one query and 10 or 100 subject sequences with 0.13 or 0.006 segregating sites/nucleotide, respectively, between the query and its closest neighbor using the program Dawg (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cartwright, 2005</ref>).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2A</ref>shows the runtime on a single AMD Opteron 2.3 GHz processor as a function of sequence length. The runtime grows approximately linearly in the sample size and the sequence length, as expected from the analysis in Section 2.2. Similarly, the memory requirement is linear in the amount of sequence data, as expected for a suffix array-based procedure (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2B</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Accuracy of homology detection</head><p>To test the accuracy of local homology detection by alfy, we simulated samples of three pure subject sequences and one recombinant query again using Dawg (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cartwright, 2005</ref>). As shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref>, this was done by generating sequences with distance 2s between Q and S 1 or between Q and S 2. Five such segments were generated, each segment evolving either along genealogy G 1 or along genealogy G 2. Detection accuracy was scored as the fraction of nucleotides correctly assigned to S 1 or S 2. For segments of length 2 kb, the detection accuracy increased with distance up to s ≈ 0.05, while it A Bdecreased significantly for distances greater than s ≈ 0.1 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4A</ref>). Short segments were generally more difficult to locate correctly than long segments and as a result<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4A</ref>with fragment length 2 kb displays a lower overall accuracy than<ref type="figure">Figure</ref>while for intermediate s the detection accuracy is less sensitive to window length.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Application to genome data</head><p>We applied our homology detection method to viral and bacterial genomes in order to solve two common tasks: genotyping of circulating recombinant forms of HIV-1, and detection of horizontal gene transfer and unique segments among E.coli genomes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.1">Detection of circulating recombinant forms of HIV-1 We</head><p>started the analysis by comparing alfy to two fast HIV-1-subtyping tools: the NCBI genotyping tool (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Rozanov et al., 2004</ref>), and the k-word-based clustering method by<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al. (2007)</ref>. These programs and alfy were applied to two published HIV-1 datasets using the approach outlined by<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al. (2007)</ref>, who considered the top two closest sequences as valid annotations. The first dataset consisted of 91 circulating recombinant forms (CRFs, query) compared to 42 pure subtype strains (subject) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Leitner et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al., 2007</ref>). The accuracy of alfy was 93.4%, while<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al. (2007)</ref>reported the accuracy of the NCBI tool as 73.4%, and that of their own tool as 87.3%. The window size for alfy was 300, the same as that used in the NCBI tool.The second dataset consisted of a query set of 266 HIV-1 CRFs compared to a subject set consisting of 42 pure subtype strains and 65 recombinant strains of known subtype (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Leitner et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al., 2007</ref>). Here, alfy subtyped 263 strains correctly, the NCBI tool 264 and<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al. (2007)</ref>annotated 242 strains correctly. In addition to these two fast typing methods, we compared alfy to SCUEAL. This is a phylogeny-based HIV-1 subtyping software that relies on a genetic algorithm to pick the most likely recombinant pattern given a query sequence and an alignment of subject sequences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Kosakovsky Pond et al., 2009</ref>). Its authors report that it detects &lt; 1% false positives on simulated data and we used it to type a single HIV-1 strain (A_DQ083238) against our standard 42 pure strains. This query was originally annotated as a pure A strain, but we have previously noted that it is an A/C recombinant (Domazet<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Lošo and Haubold, 2009</ref>). Correspondingly, SCUEAL and alfy report the transfer of two large C fragments amounting to 24.3% (SCUEAL) and 25.1% (alfy) of the genome (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 5</ref>). The location of the two C-segments determined by SCUEAL (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 5</ref>, top) is similar to the annotation by alfy (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 5</ref>, bottom). We also used the comparison between strain A_QD083238 and the 42 reference strains to benchmark the resource requirements of alfy, the NCBI tool, the<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al. (2007)</ref>tool and SCUEAL.<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>shows that alfy took 0.4 s for this analysis. Unfortunately, the timing of the NCBI tool is not straight forward since this is only available as a web service. To get a rough estimate, we repeatedly ran BLAST with a 300 bp query taken from the query strain against the 42 reference strains. 97 such calls would cover the query in 100 bp steps and this took 1.4 s, which is presumably an upper bound on the true runtime. The Java program by<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al. (2007)</ref>took 3.5 min, while SCUEAL took 6.9 h. As to memory requirements, BLAST used much less memory than alfy (2.2 KB versus 9 MB;<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>). This is expected for a method that indexes the short query (BLAST) as opposed to indexing the long subject (alfy).<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al. (2007)</ref>required the most memory (2.2 GB), while SCUEAL still used over 17 times more memory than alfy (160 MB).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.2">Investigating genomes of pathogenic E.coli</head><p>To test the hypothesis that E.coli strains pathogenic in birds might also infect humans,<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Johnson et al. (2007)</ref>sequenced a strain of avian pathogenic E.coli (APEC_O1) and compared it to the genomes of four fully sequenced E.coli strains, three of which cause urinary tract infection in humans (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 6</ref>). Consistent with their hypothesis, they found that APEC_O1 is very similar to the human uropathogenic strain UTI89.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 7</ref>shows the comparison between APEC_O1 as query and the remaining four E.coli strains as subject using alfy with a window Page: 1470 1466–1472<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8</ref>shows the phylogeny of these strains with the five taxa investigated by<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Johnson et al. (2007</ref>) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 6</ref>) marked in bold. The analysis of the 151.8 MB that make up these genomes plus APEC_01 took alfy 744 s and occupied 5.8 GB of memory. The private fraction of the genome shrank from 3.0% to 0.7% and<ref type="figure">Table 2</ref>shows the 10 unique regions of length 1000 bp or greater that we identified. The longest private region was located between 2 190 501 and 2 196 650. We used megablast to compare<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Johnson et al. (2007)</ref>based on distances calculated using kr (Domazet<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Lošo and Haubold, 2009</ref>). The three uropathogenic strains are italicized. these 6150 bp against the full nucleotide database (nr) and found a single hit that spanned the entire query. This hit comprised part of the gene cluster that specifies the O1-antigen of E.coli serogroup O1. It is filed under Accession GU299791 and was recently sequenced from E.coli strain G1632 that was isolated from a patient with urinary tract infection (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Li et al., 2010</ref>). An optimal local alignment between all 10 301 bp of the O1-antigen gene cluster and the genome of APEC_O1 resulted in an alignment comprising 10 300 bp with 11 mismatches and 3 single nucleotide indels. This high similarity between the O1-antigen region of a clinical isolate and an avian pathogenic E.coli is strong additional evidence that avian pathogenic E.coli can cause urinary tract infections in humans.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>M.Domazet-Lošo and B.Haubold</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>The 'conversion of data to knowledge' is perhaps the greatest challenge in the field of genomics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Brenner, 2010</ref>). This conversion depends on the availability of computational tools that match the</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>[15:09 12/5/2011 Bioinformatics-btr176.tex]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Finding closest neighbors intervals. (A) Unaligned input sequences. (B) Generalized suffix tree of input sequences. (C) Table of longest shustring lengths, H p , and the sets of subject sequences that induce the longest shustring length, S p. (D) The two closest neighbors intervals along Q. See text for further details.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>[15:09 12/5/2011 Bioinformatics-btr176.tex] Page: 1468 1466–1472</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Runtime (A) and memory consumption (B) of alfy as a function of sequence length and sample size, n.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Samples of four sequences were simulated in five segments alternately along genealogies G 1 and G 2. The closest homolog of query Q therefore switched between S 1 and S 2 along its length as illustrated at the bottom.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Accuracy of local homology detection as a function of evolutionary distance, s, using sliding windows of length w. (A) Query consists of 2 kb fragments; (B) query consists of 20 kb fragments. The query structure and the meaning of s are illustrated in Figure 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. HIV-1 strain A_DQ083238 is an A/C recombinant. The position of the material transferred from a C strain is shown in dark gray as diagnosed by SCUEAL (top) and alfy (bottom). alfy was run with window size 300 bp.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig.6.</head><figDesc>Fig. 6. Whole-genome phylogeny of the five E.coli strains investigated by Johnson et al. (2007) based on distances calculated using kr (Domazet-Lošo and Haubold, 2009). The three uropathogenic strains are italicized.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig.8.</head><figDesc>Fig. 8. Whole-genome phylogeny of 30 strains of Escherichia coli based on distances calculated using kr (Domazet-Lošo and Haubold, 2009). The five strains shown in Figure 6 are typeset in bold.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig.7.</head><figDesc>Fig. 7. The genome of E.coli strain APEC_O1 compared to the four other E.coli strains shown in Figure 6. The horizontal bar pointed to by the arrow indicates the 48 kb region transferred from CFT073; length of sliding window: 1 kb.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Time and memory requirements of four HIV-1 typing tools when applied to one query and 42 subject genomes</figDesc><table>Tool 
Time 
Memory 

alfy 
0.4 s 
9 MB 
BLAST 
1.4 s 
2.3 KB 
Wu et al. (2007) 
3.5 m 
2.2 GB 
SCUEAL 
6.9 h 
160 MB 

size of 1 kb. This analysis of the 25.0 MB of sequence data required 
85 s runtime and 961 MB of memory on our reference machine. As 
expected, a high proportion (90.5%) of the APEC_01 genome is 
most similar to its closest relative, UTI89. However, like Johnson 
et al. (2007) we found that between positions 4.71 and 4.76 MB, 
there is a 48 kb region that has been horizontally transferred from 
a strain like CFT073 (Fig. 7, arrow). Johnson et al. (2007) also 
observed that 4.5% of APEC_O1 open reading frames (ORFs) had 
no homolog among the other E.coli strains investigated, that is, these 
ORFs were private to APEC_01. This is similar to our estimate of 
3.0% private nucleotides in that strain. 
The number of fully sequenced E.coli strains contained in RefSeq 
has grown to 29 since the study by Johnson et al. (2007). </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank Peter Pfaffelhuber and Angelika Börsch-Haubold for helpful comments on the manuscript.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sequence similarity</head><p>capabilities of the instruments used to gather the data in the first place. In the realm of sequence analysis, the first big advance came through optimal inexact matching methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Needleman and Wunsch, 1970</ref>; Smith and<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Waterman, 1981</ref>). By combining fast exact matching with the inherently slower inexact matching techniques, fast programs like BLAST and its descendants were created (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Altschul and Lipman, 1990</ref>). In this article, we take this expansion of the role of exact matching in sequence comparison to its logical conclusion by eliminating the inexact matching phase altogether when looking for close local homologs of a query sequence among a set of subject sequences. The result is not a substitute for residueby-residue alignment but a guide to where this level of detail might be applied most profitably. We based our program on the enhanced suffix array library by<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Manzini and Ferragina (2002)</ref>because it is known to be one of the most efficient implementations available (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Puglisi et al., 2007</ref>). As a result, enhanced suffix array construction in alfy remains fast even when analyzing sets of closely related bacterial genomes (). Such run time behavior is not guaranteed, as in the limit of sorting very long identical suffixes the library regresses to its worst case run time, which is quadratic in the number of characters. However, in our experience this has not been a problem in any of our applications ranging from HIV-1 genomes and near-identical E.coli genomes in this article to the complete genomes of 12 Drosophila species (Domazet<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Lošo and Haubold, 2009</ref>). In software based on suffix arrays, the time-consuming construction of the enhanced suffix array is often kept separate from its quick traversal. This makes it possible to apply the traversal to a pre-computed index. However, in alfy we regard each run as a one-off analysis during which the enhanced suffix array is computed on the fly. An implementation based on pre-computed suffix arrays would, of course, be much faster. For example, 80% of the time taken to compare APEC_O1 to 29 E.coli genomes is used for the construction of the enhanced suffix array. Given a pre-computed enhanced suffix array, the runtime of alfy could therefore be reduced up to 5-fold. More important than the exact runtime details of our particular implementation are therefore the program's general properties: for a single query, both its run time and its memory requirement scale linearly with the size of simulated subject sets (). Our simulations inshow that such algorithmically minimal utilization of time and memory is sufficient to obtain reasonably accurate detection of closest neighbors as long as the number of mutations in the sample is not too small or greater than ∼ 0.2 substitutions per site between the query and its closest neighbor. Another requirement for accuracy is that the window size does not exceed the size of the shortest recombinant segment one wishes to detect. Otherwise, the annotation process is hampered by averaging shustring lengths over two or more regions of distinct ancestry. This consideration determined our choice of window size. In the case of HIV, 300 bp windows are also used by the NCBI genotyping tool. In the case of E.coli, we were interested in transfer events spanning at least 1 kb, hence the window size of 1 kb for that analysis. Given these restrictions, alfy could classify recombinant group M HIV-1 strains as reliably as the NCBI tool (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Rozanov et al., 2004</ref>) and the program by<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wu et al. (2007)</ref>. It is certainly possible to achieve greater accuracy as shown by the phylogeny-based tool SCUEAL (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Kosakovsky Pond et al., 2009</ref>), albeit at the cost of escalating the runtime from 0.4 s to 6.9 h for the analysis of a single HIV-1 genome. While such extensive runtime requirements may be acceptable in patient care, it makes SCUEAL difficult to apply to the over 500 times larger genomes of bacteria like E.coli. In our comparison between the avian pathogen APEC_O1 and other E.coli strains we first replicated the analysis by<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Johnson et al. (2007)</ref>. This showed that APEC_O1 is most closely related to strain UTI86, which causes urinary tract infections in humans (Figs 6 and 7). Spliced into this 'clonal frame' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Milkman and McKane Bridges, 1990</ref>) are regions horizontally transferred from other E.coli strains, most notably the 48 kb or more obtained from a strain similar to CFT073, another human pathogen ().<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Johnson et al. (2007)</ref>speculated that the APEC_O1-specific regions they found might be particularly helpful when searching for a link to human disease. We therefore compared APEC_O1 to the 29 E.coli genomes currently available () and found that the longest private region is part of the gene cluster specifying the O1 serotype of APEC_O1. Fortuitously, the entire 10 kb covering the O1 region had just been sequenced in a clinical isolate (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Li et al., 2010</ref>) resulting in a match to the corresponding region in APEC_O1 with only one mismatch per kilobase. Since APEC_O1 infects chickens (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Johnson et al., 2007</ref>), this is further evidence that E.coli pathogens of poultry can infect humans. The near identity of the O-antigen cluster in APEC_O1 and a clinical isolate could have been discovered by simply blasting the newly sequenced O1 antigen cluster against GenBank. However, our approach to study the regions private to APEC_O1 was the one suggested without the benefit of hindsight (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Johnson et al., 2007</ref>). Moreover, alfy directly identifies regions without strong homology, which makes it a convenient tool for this kind of analysis.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>btr176. .tex]</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1471" to="1466" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">09 12</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>btr176. .tex]</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1472" to="1466" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Domazet-Lošo and B.Haubold Conflict of Interest: none declared</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The enhanced suffix array and its applications to genome analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">References</forename>
				<surname>Abouelhoda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Algorithms in Bioinformatics</title>
		<meeting>the Second Workshop on Algorithms in Bioinformatics<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="463" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein database searches for multiple alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Lipman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5509" to="5513" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequences and consequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Brenner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">365</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA assembly with gaps (Dawg): simulating sequence evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Cartwright</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 3</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inference of bacterial microevolution using multilocus sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Didelot</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Falush</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">175</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1251" to="1266" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inference of homologous recombination in bacteria using whole genome sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Didelot</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">186</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1435" to="1449" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient estimation of pairwise distances between genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Domazet-Lošo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Haubold</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3221" to="3227" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PHYLIP-phylogeny inference package (Version 3.2)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Felsenstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cladistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="164" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compressed text indexes: from theory to practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Ferragina</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM J. Exp. Algorithmics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1312</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free estimation of nucleotide diversity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Haubold</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How repetitive are genomes?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Haubold</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Wiehe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">541</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome comparison without alignment using shortest unique substrings</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Haubold</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">123</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating mutation distances from unaligned genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Haubold</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1487" to="1500" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genome sequence of avian pathogenic Escherichia coli strain O1:K1:H7 shares strong similarities with human extraintestinal pathogenic E.coli genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Johnson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bacteriol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">189</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3228" to="3236" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An evolutionary model-based algorithm for accurate phylogenetic breakpoint mapping and subtype prediction in HIV-1</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Kosakovsky</forename>
				<surname>Pond</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000581</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting genomic islands using bioinformatics approaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G I</forename>
				<surname>Langille</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="382" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HIV sequence compendium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Leitner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theoretical Biology and Biophysics Group</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>NM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>NM</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multiplex PCR method to detect 14 Escherichia coli serogroups associated with urinary tract infectcions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Microbiol. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Engineering a lightweight suffix array construction algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Manzini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Ferragina</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ESA &apos;02: Proceedings of the 10th Annual European Symposium on Algorithms</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="698" to="710" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Localized sex in bacteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Maynard</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">349</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular evolution of the Escherichia coli chromosome. III. Clonal frames</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Milkman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Mckane</forename>
				<surname>Bridges</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="505" to="517" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general method applicable to the search for similarities in the amino acid sequence of two proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Needleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Wunsch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="453" />
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A taxonomy of suffix array construction algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Puglisi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Comput. Surv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free sequence comparison (i): statistics and power</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Reinert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1615" to="1634" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A web-based genotyping resource for viral sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Rozanov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="654" to="659" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of common molecular subsequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Waterman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="197" />
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis of multiple pathogenic isolates of Streptococcus agalactiae: implications for the microbial &apos;pan-genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Tettelin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13950" to="13955" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free sequence comparison—a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Vinga</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Almeida</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="523" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate detection of recombinant breakpoints in whole-genome alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Westesson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Holmes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1000318" to="1000318" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nucleotide composition string selection in HIV-1 subtyping using whole genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1744" to="1752" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>