
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:29+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology AMIGO2, a toolbox for dynamic modeling, optimization and control in systems biology</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eva</forename>
								<surname>Balsa-Canto</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Bioprocess Engineering Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">IIM-CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>36208</postCode>
									<settlement>Vigo</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<surname>Henriques</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Bioprocess Engineering Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">IIM-CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>36208</postCode>
									<settlement>Vigo</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Attila</forename>
								<forename type="middle">G</forename>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Bioprocess Engineering Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">IIM-CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>36208</postCode>
									<settlement>Vigo</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Julio</forename>
								<forename type="middle">R</forename>
								<surname>Banga</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Bioprocess Engineering Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">IIM-CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>36208</postCode>
									<settlement>Vigo</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology AMIGO2, a toolbox for dynamic modeling, optimization and control in systems biology</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw411</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 11, 2016; revised on June 16, 2016; accepted on June 22, 2016</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Contact: ebalsa@iim.csic.es Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Many problems of interest in dynamic modeling and control of biological systems can be posed as non-linear optimization problems subject to algebraic and dynamic constraints. In the context of modeling, this is the case of, e.g. parameter estimation, optimal experimental design and dynamic flux balance analysis. In the context of control, model-based metabolic engineering or drug dose optimization problems can be formulated as (multi-objective) optimal control problems. Finding a solution to those problems is a very challenging task which requires advanced numerical methods. Results: This work presents the AMIGO2 toolbox: the first multiplatform software tool that automa-tizes the solution of all those problems, offering a suite of state-of-the-art (multi-objective) global optimizers and advanced simulation approaches. Availability and Implementation: The toolbox and its documentation are available at: sites.google. com/site/amigo2toolbox.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Optimization is at the core of many problems related to the modeling and design of biological systems (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Banga, 2008</ref>). For example, model parametric identification involves two types of optimization problems (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Balsa-Canto et al., 2010</ref>): parameter estimation, to compute unknown parameters by data fitting and optimal experimental design, to design the best experimental dynamic scheme for model identification. The organization and behavior of biological systems can also be described based on optimality principles. This is the case in, e.g. (dynamic) flux balance analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kauffman et al., 2003</ref>) or in the analysis of activation of metabolic pathways (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Klipp et al., 2002</ref>). In this context, model-based dynamic optimization aims the computation of time-varying fluxes or enzyme concentrations and expression rates that minimize (or maximize) a given objective function (biomass production) or the best trade-off between various objectives (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">de Hijas-Liste et al., 2014</ref>). Models can be used to confirm hypotheses, to draw predictions and to find those (time varying) stimulation conditions that result in a particular desired behavior via (multi-objective) optimal control. This is the case in, e.g. model-based metabolic engineering (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Villaverde et al., 2016</ref>), pattern formation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Vilas et al., 2012</ref>) or drug dose optimization (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Jayachandran et al., 2015</ref>). All these problems can be stated as—or transformed to—(multiobjective) non-linear programming problems with algebraic and dynamic constraints. Their solution requires the combination of the control vector parameterization approach, a simulation method and a global optimizer. AMIGO2 is the first multi-platform (MATLAB-based) environment that automatizes the solution of all these problems (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>and Supplementary Tables S1 and S2). It fully covers the iterative identification of dynamic models, it allows using optimality principles for predicting biological behavior and it deals with the optimal control of biological systems using constrained multiobjective dynamic optimization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Summary of features</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Models</head><p>The tool supports general non-linear deterministic dynamic models and black-box simulators, dealing with ordinary, partial or delay differential equations. Biological networks can be visualized linking to Cytoscape (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Shannon et al., 2003</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Experimental scheme and data</head><p>Users can define multi-experiment schemes with maximum flexibility and several types of Gaussian experimental noise with known or unknown observable dependent variance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Parameter estimation with regularization</head><p>It is possible to estimate parameters and initial conditions which may depend on the experiment using weighted least squares or loglikelihood functions. Ill-conditioned problems can be handled using Tikhonov regularization. Users may fix the regularization parameter or let the tool to automatically compute the most appropriate using the L-shaped Pareto curve (G abor and<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Banga, 2015</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Identifiability and best fit post-analysis</head><p>The tool offers various methods to analyze model identifiability: (i) local and global parametric sensitivities; (ii) the Fisher Information Matrix for an asymptotic analysis; (iii) cost contour plots and (iv) a robust Monte-Carlo sampling approach. Results can be used to define and solve optimal experimental design problems aimed at improving identifiability. Besides, the validity of models along with the significance and determinability of their parameters are assessed using the v 2 goodness of fit and Pearsons v 2 tests, the autocorrelation of residuals, and the Akaike and Bayesian information criteria.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Optimal experimental design</head><p>To improve identifiability, users may automatically design simultaneous or sequential experiments optimizing observables, initial and stimulation conditions, number and location of sampling times and experiment durations. The tool allows for different design objectives and experimental error descriptions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">(Multi-objective) Optimal control</head><p>AMIGO2 solves optimal control problems with flexibility in the objective functional, stimuli interpolation, and path and point constraints. The aim is to find time varying stimulation conditions to maximize or minimize a given objective related to cell performance or to a desired behavior. The control vector parameterization method with mesh refining allow the efficient solution for smooth control profiles. Pareto fronts with best trade-offs for multiobjective cases can be obtained with the weighted sum method, the-constraint approach or the multi-objective genetic algorithm NSGA-II (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Deb et al., 2002</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7">C based enhancements</head><p>The tool generates C code to offer the following modes of operation:</p><p>(i) C based simulation, compatible with all tasks; (ii) C based cost function and (iii) stand-alone C code for parameter estimation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.8">Numerical methods</head><p>AMIGO2 incorporates the MATLAB-based initial value problem solvers as well as CVODES (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hindmarsh et al., 2005</ref>) to cover stiff, non-stiff and sparse dynamic systems. Parametric sensitivities can be computed by either direct methods or various finite differences schemes. Also, exact Jacobians can be obtained using symbolic manipulation. Regarding the optimizers, AMIGO2 interfaces to a suite of state-of-the-art solvers to cover constrained convex and nonconvex, multi-objective non-linear optimization problems. Users can also test their optimizers within the toolbox.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.9">Documentation</head><p>Descriptions of tool underlying theory, numerical methods, and usage are provided on the web page. Users can access HTML documentation from the MATLAB Help menu. Step by step examples illustrate the usage of the tool and serve as templates for new problems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(MO) Optimal control</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. AMIGO2 features and tasks</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">E.Balsa-Canto et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from Conflict of Interest: none declared.</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors acknowledge the different beta-testers and M. Pérez-Rodr ıguez for the AMIGO2 logo design.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An iterative identification procedure for dynamic modeling of biochemical networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Balsa-Canto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimization in computational systems biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Banga</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global dynamic optimization approach to predict activation in metabolic pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>De Hijas-Liste</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fast and elitist multiobjective genetic algorithm: NSGAII</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Deb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Evol. Comp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="197" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust and efficient parameter estimation in dynamic models of biological systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Abor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Banga</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sundials: suite of nonlinear and differential/algebraic equation solvers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Hindmarsh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Trans. Math. Softw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="396" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model-based individualized treatment of chemotherapeutics: Bayesian population modeling and dose optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Jayachandran</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13324</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advances in flux balance analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Kauffman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="491" to="496" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of temporal gene expression. metabolic optimization by re-distribution of enzyme activities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Klipp</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">269</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5406" to="5413" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Shannon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2498" to="2504" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic optimization of distributed biological systems using robust and efficient numerical techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Vilas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolic engineering with multi-objective optimization of kinetic models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Villaverde</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">222</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AMIGO2</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>