
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:46+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression An improved method for computing q-values when the distribution of effect sizes is asymmetric</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">. 21 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Megan</forename>
								<surname>Orr</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>megan.orr@ndsu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">North Dakota State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>58102</postCode>
									<settlement>Fargo</settlement>
									<region>ND</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Peng</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Iowa State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>50011</postCode>
									<settlement>Ames</settlement>
									<region>IA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dan</forename>
								<surname>Nettleton</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Iowa State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>50011</postCode>
									<settlement>Ames</settlement>
									<region>IA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression An improved method for computing q-values when the distribution of effect sizes is asymmetric</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="3044" to="3053"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">. 21 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu432</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 18, 2013; revised on June 26, 2014; accepted on July 3, 2014</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Ziv Bar-Joseph Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Asymmetry is frequently observed in the empirical distribution of test statistics that results from the analysis of gene expression experiments. This asymmetry indicates an asymmetry in the distribution of effect sizes. A common method for identifying differentially expressed (DE) genes in a gene expression experiment while controlling false discovery rate (FDR) is Storey&apos;s q-value method. This method ranks genes based solely on the P-values from each gene in the experiment. Results: We propose a method that alters and improves upon the q-value method by taking the sign of the test statistics, in addition to the P-values, into account. Through two simulation studies (one involving independent normal data and one involving microarray data), we show that the proposed method, when compared with the traditional q-value method, generally provides a better ranking for genes as well as a higher number of truly DE genes declared to be DE, while still adequately controlling FDR. We illustrate the proposed method by analyzing two microarray datasets, one from an experiment of thale cress seedlings and the other from an experiment of maize leaves. Availability and implementation: The R code and data files for the proposed method and examples are available at Bioinformatics online.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Performing tens of thousands of hypothesis tests for one experiment has become a commonplace as technologies for producing high-dimensional data are becoming more prominent. This is especially the case in the field of statistical genomics, where technologies such as microarray and RNA-seq [see Brown and Botstein (1999) or Metzker (2010) for reviews of these<ref type="bibr">technologies]</ref>measure the abundance of messenger RNA transcripts for thousands of genes in each subject of a gene expression study. Oftentimes, researchers are interested in comparing the gene expressions of subjects from two treatment groups. A major objective of such experiments is to identify genes that exhibit differential expression, i.e. a difference in the population treatment mean expression levels. Meaningful biological results depend on reliable detection of differentially expressed (DE) genes. Hence, the power of detecting differential expression for genes that are truly DE should be as high as possible, whereas genes that are equivalently expressed (EE)—i.e. genes that have no difference in the population treatment mean expression levels—should have a minimal chance of being declared DE. Thus, we must find an appropriate method for testing multiple hypotheses that provides good power while controlling some multiple testing errors. When considering a traditional multiple testing problem, family-wise error rate (FWER) is often the preferred error rate used to control multiple testing error. The Bonferroni method and Holm's (1979) method are commonly used for this purpose. These methods, however, are not appropriate for highdimensional gene expression data, as controlling FWER results in extremely low power for detection of differential expression. As a consequence, an alternative error rate known as false discovery rate (FDR;<ref type="bibr">Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995</ref>) is usually used. FDR is simply the expected proportion of EE genes among all genes declared to be DE, where the proportion is defined to be zero if no genes are declared to be DE. Although FDR allows for more Type I errors than FWER when controlling these different error rates at the same numeric level , the power for detecting differential expression is greatly increased, as discussed in Storey and Tibshirani (2003). A common method for identifying DE genes while controlling FDR in a gene expression experiment is the q-value method, first proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Storey (2002)</ref>. The q-value for a given gene represents the estimated FDR if the given gene and all genes with smaller q-values are declared to be DE. This method estimates FDR based on a set of P-values corresponding to m hypothesis tests. As previously mentioned, researchers are often interested in studying gene expression differences between groups of subjects. This is most often accomplished by performing a hypothesis test for a difference in treatment expression means for each gene, converting the P-values from the resulting tests to q-values, and then declaring genes with a q-value less than an FDR threshold to be DE. Potentially relevant information that this method does not take into account is the signs of the test statistics.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>shows a histogram of t-test statistics from a microarray experiment described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Jang et al. (2014)</ref>. In this experiment, gene expressions from wild-type cells in thale cress seedlings were compared with those from mutant cells.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>shows the distribution of observed test statistics for 22 810 gene. Although it is not visually obvious, there is asymmetry in the distribution of test statistics, as more genes have negative test statistics than positive test statistics, which indicates asymmetry *To whom correspondence should be addressed. in the distribution of effects sizes (i.e. the true differences in gene expression treatment means) as well. We propose a new method for FDR estimation that alters the traditional q-value method by separating the two-sided P-values from an experiment into two subsets of P-values based on the sign of the test statistics, and then computing the q-values separately for each subset to create a better ranking of the genes with respect to differential expression. Through simulation studies using both independent normally distributed data and real gene expression data, we demonstrate how the proposed method can result in an improved ranking of genes with respect to differential expression over the traditional q-value method while still adequately controlling FDR. The rest of the article is organized as follows. Section 2 reviews Storey's (2002) q-value method and introduces the proposed method for FDR estimation. Section 3 describes two simulation studies and uses the results of these studies to compare the performances of the proposed method and traditional q-value method by looking at the ranking of genes with respect to differential expression, the number of truly DE genes declared to be DE and also how well each method controls FDR. Section 4 presents analysis of two real microarray datasets, both from two-sample studies. Section 5 presents an analysis of a threetreatment gene expression experiment to illustrate how the proposed method can be generalized. Finally, Section 6 concludes the article with some discussion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>This section describes the proposed method for estimating FDR when effect sizes in an experiment are asymmetric. Section 2.1 reviews Storey's (2002) q-value method, and Section 2.2 describes how the proposed method alters Storey's method to obtain a better FDR estimator when the distribution of treatment effects is asymmetric. Finally Section 2.3 discusses the advantages of the proposed method.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Review of Storey's q-value method</head><p>Suppose we wish to test m null hypotheses H 1 ;. .. ; H m , where H j is true if gene j is EE and false if gene j is DE. We will assume that p j , the two-sided P-value that corresponds to H j , follows a Uniform(0,1) distribution if gene j is EE and a distribution stochastically smaller than uniform if gene j is DE. These are standard assumptions made so that an unbiased size test is obtained by rejecting H j if and only if p j. In the case of a two-sample t-test, assuming a uniform null distribution for the P-values is equivalent to assuming a central t-distribution for the test statistic of any EE gene.<ref type="bibr">Benjamini and Hochberg (1995)</ref>defined FDR in a manner equivalent to FDR=E V=max fR; 1g ð Þ , where V is the random variable representing the number of EE genes declared to be DE (or the number of Type I errors), and R is the random variable representing the total number of genes declared to be DE. Many methods have been proposed for estimating FDR, but the q-value method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Storey, 2002</ref>) is likely the most commonly used approach for gene expression experiments. The formal definition of the q-value is given as q ðjÞ =min p ðrÞ ^ m 0 r : r=j;. .. ; m ; ð1Þ where q ðjÞ is the q-value corresponding to p ðjÞ , the j th smallest P-value, and ^ m 0 is the estimated number of EE genes among all m genes in the experiment. Specifically, q j represents the estimated FDR if we declare gene j to be DE along with all other genes with q-values smaller than q j .Storey and Tibshirani (2003) developed an alternative method for estimating m 0 by first calculating ^ m 0 ðÞ for a series of values between 0 and 1 using (2). Then the relationship between and ^ m 0 ðÞ is estimated by fitting a natural cubic spline through the points ð; ^ m 0 ðÞÞ. Finally, m 0 is estimated by evaluating this function at =1. This approach will be used to estimate m 0 in the simulation studies and real data analyses in Sections 3, 4 and 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">FDR estimation using two subsets of P-values</head><p>Consider the problem of identifying genes that are DE in an experiment. To do this, a test statistic t j and corresponding two-sided P-value p j is obtained for each gene j=1;. .. ; m by testing the null hypothesis H j : j1 = j2 against a two-sided alternative, where jt is the population treatment mean expression for gene j under treatment t for t = 1, 2. We make the same assumptions about p j as those described in Section 2.1. Our proposed method begins by estimating m 0 for the entire set of m P-values. This can be done, for example, using any of the methods cited in Section 2.1. Then the P-values are divided into two subsets based on the sign of the corresponding test statistics. Let fp ð1Þ k : k=1;. .. ; m 1 g represent the subset of P-values corresponding to genes with negative test statistics, and let fp ð2Þ k : k=1;. .. ; m 2 g represent the remaining P-values, which correspond to genes with positive test statistics. Then the q-value method is applied separately to each subset of P-values. Therefore, for each gene k in each subset, the q-value is q ðiÞ ðkÞ =min p ðiÞ ðrÞ ^ m 0 =2 r : r=k;. .. ; m i</p><formula>( ) ; ð3Þ</formula><p>where p ðiÞ ðrÞ is the r th smallest P-value in the i th subset (i = 1, 2). The estimators of FDR in (3) are based on the expectation that there are an equal number, m 0 =2, of positive and negative test statistics corresponding to EE genes. This expectation follows from the assumption that EE genes have a Uniform(0,1) distribution, which also implies that the numerator intype cells were compared with those in mutant cells in thale cress seedlings P-values less than or equal to p ðiÞ ðrÞ among genes whose test statistics have sign ðÀ1Þ i. Thus, q ðiÞ ðkÞ is a natural expression for the q-value associated with p ðiÞ ðkÞ .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Advantages of the proposed method</head><p>Sun and<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Cai (2007)</ref>showed that multiple testing methods that rank the significance of hypothesis tests solely on the resulting P-values, such as the traditional q-value method, are often inefficient in terms of minimizing the 'false non-discovery rate' (i.e. the expected proportion of DE genes declared to be EE). In many cases, additional information can be used to improve this ranking. When the distribution of effects sizes is asymmetric in an experiment, dividing the set of P-values from a gene expression experiment into two subsets based on the sign of the test statistics and calculating q-values separately for each subset, as described in Section 2.2, improves efficiency.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2</ref>helps illustrate this idea. The histogram on the left plots the two-sided P-values for genes that have negative test statistics from the microarray experiment in thale cress seedlings described in Jang et al. (2014). The histogram on the right plots the two-sided P-values for genes with positive test statistics from the same experiment. A horizontal dashed line is plotted at the estimated proportion of EE genes, ^ ðiÞ 0 , for each subset, and represents the estimated density for a P-value from an EE gene in subset i. This estimate is calculated as</p><formula>^ ðiÞ 0 = ^ m 0 =2 m i ð4Þ</formula><p>for i = 1, 2 and again is based on the expectation of an equal number of positive and negative test statistics from EE genes. For each plot, the area of the left-most bar in each histogram represents the proportion of P-values that are50.05. The estimated proportion of EE genes among genes with test statistics of the same sign is represented by the proportion of area of the bar below the dashed line. Because the area of this bar is larger for the histogram that corresponds to negative test statistics than the one that corresponds to positive test statistics, and the area of the bar below the dashed line is relatively smaller, the estimated proportion of EE genes among genes with test statistics of the appropriate sign and P-values50.05 will be lower for the first histogram than the second. Thus, a gene with a P-value close to 0.05 will have a smaller q-value if this gene has a negative test statistic than if it has a positive test statistic. More generally, a gene with a small P-value will be more likely to be declared DE if it corresponds to a negative test statistic than if it corresponds to a positive test statistic, and it is possible for a gene with a higher P-value that corresponds to a negative test statistic to be ranked more significant (i.e. have a lower q-value) than a gene with a smaller P-value that corresponds to a positive test statistic. This reasoning agrees with (3), as the denominator in the formula corresponding to i = 1 will be larger than the denominator in the corresponding formula for i = 2 for the same two-sided P-value. Thus, two genes that have the same P-value but different signs of their corresponding test statistics will have different q-values, and the gene with the negative test statistic will have the lower q-value. We show via simulation in the next section that this strategy often results in a better significance ranking of genes when effect sizes are asymmetric.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">SIMULATION STUDIES</head><p>To evaluate the performance of the proposed method and compare it with that of the traditional q-value method, we performed two sets of simulation studies. For each simulated dataset, each gene j of the m=10 000 total genes was tested for differential expression by testing H j : j1 = j2 against a two-sided alternative. For each test, a corresponding test statistic, t j , and P-value, p j , were computed using the moderated t-test proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Smyth (2004)</ref>. This method was developed specifically for analyzing data from microarray experiments and borrows information across all genes to more accurately estimate the error variances for each individual gene. The resulting P-values were then analyzed by the traditional q-value method and the proposed method described in Section 2.2. Note that both methods use the same estimate of 0 , obtained by the natural cubic spline approach of Storey and<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Tibshirani (2003)</ref>, briefly described in Section 2.1. Two sets of simulations studies were performed. The first simulation study involved generating datasets with independent normally distributed data to evaluate the methods with data that are consistent with assumptions used to derive the moderated ttest. The second set of simulation studies used real gene expression data to evaluate the methods under conditions that are not ideal, but are generally observed in gene expression data, namely, data with a complex correlation structure that cannot be perfectly modeled with common probability distributions. For each simulation study, four variables were manipulated to evaluate the methods under different situations. Sample sizes of n = 4, n = 10 and n = 20 for each gene in each treatment were used. These sample sizes were chosen because gene expression experiments tend to have small sample sizes; $90% of gene expression datasets on the Gene Expression Omnibus (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Edgar et al., 2002</ref>) have a total sample size (i.e. the number of subjects across all treatments for each gene) no 440. Thus, a maximum total sample size of 2n=40 was chosen for the simulations performed. The number of EE genes was also varied from m 0 = 5000 to m 0 =9500 of m=10 000 total genes. Four levels of an asymmetry parameter ( A ) were considered to examine performance as the distribution of effect sizes ranged from symmetric about zero to highly asymmetric about zero. This asymmetry parameter is explained in more detail in the Section 3.1, but its impact on the effect size distribution can be seen in<ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>, which plots the density for each value of A from which effect sizes, relative to the standard deviations of the genes, were randomly drawn for DE genes. Finally, two values of the mean of the effect sizes, relative to the standard deviation of the genes, were implemented in the simulations: =1 and =2. Thesevalues were chosen so that the proportion of genes identified as significantly DE in our simulation study would range over values typically seen in practice. For each simulation setting in each simulation study, 500 datasets were randomly generated and analyzed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Simulations using independent normal data</head><p>In the first simulation study, data were randomly generated from independent normal distributions. For each dataset, data for each gene j=1;. .. ; 10 000 were generated as follows. The variance 2 j was randomly selected from an inverse gamma distribution. The parameters of the inverse gamma distribution were calculated from the dataset of an experiment described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hannenhalli et al. (2006)</ref>using methods proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Smyth (2004)</ref>. If gene j was EE, then j1 = j2 =0. If gene j was DE, then j1 =0 and the effect size j2 = j was randomly drawn from the mixture distribution</p><formula>h j ðÞ= A ð; j ; 2 j Þ+ð1 À A Þð; À j ; 2 j Þ; ð5Þ</formula><p>where ð; ; 2 Þ is the normal density with mean and variance 2 evaluated at. Finally, n values were randomly drawn from a Normal( jt , 2 j ) distribution for each treatment t = 1, 2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Simulations using gene expression data</head><p>The second simulation study used microarray data from an experiment in which gene expressions were measured from the heart tissue of N = 108 human subjects suffering from idiopathic dilated cardiomyopathy. This experiment is described in detail in<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hannenhalli et al. (2006)</ref>, and the data generated from this experiment are available from the Gene Expression Omnibus under accession number GSE5406. Although this dataset contains data from over 20 000 genes, m=10 000 genes were randomly selected for analysis in the simulation study. The expression values for each dataset were generated as follows. For each gene j=1;. .. ; m, the variance s 2 j was calculated from all N subjects. Then, data from two n subjects were randomly drawn, without replacement, from the microarray dataset. From this subset of data, the data from n subjects were randomly chosen to be in the first treatment, and the data from the remaining n subjects were assigned to the second treatment. Note that, at this point, because the data from both treatments were randomly drawn from the same population, the population treatment means were equal (i.e. j1 = j2 ) for each gene. If gene j was EE, the data from this gene was not altered in any way. If gene j was DE, then the effect size, j , was randomly chosen from mixture model (5), but by replacing j with s j. Then j was added to the data from gene j in the second treatment. Note that this method of data generation did not change the correlation structure of the data in any way but only shifted the mean of the data between the two treatments for DE genes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Results</head><p>Tables 1 and 2 as well as Supplementary Tables S1 and S2 (provided in the Supplementary Materials) present the results of the simulation studies. For each setting in each simulation study, the mean (based on the 500 simulated datasets) partial area under the receiver-operating characteristic (ROC) curve (pAUC) is given with its corresponding standard error in parentheses. These are partial areas because we considered only the most relevant region of the ROC curve where the false-positive rate was 0.10. The method that ranks the genes better with regard to differential expression will have a higher pAUC. For each simulation setting, a traditional paired t-test was performed to test for a difference in the mean pAUCs of the proposed method and the traditional q-value method. If this test was significant at 5%, then the higher mean pAUC is presented in bold font in Tables 1 and 2 and the supplementary tables. Additionally, if the higher mean pAUC is at least 5% greater than the lower mean pAUC, then the higher mean pAUC is also underlined, and this method was considered to 'outperform' the other method. The 5% improvement criterion was used to avoid situations where the mean pAUC was very similar between the proposed and traditional methods, in some cases equal when rounded to one decimal, but the t-test indicated a statistically significant (though not practically significant) difference. The combination of the two criteria allowed for the identification of simulation settings where both practical and statistical significance were present. In addition, mean S, the mean number of DE genes that were declared to be DE when FDR is nominally controlled at 5% is also given for each setting to observe the number of correctly identified DE genes, on average. Similar to the pAUCs, t-tests were used to determine whether one method produced a larger mean S and whether the higher mean S was at least 5% greater than the lower mean S. Also, to verify that each method adequately controls FDR, the empirical approximation of FDR was calculated for each method while nominally controlling FDR at 5%. We will call this quantity V=R, which is the average of the dataset-specific fractions defined as the proportion of EE genes among all genes with q-values 0.05 or 0 if no genes have q-values 0.05. Regardless of data type, both mean pAUC and mean S increase as the sample size increases as well as when the mean effect size increases for both the proposed and traditional q-value methods. This is unsurprising, as increasing the sample size or the mean effect size increases the power for detecting differential expression. For the simulations involving normally distributed data with =1 (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>), the proposed method performed better in 12 of 60 simulation settings with regard to mean pAUC, includingsettings with n = 4. In regard to mean S, the proposed method performed better in 25 of 60 simulation settings, including 18 of 20 settings with n = 4. The traditional method did not perform better than the proposed method in any simulation setting in terms of mean pAUC or mean S. When the mean effect size is increased to =2 (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>in the Supplementary Materials), the proposed method outperformed the traditional method with regard to pAUC in 8 of 60 settings, all of which are in simulation settings with n = 4. For mean S, the proposed method outperformed the traditional method in 16 of 60 settings, including 14 of 20 settings with n = 4. As with =1, the traditional method did not outperform the proposed method in terms of mean pAUC or mean S in any simulation setting. For simulations involving microarray data with =1, the proposed method performed better than the traditional methods in 17 of 60 (14 of 20 settings with n = 4) and 23 of 60 (17 of 20 settings with n = 4) simulation settings in regard to mean pAUC and mean S, respectively. The traditional method did not perform better than the proposed method in any simulation setting in terms of mean pAUC or mean S. When =2 (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table S2</ref>in the Supplementary Materials), the proposed method outperformed the traditional method in mean pAUC in only 5 of 60 simulation settings, all when n = 4. In terms of mean S, the proposed method outperformed the traditional method in 15 of 60 settings, 13 of which when n = 4. The traditional method did not outperform the proposed method in any simulation settings in terms of mean pAUC or mean S. When taking into account all simulation settings with normally distributed data, all of the 20 simulation settings in which the proposed method outperformed the traditional method in terms of mean pAUC were with A ! 0:8. For mean S, 33 (80.1%) of the 41 simulation settings in which the proposed method performed better had A ! 0:8. Among all simulation settings involving microarray data, 18 (81.8%) of the 22 simulation settings in which the proposed method outperformed the tradition method in terms of pAUC occurred when A ! 0:8. For mean S, this occurred in 31 (81.6%) of 38 settings. Additionally, among the 42 simulation settings across all 240 simulations in which the proposed method outperformed the traditional method in terms of pAUC, 39 (92.9%) occurred in simulation settings with n = 4. Among the 79 simulation settings where the proposed method outperformed the traditional method in terms of mean S, 62 (78.5%) occurred in simulation settings with n = 4. The proposed method never outperformed the traditional method in simulation settings with n = 20 with regard to either mean pAUC or mean S. The traditional method did not outperform the proposed method in any simulation setting. As shown in the last two columns of Tables 1 and 2 and Supplementary Tables S1 and S2, both the proposed and traditional methods adequately controlled FDR near the 5% level across all simulation settings and data types.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">REAL DATA ANALYSIS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Thale cress seedlings</head><p>In this section, we analyze data from a study described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Jang et al. (2014)</ref>using both the proposed and traditional q-value methods. In this study, expressions from m = 22 810 genes in thale cress seedlings were compared between two genotypes, wild-type and mutant, using six Affymetrix Arabidopsis Genome ATH1 Arrays, with n = 3 for each genotype. Mutant seedlings contained a transfer DNA insertion that the wild-type seedlings did not. Data from this experiment are available from the Gene Expression Omnibus under access number GSE48114. The test statistics from this experiment are shown in the histogram in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>. There is asymmetry in this histogram, as there are more negative test statistics than positive test statistics, suggesting asymmetry in the effect sizes. More specifically, there are m 1 =12 355 genes with negative test statistics and m 2 =10 455 genes corresponding to positive test statistics. The asymmetry becomes more evident in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2</ref>, where P-values corresponding to negative test statistics follow a distribution that is stochastically smaller than the distribution of P-values corresponding to positive test statistics. Using Storey and Tibshirani's (2003) natural cubic spline method, the estimated number of EE genes in this experiment is ^ m 0 =17 933:75. Because we expect there to be the same number of negative and positive test statistics among the EE genes, we estimate that there are ^ m 0 =2=8966:875 EE genes with negative test statistics and ^ m 0 =2=8966:875 EE genes with positive test statistics. From these estimates, we can also estimate<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref>plots the log ratio of the q-values versus the test statistics from the proposed and traditional method for the gene expression experiment in thale cress seedlings. Negative log ratios correspond to cases where the q-value from the proposed method was less than the q-value from the traditional method. Positive log ratios correspond to larger q-values for the proposed method. From this scatterplot, we can clearly see that the proposed method produces smaller q-values than the traditional method for genes with negative test statistics and larger q-values for genes with positive test statistics, with a clear separation when the test statistic is 0. This is not surprising based on<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2</ref>and the discussion in Section 2.3. Using the traditional q-value method, 490 genes were declared to be DE when controlling FDR at 5%. The proposed method declared 617 genes DE, a 25.9% increase over the traditional method. There were 417 genes that both methods declared to be DE. All 200 of the genes that were only declared DE by the proposed method had negative test statistics. Similarly, all of the 73 genes that were only declared DE by the traditional method had positive test statistics. This is what we would expect based on the higher number of negative test statistics than positive test statistics in this experiment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Maize leaves</head><p>The analysis of data from a microarray experiment described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Covshoff et al. (2008)</ref>is briefly summarized here. In this study, expressions from m = 7377 genes in the mesophyll cells of maize leaves were compared between two genotypes, wild-type and mutant, using n = 6 two-color microarray slides. Mutant plants lacked the PSII activity of wild-type plants, and researchers were interested in identifying genes that have different mean expressions due to this lack of activity. Data from this experiment are available at the Gene Expression Omnibus under accession number GSE9698. The empirical distribution of test statistic values, shown in the histogram in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>, is clearly asymmetric. There are m 1 =4141 genes with negative test statistics and m 2 =3236 genes corresponding to positive test statistics. Estimating the number of EE genes results in ^ m 0 =2907:11. Using similar methods as in Section 4, we estimate that $2687 genes are DE with negative effect sizes, and 1782 genes are DE with positive effect sizes, resulting in an estimated 60.1% of DE genes having negative effect sizes. The proposed method declares fewer genes to be DE than the traditional method (2260 versus 2446). Similar to the analysis of</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">EXTENSION OF THE TWO SAMPLE CASE</head><p>This section illustrates how the idea of partitioning P-values can be extended to gene expression experiments with more than two treatments. Consider the microarray experiment described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Lattanzi et al. (2007)</ref>in which researchers wished to identify genes associated with the presence of trimethyltin (TMT) in rats. Three rats were assigned to each of the three treatment groups: control, 1 mol/L concentration of TMT and 5 mol/ L concentration of TMT. For each of the 15 866 genes, analysis of variance was used to determine whether significant differences among the treatment means existed. This dataset (available at the Gene Expression Omnibus under accession number GSE5073) will be re-analyzed in this section. Using the moderated F-test (the generalization of Smyth's (2004) moderated t-test), a P-value for each gene was calculated to test the null hypothesis H j : j1 = j2 = j3 ; where jt is the population treatment mean expression for gene j in treatment t. For this experiment, t = 1 corresponds to the control treatment, t = 2 corresponds to the treatment of 1 mol/L concentration of TMT and t = 3 corresponds to the treatment of 5 mol/L concentration of TMT. Using these P-values, the methods described in Section 2 were used to estimate m 0 as ^ m 0 =10 440:72, corresponding to ^ 0 =0:658. Because an F-test was performed on the data for each gene, all of the test statistics in the analysis of the TMT experiment are positive. Thus, the sign of the test statistic can not be used to partition the P-values, and a different partitioning rule needs to be implemented. The treatments in this experiment can easily be ranked based on the concentration of TMT. We might also expect that many genes that are DE will exhibit sample mean expressions that are monotone in the ranked treatments. In other words, we might expect to observe more DE genes with one of the following relationships:</p><p>(1) y j1 5y j2 5y j3 (monotone increasing) or</p><p>(2) y j1 4y j2 4y j3 (monotone decreasing), where y jt is the sample treatment mean expression for gene j in treatment t. Based on this reasoning, we will consider partitioning the P-values by two different rules. The first partitioning rule will include two subsets of P-values:</p><p>(i) fp ð1Þ k : k=1;. .. ; m 1 g, the set of P-values corresponding to genes which have sample treatment means that are not monotone in the ranked treatments and (ii) fp ð2Þ k : k=1;. .. ; m 2 g, the set of P-values corresponding to genes that do have sample treatment means that are monotone (increasing or decreasing) in the ranked treatments. In the TMT experiment, m 1 =9603 and m 2 = 6263 for the first partitioning rule. The second partitioning rule will include three subsets of P-values: (i) fp ð1Þ k : k=1;. .. ; m 1 g, the set of P-values corresponding to genes which have sample treatment means that are not monotone in the ranked treatments, (ii) fp ð2Þ k : k=1;. .. ; m 2 g, the set of P-values corresponding to genes that have sample treatment means that are monotone increasing in the ranked treatments and (iii) fp ð3Þ k : k=1;. .. ; m 3 g, the set of P-values corresponding to genes that have sample treatment means that are monotone decreasing in the ranked treatments. In the TMT experiment, m 1 =9603, m 2 =2383 and m 3 =3880. If a gene is EE, the ranking of sample means is random. For a three sample experiment, there are 3! = 6 possible rankings of the sample means. Thus, an EE gene will have sample means that are monotone increasing or monotone decreasing in the ranked treatments with probability 2=6 % 0:333, and this gene will have sample means that are not monotone in the ranked treatments with probability 4=6 % 0:667. Therefore, for the first partitioning rule, ^ m ð1Þ 0 =10 440:72ð4=6Þ=6960:48 and ^ m ð2Þ 0 =10 710ð2=6Þ=3480:24, calculated using formula (3). Using formula (3), but replacing ^ m 0 =2 with ^ m ðiÞ 0 (i = 1,2), q-values for each gene were calculated. For the second partitioning rule, ^ m ð1Þ 0 remains the same, but ^ m ð2Þ 0 = ^ m ð3Þ 0 =10440:72ð1=6Þ=1740:12. Again using altered formula (3) and an analogous formula for i=1; 2 and 3, q-values for each gene were calculated. The histograms of P-values corresponding to partitioning rule two are provided in<ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>. The empirical distributions of P-values corresponding to genes with sample means that are monotone in the ranked treatments are noticeably stochastically smaller than the empirical distributions of P-values corresponding to genes where monotonicity is not observed. This indicates a higher proportion of genes are DE among the genes that exhibit monotonicity in the ranked treatment means than the genes that do not exhibit monotonicity. The number of genes declared to be DE using the proposed method for each partitioning rule as well as the traditional q-value method is summarized in<ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>. Although there is a large overlap in the genes declared to be DE among all three methods, partitioning the P-values results in a higher number of genes declared to be DE than if no partitioning is performed. Partitioning rule two resulted in a slightly higher number of significant genes than partitioning rule one (442 versus 434). Additionally, more genes are declared DE when partitioning is applied. Having a larger set of significant genes could aid researchers in more easily identifying the</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">DISCUSSION</head><p>The proposed method for estimating FDR by first estimating 0 using all P-values and then analyzing two subsets of P-values separately based on the sign of the test statistics has advantages over the traditional q-value method when effect sizes are asymmetric. The proposed method was never outperformed by the traditional method in terms of mean pAUC or mean S in the two simulation studies, and ranked genes better with respect to differential expression in 17.5% of the simulation settings while adequately controlling FDR. The proposed method performed especially well for simulation settings with the smallest sample size (n = 4). Compared with the traditional method, the proposed method also declared more truly DE genes DE, on average, in 37.1% of simulation settings, and was never outperformed by the traditional method, even in simulation settings with symmetric effect sizes. Similar to the results for pAUC, the proposed method performed exceptionally well in simulation settings with n = 4. Therefore, we suggest that the proposed method be used to analyze datasets with small sample sizes (n 10) when the distribution of test statistics is asymmetric. Another advantage to the proposed method is that it can be generalized to analyze many gene expression experiments with more than two treatments, especially if the treatments in the experiment can be ordered by factors such as time or dose. Although the criteria used to partition the P-values differs depending to the treatment structure, the analysis is very similar once the partitioning has been performed.Improved q-values</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Many approaches have been proposed for estimating m 0 by estimating the density of the P-values at p j =1 and multiplying this by m. Liang and Nettleton (2012); Nettleton et al. (2006); Storey (2002); Storey et al. (2004) have proposed approaches for doing this by developing methods for selecting a 2 ð0; 1Þ and estimating m 0 as</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. A histogram of t-statistics from an experiment described in Jang et al. (2014) in which gene expressions from wild-type cells were compared with those in mutant cells in thale cress seedlings</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. A histogram of P-values for the thale cress data corresponding to (a) negative t-test statistics and (b) positive t-test statistics. The estimated proportion of EE genes, ^ ðiÞ 0 ; i=1; 2, is plotted as the dashed horizontal line in each plot</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Scatterplot of the log ratio of the q-values versus the test statistics for the experiment in thale cress seedlings. Negative log ratios correspond to cases where the q-value produced by the proposed method is less than the q-value from traditional method. Positive log ratios correspond to larger q-values for the proposed method</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. A histogram of t-statistics from an experiment described in Covshoff et al. (2008) in which gene expressions from wild-type cells were compared with those in mutant cells in maize leaves</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: This research was partially supported by the USDA NRICGP Microbial Functional Genomics program (grant no. 2008-3560418805) and the National Science Foundation (NSF) Plant Genome Research Program (grant no. IOS-1127017). Conflict of interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig.7.Fig.6.</head><figDesc>Fig. 7. Venn diagram of genes declared to be DE for the different partitioning rules</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. The mean pAUC, mean S and V=R with corresponding standard errors in parentheses for the proposed and traditional q-value methods for each setting in the simulation study using independent normal data with =1</figDesc><table>n 
m 0 
A 
Mean pAUC (%) 
Mean S 
V=R (%) 

Proposed 
Traditional 
Proposed 
Traditional 
Proposed 
Traditional 

4</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Continued</figDesc><table>n 
m 0 
A 
Mean pAUC (%) 
Mean S 
V=R (%) 

Proposed 
Traditional 
Proposed 
Traditional 
Proposed 
Traditional 

5000 
1</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. The mean pAUC, mean S and V=R with corresponding standard errors in parentheses for the proposed and traditional q-value methods for each setting in the simulation study using microarray data with =1</figDesc><table>n 
m 0 
A 
Mean pAUC (%) 
Mean S 
V=R (%) 

Proposed 
Traditional 
Proposed 
Traditional 
Proposed 
Traditional 

4</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. Continued</figDesc><table>n 
m 0 
A 
Mean pAUC (%) 
Mean S 
V=R (%) 

Proposed 
Traditional 
Proposed 
Traditional 
Proposed 
Traditional 

5000 
1</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">Improved q-values at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.Orr et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">the means of the proposed and traditional methods at 5% significance If the t-test was not significant, bold font is not used. Statistically significant improvements that we deemed practically significant (at least 5% improvement) are indicated by underlining</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Note: For each setting</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Note: For each setting, for both the mean pAUC and mean S, the highest values are given in bold font if a t-test has determined that there is a difference in the means of the proposed and traditional methods at 5% significance. If the t-test was not significant, bold font is not used. Statistically significant improvements that we deemed practically significant (at least 5% improvement) are indicated by underlining Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Hochberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">REFERENCES Benjamini J. R. Stat. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the new world of the genome with DNS microarrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Brown</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Botstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet. Supp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deregulation of maize C4 photosynthetic development in a mesophyll cell-defective mutant</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Covshoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">146</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1469" to="1481" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array repository</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Edgar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptional genomics associates FOX transcription factors with human heart failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hannenhalli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1269" to="1276" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple sequentially rejective multiple test procedure. Scand</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Holm</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A homolog of splicing factor SF1 is essential for development and is involved in alternative splicing of pre-mRNA in Arabidopsis thaliana</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Jang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="591" to="603" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hypoxia-like transcriptional activation in TMT-induced degeneration: microarray analysis on PC12 cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Lattanzi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1688" to="1702" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive and dynamic adaptive procedures for false discovery rate control and estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Liang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Nettleton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Stat. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequencing technologies–the next generation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Metzker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the number of true null hypotheses from a histogram of P values</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Nettleton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Agr. Biol. Envir. St</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="356" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linear models and empirical Bayes methods for assessing differential expression in microarray experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Smyth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Appl. Genet. Mol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Article. 3</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A direct approach to false discovery rates</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Storey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Stat. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="479" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical significance for genomewide studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Storey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Tibshirani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">P. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9440" to="9445" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Strong control, conservative point estimation and simultaneous conservative consistency of false discovery rates</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Storey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>unified. approach</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="205" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oracle and adaptive compound decision rules for false discovery rate control</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Sun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Cai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="901" to="912" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>