
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:43+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies An infrastructure for ontology-based information systems in biomedicine: RICORDO case study</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sarala</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Wimalaratne</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">European Bioinformatics Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1SD</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pierre</forename>
								<surname>Grenon</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">European Bioinformatics Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1SD</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Robert</forename>
								<surname>Hoehndorf</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cambridge</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB2 3EH</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Georgios</forename>
								<forename type="middle">V</forename>
								<surname>Gkoutos</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cambridge</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB2 3EH</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bernard</forename>
								<surname>De Bono</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">European Bioinformatics Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1SD</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Auckland Bioengineering Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Auckland</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Symonds Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>1010</postCode>
									<settlement>Auckland</settlement>
									<country key="NZ">New Zealand</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies An infrastructure for ontology-based information systems in biomedicine: RICORDO case study</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="448" to="450"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr662</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on September 28, 2011; revised on November 23, 2011; accepted on November 24, 2011</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: ES MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [13:56 31/12/2011 Bioinformatics-btr662.tex] Page: 448 448–450 Associate Editor: Martin Bishop</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The article presents an infrastructure for supporting the semantic interoperability of biomedical resources based on the management (storing and inference-based querying) of their ontology-based annotations. This infrastructure consists of: (i) a repository to store and query ontology-based annotations; (ii) a knowledge base server with an inference engine to support the storage of and reasoning over ontologies used in the annotation of resources; (iii) a set of applications and services allowing interaction with the integrated repository and knowledge base. The infrastructure is being prototyped and developed and evaluated by the RICORDO project in support of the knowledge management of biomedical resources, including physiology and pharmacology models and associated clinical data. Availability and implementation: The RICORDO toolkit and its source code are freely available from http://www.ruffus.org.ukand
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Improvement in computer technology makes it possible to store large volumes of biomedical resources (e.g. mathematical models of physiological processes and related data). The biomedical community is becoming increasingly aware of the importance of annotating this data in order to enable querying and retrieval. As a result, communities are engaged in working together to create annotation standards [e.g. MIRIAM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Le Novère et al., 2005)]</ref>and biomedical ontologies [e.g. OBO (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Smith et al., 2007</ref>)] to provide a consistent method of sharing heterogeneous resources. These initiatives have improved the prospect of semantic interoperability of resource annotation based on biology. Nevertheless, reaching this interoperability goal remains a challenge. While simple retrieval based on direct matching of terms used in annotation is certainly straightforward, search using complex descriptions of biological entities denoted by those terms involves possibly demanding reasoning over ontologies. Reasoning is the process by which statements are automatically inferred based on a set of axioms. Automated reasoning enables flexible retrieval of). The applications are deployed in a tomcat application server. The applications interact with (i) the OWL knowledge base which is deployed in a Pellet OWLlink server, and (ii) the virtuoso RDF repository. The application does not require access to original data and model resources, but has to point to a relevant set of IDs, thus resources are depicted outside the box. a knowledge base created by the Pellet OWLlink server, it is possible to query over the ontologies using OWLlink API requests and responses. The infrastructure includes a web application for user interaction with resources, as well as web services that provide programmatic access to the OWL reasoner server. On the client side, the web application is implemented in Google Web Toolkit (http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/) and hosted on a Tomcat (http://tomcat.apache.org/) server, with query services running on the server side to interact with the resources. REST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Fielding, 2000</ref>)/JSON (http://www.json.org/) based web services provide external access to the OWL reasoner server, thus enabling the integration of reasoning over large ontologies into third-party applications. The web application supports a number of functionalities, including: (i) the annotation of resources, using a URI for the resource to be annotated and a URI for an ontology term to be associated with that resource, to create a related RDF statement that is stored; (ii) the definition of complex terms based on class expressions in OWL-EL and using terms and relations from biomedical ontologies. We call such defined terms 'composites' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">de Bono et al., 2011</ref>). Defining a composite assigns a unique identifier to this term for the storage and subsequent re-use of its definition; (iii) the querying of resources, achieved in two steps. The first generates a list of ontology terms by querying the OWL knowledge base. The RDF store is then queried for resources annotated with terms from this list. In our current configuration, the knowledge base includes biomedical ontologies relevant to data and model resources. This set of core ontologies (CORDO) includes FMA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Rosse and Mejino, 2007</ref>), PATO (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Gkoutos et al., 2005</ref>), GO (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ashburner et al., 2000</ref>), Cell Type (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bard et al., 2005</ref>), ChEBI (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">De Matos et al., 2010</ref>), HPO and its class definitions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gkoutos et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Robinson and Mundlos, 2010</ref>), as well as composite terms developed within RICORDO. The RDF store maps ontology terms according to the<ref type="bibr">, 2007</ref>) are applied to resolve MIRIAM URNs. An example of a search is to query the RDF store for resources related to volumes of some part of the heart. Finding the relevant ontology terms is achieved by querying the knowledge base, using the Manchester OWL Syntax (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Horridge et al., 2006</ref>). In this use case, PATO_0000918 and inheres-in some (part_of some FMA_7088) represents the class of volumes of a part of the heart. This class definition is used to generate a list of subclasses and equivalent classes from the knowledge base via the OWLlink interface. This list is then passed to the RDF query engine. The application implements a set of templates that allow the formulation of queries. Each template has a particular form to specify the query terms and relations. An example of a query template is &lt;relation&gt; some &lt;term&gt; where relation and term refer to an ontology property and a class, respectively. Selecting a particular template generates fields to capture the terms and relations entering into the description of an OWL class. Auto completion of ontology terms and relations in these fields is supported by the Ontology Lookup Service (<ref type="bibr">Côté et al., 2008</ref>). Performance of the overall prototype is largely influenced by performance of the OWL reasoning module, thus an initial evaluation of reasoning over the CORDO ontologies was performed. This was carried out on a server with a dual CPU Intel Xeon 2.4 GHz with 24 GB memory. The start up of the KB involves loading the ontologies (90 s) and classification of the ontologies (9.4 min). Query times depend on the complexity of the queries as well as caching. Thus, the results of the query 'PATO_0000918 and inheres-in some (part-of some FMA_7088)' can be retrieved in 0.1 s (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RICORDO case study</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DISCUSSION</head><p>The prototypical implementation of the infrastructure in the RICORDO context allows searching data and model resources using ontologies. The web applications allow the retrieval and annotation of resources with both terms from reference ontologies and composites of those terms. Web services provide programmatic access to the ontology resources. Future work will include distribution of the RDF store and OWL reasoning. The metadata is stored independently of the annotated resources. This independent storage supports efficient metadata management and preserves both the structural integrity and confidentiality of these resources. Furthermore, the separation of data and ontologies, as well as the subsequent separation of querying of metadata and reasoning over ontologies, allows the storage of large amounts of metadata without affecting the performance of ontological reasoning. The architecture can be employed to support ontologybased metadata management in any area of application. The solution</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S.M.Wimalaratne et al.</head><p>is general and reusable by multiple biomedical communities in integrating and sharing metadata.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The current implementation of the infrastructure (enclosed by a black margin). The applications are deployed in a tomcat application server. The applications interact with (i) the OWL knowledge base which is deployed in a Pellet OWLlink server, and (ii) the virtuoso RDF repository. The application does not require access to original data and model resources, but has to point to a relevant set of IDs, thus resources are depicted outside the box.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: ES MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [13:56 31/12/2011 Bioinformatics-btr662.tex] Page: 450 448–450</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: European Commission, grant agreement number (248502) (RICORDO) and 223920 (VPH NoE) within the 7th Framework Programme. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Query times in order of which they were executed</figDesc><table>Query 
Query 
time (ms) 

FMA_7088 
528 
part-of some FMA_7088 
34 468 
inheres-in some (part-of some FMA_7088) 
2035 
PATO_0000918 and inheres-in some (part-of some FMA_7088) 
101 

MIRIAM URN scheme (Le Novère et al., 2005), and MIRIAM 
web services (Laibe and Le Novère</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. stated and inferred knowledge, as well as consistency checking. However, with an increasing number of classes and relations in an ontology, such a task can become increasingly more complex and requires extensive computational power. The difficulty is further compounded when integrating knowledge across multiple communities (de Bono et al., 2011). In this article, we propose an infrastructure for real-time reasoning over very large ontologies to express complex ontology concepts and use these concepts to retrieve relevant resource metadata. Our use case, the RICORDO project (de Bono et al., 2011), focuses on biomedical resources, and related ontologies, relevant to a number of communities including the physiology modeling community (VPH; http://www.vph-noe.eu/), the pharmacology modeling community (DDMORE; http://www.ddmore.eu) and the medical education community (e.g. http://www.meducator.net). These communities mainly deal with large collections of anatomical, physiological and pathological resources including computational models, such as models encoded in CellML (Lloyd et al., 2004) and SBML (Hucka et al., 2004), and clinical databases. 2 IMPLEMENTATION The central module in the infrastructure is a store of ontologybased annotations of resources that are machine processable. The infrastructure comprises components for managing this central module. This management includes (i) store maintenance and (ii) querying that is achieved through intermediate reasoning over ontologies used in annotating resources (Fig. 1). The centralized store consists of metadata statements that link identified resources and their components to named terms in biomedical ontologies. The Resource Description Framework (RDF; http://www.w3.org/RDF/) is used to record these statements. Storing metadata in RDF also supports complex querying via SPARQL (http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-sparql-query/), a query language for RDF. A Virtuoso (Erling and Mikhailov, 2007) server is used to store metadata in RDF while the Virtuoso API, coupled with Jena API (http://jena.sourceforge.net/), is used to handle RDF triples and SPARQL queries. The OWLlink server (http://owllink-owlapi.sourceforge.net/) stores OWL-EL versions of ontologies (http://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-profiles/). OWL-EL is used as it allows automated reasoning over large ontologies (Hoehndorf et al., 2011). In addition, OWLlink supports OWL reasoning using the Pellet reasoner (http://clarkparsia.com/pellet/). Once the ontologies are loaded into</note>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An ontology for cell types</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Bard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The RICORDO approach to semantic interoperability for biomedical data and models: strategy, standards and solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>De Bono</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Res. Notes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">313</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Ontology Lookup Service: more data and better tools for controlled vocabulary queries</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Côté</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="372" to="376" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RDF support in the virtuoso DBMS</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Erling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Mikhailov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Network. Know. Network. Media</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">221</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Architectural Styles and the Design of Network-based Software Architectures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Fielding</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using ontologies to describe mouse phenotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Gkoutos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entity/quality-based logical definitions for the human skeletal phenome using PATO</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Gkoutos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Conf. Proc. IEEE Eng. Med. Biol. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7069" to="7072" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A common layer of interoperability for biomedical ontologies based on OWL EL</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Hoehndorf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1001" to="1009" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Manchester OWL Syntax</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Horridge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syntax</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">216</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolving a lingua franca and associated software infrastructure for computational systems biology: the Systems Biology Markup Language (SBML) project</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hucka</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MIRIAM resources: tools to generate and resolve robust cross-references in Systems Biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Laibe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Le</forename>
				<surname>Novère</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">58</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CellML: its future, present and past</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Lloyd</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Progr. Biophys. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="450" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ChEBI: a chemistry ontology and database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">De</forename>
				<surname>Matos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cheminformat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimum information requested in the annotation of biochemical models (MIRIAM)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Le</forename>
				<surname>Novère</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1509" to="1515" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human phenotype ontology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Mundlos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="525" to="534" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The foundational model of anatomy ontology. Esophagus</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Rosse</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L V</forename>
				<surname>Mejino</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="117" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The OBO Foundry: coordinated evolution of ontologies to support biomedical data integration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1251" to="1255" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>