
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:43+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Annocript: a flexible pipeline for the annotation of transcriptomes able to identify putative long noncoding RNAs</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Francesco</forename>
								<surname>Musacchia</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Biology and Evolution of Marine Organisms</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stazione Zoologica &quot; Anton Dohrn &quot;</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Villa Comunale</addrLine>
									<postCode>80121</postCode>
									<region>Naples</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Swaraj</forename>
								<surname>Basu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Biology and Evolution of Marine Organisms</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stazione Zoologica &quot; Anton Dohrn &quot;</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Villa Comunale</addrLine>
									<postCode>80121</postCode>
									<region>Naples</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Giuseppe</forename>
								<surname>Petrosino</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Biology and Evolution of Marine Organisms</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stazione Zoologica &quot; Anton Dohrn &quot;</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Villa Comunale</addrLine>
									<postCode>80121</postCode>
									<region>Naples</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Marco</forename>
								<surname>Salvemini</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Naples Federico II</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Mezzocannone 8</addrLine>
									<postCode>80134</postCode>
									<settlement>Naples</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Remo</forename>
								<surname>Sanges</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Biology and Evolution of Marine Organisms</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stazione Zoologica &quot; Anton Dohrn &quot;</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Villa Comunale</addrLine>
									<postCode>80121</postCode>
									<region>Naples</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Annocript: a flexible pipeline for the annotation of transcriptomes able to identify putative long noncoding RNAs</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv106</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 26, 2014; revised on January 22, 2015; accepted on February 11, 2015</note>
					<note>Sequence analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Associate Editor: John Hancock Availability and implementation: Annocript is distributed under the GNU General Public License (version 3 or later) and is freely available at https://github.com/frankMusacchia/Annocript. Contact: remo.sanges@szn.it</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The eukaryotic transcriptome is composed of thousands of coding and long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs). However, we lack a software platform to identify both RNA classes in a given tran-scriptome. Here we introduce Annocript, a pipeline that combines the annotation of protein coding transcripts with the prediction of putative lncRNAs in whole transcriptomes. It downloads and indexes the needed databases, runs the analysis and produces human readable and standard outputs together with summary statistics of the whole analysis.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>RNA-Seq has effectively portrayed the transcriptional complexity in eukaryotes demonstrating the widespread transcription of lncRNAs in a diverse group of organisms. However, annotation of de novo generated transcriptomes, remains a complex task requiring efficient management of large datasets. Current tools for annotation identify coding sequences by similarity searches (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Conesa et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Koski et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Philipp et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Schmid and Blaxter, 2008</ref>) while lncRNAs are typically predicted relying on sequence composition, lack of conservation and lack of ORFs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Kong et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Lin et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Liu et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Wang et al., 2013</ref>). To fulfill the need of a single platform, we developed Annocript, a pipeline linking together these processes. It uses multiple programs to annotate sequences based on similarity and composition. It is capable of assigning protein names, domains, metabolic pathways (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Morgat et al., 2012</ref>), Enzyme classes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bairoch, 2000</ref>), GO terms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ashburner et al., 2000</ref>) and other annotations. Further, it can identify putative lncRNAs based upon lack of any protein/domain similarity, lack of long ORFs and high non-coding potential. By default, a transcript is classified as lncRNA if it satisfies all the following conditions: (i) length 200 nucleotides, (ii) lack of similarity with any protein, domain and other short ncRNA from Rfam and rRNAs, (iii) longest open reading frame (ORF) &lt; 100 amino acids and (iv) non-coding potential score 0.95.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Implementation</head><p>Annocript will annotate any FASTA containing a transcriptome given as input. There is no limit in the number of sequences it can analyze. The pipeline runs on Linux systems and requires the presence of (tested versions): Perl (5.10), BioPerl (1.6) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Stajich et al., 2002</ref>), Python (2.7.3), R (3.1.0) and MySQL (5.5). A single configuration file allows the user to alter programs parameters or run only specific analysis steps. Annocript performs the following analysis steps. V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Database creation</head><p>This step downloads the sequence and annotation databases required for similarity searches: UniRef or TrEMBL coupled with SwissProt (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">UniProt Consortium, 2013</ref>), Rfam (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Burge et al., 2012</ref>) and Conserved Domains Database (CDD) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Marchler-Bauer et al., 2013</ref>). The UniRef/TrEMBL and SwissProt FASTA headers are used to build a MySQL database containing information on taxonomy, protein id, name and description. The downloaded FASTA are indexed for BLAST searches (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Camacho et al., 2009</ref>). Annocript also downloads ID mappings to associate UniProt and Pfam IDs to Enzymes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bairoch 2000</ref>), GO and pathways into the MySQL database. The database construction requires a few hours on high memory machines. A pure Perl hash table is created to build relations between the tables before to store them into the database. This usage of Perl hash tables is a memory-intensive task that permits to build the database quickly (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). Nevertheless, the pipeline can be run on low-memory machines with as little as 4 GB RAM using a different approach and longer computational time. By default Annocript requires 20 GB to build the hash table and this would be sufficient to build a database using UniRef90 þ SwissProt. In our tests the peak amount of RAM used by the hash when loading the entire UniProt knowledge-base (TrEMBL þ SwissProt, August 2014), is 44 GB. The database creation step is needed only for the first run of Annocript or when the user needs to update it.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Programs execution</head><p>This step is responsible for the execution of the programs. It performs the following similarity searches: BLASTX against TrEMBL/ UniRef and SwissProt, RPSBLAST against CDD profiles, BLASTN against Rfam and rRNAs. By default, Annocript uses speedoptimized BLASTX and BLASTP parameters and a custom parallelization of RPSBLAST to achieve a faster execution. The dna2pep (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Wernersson et al., 2006</ref>) and Portrait softwares (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arrial et al., 2009</ref>) are used to identify, respectively, the longest ORF and the noncoding potential of each query sequence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Results parsing and statistics</head><p>This step integrates all the results generated in previous steps building a comprehensive tab delimited text file and other standard outputs. The pipeline collects the best-hit and related annotations from each search. The output table contains specific columns for every search executed. In this way, the user can decide to choose a specific classification for cases of uncertainty based on scores or lengths or any other criteria. The columns of the file represent assigned proteins, domains, GO terms, Enzymes, pathways, short and ribosomal RNAs, longest ORF size and non-coding potential. Information about the score, position, coverages and combination of domains are also provided. The table provides a binary classification for each transcript to be a protein coding or a lncRNA. Annocript also generates FASTA files with the predicted lncRNAs, protein sequences from the longest ORFs and GFF3 files of complete BLAST outputs. Finally, a summary of the annotation is given as a HTML-formatted document. Examples of whole transcriptome annotations made by Annocript can be downloaded from http://bit.ly/ 15vnALW.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Optimization</head><p>To reduce the computational time, Annocript uses the following parameters in BLASTX and BLASTP searches: threshold ¼ 18 and word_size ¼ 4 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Korf 2003</ref>). We show that this customization does not affect the results on two sample datasets: transcripts from a species present in UniProt and from a species not present in UniProt at the time of analysis. The two datasets contain, respectively, 1500 coding sequences from Homo sapiens and 1500 transcripts from Acipenser naccarii (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Vidotto et al., 2013</ref>). Annocript was executed for each species with BLAST default and Annocript optimized BLAST parameters. The results for human were identical while for the sturgeon, using optimized parameters, out of 899 transcripts annotated in the BLAST default run, 891 (99%) were identical, 3 (0.003%) were missing and 5 matched on different, but homolog hits. At a negligible cost in sensitivity, the computational time was reduced more than 5-folds (<ref type="figure">Table 2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Discussion</head><p>Annocript is a pipeline for the annotation of transcriptomes. The pipeline is optimized to run quickly without bargaining on accuracy. It is the first platform with the ability to annotate coding genes along with the prediction of putative lncRNAs without the need for a reference genome or comparative supporting data.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>1.</head><figDesc>Time required to build the internal MySQL databaseTime to create the MySQL database from TrEMBL þ SwissProt or UniRef90 þ SwissProt (April 2014) using machines with different number of cores and RAM: 24 cores/98GB (L), 24 cores/24GB (M), 8 cores/8GB (S), 2 cores/4GB (XS).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Table</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. Time required to run searches with default and optimized parameters</figDesc><table>Organism 
BLASTX SP def 
BLASTX SP cust 
BLASTX Uf def 
BLASTX Uf cust 
RPSBLAST CDD def 
RPSBLAST CDD cust 

Human 
50.2 min 
10.9 min 
33.4 h 
5.2 h 
9.4 h 
67.5 min 
Sturgeon 
12.8 min 
2.07 min 
8.2 h 
54.3 min 
2.7 h 
14.4 min 

Note: Analysis performed on human coding transcripts (avg. length 4200 bp) and A. naccarii transcripts (avg. length 1200 bp) using 24 cores (2.67 GHz) and 
24 GB RAM and default BLAST parameters (def) or Annocript-optimized parameters (cust). </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">F.Musacchia et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Screening noncoding RNAs in transcriptomes from neglected species using PORTRAIT: case study of the pathogenic fungus Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Arrial</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">239</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ENZYME database in</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Bairoch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="304" to="305" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rfam 11.0: 10 years of RNA families</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Burge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="226" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BLASTþ: architecture and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Camacho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">421</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics research</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Conesa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3674" to="3676" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CPC: assess the protein-coding potential of transcripts using sequence features and support vector machine</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Kong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="349" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Serial BLAST searching</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Korf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1492" to="1496" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AutoFACT: an automatic functional annotation and classification tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Koski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">151</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PhyloCSF: a comparative genomics method to distinguish protein coding and noncoding regions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinguishing protein-coding from noncoding RNAs through support vector machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">29</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CDD: conserved domains and protein threedimensional structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Marchler-Bauer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="348" to="352" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UniPathway: a resource for the exploration and annotation of metabolic pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Morgat</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="761" to="769" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The transcriptome analysis and comparison explorer–T-ACE: a platform-independent, graphical tool to process large RNAseq datasets of non-model organisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E R</forename>
				<surname>Philipp</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="777" to="783" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">annot8r: GO, EC and KEGG annotation of EST datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Schmid</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Blaxter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">180</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Bioperl Toolkit: Perl Modules for the Life Sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Stajich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1611" to="1618" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Update on activities at the Universal Protein Resource (UniProt) in 2013</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Uniprot</forename>
				<surname>Consortium</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptome sequencing and de novo annotation of the critically endangered Adriatic sturgeon</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Vidotto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">407</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CPAT: Coding-potential assessment tool using an alignment-free logistic regression model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">74</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual Ribosome–a comprehensive DNA translation tool with support for integration of sequence feature annotation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Wernersson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="388" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>