
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:48+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining Anonymous nuclear loci in non-model organisms: making the most of high-throughput genome surveys</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Terry</forename>
								<surname>Bertozzi</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>terry.bertozzi@samuseum.sa.gov.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Evolutionary Biology Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">South Australian Museum</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">North Terrace</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5000</postCode>
									<settlement>Adelaide</settlement>
									<region>SA</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Molecular and Biomedical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">North Terrace</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5000</postCode>
									<settlement>Adelaide</settlement>
									<region>SA</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kate</forename>
								<forename type="middle">L</forename>
								<surname>Sanders</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Ecology, Evolution and Landscape Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Adelaide</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">North Terrace</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5000</postCode>
									<settlement>Adelaide</settlement>
									<region>SA</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mark</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Sistrom</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>06520-8106</postCode>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">G</forename>
								<surname>Gardner</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">School of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Flinders University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>GPO Box 2100</postBox>
									<postCode>5001</postCode>
									<settlement>Adelaide</settlement>
									<region>SA</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">School of Earth and Environmental Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Australian Centre for Evolutionary Biology and Biodiversity</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Adelaide</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5000</postCode>
									<settlement>Adelaide</settlement>
									<region>SA</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining Anonymous nuclear loci in non-model organisms: making the most of high-throughput genome surveys</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS DISCOVERY NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1807" to="1810"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts284</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on November 21, 2011; revised on April 20, 2012; accepted on May 5, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: DISCOVERY NOTE [10:32 18/6/2012 Bioinformatics-bts284.tex] Page: 1807 1807–1810 Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: When working with non-model organisms, few if any species-specific markers are available for phylogenetic, phylogeographic and population studies. Therefore, researchers often try to adapt markers developed in distantly related taxa, resulting in poor amplification and ascertainment bias in their target taxa. Markers can be developed de novo and anonymous nuclear loci (ANL) are proving to be a boon for researchers seeking large numbers of fast-evolving, independent loci. However, the development of ANL can be laboratory intensive and expensive. A workflow is described to identify suitable low-copy anonymous loci from high-throughput shotgun sequences, dramatically reducing the cost and time required to develop these markers and produce robust multilocus datasets. Results: By successively removing repetitive and evolutionary conserved sequences from low coverage shotgun libraries, we were able to isolate thousands of potential ANL. Empirical testing of loci developed from two reptile taxa confirmed that our methodology yields markers with comparable amplification rates and nucleotide diversities to ANLs developed using other methodologies. Our approach capitalizes on next-generation sequencing technologies to enable the development of phylogenetic, phylogeographic and population markers for taxa lacking suitable genomic resources. Contact:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>In a recent review,<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Thomson et al. (2010)</ref>noted that next-generation sequencing methodologies make the acquisition of many-marker datasets readily feasible. The ability to generate libraries of random sequence from across the genome at a relatively low expense has already changed the way that markers are developed for phylogenetic and population genetic studies. In particular, the use of the Roche 454 platform for generating large fragments of randomly sheared genomic DNA has already provided a wealth of markers. Most marker development studies have focussed on the large number of microsatellites that can be readily obtained from partial sequencing runs on non-model organisms (e.g.<ref type="bibr">Abdelkrim et al., *</ref>To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p><p>2009;<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Allentoft et al., 2009</ref>), and large numbers of species can be analysed simultaneously on this platform (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Gardner et al., 2011</ref>). In addition, almost entire mitochondrial genomes and a number of protein-coding genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Rasmussen and Noor, 2009</ref>) have been recovered from these kind of data. One class of marker that should be present in high numbers but has yet to be exploited from these data are anonymous nuclear loci (ANL) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Karl and Avise, 1993</ref>). ANL represent randomly selected fragments of DNA that, by chance, are likely to be from non-coding regions of the genome, given that a large percentage of eukaryotic genomes comprise non-coding regions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Thomson et al., 2010</ref>). The advantages of these markers are numerous: they are likely to be independent; not biased to a single area of the genome and unlikely to be under selection and so free to accumulate mutations at varying rates, providing a suite of sufficiently fast-evolving markers useful for phylogenetics, phylogeography and population genetics. ANL have been successfully used in multilocus reconstruction of phylogenetic (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Thomson et al., 2008</ref>) and phylogeographic (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Rosenblum et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Lee and Edwards, 2008</ref>) histories. A criticism of using anonymous markers is that paralogous loci and repetitive elements may go undetected, potentially confounding phylogenetic and phylogeographic inferences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Thomson et al., 2010</ref>). In addition, the development of these markers has required intensive laboratory methods including a substantial amount of cloning during development from small insert libraries (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Lowe et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Jennings and Edwards, 2005</ref>), Bacterial Artificial Chromosome libraries (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Thomson et al., 2008</ref>) and Amplified Fragment Length Polymorphism fragments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Brugmans et al., 2003</ref>). Herein, we describe the development of ANL from randomly generated sequences produced by the Roche 454 platform and provide empirical data to evaluate the methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Marker development</head><p>Sequence reads were generated for two squamate reptiles, the gecko Gehyra lazelli and the sea snake Hydrophis spiralis, by sequencing randomly sheared genomic DNA on the Roche 454 GS-FLX titanium platform at the Australian Genomic Research Facility, Brisbane, Australia, following the methodology of<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Gardner et al. (2011)</ref>was designed to successively filter out sequence reads of non-interest (i.e. repetitive, highly conserved and coding sequences) using software available in the public domain. All analyses were run on an Intel quad core 2.4 Ghz PC with 8 GB RAM running Fedora Linux (Release 11). When possible, parallel processing capabilities using multiple processor cores were used to speed up analyses. Default parameter values were utilized for all software unless otherwise stated. The sequences for each species were analysed separately. FASTA formatted sequence reads were extracted from the GS-FLX output files using the 'sffinfo' program, available as part of the Roche GSassembler suite. RepeatScout (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Price et al., 2005</ref>) was used to identify highly repetitive sequences in the data after running the build_ lmer_table script, which is included with the package. The repeat library generated contained high copy number sequences including mitochondrial fragments, simple sequence repeats (microsatellites), transposable elements and species-specific repeats. This repeat library was used as a 'custom library' in RepeatMasker (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Smit et al., 1996</ref>–2010) to mask these highly repetitive sequences in the original FASTA file. In addition, repeats included in the Repbase Update (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Jurka et al., 2005</ref>) 'repeatmaskerlibraries-20090604' were also used with RepeatMasker to remove known repeats that were present in low copy number. The parallel processing option was enabled and the bacterial insertion element check skipped (using the '–no_is' option). Masked areas were removed from sequences using the SeqClean PERL script (available from http://compbio.dfci.harvard.edu/tgi/software) enabling the parallel processing option. The SeqClean script was run three times with the minimum 'clear range' (-l option) set to 250, 350 and 450 bp, respectively, to determine the number of sequences of each size class available for further analysis. To remove highly conserved sequence or known coding regions, the resulting reads were compared to existing GenBank sequences using BLASTN (version 2.2.21). The makeblastdb package included in the BLAST distribution was used to create local, searchable BLAST databases comprising available messenger RNA (mRNA) and EST sequences from the family Elapidae, which includes the subfamily Hydrophiinae, to compare to the H. spiralis reads and similarly mRNA and EST sequences from the genus Gekko to compare to the G. lazelli reads. An additional BLAST database constructed from the squamate Anolis carolinensis genome (AnoCar 1.0, February 2007, Broad Institute) was also used to screen each dataset. Finally, matches to mitochondrial sequences from Bungarus fasciatus (Elapidae: GenBank accession NC_011393) and Gekko gecko (Gekkonidae: GenBank accession NC_007627) were determined to remove any low copy number mitochondrial sequences not removed by the RepeatScout program. High similarity matches, defined as e-value &lt;10 −4 , were output in tabular format and removed from the FASTA files using an in-house PERL script. A PERL script automating the analysis pipeline to this point is available from http://www.samuseum.sa.gov.au/assets/files/science/ evolutionary-biology-unit/anonmarker.tar.gz. Primer design was carried out using the program 'Primer3' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Rozen and Skaletsky, 2000</ref>), as implemented in software package Geneious, by specifying a product size between 400 and 500 bp and using default setting for optimal primer size (20 bp), Tm (60˚C), %GC content (50%) and minimizing hairpins and primer dimers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Evaluation of anonymous nuclear loci</head><p>For all taxa examined, genomic DNA was extracted from frozen and ethanol preserved tissue using a Puregene DNA isolation kit (Gentra Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA) following the manufacturer's protocol for DNA purification from solid tissue. All loci examined were amplified using either AmpliTaq Gold DNA polymerase (Applied Biosystems) or HotMaster Taq polymerase (PerkinElmer) following standard PCR protocols and visualization of double-stranded amplification products on 1.5% agarose gels. Purification of PCR products and cycle-sequencing using the BigDye<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Townsend et al., 2008</ref>). Sea snake primers were tested for cross-amplification using four taxa that span the crown hydrophiine sea snake radiation (H. spiralis, Enhydrina schistosa, Ephalophis greyi and Aipysurus apraefrontalis). Ten additional crown group taxa were added per locus to calculate the polymorphism statistics presented in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>; the maximum corrected (HKY) pairwise divergence among these taxa was ∼18% divergence over 808 bp of the ATP synthase gene and ∼1.5% divergence at the PRLR locus. Polymorphism statistics were re-calculated for a reduced set of recently diverged Hydrophis subgroup species, which show maximum pairwise divergence of only 10% for the ATP synthase gene and 0.3% for the PRLR locus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Marker development</head><p>The number of sequences for each taxon with contiguous sequence lengths &gt;250, 350 and 450 bp after masking repeats and other highly repetitive sequence is shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. Since our aim was to maximize the information from each locus developed for screening, only sequences with lengths &gt;450 bp were selected for further development. Approximately 25–30% of these sequences were discounted due to close matches to the mRNA, EST and mitochondrial sequences obtained from GenBank or A. carolinensis genomic resources (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). The number of sequences for which we were able to generate suitable primer pairs is also shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Characteristics of the evaluated anonymous loci</head><p>Twelve of the 15 primer pairs tested in G. lazelli amplified successfully, while only six amplified for both this taxon and Gehyra mutilata. Of the four loci that sequenced successfully, one was not variable and one was polymorphic for a large (&gt;500 bp) indel,<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Librado and Rozas, 2009</ref>). Loci developed in this study are emphasized in 'bold'. making it unsuitable as a phylogenetic marker. Of the 17 primer pairs developed from H. spiralis, 12 amplified successfully in this taxon and three other taxa spanning the sea snake crown group. Eight of these loci were polymorphic across hydrophiines; however, five showed evidence of paralog co-amplification based on fixed site heterozygosity across all individuals and were discarded. Details of the loci that amplified in all species and showed no evidence of paralogs are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>. For both reptile groups, the anonymous loci exhibited comparable or greater nuclear diversity than the other nuclear markers examined for that group.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anonymous nuclear loci in non-model organisms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>The use of low coverage genome surveys has revolutionized microsatellite development in non-model organisms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Gardner et al., 2011</ref>), and we have now developed a workflow to further exploit these genomic resources to develop markers suitable for phylogenetic, phylogeographic and population studies. Our approach targets low copy number sequences which, due to the nature of the data and the methodology we have chosen, are likely to be from non-coding regions of the genome. Although these regions are likely to accumulate mutations relatively quickly, they are also rich in repetitive elements.<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Thomson et al. (2008)</ref>found that repetitive elements still posed a problem after screening against GenBank and known repeat libraries. Although we have also utilized known repeat libraries in our methodology, our approach further minimizes potential problems caused by repetitive elements by de novo determination and exclusion of sequences that are repetitive within the dataset. This effectively removes species-specific SINES and other high copy number elements not present in repeat libraries or in public databases. Paralogous sequences are more difficult to detect but removing loci with sites that are heterozygous across all sequenced individuals has been demonstrated as a practical solution (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Jennings and Edwards, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Rosenblum et al., 2007</ref>), and this is the approach we used for the sea snake analysis. Even though we tested a small number of loci, successful amplification in the reference taxa (80% and 71% for G. lazelli and H. spiralis, respectively) is comparable to amplification success reported in other studies (65% in<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Rosenblum et al., 2007</ref>; 76% in<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Thomson et al., 2008</ref>). During the screening process, the attrition rate of markers was high, but the reasons for attrition varied, primarily based on the phylogenetic span of trialled taxa. In the Gehyra study, 50% of the markers did not amplify in the outgroup and only one of the four sequenced products was invariant. In contrast, within the more recently diverged Hydrophis group, 33% of the loci tested were invariant and a further 42% showed evidence of paralogs. Nevertheless, the relatively high attrition rate of loci during screening is more than offset by the large number of sequenced fragments suitable for screening. If a larger pool of potential loci are desired, increasing the size range of fragments considered or altering primer design parameters will increase the yield of potential markers.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: DISCOVERY NOTE [10:32 18/6/2012 Bioinformatics-bts284.tex] Page: 1809 1807–1810</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>. Approximately, one-eighth of a titanium flow cell for each species returned a total of 87 899 reads for G. lazelli (average length</figDesc><table>Copyedited by: SK 

MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: DISCOVERY NOTE 

[10:32 18/6/2012 Bioinformatics-bts284.tex] 
Page: 1808 1807–1810 

T.Bertozzi et al. 

of 358 bp) and 149 075 reads for H. spiralis (average length of 345 bp). 
The sequences are available from the Dryad Digital Repository doi:10.5061/ 
dryad.f1cb2. 
A workflow </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Number of sequences with lengths &gt;250, 350 and 450 bp after the removal of repetitive and high copy number sequences</figDesc><table>Taxon 
Contiguous sequence length (bp) 
≥250 
≥350 
≥450 

Gehyra lazelli 
29 054 
17 873 
7957 
Hydrophis spiralis 
32 085 
19 901 
7733 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2. Number of sequences ≥450 bp remaining after further filtering and automated PCR primer design Taxon Sequences Sequences PCR PCR ≥450 bp ≥450 bp product product after filtering &gt;400 bp &gt;500 bp and 17 for hydrophiine sea snakes were assayed for amplification success and polymorphism within each group. Initial screening in Gehyra used G. multilata and G. lazelli which show ∼15% divergence over 1200 bp of ND2 and ∼5% for the protein-coding gene PRLR (</figDesc><table>Gehyra lazelli 
7957 
5560 
3874 
245 
Hydrophis spiralis 
7733 
5822 
4398 
76 

Terminator v3.1 cycle-sequencing kit (Applied Biosystems) was outsourced 
to the Australian Genome Research Facility Ltd. (AGRF) in Brisbane, 
Australia. 
A subset of 15 loci for Gehyra </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 3.</figDesc><table>Descriptive statistics for loci compared in the study 

Locus 
Marker type 
L 
n 
h 
μ 

Gehyra 
A1 
ANL 
658 
42 
34 
0.0612 
A2 
ANL 
529 
42 
13 
0.02649 
H3 
Coding 
442 
100 
30 
0.035 
PRLR 
Coding 
526 
103 
20 
0.0269 
MC1R 
Coding 
608 
34 
19 
0.04308 
RAG1 
Coding 
756 
24 
22 
0.01388 
ND2 
mtDNA 
1049 
123 
110 
0.22 
Sea snakes 
G1888 
ANL 
439 
14 (7) 
8 (4) 0.0124 (0.0021) 
G1894 
ANL 
445 
14 (7) 
12 (5) 0.0162 (0.0071) 
G1914 
ANL 
494 
14 (7) 
13 (6) 0.0088 (0.0021) 
PRLR 
Coding 
561 
14 (5) 
7 (2) 0.0156 (0.0009) 
cmos 
Coding 
915 
14 (6) 
11 (6) 0.0067 (0.0038) 
RAG1 
Coding 
1002 
14 (7) 
12 (5) 0.0047 (0.0017) 
ODC 
Intron 
382 
6 (5) 
2 (2) 0.0028 (0.0011) 
ATP synthase mtDNA 
808 
14 (6) 
14 (6) 0.1851 (0.0833) 
CYTB 
mtDNA 
1112 
14 (7) 
14 (7) 0.1471 (0.0788) 

Sequence length (L) includes alignment gaps. The number of individuals sequenced 
(n) and the number of haplotypes recovered (h) are shown for each locus. Figures for 
the sea snakes include separate analyses for the overall sea snake crown group and the 
nested Hydrophis subgroup (in parentheses). Nucleotide diversity (μ) was calculated 
using DnaSP version 5.10.01 (</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast, cost-effective development of species-specific microsatellite markers by genomic sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Abdelkrim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechniques</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="192" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of microsatellites from an extinct moa species using high-throughput (454) sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Allentoft</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechniques</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new and versatile method for the successful conversion of AFLP markers into simple single locus markers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Brugmans</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rise of the machines, recommendations for ecologists using next generation sequencing for microsatellite development</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Gardner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ecol. Resour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1093" to="1101" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Speciational history of Australian grass finches (Poephila) inferred from thirty gene trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Jennings</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Edwards</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2033" to="2047" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Repbase Update, a database of eukaryotic repetitive elements. Cytogent</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Jurka</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="467" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PCR-based assays of Mendelian polymorphisms from anonymous single-copy nuclear DNA: techniques and applications for population genetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Karl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Avise</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="342" to="361" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Divergence across Australia&apos;s carpentarian barrier: statistical phylogeography of the red-backed fairy wren (Malurus melanocephalus)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Edwards</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3117" to="3134" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DnaSP v5: a software for comprehensive analysis of DNA polymorphism data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Librado</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Rozas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1451" to="1452" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification and characterization of nuclear, cleaved amplified polymorphic sequence (CAPS) loci in Irvingia gabonensis and I. wombolu, indigenous fruit trees of west and central Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Lowe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1771" to="1788" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bioinformatics-bts284.tex] Page</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="50" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Bertozzi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">De novo identification of repeat families in large genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Price</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What can you do with 0.1x genome coverage? A case study based on a genome survey of the scuttle fly Megaselia scalaris (Phoridae)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Rasmussen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A F</forename>
				<surname>Noor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">382</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anonymous nuclear markers for the eastern fence lizard, Sceloporus undulatus</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Rosenblum</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ecol. Notes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="116" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Rozen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Skaletsky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">RepeatMasker Open-3.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F A</forename>
				<surname>Smit</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>last. accessed date November 11</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing markers for multilocus phylogenetics in nonmodel organisms: a test case with turtles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Thomson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Phylogen. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="514" to="525" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-enabled development of DNA markers for ecology, evolution and conservation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Thomson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2184" to="2195" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid development of multiple nuclear loci for phylogenetic analysis using genomic resources: an example from squamate reptiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Townsend</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Phylogenet. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>