
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:31+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis ASPeak: an abundance sensitive peak detection algorithm for RIP-Seq</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">19 2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alper</forename>
								<surname>Kucukural</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>Contact: alper.kucukural@umassmed.edu or ccenik@stanford.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Howard Hughes Medical Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Massachusetts Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>01605</postCode>
									<settlement>Worcester</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">O</forename>
								<forename type="middle">¨</forename>
								<surname>Zadam</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Howard Hughes Medical Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Massachusetts Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>01605</postCode>
									<settlement>Worcester</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Guramrit</forename>
								<surname>Singh</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Howard Hughes Medical Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Massachusetts Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>01605</postCode>
									<settlement>Worcester</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Melissa</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Moore</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Howard Hughes Medical Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Massachusetts Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>01605</postCode>
									<settlement>Worcester</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Can</forename>
								<surname>Cenik</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Howard Hughes Medical Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Massachusetts Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>01605</postCode>
									<settlement>Worcester</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94305</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis ASPeak: an abundance sensitive peak detection algorithm for RIP-Seq</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2485" to="2486"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">19 2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt428</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 8, 2013; revised on July 17, 2013; accepted on July 20, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Michael Brudno</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Unlike DNA, RNA abundances can vary over several orders of magnitude. Thus, identification of RNA–protein binding sites from high-throughput sequencing data presents unique challenges. Although peak identification in ChIP-Seq data has been extensively explored, there are few bioinformatics tools tailored for peak calling on analogous datasets for RNA-binding proteins. Here we describe ASPeak (abundance sensitive peak detection algorithm), an implementation of an algorithm that we previously applied to detect peaks in exon junction complex RNA immunoprecipitation in tandem experiments. Our peak detection algorithm yields stringent and robust target sets enabling sensitive motif finding and downstream functional analyses. Availability: ASPeak is implemented in Perl as a complete pipeline that takes bedGraph files as input. ASPeak implementation is freely available at https://sourceforge.net/projects/as-peak under the GNU General Public License. ASPeak can be run on a personal computer, yet is designed to be easily parallelizable. ASPeak can also run on high performance computing clusters providing efficient speedup. The documentation and user manual can be obtained from http://master. dl.sourceforge.net/project/as-peak/manual.pdf.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>High-throughput sequencing of short RNA fragments directly associated with RNA-binding proteins enables transcriptomewide mapping of protein binding sites on RNAs. Such binding sites can be enriched by either immunopurification (IP) of RNA– protein complexes (RIP) or cross-linking followed by IP (CLIP) (<ref type="bibr">Ko¨nigKo¨nig et al., 2012</ref>). These approaches are analogous to ChIP experiments for DNA-binding proteins. Although identification of peaks in ChIP-Seq data has been addressed by numerous approaches (<ref type="bibr">Ji et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rashid et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rozowsky et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2008</ref>), development of specific bioinformatics tools for RNA–protein binding site identification has lagged behind with few alternatives (<ref type="bibr">Kishore et al., 2011</ref><ref type="bibr">, Li et al., 2013</ref><ref type="bibr">, Uren et al., 2012</ref>). With the recent explosion of high-throughput sequencing data for dozens of RNA-binding proteins, there is an urgent need to develop efficient and userfriendly applications to better address the computational challenges of identifying peaks in sequences with variable starting abundances. Here, we describe a new peak detection algorithm that is sensitive to differential expression levels of target transcripts. This approach enables robust peak detection even in low abundance transcripts. We previously used our algorithm to define binding sites for the exon junction complex (EJC) (<ref type="bibr">Singh et al., 2012</ref>). Here we describe an open-source and a much-improved implementation of this abundance sensitive peak detection algorithm (ASPeak).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">IMPLEMENTATION AND ALGORITHM</head><p>RIP and CLIP are enrichment strategies where IP with an RNAbinding protein-specific antibody leads to efficient and specific pull-down of target RNAs. Consider an example where an RIP protocol enriches the targets of an RNA-binding protein by 1000-fold. Let us assume that there are two RNA species with different abundances: RNA-X at 1 molecule/cell and RNA-Y at 1000 molecules/cell. If we assume that an RNA-binding protein binds all molecules of RNA-X and 1 molecule/cell of RNA-Y, we expect to obtain an equal number of sequence fragments from both RNA-X and RNA-Y after IP. Consistent with this, we previously observed a Spearman correlation of 0.87 between RIP-Seq and RNA-Seq read numbers for individual genes (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1A</ref>,<ref type="bibr">Singh et al., 2012</ref>). For accurate peak calling in transcripts of varying abundance, it is essential to consider the dependence between background levels and expression. Consequently, the observed number of sequencing reads in a RIP-Seq library is expected to correlate significantly with the parallel RNA-Seq library. The user is free to choose between RIP-input or any other appropriate RNA-Seq data to estimate expression levels. For simplicity, we used RNASeq as our expression measure. Our algorithm computes expression-sensitive backgrounds with respect to user-defined genomic intervals. Most commonly, users are interested in peaks within specific transcripts. In this case, the intervals can be from an annotation source such as RefSeq, and can include coding exons, 3 0 UTRs, 5 0 UTRs and introns. Additionally, intergenic regions or any interval discovered using ab initio methods such as Cufflinks (Roberts *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>y</head><p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First<ref type="bibr">Authors. et al., 2011</ref>) can be used. Specifically, we modeled read counts for each interval as a negative binomial (NB) distribution, parameterized by interval-specific p and r. To estimate p and r for each interval, we used the method of moments approach as described in the user manual. Peaks on each interval were detected using its specific p and r and an NB test whose distribution function is given by</p><formula>Fðk, p, rÞ¼ X k i¼0 rþkÀ1 k À Á p r ð1 À pÞ k</formula><p>where k is the number of observed reads. This test is applied to each nucleotide such that the probability of observing k or more reads at any given position is 1 À F(k, p, r). If a P510 À2 is found, the next L nucleotides are considered for inclusion into the peak. We considered only the center of each aligned read. Consequently, read counts from distinct nucleotide positions are modeled as independent random variables. The P-value upon peak extension is calculated as a sum of N NB distributions as background. We required the extended peak P-value to be also 510 À2. When no such extension is possible, a final P-value for the entire peak is calculated using all contiguous positions (see User Manual). For intervals with no detectable expression in the RNA-Seq data, a local window approach is used. Three nucleotide windows (default: 1k, 5k and 10k, as in<ref type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2008</ref>) centered on the position of interest were used to estimate the NB distribution parameters p and r. The combination that maximizes the expected value of the distribution was used to call the peaks as above (see User Manual for details).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CASE STUDY</head><p>To compare the performance of ASPeak, we used two popular alternative peak calling approaches [MACS v.1.4.1 (<ref type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2008</ref>) and Piranha v.1.2.0 (<ref type="bibr">Uren et al., 2012)]</ref>. Ideally, we would want to test the performance on a gold standard dataset. However, no such information is currently available for either RIP-Seq or CLIP-Seq. Therefore, we relied on prior biological knowledge about one RNA-binding protein complex, EJC, for evaluation. Specifically, previous work showed that the multi-protein EJC is deposited $24 nt upstream of exon–exon junctions. Recently,<ref type="bibr">Singh et al. (2012</ref><ref type="bibr">) andSauliè re et al. (2012</ref>generated both RIP-Seq and CLIP-Seq data for EJC. We called peaks using ASPeak, MACS or Piranha and compared the fraction of called peaks that fall into the expected position of $24 nt upstream of the exon–exon junction. We found that ASPeak reported a higher fraction of such peaks overall despite strong overlap between the three programs. We additionally tested performance on two RIP-Seq and two CLIP-Seq data (see User Manual).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>ASPeak is a fast and efficient expression-sensitive peak caller for CLIP-and RIP-Seq data. ASPeak implementation has the ability to run on multiple processors resulting in a significant speedup when used on high performance computing centers. Compared with MACS or Piranha, ASPeak provides comparable or better results when used in an expression-sensitive mode. In addition, ASPeak is supported with extensive documentation that allows experienced bioinformaticians to customize their analyses using detailed parameter files. Finally, a streamlined mode is available for biologists with limited knowledge of Linux systems to easily run ASPeak using default settings. Our implementation, ASPeak, is an open-source command-line program. Input files are RNA-Seq, CLIP-/ RIP-Seq data in BED/ SAM/BAM/BOWTIE format and region annotation files such as RefSeq in BED format. Peak regions are output in a tab-separated format. ASPeak can be run using a single command in a streamlined and simple manner. Additionaly, ASPeak can be parallelized and allows advanced users to run different steps separately for effective debugging and specialized applications.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: NIH grant # GM53007 (to M.J.M.). M.J.M. is an HHMI Investigator.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. (A) Scatter plot for RNA-Seq versus RIPiT data (Singh et al., 2012). Each data point indicates the log10 of the number of reads mapped to a transcript. (B) ASPeak, MACS 1.4.1 or Piranha v.1.2.0 was used to call peaks as detailed in the user manual. A Venn diagram showing the overlap between three approaches with respect to the number of peaks intersecting the exon junction region (15–35 nt upstream of the exon– intron boundary) was shown. (C) We ranked called peaks by programspecific scores from the highest to lowest confidence. Then, we separated each list into 100 equal size bins and plotted the ratio of EJC peaks to all peaks (precision) in each bin cummulatively</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">A.Kucukural et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>