
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining AutoBind: automatic extraction of protein–ligand-binding affinity data from biological literature</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Tien-Hao</forename>
								<surname>Darby</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<surname>Chang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chao-Hsuan</forename>
								<surname>Ke</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Information Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Cheng Kung University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70101</postCode>
									<settlement>Tainan</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jung-Hsin</forename>
								<surname>Lin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Pharmacy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Taiwan University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10051</postCode>
									<settlement>Taipei</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biomedical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Academia Sinica</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>11529</postCode>
									<settlement>Taipei</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jung-Hsien</forename>
								<surname>Chiang</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>jchiang@mail.ncku.edu.tw</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Information Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Cheng Kung University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70101</postCode>
									<settlement>Tainan</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alex</forename>
								<surname>Bateman</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining AutoBind: automatic extraction of protein–ligand-binding affinity data from biological literature</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2162" to="2168"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts367</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on December 30, 2011; revised on June 8, 2012; accepted on June 25, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: RP MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [18:54 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts367.tex] Page: 2162 2162–2168 Associate Editor: of the deposited binding affinities have been refined and approved manually before being released. Contact: Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Determination of the binding affinity of a protein– ligand complex is important to quantitatively specify whether a particular small molecule will bind to the target protein. Besides, collection of comprehensive datasets for protein–ligand complexes and their corresponding binding affinities is crucial in developing accurate scoring functions for the prediction of the binding affinities of previously unknown protein–ligand complexes. In the past decades, several databases of protein–ligand-binding affinities have been created via visual extraction from literature. However, such approaches are time-consuming and most of these databases are updated only a few times per year. Hence, there is an immediate demand for an automatic extraction method with high precision for binding affinity collection. Result: We have created a new database of protein–ligand-binding affinity data, AutoBind, based on automatic information retrieval. We first compiled a collection of 1586 articles where the binding affinities have been marked manually. Based on this annotated collection, we designed four sentence patterns that are used to scan full-text articles as well as a scoring function to rank the sentences that match our patterns. The proposed sentence patterns can effectively identify the binding affinities in full-text articles. Our assessment shows that AutoBind achieved 84.22% precision and 79.07% recall on the testing corpus. Currently, 13 616 protein–ligand complexes and the corresponding binding affinities have been deposited in AutoBind from 17 221 articles. Availability: AutoBind is automatically updated on a monthly basis, and it is freely available at http://autobind.csie.ncku.edu.tw/
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Determination of the binding affinity is essential for quantifying the protein interactions with other bio-molecules. For example, actually estimating the protein–DNA-binding affinity is an important step * To whom correspondence should be addressed. in understanding the regulation mechanisms of cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chen et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Chien et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Morozov and Siggia, 2007</ref>). In the field of drug design, the binding affinity of a ligand to a given protein target is used to judge whether this ligand can be considered as a potential drug candidate. Several databases of protein–ligand-binding affinities have been proposed, including Ligand-Protein Database (LPDB) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Roche et al., 2001</ref>), Protein Ligand Database (PLD) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Puvanendrampillai and Mitchell, 2003</ref>), PDBbind (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wang et al., 2004</ref>), Binding MOAD (), AffinDB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Block et al., 2006</ref>) and BindingDB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Chen et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Liu et al., 2007</ref>). These databases depend on structure databases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Berman et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chang et al., 2012</ref>) and require much time and cost for the manual inspection of the literature. Until September 2011, more than 21 million articles indexed contain the descriptions of binding affinity in the MEDLINE database. The time-consuming manual extraction cannot timely accommodate the astonishingly increasing number of full-text articles. Therefore, there is an immediate demand for automatic extraction of protein– ligand-binding affinities. Information Retrieval (IR) is a computational technique aiming at extracting information from the literature without manual intervention (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Krallinger and Valencia, 2005</ref>). Summarization is a widely seen IR application in various areas, which can automatically compile extractive summaries that include the important aspects of full-text articles (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bhattacharya et al., 2011</ref>). In the biomedical field, this technique is used to generate gene annotations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Chiang et al., 2006</ref>) and to search bio-images (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Agarwal and Yu, 2011</ref>). In recent years, IR has been used to extract biological entities of interest and their relationships (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rindflesch et al., 2000</ref>). For example, 'activate' and 'interact' are two common relation terms that connect molecule entities. This technique has been applied to protein–protein interactions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Blaschke et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Koike and Takagi , 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Zhou and He, 2008</ref>), pathway networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">McDonald et al., 2004</ref>) and drug interactions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Tari et al., 2010</ref>). However, so far there have been only a few studies that attempted to extract biological values or parameters. For example, Spasi´cSpasi´c et al. used terminology concept to index and select literature, then a score function was implemented to rank the retrieved articles by relevance of parameters for kinetic modeling of yeast metabolic pathways (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Spasi´cSpasi´c et al., 2009</ref>);<ref type="bibr">Heinen et al.</ref>used a rule-based approach to collect kinetic information of enzymes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Heinen et al., 2010</ref>). In general, the experimental procedures or results described in fulltext articles are hard for researchers to re-use (<ref type="bibr">Névéol et al., 2011</ref>). The fact that comparisons with events, values and parameters are usually recorded in a more flexible way in the literature makes the<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Milo et al., 2010</ref>). In this article we describe the construction of AutoBind, an automatic information extraction system dedicated to protein– ligand-binding affinity. Our system includes four patterns to identify candidate sentences describing protein–ligand-binding affinity and a scoring function to rank the identified sentences for extracting binding affinities. We applied AutoBind on the primary citations of all entries in the Protein Data Bank (PDB). Many primary citations contain multiple affinities corresponding to different experimental conditions, such as wild-type and mutated proteins, but only one represents the actual binding affinity of the crystal structure. In this study, we focused on the affinity corresponding to the structure in each primary citation since 1996, whose full-text references can be easily retrieved. Finally, the extracted protein–ligand-binding affinities and the corresponding complex structures were organized as a public database named AutoBind. Note that AutoBind in this article refers both the extraction algorithm and the database. The extraction algorithm is completely automatic. However, the binding affinities deposited in the database have been approved manually, in order to refine them and eliminate possible errors and inconsistencies. On the other hand, all the reported performances (in Tables 3–6 and Sections 4.1 and 4.2) were evaluated on the results obtained before the manual approval. In short, this article presents an automatic extraction algorithm to expedite constructing and maintaining a database, but the database construction was not fully automatic. The AutoBind database currently contains 13 616 protein–ligand complexes. To our knowledge, this is the largest collection of protein-binding affinities. The database will be updated regularly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">BINDING AFFINITY RECORD</head><p>In this section, we describe the definition of a binding affinity record in this study, which frames the data that AutoBind extracted. The binding affinity is a measure of the effectiveness of a compound in connecting other molecules. It is thermodynamically quantified as dissociation constant (K d ), inhibition constant (K i ) or half maximal (50%) inhibitory concentration (IC 50 ). The detailed definitions of these measures can be found in the Supplementary Data. We carried out an analysis on a set of full-text articles collected from the PDBbind database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wang et al., 2004</ref>), denoted PDBbind_corpus, where the actual binding affinities as well as the associated protein–ligand complexes were known. In this corpus, we observed that a description of a binding affinity has four major objects: @BULLET &lt;PROTEIN&gt;: functional polypeptides or macromolecules. @BULLET &lt;LIGAND&gt;: the meta-ions and small organic/inorganic ions and organic solvent molecular. @BULLET &lt;EVENT&gt;: the interaction/relation between the protein and ligand. @BULLET &lt;VALUE&gt;: binding affinity.</p><p>Example 1 shows an example of describing protein-binding interaction and their binding affinity, where all the four objects (italicized) appeared in the same sentence.However, authors frequently use variable writing styles to make the articles fluent. Example 2 shows a description of protein–ligand binding without precisely describing the &lt;LIGAND&gt;.Therefore in this study we have relaxed the requirement widely used in previous studies that an effective description of a relation between two entities must contain both entities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bui et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Jang et al., 2006</ref>). However, if only considering the sentence of Example 2, it is difficult to know the ligand. In AutoBind, the PDB TITLE, which was written by the author of the structure to describe the main molecules in the structure, is adopted to overcome this problem. The PDB TITLE corresponding to Example 2 (PDB ID: 3CTR) is 'Crystal structure of the RRM-domain of the poly(A)specific ribonuclease PARN bound to m7GTP'. The protein and ligand names are PARN and m7GTP, respectively. Thus, AutoBind can restore the missing ligand name in Example 2 to m7GTP. It is worthwhile to note that an article may contain multiple descriptions of binding affinities but some of them correspond to ligands not of interest. The biologically relevant ligand in this work is defined as (i) non-covalently bound to the protein and (ii) formed an unambiguously complex with the protein. However, in some cases, two ligands bind together inside the same binding site on the protein. In such cases, experimental measurement of the binding affinity of each individual ligand becomes much more complicated. In a PDB file, there could be some biologically irrelevant ligands [e.g. GOL (glycerol) in PDB entry 3GBA, where glycerol was added to the solution as a cryoprotectant] that were crystallized along with the main molecules. In the TITLE records of the 1486 PDB entries of the PDBbind_corpus, only 58 do not describe the biologically relevant ligands and none of them describes biologically irrelevant ligands. Thus in practice, we resorted to the TITLE record in a PDB file, which was written by the author of the structure to describe the main molecules in the structure, to identify the biologically relevant ligands. For example, Examples 3 and 4 are two descriptions of protein–ligand-binding affinity in the same primary citation of a complex structure (PDB ID: 2HAW; PMID: 17095506). Example 3 describe the affinities of PPase binding with Mg 2+ and Mn 2+ ions, both of which are not the ligand of interest for family II PPase.In this study, Example 4 was treated as an effective binding affinity and was collected in AutoBind; while Example 3 was not.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">MATERIALS AND METHODS</head><p>The PDB release in September 2011 contained 76 114 entries from 32 986 primary citations, which are the original published articles of the affinity measurement for the corresponding protein–ligand complex. We collected 17 221 articles whose full text is publicly accessible. The binding affinities of 1586 articles of the 17 221 primary citations were annotated in the PDBbind database release of September 2011. We named the 1586 full-text articles as PDBbind_corpus and adopted the corresponding binding affinities as a gold standard to evaluate the performance of our automatic extraction method. We used 100 articles from PDBbind_corpus to construct the four patterns (see Section 3.2.2) and used the remaining 1486 articles as the testing corpus. The workflow of constructing AutoBind is shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. In automatic extraction phase, it includes three major stages: (i) text preprocessing, (ii) sentence extraction and (iii) sentence ranking. AutoBind also provides a friendly web-based interface for users to query and view the identified binding affinity. The details of each stage in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>are described in the following subsections. The last subsection describes a naive extraction algorithm we implemented as a comparison baseline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Text preprocessing</head><p>AutoBind first splits full text into sentences and marks the protein and ligand names in sentences using named entity recognition (NER). We used a protein name recognizer, NLProt (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Mika and Rost, 2004</ref>), and a lexicon, UniProt (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bairoch et al., 2005</ref>), to recognize protein names. If a term is (i) recognized as protein name by NLProt or (ii) identical to a protein name/synonym in UniProt, it is marked as a protein name. Namely, AutoBind used the union of the results of NLProt and UniProt as the protein names. Similarly, we used a compound name recognizer, OSCAR4 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Jessop et al., 2011</ref>), and a chemical molecules databases, PubChem (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Wang et al., 2009</ref>), to recognize ligand names. As protein recognition, the union of the results of OSCAR4 and PubChem was used as the ligand names. The detailed information about the used NER tools can be found in the supplementary data. To solve the problem of name variants, including orthographic variation (e.g. 'EBNA3', 'EBNA-3' and 'EBNA 3'), Greek alphabet letter (e.g. 'p38 alpha' and 'p38 α') and extra words (e.g. 'TRAM' and 'TRAM protein'), AutoBind converted Greek alphabet letters to the corresponding English letters and removed three specific words 'protein', 'gene' and 'product'. Abbreviation discrimination is another critical problem in NER (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Zhou et al., 2006</ref>). In AutoBind, if a name is followed by a parentheses-surrounded term, this term is dynamically labeled as an abbreviation to that name. The protein and ligand abbreviations are considered identical to the protein and ligand names in the following stages. Frequently, there are multiple binding affinities in a full-text article that, for example, correspond to the binding under different experimental conditions or the binding of the wild-type and mutated proteins. To identify the target protein and ligand of the extracted article, however, is difficult and requires much domain knowledge. Examples 3 and 4 in the previous section demonstrated that the title of the complex structure is a sentence well describing the crystal structure. In this study we focus on the affinity corresponding to the crystal structure and adopted the PDB TITLE to make the step of selecting protein and ligand in an article automated. Therefore, we also used NER to recognize protein and ligand names in the PDB TITLE. The recognized names were used to select binding affinity records later. The benefit of this strategy is that the extracted binding affinity is guaranteed to have a corresponding protein–ligand complex structure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Sentence extraction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Trigger detection</head><p>Trigger is usually a noun, noun phrase (NP), verb or verb phrase (VP), used to detect relation or event between entities in a sentence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Stapley and Benoit, 2000</ref>). Setting a collection of triggers is a useful practice to rapidly filter large sentences in a full-text article before deeper parsing. AutoBind defined two types of triggers to detect &lt;VALUE&gt;, T value , and &lt;EVENT&gt;, T event .<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>shows the 19 T value and<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>shows the seven T event identified by examining PDBbind_corpus manually. Each word in T event stands for all its morphological variations. In AutoBind, &lt;VALUE&gt; is more precisely defined by four components: trigger, sign, value and unit, such as 'K d = 26 μM' ('K d ': trigger; '=': sign; '26': value and 'μM': unit). The four components are not required to be consecutive (e.g. 'shows a K d value of 0.77 μM' in PMID: 18596699 is a valid &lt;VALUE&gt; in AutoBind). To simplify the following steps, AutoBind rearranges &lt;VALUE&gt; to its compact form as follows:</p><p>(1) Identify the position of T value in the sentence.</p><p>(2) Extract the words from the position of T value to the first encountered unit term (mM, μM, nM and pM).</p><p>(3) If all of trigger, value and unit are present in the extracted words, AutoBind rearranges them into the form of 'trigger = value unit'.</p><p>Here we use the sentence 'We first showed that Ap5G is an efficient inhibitor of EcGMPK, with an IC 50 of about 0.5 μM'Event word Inhibit (ion, ed, ive) + with/at Bind(s/ bound(s) + with/at/to Interact (ion, ed, ive, ved) + with/at/to Mutant + with/at/to Complex + with/to Activat (ion, e, ed) React (ion, ed, ive) + with/at/on an example. The trigger 'IC 50 ' is first identified. Then 'IC 50 of about 0.5 μM' is extracted and parsed. The final &lt;VALUE&gt; in this example is rearranged as 'IC 50 = 0.5μM'.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Pattern matching</head><p>After trigger detection, the remaining sentences that contain triggers are matched to the following patterns. The four patterns were based on manually reviewing 100 articles randomly selected from the PDBbind_corpus. In each of the pattern-based sentence patterns listed below, a symbol '-' indicates a word gap that can be filled with any number of words within the sentence. A token followed by a symbol '?' indicates that the token is optional.Pattern 1 accommodates for a typical description of a protein combined with a small molecular. The &lt;P/L&gt; (short of &lt;PROTEIN&gt;/&lt;LIGAND&gt;) indicates the protein/ligand names recognized by NER, &lt;EVENT&gt; indicates triggers recognized by T event and &lt;VALUE&gt; indicates triggers recognized by T value. A specific rule for the patterns containing two &lt;P/L&gt;s is that one must be &lt;PROTEIN&gt; and the other must be &lt;LIGAND&gt; with no order restrictions. BEV (to be verb) or PREP (preposition) connects &lt;PROTEIN&gt; and &lt;LIGAND&gt; to &lt;VALUE&gt;. Example 5 describes that lumazine synthase binds with riboflavin, where the binding affinity evaluated by the dissociation constant (K d ) is 1.2 μM. Example 6 shows an example where &lt;LIGAND&gt; appeared before &lt;PROTEIN&gt;. Pattern 2 is designed to identify descriptions of passive form. In this pattern, &lt;EVENT&gt; is in between &lt;PROTEIN&gt; and &lt;LIGAND&gt;, and &lt;VALUE&gt; is at end of the sentence.Pattern 3 accommodates sentences where &lt;PROTEIN&gt; and &lt;LIGAND&gt; are connected with a BEV or PREP rather than &lt;EVENT&gt;.</p><p>The design of Pattern 3 is distinct to previous IR studies requiring a verb to link two entities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bui et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Fundel et al., 2007</ref>). However, we observed that some sentences contain binding affinities even without any T event (Example 8).Pattern 4 is a commonly observed writing style which describes the result (&lt;VALUE&gt;) first and then the details (&lt;P/L&gt;s and &lt;EVENT&gt;). Example 9 is an example of this pattern. &lt;EVENT&gt; in sentences of this pattern is not used to connect entities and could be omitted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pattern 4 &lt;VALUE&gt;-PREP-&lt;P/L&gt; − &lt;EVENT/BEV&gt;?</head><p>Example 9 The K i values of 44 and 220 μM&lt;VALUE&gt; for/PREP (S)-and (R)-propranolol&lt;LIGAND&gt;, respectively, show that the (S)-form binds&lt;EVENT&gt; almost as strong as the natural product cellobiose<ref type="bibr">[K i 20 μM]</ref>, whereas the binding of the (R)-form is about 5 times weaker. (PMID: 11114249)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Sentence ranking</head><p>The sentences extracted from a full-text article in the previous stages were denoted S = C {S i } , where s i is the ith extracted sentence matching at least one of the defined patterns. In this stage, AutoBind ranks S with a scoring function shown below. In evaluation, a successful extraction is counted if it is retrieved in the three highest ranked sentences. The experimental results shown in the next section reveal that the correct binding affinity appeared in the top three sentences in 79.07% articles.</p><formula>f i = ω −|{e i |e i ∈γ}| ω (1) g i = e i ∩γ e i (2) F i = f i +g i ,</formula><formula>(3)</formula><p>where ω is the number of distinct protein and ligand names in all extracted sentences in the article, γ is the set of protein and ligand names in the corresponding PDB TITLE, f i measures the overlap of protein and ligand names of S to the corresponding PDB TITLE, e i is the number of protein and ligand names ins i and g i is the ratio of entities in s i that are also in the corresponding PDB TITLE. In other words, f i measures the correlation of the article to the PDB TITLE, g i measures the correlation of s i to the PDB TITLE, while F i is the sum of the two measures. The final score, F i , is the sum of f i and g i .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Co-occurrence method</head><p>As AutoBind is the first automatic extraction system dedicated for protein– ligand binding affinity, we implemented an algorithm that simply identifies sentences containing both the target protein and ligand. This algorithm, named sentence-level co-occurrence method in other studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">He et al., 2009</ref>), was adopted as a comparison baseline.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>shows that AutoBind could extract sentences containing the correct binding affinity with 84.22% precision and 79.07% recall, where the P-value of the Wilcoxon signed ranked sum test (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wilcoxon, 1947</ref>) to the baseline is &lt; 1E −10 (the evaluation metrics are explained in the Supplementary Data). Comparing with AutoBind, the low recall of the co-occurrence method is mainly due to requiring both protein and ligand to appear in the sentence. The results indicate that more than half of the binding affinity articles describe the correct binding affinities in sentences not containing either the target protein or ligand. This reveals the importance of relaxing the requirement of the presence of entities in the proposed patterns. An analysis of the errors of AutoBind and a discussion of the limitation of AutoBind can be found in the Supplementary Data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">BENCHMARKING</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Evaluation of binding affinity extraction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Evaluation of NER</head><p>The NER module of AutoBind was actually a union of a dictionaryand a learning-based method (see Section 3.1 for details). In this experiment, we compared the performance of the dictionarybased method, the learning-based method and their union (denoted Hybrid in the context). The results of NER performance for protein and ligand names are shown in Tables 4 and 5, respectively.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>shows that using both techniques outperformed the protein recognition performance over those using individual techniques. The P-values show that the differences of NLProt to UniProt and Hybrid were relatively significant than the difference between UniProt and Hybrid. Namely, the good performance of Hybrid came mainly from UniProt with a little Hybrid came mainly from UniProt with a little help from NLProt in protein recognition. Thisenhancement was also observed in ligand recognition (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_5">Table 5</ref>). The P-values show that the differences of Hybrid to the two individual methods were significant. Namely, combining PubChem and OSCAR4 significantly helps ligand recognition. In both protein and ligand name recognition, the dictionary-based methods achieved better precision than that using learning-based methods. On the other hand, dictionary-based methods may have many false negatives because some new compound names have not been collected in the adopted dictionary. For example, ligand recognition using PubChem had lower recall than that using OSCAR4. This problem was relatively moderate in protein recognition (comparing NLProt and UniProt in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>) since the catalogue of proteins is more mature than that of ligands. Our results concur with previous studies that hybridizing both techniques enhances recognition performance (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Wermter et al., 2009</ref>). The next question is whether the improvement of hybridizing dictionary-and learning-based techniques in entity recognition benefits the performance of affinity extraction. Many studies that used IR technologies to extract biomedical information, e.g. protein–protein interaction (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Zhou and He, 2008</ref>) and protein phosphorylation (), observed that a large amount of incorrect extractions were owing to the poor recognition of protein entities. Many incorrect words or phrases tagged as entities will largely increase the false-positive extractions and reduce the entire extraction performance. We carried out an evaluation of the binding affinity extraction using the dictionary-based, the learning-based and the hybrid method. The experiment shows the hybrid recognition scheme used in this study can effectively improve the performance of binding affinity extraction. The results are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_6">Table 6</ref>. Note that the precisions, recalls and F-scores in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_6">Table 6</ref>are the performance of affinity extraction, namely comparable with those in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>, and should not be compared with those in Tables 4 and 5. The results reveal that accurate NER is critical to affinity extraction. This conclusion is similar to the study of<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kim et al. (2009)</ref>. Furthermore, the P-values show that the differences of Learning to Dictionary and Hybrid were relatively significant than the difference between Dictionary and Hybrid. The results in Tables 4 and 5 suggest that the relatively small difference between Dictionary and Hybrid was due to the small difference in protein recognition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Comparison with other databases</head><p>During the past decade, several protein–ligand binding affinity databases were published, in which all of the collected data were based on manual reading (). Except PDBbind, other databases are rarely updated. AutoBind contains 13 616 protein–ligand-binding affinities of which 6217 were automatically extracted (45.66%) and 7399 were curated by experts. It contains almost twice binding affinities compared to other databases of similar data. The guideline of AutoBind to the experts can be found in the Supplementary Data. Furthermore, AutoBind is updated every month. The higher update frequency is achieved by the automatic extraction system that alleviates manual loading. For each update, the newly released structures and the primary citations will be automatically downloaded from PDB and PubMed. The processing binding affinity extraction of each article takes 1 min in average using an Intel Xeon 2.5 GHz processor. Additionally, we adopted AutoBind early release version (updated on September 2011, 11 897 affinities were collected) to carry out a simple test to estimate the time needed for a biologist to review and record binding affinity data from protein structure-related articles. Our curators took ∼20 days to confirm the 5160 automatically extracted binding affinities while took about 3 months without the assistance of the automatic system to extract the other 6737 binding affinities. This reveals the importance of automatic extraction, which facilitated manual curation, hence drastically reducing the required time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">CONCLUSION</head><p>This work presents a new automatic system, AutoBind, for extracting protein-binding affinity from literature. Overall, our automatic extraction method collected almost twice binding affinities compared to other databases of similar data. The automatic extraction process contains four NER methods for protein and ligand names, four sentences patterns for sentence extraction and a ranking method to pick sentence that correctly describes binding affinities. The experimental results show that hybridizing multiple NER methods improved the performance of binding affinity extraction. These sentence patterns can quickly identify candidate sentences that may contain a protein-binding affinity. These patterns were designed to ensure minimal false negatives for, as shown in the experimental results, high extraction recall. Finally, the proposed ranking method ensures minimal false positives for high precision. The rank-based design facilities the following manual checking step. Biologists can start from the highest ranked sentences and stop immediately after a correct sentence is found. The entire system significantly reduces the extraction time while preserving the quality of the extracted binding affinities.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Example 1 The lack of electron density for the adenosine moiety of the TP4A&lt;LIGAND&gt; molecule bound to&lt;EVENT&gt; hTK1&lt;PROTEIN&gt; is surprising, taking into account the very high affinity of the bisubstrate analog for hTK1, with a K d of 29 nM&lt;VALUE&gt;. (PMID: 17407781)</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><figDesc>Example 3 Interestingly, Mg 2+ &lt;LIGAND&gt; confers lower activity but greater substrate-binding affinity on/PREP family II PPases&lt;PROTEIN&gt; than Mn 2+ &lt;LIGAND&gt; (K d of 60 μM versus 180 μM)&lt;VALUE&gt;, whereas, in family I enzymes, the reverse is true. In contrast, Example 4 shows the K d value (60 μM) of family II PPase binding with PNP, which is the ligand of interest in the to family II PPases&lt;PROTEIN&gt; (12 μM)&lt;VALUE&gt; is reasonably close to that for PPi&lt;PROTEIN&gt; (60 μM)&lt;VALUE&gt;, in agreement with their very similar three-dimensional structures.</figDesc><table>Copyedited by: RP 

MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER 

[18:54 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts367.tex] 
Page: 2164 2162–2168 

D.T-H.Chang et al. 

Fig. 1. System architecture of AutoBind. The extraction phase of AutoBind 
includes three stages: (1) text preprocessing, (2) sentence extraction and 
(3) sentence ranking. The result page of AutoBind includes four parts: 
(A) binding affinities extracted by AutoBind along with those deposited in 
other published databases, (B) full-sentenced descriptions where the binding 
affinity were extracted and the information of (C) the protein and (D) the 
ligand in the binding 

article and conforms to the PDB TITLE 'Crystal structure of family 
II Inorganic pyrophosphatase in complex with PNP'. 

Example 4 
The dissociation constant for PNP&lt;LIGAND&gt; 
binding&lt;EVENT&gt; </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><figDesc>(PMID: 16690197) as Copyedited by: RP MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [18:54 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts367.tex] Page: 2165 2162–2168 AutoBind Table 1. A set of triggers (T value ) for recognition of protein-binding affinity data K d , K i , IC 50 , EC 50 , K ii , K a , K m , K diss , pK i , pK d , pK a , dissociation constant, inhibition constant, association constant, 50% inhibitory concentrations, half maximal effective concentration, binding constant(s), Michaelis constant(s), Kinetic Parameter(s)</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2. Directions of semantic relations (T event )</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="false"><figDesc>Pattern 1 &lt;P/L&gt; − &lt;EVENT&gt; − &lt;P/L&gt;-BEV/PREP&lt;VALUE&gt; Example 5 The enzyme from S. pombe was the first described lumazine synthase&lt;PROTEIN&gt; that was found to bind&lt;EVENT&gt; riboflavin &lt;LIGAND&gt; with/PREP relatively high affinity (K D of 1.2 μM) &lt;VALUE&gt;. (PMID: 12083520) Example 6 Kinetic assays showed that pteroic acid&lt;LIGAND&gt; could inhibit&lt;EVENT&gt; RTA&lt;PROTEIN&gt; activity with/PREP an apparent K i of 0.6 mM &lt;VALUE&gt;. (PMID: 9086280)</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="false"><figDesc>Pattern 2 &lt;P/L&gt;-BEV-&lt;EVENT&gt;-PREP&lt;P/L&gt; − &lt;VALUE&gt; Example 7 OXA-13&lt;PROTEIN&gt; was found to be/BEV inhibited&lt;EVENT&gt; efficiently by&lt;PREP&gt; imipenem and meropenem&lt;LIGAND&gt; (IC 50 = 0.02 μM)&lt;VALUE&gt;. (PMID: 11453693)</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8" validated="false"><figDesc>Pattern 3 &lt;P/L&gt;-BEV/PREP-&lt;P/L&gt;-(BEV)?-&lt;VALUE&gt; Example 8 The affinity of I219A hGST A1-1&lt;PROTEIN&gt; for/PREP GTX&lt;LIGAND&gt; (K d = 1.3 μM, 25˚C25˚C)&lt;VALUE&gt; is an order of magnitude weaker than that of the wild-type protein (K d = 0.07 μM, 25˚C25˚C)&lt;VALUE&gt;. (PMID: 15893769)</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 3. Performance of binding affinity extraction between AutoBind and co-occurrence is &lt; 1E −10.</figDesc><table>TP + FN TP 
TP + FP Precision Recall F-score 

AutoBind 
1486 
1175 1395 
84.22 
79.07 81.56 
Co-occurrence 1486 
757 1081 
70.03 
50.94 58.98 

The P-value </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 4. Recognition performance of protein names</figDesc><table>Method 
Precision 
Recall 
F-score 

UniProt 
77.66 
61.93 
68.91 
NLProt 
62.82 
70.59 
66.47 
Hybrid 
72.87 
74.61 
73.73 

The P-values of NLProt to the other two methods are &lt; 1E −10; the P-value between 
UniProt and Hybrid is 0.0025. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 5. Recognition performance of ligand names of any two methods are &lt; 1E −10.</figDesc><table>Method 
Precision 
Recall 
F-score 

PubChem 
85.37 
51.79 
64.47 
OSCAR4 
63.43 
64.08 
63.75 
Hybrid 
68.29 
68.89 
68.59 

The P-values </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 7). LPDB is the earliest database, containing 195 complexes with binding affinities. A main feature of LPDB is providing computer-generated 'docking decoys' for developing and testing docking methods. BindingDB, first published in 2001, collected experimentally determined binding affinities of small molecules used for drug discovery. It provides various search</figDesc><table>Copyedited by: RP 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 7. Comparison of AutoBind to other databases</figDesc><table>Protein Number of 
Last 
First 
complex entries 
updated 
published 
(affinity data) date 
year 

AutoBind 
37 929 13 616 
December 1, 2011 This work 
PDBBind 
7986 
7986 
September 22, 2011 2004 
Binding MOAD 16 955 5630 
2010 
2005 
BindingDB 
3056 
1817 
March, 2010 
2001 
AffinDB 
474 
748 
2006 
2006 
PLD 
149 
149 
2003 
2003 
LPDB 
195 
195 
2001 
2001 

facilities of, for example, compound names, chemical structures and 
binding affinities, for accessing the collected data. AffinDB collected 
binding affinities from two kinds of scientific literatures: (i) primary 
sources describing the original experiments of affinity determination 
and (ii) secondary references collecting many binding affinities from 
primary references. It also provided experiment details such as 
pH values and temperature. Before 2010, Binding MOAD was the 
largest database that screened the entire PDB for primary citations 
containing binding affinities, but it has not been updated since 2010. 
It did not include small organic molecules or cofactors. PDBbind was 
another database that performed PDB-wide extraction. The most 
recent update of PDBbind is on September 22, 2011 (version 2011</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We would like to thank all the participants for their contribution to the manual evaluation. We also would like to thank Jing-Yeh Chen for his suggestions in biology and Patrick Chiang for professional proofreading.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Figure summarizer browser extensions for PubMed Central</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Agarwal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Yu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1723" to="1724" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Universal Protein Resource (UniProt)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Bairoch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The protein data bank</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Berman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MeSH: a window into full text for document summarization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic extraction of biological information from scientific text: protein-protein interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Blaschke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Seventh International Conference on Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology</title>
		<meeting>the Seventh International Conference on Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>AAAI Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="67" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AffinDB: a freely accessible database of affinities for proteinligand complexes from the PDB</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Block</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="522" to="526" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A hybrid approach to extract protein–protein interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q.-C</forename>
				<surname>Bui</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AH-DB: collecting protein structure pairs before and after binding</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T.-H</forename>
				<surname>Chang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="472" to="478" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting target DNA sequences of DNA-binding proteins based on unbound structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C.-Y</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">30446</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bioinformatics-bts367.tex] Page</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="73" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T-H</forename>
				<surname>Chang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Binding Database: data management and interface design</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeneLibrarian: an effective gene-information summarization and visualization system</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J.-H</forename>
				<surname>Chiang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">392</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DBD2BS: connecting a DNA-binding protein with its binding sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T.-Y</forename>
				<surname>Chien</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="179" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RelEx—relation extraction using dependency parse trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Fundel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="371" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PPI finder: a mining tool for human protein-protein interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4554</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KID—an algorithm for fast and efficient text mining used to automatically generate a database containing kinetic information of enzymes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Heinen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">375</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Binding MOAD (Mother Of All Databases)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Hu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prot. Struct. Funct. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="340" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Literature mining and database annotation of protein phosphorylation using a rule-based system</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Z</forename>
				<surname>Hu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2759" to="2765" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding the evidence for protein-protein interactions from PubMed abstracts</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Jang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="220" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OSCAR4: a flexible architecture for chemical text-mining</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Jessop</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cheminform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overview of BioNLP&apos;09 shared task on event extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J.-D</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the BioNLP 2009 Workshop Companion Volume for Shared Task</title>
		<meeting>the BioNLP 2009 Workshop Companion Volume for Shared Task<address><addrLine>Boulder, Colorado</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PRIME: automatically extracted protein interactions and molecular information database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Koike</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Takagi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In Silico Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Text-mining and information-retrieval services for molecular biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Krallinger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Valencia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">224</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BindingDB: a web-accessible database of experimentally determined protein–ligand binding affinities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="198" to="201" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracting gene pathway relations using a hybrid grammar: the Arizona Relation Parser</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Mcdonald</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3370" to="3378" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NLProt: extracting protein names and sequences from papers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Mika</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Rost</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="634" to="637" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioNumbers—the database of key numbers in molecular and cell biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Milo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="750" to="753" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Connecting protein structure with predictions of regulatory sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Morozov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Siggia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7068" to="7073" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extraction of data deposition statements from the literature: a method for automatically tracking research results</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Névéol</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3306" to="3312" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein Ligand Database (PLD): additional understanding of the nature and specificity of protein–ligand complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Puvanendrampillai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B O</forename>
				<surname>Mitchell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1856" to="1857" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracting molecular binding relationships from biomedical text</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Rindflesch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the sixth conference on Applied natural language processing</title>
		<meeting>the sixth conference on Applied natural language processing<address><addrLine>Seattle, WA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="188" to="195" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ligand-Protein DataBase: linking protein-ligand complex structures to binding data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Roche</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3592" to="3598" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KiPar, a tool for systematic information retrieval regarding parameters for kinetic modelling of yeast metabolic pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Spasi´cspasi´c</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1404" to="1411" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biobibliometrics: information retrieval and visualization from co-occurrences of gene names in medline abstracts</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Stapley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Benoit</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the fifth Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing. Hawaii</title>
		<meeting>the fifth Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing. Hawaii</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="540" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovering drug–drug interactions: a text-mining and reasoning approach based on properties of drug metabolism</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Tari</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="547" to="553" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The PDBbind database: collection of binding affinities for proteinligand complexes with known three-dimensional structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2977" to="2980" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PubChem: a public information system for analyzing bioactivities of small molecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="623" to="633" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-performance gene name normalization with GeNo</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Wermter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="815" to="821" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probability tables for individual comparisons by ranking methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Wilcoxon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="122" />
			<date type="published" when="1947" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracting interactions between proteins from the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Zhou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biomed. Informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="393" to="407" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ADAM: another database of abbreviations in MEDLINE</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Zhou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2813" to="2818" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>