
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:50+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis bammds: a tool for assessing the ancestry of low-depth whole-genome data using multidimensional scaling (MDS)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">20 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anna-Sapfo</forename>
								<surname>Malaspinas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for GeoGenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Natural History Museum of Denmark</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1350</postCode>
									<settlement>Copenhagen K</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ole</forename>
								<surname>Tange</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for GeoGenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Natural History Museum of Denmark</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1350</postCode>
									<settlement>Copenhagen K</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jos</forename>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">V</forename>
								<surname>Ictor Moreno-Mayar</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Morten</forename>
								<surname>Rasmussen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for GeoGenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Natural History Museum of Denmark</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1350</postCode>
									<settlement>Copenhagen K</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94305</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<surname>Degiorgio</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for GeoGenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Natural History Museum of Denmark</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1350</postCode>
									<settlement>Copenhagen K</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Wartik Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>University Park</addrLine>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<region>PA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yong</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Theoretical Evolutionary Genomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Departments of Integrative Biology and Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720-3140</postCode>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Ancestry.com DNA LLC</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94107</postCode>
									<settlement>San Francisco</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Cristina</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Valdiosera</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for GeoGenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Natural History Museum of Denmark</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1350</postCode>
									<settlement>Copenhagen K</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Archaeology, Environment and Community Planning Faculty of Humanities and Social Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">La Trobe University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3086</postCode>
									<settlement>Melbourne</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gustavo</forename>
								<surname>Politis</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">INCUAPA-CONICET</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Universidad del Centro de la Provincia de Buenos Aires</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>7600 Olavarr ıa</addrLine>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="institution">Ciencias Naturales y Museo de La Plata</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1900 La Plata</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="institution">Argentina Associate Editor: Inanc Birol</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eske</forename>
								<surname>Willerslev</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for GeoGenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Natural History Museum of Denmark</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1350</postCode>
									<settlement>Copenhagen K</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rasmus</forename>
								<surname>Nielsen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for GeoGenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Natural History Museum of Denmark</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1350</postCode>
									<settlement>Copenhagen K</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Theoretical Evolutionary Genomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Departments of Integrative Biology and Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720-3140</postCode>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis bammds: a tool for assessing the ancestry of low-depth whole-genome data using multidimensional scaling (MDS)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2962" to="2964"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">20 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu410</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 10, 2014; revised on June 16, 2014; accepted on June 23, 2014</note>
					<note>Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present bammds, a practical tool that allows visualiza-tion of samples sequenced by second-generation sequencing when compared with a reference panel of individuals (usually genotypes) using a multidimensional scaling algorithm. Our tool is aimed at determining the ancestry of unknown samples—typical of ancient DNA data—particularly when only low amounts of data are available for those samples. Availability and implementation: The software package is available under GNU General Public License v3 and is freely available together with test datasets https://savannah.nongnu.org/projects/bammds/. It is using R (http://www.r-project.org/), parallel (http://www.gnu.org/-software/parallel/), samtools (https://</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Population structure plays an important role in determining the evolutionary history of a group. A great deal has been learned from single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) array technology providing unmatched information of the population structure of several species [for humans, see (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Novembre and Ramachandran, 2011)]</ref>. The advent of new sequencing platforms, which can deliver millions to billions of sequencing reads within days, has shifted the focus from SNP array data to whole-genome shotgun (WGS) data. While the cost has steadily decreased (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Sboner et al., 2011</ref>), obtaining many high-depth genomes remains prohibitive for many laboratories, in particular when working with ancient DNA (aDNA) samples where it is often desirable to screen many samples of potential interest while keeping the cost at a minimum. Methods based on non-parametric multidimensional statistics (more specifically principal components analysis, PCA) were first applied to genetic data more than 30 years ago (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Menozzi et al., 1978</ref>). PCA has since become a standard tool in population genetics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Patterson et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Wang et al., 2014</ref>) owing in particular to (i) the low computational demand of such analyses, (ii) the appealing graphical result and (iii) its ease of use. Here, we describe a tool that allows to assign an ancestry to low-depth mapped WGS data when compared with an existing reference panel of genotype data using multidimensional scaling (MDS) based on genetic distances, a related method that provides results similar to those of PCA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cox and Cox, 2000</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>In what follows, we assume that WGS data have been mapped to a reference genome and that files in BAM format are available (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Li et al., 2009</ref>). Calling genotypes for low-depth data is a challenging task (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Nielsen et al., 2011</ref>), particularly for aDNA, as ancient damage (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Briggs et al., 2007</ref>) and contamination are not incorporated into sequence data error models. To avoid calling genotypes, we sample a read at every position for the WGS data, similar in spirit to previous aDNA approaches (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Green et al., 2010</ref>). Specifically, for the reference set of individuals, we randomly sample one of the alleles from each individual, and for the WGS data, we choose an allele from a randomly selected read covering that site. If no read covers that site or if the sampled allele is not the minor or the major allele in the reference panel, we then assume that the data for this site are missing for that sample. In other words, the data in both the reference panel and the WGS samples become either one allele (A, C, G or T) or missing data. For site k, let d k ij = 1 if individuals i and j have a different randomly chosen allele and 0 if that allele is the same or if one of the individuals has missing data. Assume that the number of sites in the reference panel is K. Denote ~ K ij as the number of sites where neither of individual i and j have missing data. Then, the allele-sharing distance between individuals i and j *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by-nc/3.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com is as follows:</p><formula>d ij = 1 ~ K ij X K k=1 d k ij</formula><p>A matrix D=ðd ij Þ of allele-sharing distances between all pairs of individuals is computed. We then apply classical MDS to this matrix [e.g. (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cox and Cox, 2000)]</ref>. Our implementation has three major features: it is user friendly and is intended to be used by biologists with limited familiarity with a UNIX system, it is flexible in terms of formats of the reference panel and in terms of the visual output, it runs in $20 min on a machine with four 2.2 GHz cores with a reference panel including 4600 000 SNPs and $950 individuals, making it practical to screen samples of an ongoing experiment progressively as additional data are produced.</p><p>We first tested bammds through simulations using publicly available modern and ancient human data. For the WGS data, we used 10 modern human genomes from HGDP cell lines, published in<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Meyer et al. (2012)</ref>, an Australian aboriginal genome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Rasmussen et al., 2011</ref>) and the Anzick-1 genome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Rasmussen et al., 2014</ref>). We mapped and processed the data identically for all genomes (see Supplementary data). We used a public reference panel that we make available in the Supplementary data, i.e. HGDP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Li et al., 2008</ref>), which includes 4600 000 SNPs and $950 individuals subdivided into 53 populations and 7 geographic regions (Africa, Eastern-, Western-, Central-and South Asia, Europe, Oceania and Native America). For each genome, we sampled 3 Â 10 4 , 3 Â 10 5 , 3 Â 10 6 , 1:5 Â 10 7 , 3 Â 10 7 and 1:5 Â 10 8 reads (which corresponds to a depth of coverage around 0.001Â, 0.01Â, 0.1Â, 0.5Â, 1Â and 5Â, assuming $100 bp sequence reads). For each sub-sampled genome, we ran bammds with the HGDP reference panel. We summarized the simulation results using dimension 1 and 2 only of the MDS output, as we expect this to be the common usage. For each population in HGDP, we defined its centroid (or center of gravity) based on the coordinates of its members for those two dimensions. We then evaluated the results using two criteria: (i) by assessing which population was the closest when comparing the position of the WGS sample with the population centroid, and (ii) by determining if the position of the genome is within a two-dimensional 99% confidence region. We built the confidence region by assuming that the points follow a bivariate normal distribution centred around the centroid of the population to which it belongs ('population ellipse'). We present a practical example on how to use the tool to determine whether a library is heavily contaminated by processing a newly sequenced $10 000 year BP old phalange ('Gus') from Argentina that clusters with the Europeans (Supplementary data).</p><formula>O O O O O O O O O O O O O O O A AA A A A A A A A A A A A A A A R R R R R R R R R R R R R R R R R R R R R R R R R B</formula><formula>F F F F F F F F FF F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F I I I I I I I I I I I I S S S S S S SS S S S S S S S S SS S S S S S S S S S S T T T T T T T D D D D H H H H H H H H H L L L L L L LLM M M M M M M M M M O O O O O O O O O S S S S S S S SS ST T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T X X X X X X X X X YY Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y M M M M M M M M M M N N N N N N N N U U U U U U U U U U C C C C C C C C C C J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y YY Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y M F P S H Y K A N D M F P S H Y K A N D O A R B F I S T M B D P B B B H K M P S U M P C K S M P B B M Y B M S H H D D H L M O S T T X Y M N C J Y Mbuti</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>The graphical result with all 10 modern individuals at a depth of 0.1Â can be seen on<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>. We find in the simulations that for all but two cases, we recover the geographic region as the first hit for as few as 30 000 reads ($0.001Â,<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>). In the remaining two cases, the Sardinian and the Karitiana individual, a depth of 0.1Â and 0.01Â, respectively, is enough. The true nearest population was also identified in most cases within the three closest centroids for a depth above 0.01 (7/10 cases). For the second criteria, we find that in 9/10 of the cases, the WGS sample was within the population ellipse at 0.5Â and above. Only in one case (San individual) was a depth of 1Â necessary to be placed within the population ellipse. For the ancient data, we get similar results for the Aborigine, which is assigned to the correct geographic region (Oceania) as a first hit with a depth of $0.001Â and above. At a depth higher than 0.01Â, we also recover the expected population as the closest population. For the Anzick-1 individual, presumably because of increased damage, a depth of 1Â is needed to recover the geographic region as the first hit. On the other hand, a Native American population is among the three closest populations from a depth of 0.1Â and above. The results for Gus are given in Supplementary data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>The tool we present in this article is based on classical MDS, a technique that originated in the 1930s and is commonly used in other fields [see, e.g. (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Borg and Groenen, 1997</ref>) and citations therein]. We present a tool that was designed to be practical to assess the ancestry of mapped WGS data for samples sequenced at low depth, assuming that a relevant reference panel in terms of ancestry is provided. We show through simulations that useful ancestry information can be recovered for as few as 30 000 reads—corresponding to a fraction ($1/60 in early 2014) of a HiSeq 2000 lane (www.illumina.com) for a sample with 1% endogenous content (or $1/4800 of a lane for a typical modern sample).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. First two dimensions of an MDS plot including the ten 0.1X modern human genomes and the HGDP SNP data</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Table1.</head><figDesc>Summary of the simulation results for the ten modern genomes. For more details, see Supplementary data</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>The authors thank Mar ıa C. Avila-Arcos, Amhed Missael Vargas Vel azquez, Morten E. Allentoft, Hannes Schroeder, Kerttu Majander, Maanasa Raghavan and Johannes Krause for helpful discussions and testing, and the National high-throughput DNA Sequencing Center for assistance with the sequencing.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Modern Multidimensional Scaling: Theory and Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Borg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J F</forename>
				<surname>Groenen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patterns of damage in genomic DNA sequences from a Neandertal</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Briggs</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14616" to="14621" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multidimensional Scaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Cox</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A A</forename>
				<surname>Cox</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<pubPlace>Florida</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd. edn. Chapman and Hall/CRC</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A draft sequence of the Neandertal genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Green</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">328</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="710" to="722" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2078" to="2079" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Worldwide human relationships inferred from genome-wide patterns of variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Z</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">319</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1100" to="1104" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synthetic maps of human gene frequencies in Europeans</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Menozzi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">201</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="786" to="792" />
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A high-coverage genome sequence from an archaic Denisovan Individual</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Meyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">338</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="222" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genotype and SNP calling from next-generation sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Nielsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perspectives on human population structure at the cusp of the sequencing era</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Novembre</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Ramachandran</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Genomics Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Population structure and eigenanalysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Patterson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">190</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Aboriginal Australian genome reveals separate human dispersals into Asia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Rasmussen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">334</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="94" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genome of a Late Pleistocene human from a Clovis burial site in western Montana</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Rasmussen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">506</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="229" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The real cost of sequencing: higher than you think</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Sboner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">125</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ancestry estimation and control of population stratification for sequence-based association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="415" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>