
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:58+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Bandage: interactive visualization of de novo genome assemblies</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ryan</forename>
								<forename type="middle">R</forename>
								<surname>Wick</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>rrwick@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Bio21 Molecular Science and Biotechnology Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Melbourne</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mark</forename>
								<forename type="middle">B</forename>
								<surname>Schultz</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Bio21 Molecular Science and Biotechnology Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Melbourne</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Justin</forename>
								<surname>Zobel</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computing and Information Systems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Melbourne</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Parkville</settlement>
									<region>Victoria</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kathryn</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Holt</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Bio21 Molecular Science and Biotechnology Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Melbourne</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Bandage: interactive visualization of de novo genome assemblies</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv383</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 20, 2015; revised on May 29, 2015; accepted on June 15, 2015</note>
					<note>Genome analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: John Hancock Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Although de novo assembly graphs contain assembled contigs (nodes), the connections between those contigs (edges) are difficult for users to access. Bandage (a Bioinformatics Application for Navigating De novo Assembly Graphs Easily) is a tool for visualizing assembly graphs with connections. Users can zoom in to specific areas of the graph and interact with it by moving nodes, adding labels, changing colors and extracting sequences. BLAST searches can be performed within the Bandage graphical user interface and the hits are displayed as highlights in the graph. By displaying connections between contigs, Bandage presents new possibilities for analyzing de novo assemblies that are not possible through investigation of contigs alone. Availability and implementation: Source code and binaries are freely available at https://github. com/rrwick/Bandage. Bandage is implemented in Cþþ and supported on Linux, OS X and Windows. A full feature list and screenshots are available at http://rrwick.github.io/Bandage. Contact:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Current de novo genome assemblers use graphs, most typically a de Bruijn graph. An ideal graph would contain one distinct path for each underlying sequence, but complexities such as repeated sequences usually prevent this. Instead, assembly graphs contain branching structures, where one node may lead into multiple others. The longest sequences in the graph that can be determined unambiguously are saved as contigs, which are often the final result of de novo assembly (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Schatz et al., 2010</ref>). However, an assembly graph contains more information because it also has connections between sequences. It can therefore be advantageous to work with assembly graphs instead of contigs. Bandage facilitates interaction with de Bruijn graphs made by de novo assemblers such as Velvet (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Zerbino and Birney, 2008</ref>), SPAdes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bankevich et al., 2012</ref>) and Trinity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Grabherr et al., 2011</ref>). It displays the graph in a graphical user interface (GUI) using a simple, comprehensible representation. The program is interactive, allowing users to zoom, pan and manually move nodes to focus on areas of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Implementation and performance</head><p>Bandage is a GUI application written in Cþþ with Qt, giving it speed, memory efficiency and cross-platform portability. It runs on Linux, OS X and Windows. The Open Graph Drawing Framework library (http://www.ogdf.net/) is used to perform the graph layout using the fast multipole multilevel layout algorithm, which scales well for very large graphs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Hachul and Jü nger, 2007</ref>). On a 3 GHz laptop, Bandage can load and display the de novo assembly graph for a bacterial genome (5 Mb) in a few seconds, using &lt;100 MB of RAM. A large graph with hundreds of thousands of nodes, such a metagenome assembly (100 Mb or more), may take V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3350</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.minutes and multiple gigabytes of RAM to display in its entirety, but the visualization can be limited to smaller regions of the graph to improve performance and reduce memory requirements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Features and case studies using Illumina 100 bp paired end reads</head><p>A full feature list and program screenshots are available in the Supplementary Material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Assembly quality and completion</head><p>Assemblies of whole genomes can be difficult to complete if repeated sequences occur in chromosomes or plasmids. Repeated sequences cause distinctive structures in the assembly graph, limiting contig length. Bandage's visualization of the assembly graph makes it easy to identify such problematic parts of assemblies (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1a</ref>). In some cases, it is possible to manually resolve these ambiguities by using additional information not available to the assembler. Bandage facilitates this by allowing users to copy sequences directly from the graph visualization. In other cases, ambiguities cannot be resolved and the assembly cannot be completed. For these situations, Bandage provides a clear illustration of the assembly's incompleteness and comparison of one assembly's quality to another.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Resolving a complex antibiotic resistance region</head><p>Whole genome sequencing is frequently used to investigate evolution and transmission of bacterial pathogens and the mobile genetic elements responsible for antibiotic resistance. In this case study, multiple strains of Salmonella enterica were sequenced to determine the composition of their Salmonella genomic island (SGI), which can confer antibiotic resistance. The assembly of the SGI was complicated by sequences that were shared between the SGI, plasmids and a cloning vector used in the preparation of libraries for sequencing, making the contigs of limited use. With Bandage, the user could search for nodes of interest (resistance genes or known SGI sequences) and zoom in to deeply investigate those areas of the graph. By showing the graph edges, Bandage makes clear which contigs are connected, their directionality and therefore which sequences are likely to be contiguous (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1b</ref>). For many Salmonella strains, this allowed for determination that a gene of interest was or was not contained in the SGI, even when other methods were inconclusive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">16S sequence from a bacterial assembly</head><p>16S rRNA sequences are commonly used for classification of bacteria, but this is complicated by the fact that a single bacterial genome may contain multiple distinct copies of the 16S gene (V etrovskyándetrovsky´etrovskyánd<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Baldrian, 2013</ref>). Some regions of the gene are highly conserved while others regions are variable, potentially disrupting its de novo assembly. In this case study, the user sequenced a bacterial isolate with whole genome shotgun sequencing and assembled the reads with Velvet v1.2.10 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Zerbino and Birney, 2008</ref>). Bandage's BLAST integration highlighted the 16S gene in the assembly graph (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Camacho et al., 2009</ref>). It did not assemble completely, and fragments of the gene were present in seven different nodes (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1c</ref>). Consequently, the longest available 16S sequence in the contigs file was 909 bp and only partially covered the gene. By illustrating graph connections and node coverage, Bandage made it clear which path represents the gene's most abundant copy. The user was then able to extract node sequences from Bandage to manually reconstruct a 1535 bp sequence containing an entire 16S gene.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusion</head><p>By visualizing both nodes and edges, Bandage gives users easy, fast access to the connection information contained in assembly graphs. This is particularly useful when the assembly contains many short contigs—as is often the case when assembling short reads—and empowers users to examine and assess their assembly graphs in greater detail than when viewing contigs alone.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Bioinformatics, 31(20), 2015, 3350–3352doi:10.</head><figDesc>1093/bioinformatics/btv383 Advance Access Publication Date: 22 June 2015 Applications Note</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Examples of Bandage visualization (a) Left, ideal bacterial assembly (single contig); right, poor assembly with many short contigs. (b) Left, zoomed-in view of Salmonella assembly; repeated sequences (blaTEM and insertion sequence) appear as single nodes with multiple inputs and outputs. Node widths are scaled by read coverage (depth). Right, underlying gene structure deduced from Bandage visualization. (c) 16S rRNA region of a bacterial genome assembly graph, highlighted by Bandage's integrated BLAST search. Nodes are labelled with their ID numbers and their widths are scaled by coverage. Even though the 16S gene failed to assemble into a single node, the user can manually reconstruct a complete dominant gene sequence from this succession of nodes: 175, 176, 64, 65 and 190</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">R.R.Wick et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>I am grateful to both Simon Gladman and Jane Hawkey for their testing and feedback during Bandage's development.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Bankevich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="455" to="477" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BLASTþ: architecture and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Camacho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">421</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNASeq data without a reference genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Grabherr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="644" to="652" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-graph layout algorithms at work: an experimental study</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hachul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Jü Nger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Graph Algorithms Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assembly of large genomes using second-generation sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Schatz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1165" to="1173" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The variability of the 16S rRNA gene in bacterial genomes and its consequences for bacterial community analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Baldrian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">57923</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Velvet: algorithms for de novo short read assembly using de Bruijn graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Zerbino</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Birney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="821" to="829" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>