
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:53+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis BioCircos.js: an interactive Circos JavaScript library for biological data visualization on web applications</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ya</forename>
								<surname>Cui</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of RNA Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Beijing Key Laboratory of Noncoding RNA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100101</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100049</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xiaowei</forename>
								<surname>Chen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of RNA Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Beijing Key Laboratory of Noncoding RNA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100101</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Core Facility for Protein Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Biophysics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Huaxia</forename>
								<surname>Luo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of RNA Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Beijing Key Laboratory of Noncoding RNA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100101</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zhen</forename>
								<surname>Fan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of RNA Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Beijing Key Laboratory of Noncoding RNA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100101</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Core Facility for Protein Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Biophysics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jianjun</forename>
								<surname>Luo</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Shunmin</forename>
								<surname>He</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of RNA Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Beijing Key Laboratory of Noncoding RNA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100101</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Zoology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of the Zoological Systematics and Evolution</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100101</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Haiyan</forename>
								<surname>Yue</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of RNA Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Beijing Key Laboratory of Noncoding RNA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100101</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100049</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Peng</forename>
								<surname>Zhang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100049</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Runsheng</forename>
								<surname>Chen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of RNA Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Beijing Key Laboratory of Noncoding RNA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100101</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Research Network of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">RNCB</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100101</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis BioCircos.js: an interactive Circos JavaScript library for biological data visualization on web applications</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw041</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on 5 November 2015; revised on 18 January 2016; accepted on 19 January 2016</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Associate Editor: John Hancock Contact: rschen@ibp.ac.cn Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We here present BioCircos.js, an interactive and lightweight JavaScript library especially for biological data interactive visualization. BioCircos.js facilitates the development of web-based applications for circular visualization of various biological data, such as genomic features, genetic variations, gene expression and biomolecular interactions. Availability and implementation: BioCircos.js and its manual are freely available online at http://bio info.ibp.ac.cn/biocircos/.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Multi-faceted and complex biological data increasingly require visualization and sophisticated analyses. However, suitable visualization tools are not always available to come readily at hand. Furthermore, many biological visualization tools are desktop applications that may be difficult to install and configure. Circos (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Krzywinski et al., 2009</ref>) is a powerful Perl-based tool for illustrating genomic features, and is widely used in biological research. However, the graphical files it outputs are not interactive and users can thus not obtained further details by moving a mouse pointer over the data points. Alternatives to Circos, such as Circoletto (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Darzentas, 2010</ref>), CIRCUS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Naquin et al., 2014</ref>) and Rcircos (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Zhang et al., 2013</ref>), are also not interactive, whereas J-Circos (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">An et al., 2015</ref>), though interactive, is a desktop software. Web visualization applications have the advantage of generating interactive images in which all elements are interactive with mouse-over explanations and clickable buttons, and are thus far more userfriendly and provide more easily accessible information. As Circos and its alternatives do not function well on web applications, an interactive Circos-like tool for web applications would greatly facilitate visualization of biological data. Based on the powerful D3 (Data-Driven Documents) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bostock et al., 2011</ref>) and the jQuery JavaScript library, we have developed BioCircos.js, an interactive and lightweight JavaScript library especially adapted for interactive visualization of biological data on web applications. BioCircos.js thus facilitates the development of web applications for visualization of biological data in a circular format similar to that of Circos.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Implementation</head><p>BioCircos.js is written in JavaScript and generates interactive graphics with SVG element based on D3 (Data-Driven Documents) and jQuery. BioCircos.js itself is not a web application, but a library that provides the functionality to build Circos-like web tools. BioCircos.js provides the SNP, CNV, HEATMAP, LINK, LINE, SCATTER, ARC and HISTGRAM modules to display genome-wide genetic variations (SNPs, CNVs and chromosome rearrangement), gene expression and biomolecular interactions. BioCircos.js provides the BACKGROUND module to display background and axis circles, and also provides the TEXT module to facilitate the annotation of elements. Tooltips showing detailed information of SVG elements are also provided. With Twitter Bootstrap as the front-end framework, tooltips have an increased number of styles. A detailed document is available on the website. BioCircos.js supports multiple-platforms and works in all major internet browsers (Google Chrome, Internet Explorer, Mozilla Firefox, Safari, Opera). Its speed is determined by the client's hardware and the internet browser used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>The main differences between BioCircos.js and Circos are threefold. (i) BioCircos.js provides a convenient way to construct web-based applications for interactive visualization of biological data in a circular format. Additionally, BioCircos.js can generate high quality SVG vector graphics. (ii) BioCircos.js is written in web client-side JavaScript, and can thus take advantages of many web features to achieve useful interactive effects, such as binding mouse events to data points, animation effects, etc, which are not available to the Perl-based Circos.</p><p>We consider this is the most important advantage of BioCircos.js. (iii) Biocircos.js can be used by conjunction with standard browsers, thereby circumventing a number of problems, such as fixing dependencies or upgrading Perl modules, which is often necessary to perform when installing Circos on a local computer. To demonstrate the utility of BioCircos.js in generating circular images of biological data, we attempted to reproduce published Circos plots using BioCircos.js. A study published in 2010 reported a comprehensive catalogue of somatic mutations from a human cancer genome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Pleasance et al., 2010</ref>). We obtained all necessary data from the supplementary materials, including insertions, deletions, substitutions, copy number variations, loss of heterozygosity (LOH), and rearrangements, and used BioCircos.js to reproduce the plot containing all mutations (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1A</ref>). For example, we reproduced substitutions using SCATTER modules, and rearrangements using the LINK modules. A detailed description of data tracks can be found in<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Pleasance et al. (2010)</ref>.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1A</ref>shows the ability to visualize multi-faceted biological data.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1B</ref>shows how BioCircos.js can be used to visualize other types of biological data, in this case the amino acid sequence of the EGFR. The protein domains and SNPs in CDS are displayed using the ARC and SCATTER modules (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Gonzalez-Perez et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Shigematsu et al., 2005</ref>), so that the further away an SNP is located from the center, the higher its mutational frequency in population. Drug targeted mutations and indels are also displayed in the plot, all drug targeted mutations being located in the kinase domain. The mutation L858R (target of Afatinib, Iressa and Tarceva) has a higher frequency in population, and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1B</ref>clearly demonstrates the significance of L858R in drug design. To further illustrate the utility of BioCircos.js, we have provided three additional examples in the supplementary.), drug targeted mutations (L858R and T790M) and mutations (data from the IntOGen database;<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Gonzalez-Perez et al., 2013</ref>) in the CDS respectively</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BioCircos.js</head><p>BioCircos.js is not a web application for end-users but a JavaScript library for programmers. Developers need to write code around BioCircos.js to build web applications. BioCircos.js provides flexible and powerful functionality for the development of web-based circular visualization tools for multi-faceted biological data. These applications will be developed as plugins to simplify the process of generating circular image. We will continue to develop BioCircos.js to provide more features and support to the research community.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Plots constructed with BioCircos.js. (A) Reproduced plots of published somatic mutations from a human cancer genome. The outer ring represents chromosome ideograms. From outside and inwards, the data tracks represent insertions, deletions, heterozygous substitutions, homozygous substitutions, coding substitutions (silent in grey, missense in purple, nonsense in red and splice site in black), copy number variation, LOH and rearrangements. A detailed description can be found in Pleasance et al., 2010. (B) Circular visualization of protein domains, mutations and drug targeted mutations in EGFR. The outer ring represents the positions of the amino acid in EGFR. The next four tracks (from outside and inwards) are protein domains, drug targeted indels (Deletion in exon 19 and insertion in exon 20, data from Shigematsu et al., 2005), drug targeted mutations (L858R and T790M) and mutations (data from the IntOGen database; Gonzalez-Perez et al., 2013) in the CDS respectively</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 1740 Bioinformatics, 32(11), 2016, 1740–1742 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw041 Advance Access Publication Date: 27 January 2016 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We are grateful to Aiping Wu for thoughtful discussions and valuable comments on BioCircos.js design. We thank Geir Skogerbø for careful reading and valuable suggestions on the manuscript.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">J-Circos: an interactive Circos plotter</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>An</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1463" to="1465" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data-Driven Documents</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Bostock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. Comput. Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2301" to="2309" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circoletto: visualizing sequence similarity with Circos</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Darzentas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2620" to="2621" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IntOGen-mutations identifies cancer drivers across tumor types</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Gonzalez-Perez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1081" to="1082" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circos: an information aesthetic for comparative genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Krzywinski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1639" to="1645" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CIRCUS: a package for Circos display of structural genome variations from paired-end and mate-pair sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Naquin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="0198" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comprehensive catalogue of somatic mutations from a human cancer genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Pleasance</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">463</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="196" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical and biological features associated with epidermal growth factor receptor gene mutations in lung cancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Shigematsu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Natl. Cancer Inst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="346" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RCircos: an R package for Circos 2D track plots</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">244</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>