
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis CanSNPer: a hierarchical genotype classifier of clonal pathogens</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Adrian</forename>
								<surname>Lä Rkeryd</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Clinical Microbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Umeå University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kerstin</forename>
								<surname>Myrtennä</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Division of CBRN Security and Defence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">FOI, Swedish Defence Research Agency</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Edvin</forename>
								<surname>Karlsson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Division of CBRN Security and Defence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">FOI, Swedish Defence Research Agency</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chinmay</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Kumar</forename>
								<surname>Dwibedi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Clinical Microbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Umeå University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Division of CBRN Security and Defence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">FOI, Swedish Defence Research Agency</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mats</forename>
								<surname>Forsman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Division of CBRN Security and Defence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">FOI, Swedish Defence Research Agency</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pä</forename>
								<forename type="middle">R</forename>
								<surname>Larsson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Division of CBRN Security and Defence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">FOI, Swedish Defence Research Agency</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anders</forename>
								<surname>Johansson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Clinical Microbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">The Laboratory for Molecular Infection Medicine Sweden (MIMS)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andreas</forename>
								<surname>Sjö Din</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Division of CBRN Security and Defence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">FOI, Swedish Defence Research Agency</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Computational Life Science Cluster (CLiC)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Umeå University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Umeå</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Janet</forename>
								<surname>Kelso</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis CanSNPer: a hierarchical genotype classifier of clonal pathogens</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1762" to="1764"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu113</idno>
					<note>Associate Editor: Contact: adrian.larkeryd@foi.se</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Advances in typing methodologies have recently reformed the field of molecular epidemiology of pathogens. The falling cost of sequencing technologies is creating a deluge of whole genome sequencing data that burdens bioinformatics resources and tool development. In particular, single nucleotide polymorphisms in core gen-omes of pathogens are recognized as the most important markers for inferring genetic relationships because they are evolutionarily stable and amenable to high-throughput detection methods. Sequence data will provide an excellent opportunity to extend our understanding of infectious disease when the challenge of extracting knowledge from available sequence resources is met. Here, we present an efficient and user-friendly genotype classification pipeline, CanSNPer, based on an easily expandable database of predefined canonical single nucleotide polymorphisms. Availability and implementation: All documentation and Python-based source code for the CanSNPer are freely available at http:// github.com/adrlar/CanSNPer.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Whole genome sequencing of pathogen isolates will continue to improve epidemiological investigations and microbial forensics through the ability to reconstruct genetic relationships among isolates. The vast amount of information generated by whole genome sequencing can overcome the hurdles of other lessinformative rich epidemiological typing methods in establishing genetic relationships among pathogens. The overall goal is to identify similarities among strains that are a result of vertically inherited variation indicative of recent common descent. Confounding sources of polymorphisms must, however, be addressed, including sequencing errors and sequence polymorphisms introduced through horizontal transfer of sequences by both homologous and non-homologous recombination. No single typing method handles all levels of bacterial diversity. Multilocus sequence typing has been used for a decade as a portable sequence-based method for identifying clonal relationships among bacteria with various amount of recombination. In highly monomorphic and slowly evolving bacterial species such as Mycobacterium tuberculosis or Bacillus anthracis, identification of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), in comparison with a defined archetypal strain, could provide more robust phylogeny and higher resolution. In such pathogens, the inheritance pattern of specific sets of SNPs is strictly clonal (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Achtman, 2012</ref>). Several SNP detection technologies developed for this purpose over the past decades, e.g. based on real-time PCR or microarrays are predicted to be replaced by next-generation sequencing. For example, relationships among isolates of Francisella tularensis, Coxiella burnetii, Yersinia pestis and B.anthracis are amenable for characterization using specific sets of SNPs, often denoted canonical SNPs (canSNPs). It has been demonstrated that a small number of SNPs can be used to define genetic groups efficiently and to infer evolutionary relationships within F.tularensis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chanturia et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Gyuranecz et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Karlsson et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Svensson et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Vogler et al., 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Vogler et al., , 2011a</ref>), C.burnetii (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hornstra et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Karlsson et al., 2014</ref>), Y.pestis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Morelli et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Vogler et al., 2011b</ref>) and B.anthracis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Okinaka et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Simonson et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Van Ert et al., 2007</ref>). Using the new low-cost sequencing technology for SNP detection, there are vast amounts of data that can be used to characterize an isolate and its relationship with others. Wholegenome sequence typing is a powerful tool for genotyping and molecular epidemiological analysis but not completely accessible for scientists with limited computer skills (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Engelthaler et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Gillece et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">O'Farrell et al., 2012</ref>). The current bottleneck is time and computationally intensive generation of high-quality genome sequences. To take advantage of the new low-cost sequencing technology, sequence information must be presented and analyzed in a way that, for example, public health experts in epidemiology can easily interpret. Therefore, alternative methods are needed for Whole-genome sequence typing data to be used in real time. Here, we present an analysis pipeline for easy genotype classification of clonal pathogens. This program should have vast applications in clinical genomic research and will aid the expanding efforts to identify and trace pathogens during outbreaks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>We developed a pipeline for the analysis of canonical SNPs in draft genomes of clonal pathogens. CanSNPer is a fast and lightweight tool written in Python for genotype classification of pathogens based on canonical SNPs. A user-customizable *To whom correspondence should be addressed. configuration file specifies all parameter settings. Installation instructions are provided with the software distribution together with sample data and expected outputs. CanSNPer has dependencies on external software progressiveMauve (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Darling et al., 2010</ref>) and The Environment for Tree Exploration toolkit (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Huerta-Cepas et al., 2010</ref>). CanSNPer analysis could also be performed directly in a web browser as a Galaxy tool (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Blankenberg et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Giardine et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Goecks et al., 2010</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Building reference canSNP database</head><p>CanSNPer uses a local SQLite3 database to store information on canonical SNPs, the canSNP tree structure and reference sequences for each organism. The local database is created by the user, using a series of CanSNPer arguments. Preconstructed typing schemes for Y.pestis, F.tularensis, B.anthracis and C.burnetii are available for download with the software. Users may extend the local database by creating their own typing schemes in CanSNPer according to a predefined specification. The tree specification file must only contain the root of the tree on the first line, and each node in the tree has its own line with all its ancestors listed, separated by semicolon in order.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Classification of sequences</head><p>CanSNPer is designed to easily extract known canonical SNPs from a query draft sequence for classification of the pathogen isolate. The query is aligned to reference genomes for the selected reference organism using progressiveMauve (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Darling et al., 2010</ref>). CanSNPer will by default run all alignments in parallel for a significant speed increase if there are many reference sequences to a single organism. The state of each canSNP is determined, and the canSNP tree is traversed to find a classification. The pipeline uses a recursive and greedy tree walking algorithm and can classify a query sequence as either a leaf or as an intermediate node, if no more canSNPs could be determined as derived. The tree walking algorithm is also designed to handle the forcing of a number of nodes. If a region is missing in the query sequence in which one of the canSNPs is located, CanSNPer can be set to allow a mismatch in the tree and still find a classification if there are derived canSNPs further down the tree.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Visual genotype presentation</head><p>A visual representation of all SNPs in the canonical SNP tree for the query sequence can easily be generated. The visualization uses the Environment for Tree Exploration toolkit for Python (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Huerta-Cepas et al., 2010</ref>) to draw a phylogenetic canonical SNP tree (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). The complete canSNP tree for the analyzed genome sequence is visualized, and the derived SNP variants are indicated by larger filled circles.</p></div>
			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> CONCLUSION The ability of rapid and cost-efficient generation of whole genome sequence data of pathogens will transform treatment and epidemiological studies once clinicians have access to userfriendly analysis tools. We have presented the CanSNPer software written in Python to automatically genotype clonal bacterial pathogens using genome sequencing data. The identification of strain-specific SNP markers in pathogens permits the development of rapid diagnostics to greatly assist in the investigation of biocrimes and natural outbreaks that may require the analysis of hundreds or even thousands of specimens, including environmental and clinical samples. The database can be easily modified to handle other organisms of interest or similar SNP classification problems, such as cancer samples. Of interest for future improvements of the pipeline is the optimization of the classification algorithm and adding additional organisms. In conclusion, our strategy permits the identification of SNPs that are diagnostic for narrowly defined pathogen genetic lineages. The use of strain-specific SNPs for high-throughput genotyping may prove to be a valuable tool to assist in real-world forensic and epidemiological studies.</note>

			<note place="foot">CanSNPer at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">A.Lä rkeryd et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Insights from genomic comparisons of genetically monomorphic bacterial pathogens</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Achtman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">367</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="860" to="867" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Galaxy: a web-based genome analysis tool for experimentalists</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Blankenberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Protoc. Mol. Biol., Chapter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Unit. 19.10.1–Unit 19.10.21</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogeography of Francisella tularensis subspecies holarctica from the country of georgia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Chanturia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">139</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">progressiveMauve: multiple genome alignment with gene gain, loss and rearrangement</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Darling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11147</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Next-generation sequencing of Coccidioides immitis isolated during cluster investigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Engelthaler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Emerg. Infect. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Br</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Br</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>003. B.Br.001 B.Br.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Br</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>001. A.Br.006 A.Br.007 A.Br.004 A.Br.008 A.Br</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Br</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">1. Visual presentation of CanSNPer output. This example shows the genotyping of B</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Fig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Galaxy: a platform for interactive large-scale genome analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Giardine</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1451" to="1455" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole genome sequence analysis of Cryptococcus gattii from the Pacific Northwest reveals unexpected diversity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Gillece</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">28550</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Galaxy: a comprehensive approach for supporting accessible, reproducible, and transparent computational research in the life sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Goecks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">86</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogeography of Francisella tularensis subsp. holarctica</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Gyuranecz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Europe. Emerg. Infect. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="293" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid typing of Coxiella burnetii</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Hornstra</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ete: a python environment for tree exploration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Huerta-Cepas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Eight new genomes and synthetic controls increase the accessibility of rapid melt-mama snp typing of Coxiella burnetii</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Karlsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">85417</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The phylogeographic pattern of Francisella tularensis in Sweden indicates a Scandinavian origin of Eurosiberian tularaemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Karlsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="634" to="645" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Yersinia pestis genome sequencing identifies patterns of global phylogenetic diversity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Morelli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1140" to="1143" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transforming microbial genotyping: a robotic pipeline for genotyping bacterial strains</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Farrell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">48022</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single nucleotide polymorphism typing of Bacillus anthracis from sverdlovsk tissue</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Okinaka</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Emerg. Infect. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">653</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bacillus anthracis in China and its relationship to worldwide lineages</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Simonson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">71</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A real-time PCR array for hierarchical identification of Francisella isolates</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Svensson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8360</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global genetic population structure of Bacillus anthracis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Van Ert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">461</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogeography of Francisella tularensis: global expansion of a highly fit clone</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Vogler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bacteriol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2474" to="2484" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogeography of Francisella tularensis ssp. holarctica in France</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Vogler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lett. Appl. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="180" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogeography and molecular epidemiology of Yersinia pestis in Madagascar</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Vogler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Negl. Trop. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1319</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>