
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:48+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Cas-Analyzer: an online tool for assessing ge-nome editing results using NGS data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jeongbin</forename>
								<surname>Park</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hanyang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">South Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Theoretical Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kayeong</forename>
								<surname>Lim</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Genome Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Institute for Basic Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<region>South Korea</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">South Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jin-Soo</forename>
								<surname>Kim</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Genome Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Institute for Basic Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<region>South Korea</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">South Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sangsu</forename>
								<surname>Bae</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>: sangsubae@hanyang.ac.kr or jskim01@snu.ac.kr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hanyang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">South Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Materials Design</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hanyang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<region>South Korea</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Cas-Analyzer: an online tool for assessing ge-nome editing results using NGS data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Sequence analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Genome editing with programmable nucleases has been widely adopted in research and medicine. Next generation sequencing (NGS) platforms are now widely used for measuring the frequencies of mutations induced by CRISPR-Cas9 and other programmable nucleases. Here, we present an online tool, Cas-Analyzer, a JavaScript-based implementation for NGS data analysis. Because Cas-Analyzer is completely used at a client-side web browser on-the-fly, there is no need to upload very large NGS datasets to a server, a time-consuming step in genome editing analysis. Currently , Cas-Analyzer supports various programmable nucleases, including single nucleases and paired nucleases. Availability: Free access at http://www.rgenome.net/cas-analyzer/. Contact</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Programmable nucleases such as zinc finger nucleases (ZFNs), transcription-activator-like effector nucleases (TALENs), and RNA-guided endonucleases (RGENs) derived from CRISPR-Cas9/Cpf1 systems, which are adaptive immune responses in bacteria and archaea, are widely used for genome editing in many research fields including biology, biotechnology, agriculture, and medical science (<ref type="bibr">Kim and Kim, 2014</ref>). The type II Cas9 nuclease from Streptococcus pyogenes (SpCas9) was the first CRISPR nuclease used for genome editing (<ref type="bibr">Cho et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cong et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Jinek et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mali et al., 2013</ref>); since that time, various orthogonal Cas9 nucleases such as StCas9 (<ref type="bibr">Cong et al., 2013</ref>), NmCas9 (<ref type="bibr">Hou et al., 2013</ref>), and SaCas9 (<ref type="bibr">Ran et al., 2015</ref>) have been developed. Recently, putative type V Cpf1 nucleases from Acidominococcus and Lachnospiraceae were reported to mediate efficient genome editing in human cells (<ref type="bibr">Zetsche et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kim D et al., 2016</ref>) and mice (<ref type="bibr">Hur et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kim Y et al., 2016</ref>). Moreover, dimeric CRISPR nucleases such as RNA-guided nickases (<ref type="bibr">Ran et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cho et al., 2014</ref>) and RNA-guided FokI nucleases (<ref type="bibr">Tsai et al., 2014</ref>), or biochemical improvement of wild-type SpCas9 (<ref type="bibr">Slaymaker et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kleinstiver et al., 2016</ref>) have been developed for genome editing to reduce off-target effects. Programmable nucleases introduce DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs) at user-defined target sites in the genome, ultimately inducing targeted gene knockout or knock-in via the cell's own repair systems [error-prone non-homologous end joining (NHEJ) or homology-directed repair (HDR) in the presence of a DNA template, respectively]. The induced mutation rates in cells can be estimated in a straightforward manner by using Surveyor nuclease (<ref type="bibr">Perez et al., 2008</ref>), the T7 endonuclease I (T7E1) assay (<ref type="bibr">Kim et al., 2009</ref>), polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) (<ref type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2014</ref>), or droplet digital PCR (<ref type="bibr">Nelson et al., 2016</ref>). However, these methods do not allow analysis of mutant sequences and are limited by relatively poor sensitivity. Recently we and other groups have used targeted deep sequencing to detect programmable nucleaseinduced mutations with high sensitivity and precision and to analyze mutation patterns (<ref type="bibr">Baek et al., 2016</ref>). However, analysis of next generation sequencing (NGS) data is difficult for many researchers. Although a few web-based tools such as CRISPR-GA (<ref type="bibr">Güell et al., 2014</ref>), AGEseq (<ref type="bibr">Xue and Tsai, 2015</ref>), and CRISPResso (<ref type="bibr">Pinello et al., 2016</ref>) are available, they are inconvenient to use because their web interfaces require a very long time to upload large Associate Editor: Prof. Alfonso Valencia © The Author(s) 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com data files (Supplementary Note 1). AGEseq and CRISPResso also support a command-line interface, but they are not accessible to researchers who are not familiar with bioinformatics. To address this issue, we present a web-based tool, Cas-Analyzer, that is constructed with a JavaScript-based algorithm; thus, it wholly runs on the client-side so that large amounts of sequencing data do not need to be uploaded to the server. Thanks to the improvements in the newest JavaScript engines in the most recent web browsers (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>), this tool works in a reasonable time. Currently, Cas-Analyzer supports a variety of nucleases, including single nucleases (SpCas9, StCas9, NmCas9, SaCas9, CjCas9, and AsCpf1/LbCpf1) and paired nucleases (ZFNs, TALENs, Cas9 nickases, and dCas9-FokI nucleases).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Implementation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">File loading</head><p>To use Cas-Analyzer, deep sequencing data are needed, which can be obtained by amplifying the target locus of genome edited cells (Supplementary Note 2) followed by NGS. The format of the raw output data is usually Fastq or gzip-compressed, and both data types are acceptable to Cas-Analyzer (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1A</ref>). For the compressed files, we used a JavaScript library 'pako' (http://nodeca.github.io/pako/), which is slightly modified to support blocked gzip files (BGZF). If users upload paired-end sequencing data, Cas-Analyzer first merges paired-end reads by the JavaScript port of Fastq-join, a part of ea-utils (https://code.google.com/archive/p/ea-utils/).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Data analysis</head><p>Cas-Analyzer analyzes the uploaded data and calculates mutation frequencies in three steps (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1B-D</ref>): i) Cas-Analyzer first finds the cleavage point in the reference sequence for the selected nuclease. Using the given comparison range (R) parameter, Cas-Analyzer defines 12nt of indicator sequences on both sides of the given reference sequence and then selects the valid sequences, which contain both indicators with up to a 1-nt mismatch, from the uploaded data. ii) For the selected sequences, Cas-Analyzer then counts the recurrent frequency of each sequence and excludes the sequences below the given minimum frequency (n). iii) Cas-Analyzer finally classifies the filtered sequences into three different groups: 'insertion', 'deletion', or 'WT or substitution' based on comparing the sequence length with the length of the given reference sequence. Optionally, if a WT marker range (r) is given, the short sequence around the cleavage point will be used as the marker of wild-type. If this marker exists in the query sequence, it will always be classified into the 'WT or substitution' group regardless of its length. Additionally, if the donor DNA sequence for HDR is given, Cas-Analyzer defines an HDR indicator (&gt;8nt) by comparing the donor sequence with the reference sequence and classifies all query sequences that have the HDR indicator into the 'HDR' category.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Sequence alignment</head><p>For user convenience, after data analysis is complete, the results (a relatively small amount of data) are aligned to the reference sequence by using EMBOSS Needle (<ref type="bibr">Rice et al., 2000</ref>). The aligned results are categorized by mutation type and sorted in descending order by count. In addition, the position and size of insertions or deletions are depicted as interactive graphs on the results web page (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1E</ref>and F).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>This work was supported by a grant of the Korea Healthcare technology R&amp;D Project, Ministry for Health &amp; Welfare Affairs (HI16C1012) to S.B. and Institute for Basic Science (IBS-R021-D1) to J.-S.K. Conflict of Interest: none declared. References Baek,K. et al. (2015) DNA-free two-gene knockout in Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Overview of Cas-Analyzer. (A) Uploading NGS data files. Single-end reads, paired-end reads, or already merged sequencing data are allowed. (B) Basic information about the query sequences are required for using Cas-Analyzer. (C) Indicators used in the analysis step. (D) The results are summarized as a table that includes the mutation count and frequency. (E) Insertions and deletions are also visualized as graphs. (F) All filtered sequences from the input data are aligned with the reference sequence.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">Bioinformatics Advance Access published August 24, 2016 at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>