
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-11T00:00+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Cas-Designer: a web-based tool for choice of CRISPR-Cas9 target sites</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jeongbin</forename>
								<surname>Park</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sangsu</forename>
								<surname>Bae</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Materials Design</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hanyang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<region>South Korea</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jin-Soo</forename>
								<surname>Kim</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Genome Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Institute for Basic Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">South Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">South Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Cas-Designer: a web-based tool for choice of CRISPR-Cas9 target sites</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 3, 2015; revised on August 27, 2015; accepted on September 6, 2015</note>
					<note>Sequence analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: John Hancock Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present Cas-Designer, a user-friendly program to aid researchers in choosing appropriate target sites in a gene of interest for type II CRISPR/Cas-derived RNA-guided endonucleases, which are now widely used for biomedical research and biotechnology. Cas-Designer rapidly provides the list of all possible guide RNA sequences in a given input DNA sequence and their potential off-target sites including bulge-type sites in a genome of choice. In addition, the program assigns an out-of-frame score to each target site to help users choose appropriate sites for gene knockout. Cas-Designer shows the results in an interactive table and provides user-friendly filter functions. Availability and implementation: Free access at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Targeted genome editing based on the type II clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats (CRISPR) and CRISPR-associated (Cas) protein system from the prokaryotic adaptive immune response is now widely used for biomedical research and biotechnology (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Kim and Kim, 2014</ref>). CRISPR RNA-guided endonucleases (RGENs) consist of the Cas9 protein and guide RNAs (gRNAs), which are provided as two small RNAs [sequencevariable crRNA and invariable trans-activating CRISPR RNA (tracrRNA)] or as single-chain gRNAs in which essential portions of crRNA and tracrRNA are linked. RGENs cleave target DNA in a sequence-dependent manner; the repair of the resulting doublestrand breaks (DSBs) by endogenous mechanisms gives rise to targeted genome modifications in cells and whole organisms. In addition to the base pairing between gRNAs and target DNA, Cas9 also contributes to RGEN specificity by recognizing a protospaceradjacent motif (PAM) downstream of the gRNA target sequence. Cas9 proteins derived from different organisms recognize distinct PAM sequences. However, RGENs can also cleave off-target DNA sites with several mismatches (<ref type="bibr">Cho et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Fu et al., 2013</ref>) or with missing or additional nucleotides (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Lin et al., 2014</ref>), compared to gRNA sequences. We and others have presented computer programs that help researchers choose appropriate target sites for Cas9 nucleases (<ref type="bibr">Aach et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cradick et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Doench et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bae et al., 2014a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Heigwer et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hsu et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Lei et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Montague et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">O'Brien and Bailey, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Naito et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Sander et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Upadhyay and Sharma, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Xie et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Zhu et al., 2014</ref>). To the best of our knowledge, however, there is no web-based tool for providing the list of all possible gRNAs in a given input DNA sequence with their potential off-target sites with a DNA or RNA bulge in a genome of choice and with customizable PAM sequences appropriate for Cas9 derived from species other than S. pyogenes. Here we present Cas-Designer, a quick gRNA designing tool for various type II Cas9 nucleases, which lists all possible gRNA sequences from a given input DNA sequence along with their potential off-target sites in a genome of interest. Notably, Cas-Designer rapidly searches for potential off-target sites with a DNA or RNA bulge (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1A</ref>). Furthermore, Cas-Designer provides an out-of-frame score (<ref type="bibr">Bae et al., 2014b</ref>) for each gRNA to help choose appropriatesites for gene knockout. Cas-Designer is available as a commandline program or at our website.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Implementation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">gRNA selection</head><p>First, Cas-Designer finds possible target sites with a user-defined PAM sequence [5 0-NGG-3 0 or 5 0-NRG-3 0 for SpCas9, 5 0NNAGAAW-3 0 for StCas9 (<ref type="bibr">Cong et al., 2013</ref>), 5 0-NNNNGMTT-3 0 for NmCas9 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Hou et al., 2013</ref>) and 5 0-NNGRRT-3 0 for SaCas9 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Ran et al., 2015)</ref>] in a given DNA sequence. Second, Cas-Designer rapidly calculates the microhomology-associated out-of-frame score that is positively correlated with the frequency of frame-shift mutations (<ref type="bibr">Bae et al., 2014b</ref>). Cas-Designer shows cleavage positions, GC content and out-of-frame scores in this step. The tool also shows target sequences that contain more than four thymidine nucleotides in tandem in gray to indicate that these sequences are often recognized by RNA polymerase III as transcription termination signals (<ref type="bibr">Braglia et al., 2005</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Searching for potential off-target sites</head><p>Next, Cas-Designer invokes Cas-OFFinder (<ref type="bibr">Bae et al., 2014a</ref>) to rapidly identify potential off-target sites in a user-defined genome. To find potential off-target sites with a DNA or RNA bulge, we used a simple brute-force approach as shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 1B</ref>. Briefly, the program inserts up to three additional 'N' nucleotides or deletes up to 3 nucleotides in the target sequence to identify potential offtarget sites with a DNA bulge or an RNA bulge, respectively. To this end, we developed a lightweight wrapper script of CasOFFinder written in Python, which can be separately downloaded at our website. Because this step is the most time-consuming, we focused on improving Cas-OFFinder to achieve faster analysis. First, a new version now supports a 2 bit sequence format, which is smaller in size than is a FASTA format. Second, the internal OpenCL (Open Computing Language) kernels now use the local memory of the graphic card rather than the global memory. Third, the new version now uses atomic operation in OpenCL kernels and OpenMP (Open MultiProcessing) in the CPU operating part. These changes reduced the average analysis time per target by a factor of about 30 (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Output tables and filter options</head><p>Cas-Designer shows the results in an interactive table as shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 1C</ref>. A user can click on a blue-colored number or a 'Show' button to access the genomic loci of potential off-target sites. In addition, we implemented a user-friendly filter function on the results page for convenience. Output data can be filtered according to GC content, out-of-frame scores, or mismatch numbers. The filtered results are shown immediately, without whole-page refreshing, by using the AJAX (Asynchronous JavaScript and Extensible Markup Language) web development technique.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>The Plant Molecular Breeding Center of Next Generation BioGreen 21 Program (PJ01119201) and the research fund of Hanyang University (HY2015) to S.B. and Institute for Basic Science (IBS-R021-D1) to J.-S.K. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>References</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 4014 Bioinformatics, 31(24), 2015, 4014–4016 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv537 Advance Access Publication Date: 10 September 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Aach,J. et al. (2014) CasFinder: Flexible algorithm for identifying specific Cas9 targets in genomes. bioRxiv, doi:10.1101/005074. Bae,S. et al. (2014a) Cas-OFFinder: A fast and versatile algorithm that searches for potential off-target sites of Cas9 RNA-guided endonucleases. Bioinformatics, 30, 1473–1475. Bae,S. et al. (2014b) Microhomology-based choice of Cas9 nuclease target sites. Nat. Methods, 11, 705–706. Braglia,P. et al. (2005) Sequence context effects on oligo(dT) termination signal recognition by Saccharomyces cerevisiae RNA polymerase III. J. Biol. Chem., 280, 19551–19562. Cho,S.W. et al. (2014) Analysis of off-target effects of CRISPR/Cas-derived RNA-guided endonucleases and nickases. Genome Res., 24, 132–141. Cong,L. et al. (2013) Multiplex genome engineering using CRISPR/Cas systems. Science, 339, 819–823. Cradick,T.J. et al. (2014) COSMID: A web-based tool for identifying and validating CRISPR/Cas Off-target Sites. Mol. Ther. Nucleic Acids, 3, e214. Fig. 1. (A) Schematic showing off-target sites with a DNA or RNA bulge. (B) The strategy for allowing 1-nt DNA or RNA bulge based on Cas-OFFinder. (C) An example of an output table. Cas-Designer shows all possible gRNAs from input sequences along with useful information (top). If a user clicks on a blue colored number, word, or phrase, more detailed information, such as DNA (middle) or RNA (bottom) bulge targets, is provided. In addition, a user can obtain the relevant genomic information via the Ensembl genome browser (Flicek et al., 2011), by clicking on the &apos;Info at Ensembl&apos; button</note>

			<note place="foot">J.Park et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rational design of highly active sgRNAs for CRISPRCas9-mediated gene inactivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Doench</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1262" to="1267" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Flicek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="800" to="806" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-frequency off-target mutagenesis induced by CRISPR-Cas nucleases in human cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Fu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="822" to="826" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">E-CRISP: fast CRISPR target site identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Heigwer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient genome engineering in human pluripotent stem cells using Cas9 from Neisseria meningitidis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Hou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15644" to="15649" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA targeting specificity of RNA-guided Cas9 nucleases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hsu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="827" to="832" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A guide to genome engineering with programmable nucleases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J.-S</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="334" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CRISPR-P: a web tool for synthetic single-guide RNA design of CRISPR-system in plants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Lei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Plant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1494" to="1496" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CRISPR/Cas9 systems have off-target activity with insertions or deletions between target DNA and guide RNA sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7473" to="7485" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CHOPCHOP: a CRISPR/Cas9 and TALEN web tool for genome editing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Montague</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="407" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CRISPRdirect: software for designing CRISPR/ Cas guide RNA with reduced off-target sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Naito</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="1120" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GT-Scan: identifying unique genomic targets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>&apos;brien</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Bailey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="3" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vivo genome editing using Staphylococcus aureus Cas9</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Ran</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">520</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ZiFiT (Zinc Finger Targeter): an updated zinc finger engineering tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Sander</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SSFinder: high throughput CRISPR-Cas target sites prediction tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Upadhyay</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Sharma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biomed Res. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">742482</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">sgRNAcas9: a software package for designing CRISPR sgRNA and evaluating potential off-target cleavage sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Xie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100448</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CRISPRseek: a bioconductor package to identify targetspecific guide RNAs for CRISPR-Cas9 genome-editing systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Zhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108424</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>