
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:58+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">CellProfiler Analyst: interactive data exploration, analysis and classification of large biological image sets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<surname>Dao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Imaging Platform</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Technical University of Munich</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>80333</postCode>
									<settlement>Munich, Germany</settlement>
									<region>Bavaria</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Adam</forename>
								<forename type="middle">N</forename>
								<surname>Fraser</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Imaging Platform</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jane</forename>
								<surname>Hung</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Imaging Platform</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02139</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Vebjorn</forename>
								<surname>Ljosa</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Imaging Platform</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Shantanu</forename>
								<surname>Singh</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Imaging Platform</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anne</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Carpenter</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Imaging Platform</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">CellProfiler Analyst: interactive data exploration, analysis and classification of large biological image sets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw390</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received and revised on April 21, 2016; accepted on June 16, 2016</note>
					<note>Bioimage informatics † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first 3 authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Associate Editor: Robert Murphy/CellProfiler/CellProfiler-Analyst) under the BSD license. It is available as a packaged application for Mac OS X and Microsoft Windows and can be compiled for Linux. We implemented an automatic build process that sup-ports nightly updates and regular release cycles for the software. Contact: anne@broadinstitute.org Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>CellProfiler Analyst allows the exploration and visualization of image-based data, together with the classification of complex biological phenotypes, via an interactive user interface designed for biologists and data scientists. CellProfiler Analyst 2.0, completely rewritten in Python, builds on these features and adds enhanced supervised machine learning capabilities (Classifier), as well as visualization tools to overview an experiment (Plate Viewer and Image Gallery). Availability and Implementation: CellProfiler Analyst 2.0 is free and open source, available at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>CellProfiler Analyst is open-source software for biological imagebased classification, data exploration and visualization with an interactive user interface designed for biologists and data scientists. Using data from feature extraction software such as CellProfiler (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kamentsky et al., 2011</ref>), CellProfiler Analyst offers easy-to-use tools for exploration and mining of image data, which is being generated in ever increasing amounts, particularly in high-content screens (HCS). Its tools can help identify complex and subtle phenotypes, improve quality control and provide single-cell and population-level information from experiments. Some distinctive and critical features of CellProfiler Analyst are its user-friendly object-based machine learning interface, its ability to handle the tremendous scale of HCS experiments (millions of cell images), its gating capabilities that allow observing relationships among different data displays, and its exploration tools which enable interactively viewing connections between cell-level data and well-level data, and among raw images, processed/segmented images, extracted features and sample metadata. Compared to other commonly-cited open-source biological image classification software like Ilastik (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Sommer et al., 2011</ref>), CellCognition (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Held et al., 2010</ref>) and WND-CHARM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Orlov et al., 2008</ref>), CellProfiler Analyst has the advantage of containing companion visualization tools, being suitable for high-throughput datasets, having multiple classifier options, and allowing both cell and fieldof-view classification. Advanced Cell Classifier (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Horvath et al., 2011</ref>) shares many of the classification features of CellProfiler Analyst, but it lacks HCS data exploration and visualization tools. Compared to command-line-based data exploration software like cellHTS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Boutros et al., 2006</ref>) and imageHTS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Pau et al., 2013</ref>) and V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. the web tool web CellHTS2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Pelz et al., 2010</ref>), CellProfiler Analyst provides interactive object classification and image viewing. Several other software tools (e.g. the HCDC set of modules for KNIME (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Berthold et al., 2009</ref>)) are no longer available/maintained. Here, we present major improvements to CellProfiler Analyst. Since its original publication (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Jones et al., 2008</ref>), CellProfiler Analyst has been rewritten in Python (vs. its original language, Java) with significant enhancements. While keeping the original functionality allowing researchers to visualize data through histograms, scatter plots and density plots and to explore and score phenotypes by sequential gating, the key new features include: @BULLET multiple machine learning algorithms that can be trained to identify multiple phenotypes in single cells or whole fields of view, by simple drag and drop @BULLET more efficient handling of large scale, high-dimensional data @BULLET a gallery view to explore images in an experiment, and cells in individual images and @BULLET a plate layout view to explore aggregated cell measurements or image thumbnails for single or multiple plates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">New features in CellProfiler Analyst 2.0</head><p>Classifier: CellProfiler Analyst 1.0 allowed researchers to train a single classifier (Gentle Boosting) to recognize a single phenotype (twoclass) in individual cell images (rather than whole fields-of-view) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Jones et al., 2009</ref>). In CellProfiler Analyst 2.0 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>), Classifier can perform cell and field-of-view-level classification of multiple phenotypes (multi-class) using popular models like Random Forest, SVM and AdaBoost from the high performance machine learning library scikit-learn (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Pedregosa et al., 2011</ref>), which yields a 200-fold improvement in speed (Supplementary Data 1). First, cell-or wholeimage samples from the experiment are fetched and sorted by drag and drop into researcher-defined classes, making up the annotated training set. Fetching can be random, based on filters, based on perclass predictions of an already-trained classifier, or based on active learning. The new active learning option speeds annotation by presenting uncertain cases. In addition, researchers can view full images of each sample and drag and drop cells from the image for annotation. Next, a classifier is trained on this set. After training on the annotated set, a model's performance can be evaluated by cross validation in the form of a confusion matrix and precision, recall and F1 score per class. The model can then be used to quantify cell phenotypes or whole-image phenotypes. Image Gallery: CellProfiler Analyst 2.0 offers a convenient new Image Gallery tool (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1A</ref>), in addition to the existing visualization/exploration tools with standard plotting and gating capabilities in version 1.0 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Jones et al., 2008</ref>). Image Gallery provides a convenient grid view allowing an overview of images. A variety of options are provided to filter images based on experiment-specific metadata, e.g. gene name, compound treatments, etc. Multiple filters can be combined to refine the search. Images can be displayed as a custom-sized thumbnail or in full resolution, and the color assigned to each channel in the image can be customized to highlight structures of interest. Individual segmented cells can be viewed for each image, and can be dragged and dropped into the Classifier window. Plate Viewer: Many large-scale imaging experiments take place in multi-well plate format. Researchers are often interested in seeing their data overlaid on this format, to check for systematic sample quality issues, or to see results from controls placed in particular locations, at a glance. The Plate Viewer tool (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1C</ref>) displays aggregated and/or filtered measurements (according to customizable color maps) or a thumbnail image for each well. Automatically imported annotations can be viewed, and individual annotations can be manually added or deleted for each well. Additional features: Additional features added to CellProfiler Analyst vs. version 1.0 have been described elsewhere, such as Tracer, a tool that complements the object tracking functionality of CellProfiler, including visualization and editing of tracks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bray and Carpenter, 2015</ref>), as well as workspaces for saving progress and display settings across sessions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bray et al., 2012</ref>). The website, manual and tutorials have been redesigned and updated to the new version.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Future directions</head><p>The redesigned CellProfiler Analyst contains useful classification and visualization features in an interactive interface that facilitates data analysis and exploration of biological images. Its code base forms a solid foundation for integrating new classifiers into the tool, potentially including deep learning architectures. We also intend to integrate methods for constructing per-sample 'profiles' from rawmorphological measurements to support morphological profiling applications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Caicedo et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bray et al., 2016</ref>).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. User Interface of CellProfiler Analyst. (A) Main Toolbar and Image Gallery; (B) Classifier; (C) Plate Viewer</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">Bioinformatics, 2016, 1–3 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw390 Advance Access Publication Date: 26 June 2016 Applications Note Bioinformatics Advance Access published July 31, 2016 at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors thank members of their laboratory for contributing to the development of the software and this manuscript, especially Mark-Anthony Bray, Allen Goodman, Lee Kamentsky, Alison Kozol, David Logan and Mohammad Rohban.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work has been supported by the National Institutes of Health<ref type="bibr">[</ref></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KNIME-the Konstanz Information Miner: Version 2.0 and Beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Berthold</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIGKDD Explor. Newsl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of cell-based RNAi screens</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Boutros</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">66</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CellProfiler Tracer: exploring and validating high-throughput, time-lapse microscopy image data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Bray</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Carpenter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">368</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Workflow and metrics for image quality control in large-scale high-content screens</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Bray</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biomol. Screen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cell Painting, a high-content image-based assay for morphological profiling using multiplexed fluorescent dyes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Bray</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="page">49817</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Applications in image-based profiling of perturbations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Caicedo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CellCognition: time-resolved phenotype annotation in high-throughput live cell imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Held</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="747" to="754" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Machine learning improves the precision and robustness of high-content screens, using non-linear multi-parametric methods to analyze screening results</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Horvath</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biomol. Screen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1059" to="1067" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scoring diverse cellular morphologies in image-based screens with iterative feedback and machine learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1826" to="1831" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CellProfiler Analyst: data exploration and analysis software for complex image-based screens</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">482</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved structure, function and compatibility for CellProfiler: modular high-throughput image analysis software</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Kamentsky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1179" to="1180" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WND-CHARM: multi-purpose image classification using compound image transforms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Orlov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recogn. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1684" to="1693" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">imageHTS: Analysis of high-throughput microscopybased screens</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Pau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>R. package version 1.22.0</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scikit-learn: machine learning in python</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Pedregosa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mach. Learn. Res. JMLR</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2825" to="2830" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">web cellHTS2: A web-application for the analysis of highthroughput screening data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Pelz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ilastik: interactive learning and segmentation toolkit</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Sommer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging: From Nano to Macro</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="230" to="263" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">CellProfiler Analyst</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>