
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:31+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Bioimage informatics CellMissy: a tool for management, storage and analysis of cell migration data produced in wound healing-like assays</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">20 2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Paola</forename>
								<surname>Masuzzo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>9000</postCode>
									<settlement>Ghent</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Niels</forename>
								<surname>Hulstaert</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>9000</postCode>
									<settlement>Ghent</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lynn</forename>
								<surname>Huyck</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>9000</postCode>
									<settlement>Ghent</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christophe</forename>
								<surname>Ampe</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>9000</postCode>
									<settlement>Ghent</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Marleen</forename>
								<surname>Van Troys</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>9000</postCode>
									<settlement>Ghent</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lennart</forename>
								<surname>Martens</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>9000</postCode>
									<settlement>Ghent</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Protein Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">VIB</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Bioimage informatics CellMissy: a tool for management, storage and analysis of cell migration data produced in wound healing-like assays</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2661" to="2663"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">20 2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt437</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 14, 2013; revised on July 5, 2013; accepted on July 24, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Contact: lennart.martens@ugent.be Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Automated image processing has allowed cell migration research to evolve to a high-throughput research field. As a consequence , there is now an unmet need for data management in this domain. The absence of a generic management system for the quantitative data generated in cell migration assays results in each dataset being treated in isolation, making data comparison across experiments difficult. Moreover, by integrating quality control and analysis capabilities into such a data management system, the common practice of having to manually transfer data across different downstream analysis tools will be markedly sped up and made more robust. In addition, access to a data management solution creates gateways for data standardization, meta-analysis and structured public data dissemination. We here present CellMissy, a cross-platform data management system for cell migration data with a focus on wound healing data. CellMissy simplifies and automates data management, storage and analysis from the initial experimental setup to data exploration. Availability and implementation: CellMissy is a cross-platform open-source software developed in Java. Source code and cross-platform binaries are freely available under the Apache2 open source license at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Dynamic cell motility processes are essential for morphogenesis, immune responses, wound healing and cancer metastasis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Friedl et al., 2009</ref>). Investigation of the mechanisms and modes of cell migration is therefore important for fundamental scientific insight and for translational research, as molecules involved in deregulated cell migration are attractive targets for therapeutic intervention. As a result, the field has developed methods for the systematic high-throughput analysis of cell migration, with wound healing-like assays currently most amenable to multiple condition comparison or high-throughput approaches (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ashby et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hulkower et al., 2011</ref>). In these assays, a cell layer is allowed to move into a cell-free region, and the decrease in time of this area reflects cell migration velocity. The cell-free zone can be created (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Riahi et al., 2012</ref>) by scratching a confluent cell layer [typical wound healing assay (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Liang et al., 2007)]</ref>or by using non-damaging barriers during cell seeding [cell exclusion zone assay (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Gough et al., 2011)]</ref>. Advanced microscopes then allow automatic acquisition of images of the migrating cells, and specialized image processing tools are used to quantify cell migration features from these images (<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>). Specific solutions for tackling the problems in large-scale image management and storage have additionally been reported (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">de Chaumont et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Moore et al., 2008</ref>). However, a major current challenge in the cell migration field lies in the development of suitable software for the annotation, management and sharing of the quantification data obtained from such imaging-based experiments. Although software tools are available to help with several of the steps in this workflow, several key functions currently remain unmet (see<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>). We here present CellMissy, a cross-platform system for the annotation, storage, analysis and dissemination of quantitative cell migration data. It aids the user with experimental set-up and annotation, generic data import/export (downstream from image processing) and subsequent data storage, inspection and analysis. It thus provides support for the entire experimental workflow, when coupled to an image analysis algorithm of choice (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>,<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>). CellMissy is intended to facilitate local storage and analysis of acquired data, but it also provides the basic infrastructure for improved annotation, standardization and dissemination in the migration field, ultimately enabling re-analyses and meta-analyses to take place. The benefit of the latter has already been proven in other fields, where data management and dissemination infrastructure are more mature (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Matic et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Martens, 2011</ref>). The development of useroriented freely available data storage and analysis systems for cell migration data thus provides an important and timely next step for the field.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">TOOL DESCRIPTION AND FUNCTIONALITY</head><p>CellMissy is a client-server application with a graphical user interface (GUI) on the client and a relational database in the back-end to store the data (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). It is developed to follow the steps typically encountered in a cell migration experiment (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>and<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>) and is composed *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>y</head><p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the last two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. of three modules: the experiment manager, the data loader and the data analyzer. CellMissy handles wound healing-like data obtained from different experimental set-ups and after processing with different image analysis software (see<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>). CellMissy takes either generic text files as input or can be customized to load data from image acquisition software automatically.</p><p>CellMissy is written entirely in Java, and uses Swing for the GUI, the Spring framework for the logic layer and Hibernate for communication with the database.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Experiment manager–experimental set-up</head><p>This module (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1A</ref>) is used to set up a cell migration experiment. Its main interface element is a graphical presentation of a user-definable multi-well plate. For a certain biological condition, one or more wells representing technical replicates can be selected. Different informative metadata variables (e.g. cell line, treatment compound and dose) can be supplied for each condition. The resulting plate layout, well assignments and metadata are all stored in the database. To our knowledge, CellMissy constitutes the first tool in the community that provides the possibility to extensively annotate and customize the experimental set-up. CellMissy can also export the experimental design in PDF form for use in the laboratory, to actually set up the experiment and proceed to sample preparation. Furthermore, it is possible to retrieve set-up settings from previously stored experiments, thus accelerating the process of planning new experiments or setting up a replicate experiment. Templates containing all metadata information from the set-up can in addition be exported as an XML file, which can be shared between researchers and re-imported, thus allowing for comparison between different set-ups and promoting data exchange and dissemination.2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Data loader–data import and storage</head><p>As shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1B</ref>, the user then performs laboratorydedicated image acquisition and processing (see<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>for choice set-ups and image processing tools), thus producing the input data for CellMissy (see Supplementary Section S2.1). Data import and storage are handled by the data loader module (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1C</ref>) that either reads a generic text-based data input format or can be fully automated if tailored to the chosen combination of set-up/image processing tool. CellMissy expects at least one tabseparated text file for each well, listing the time and the associated area values. Multiple files can be loaded per well, allowing different imaging locations, the application of different imaging techniques (e.g. phase contrast, fluorescence) or the import of data from different image analysis algorithms for that single well. Importantly, CellMissy again provides a means to export an entire experiment to an XML file at this level, i.e. with all acquired data. This XML file can be shared with other researchers (e.g. as Supplementary Information), directly re-imported by any CellMissy user, thus enabling easy exchange of data, re-analysis and reproduction of the results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Data analyzer–data interpretation and reporting</head><p>The data analyzer module (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1D</ref>) guides the user through data analysis and interpretation.<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>demonstrates the extra features of CellMissy compared with the two reported tools dedicated to wound healing data analysis. The analysis in TScratch (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Geba¨ckGeba¨ck et al., 2009</ref>) is an extension of the TScratch image processing, whereas CellMissy uniquely combines more extensive analysis of wound healing with data storage and management and possibilities for data dissemination (see above). The analysis consists first of a pre-processing step to normalize raw data relative to the area at time 0 (see Supplementary Section S2.1). The next step handles quality control (for full details, see Supplementary Section S2.2). For each technical replicate, artifacts in area increase between time steps are detected and visualized using a kernel density estimator (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S5</ref>). The variation between technical replicates is examined using Euclidean distance (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6</ref>). In each step, the user can accept or reject the suggested correction. A linear regression model then extracts slope and R 2 value on a replicate level. The median slope across replicates then yields the median migration velocity for a condition. All pair-wise differences in median velocity between a set of user-selected conditions are subsequently analyzed using a Mann–Whitney U test with a choice of multiple hypothesis testing correction (Bonferroni or Benjamini– Hochberg) (Supplementary Section S2.3). The architecture of CellMissy is, in addition, fully pluggable for analysis algorithms. This means that different distance metrics, statistical tests, kernel density estimators, outlier detection methods and multiple hypothesis correction methods can be added by any interested developer. Such new methods can be plugged dynamically into CellMissy, and will subsequently be immediately available to the user from the CellMissy interface. Finally, CellMissy produces a detailed PDF report that summarizes experimental design details, acquired data, corresponding results and statistical evaluation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>CellMissy is a novel, cross-platform, generic data management and analysis system for cell migration experiments. CellMissy is freely available, flexible in linking to upstream experimental setups and image processing tools, easily extensible and automates data handling, processing, quality monitoring and interpretation. Its intuitive interface provides support from the experimental setup to the final reporting of the analysis including statistics. Data in CellMissy can be exported from one system and re-loaded in another system, enabling easy data sharing. In addition, it provides a framework for tool expansion toward future meta-analyses on data generated by multiple users, making it possible, for example, to compare all drug effects on cells of a particular cancer present in a shared CellMissy database. CellMissy is released as open source under the permissive Apache2 license.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Schematic workflow of a typical wound healing experiment demonstrating the tasks for which the different modules (A, C and D) from CellMissy are used to manage, import and analyze data of images that are acquired independently by an experimental set-up and image processing tool of choice (B)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>' project grant agreement number 260558, funded by the European Union 7th Framework Program. L.M. further acknowledges the support of Ghent University (Multidisciplinary Research Partnership 'Bioinformatics: from nucleotides to networks'). P.M. and C.A. acknowledge funding from BOF/FGE B/00559/01, and C.A. further acknowledges support from FWO Vlaanderen research fund G.0353.11.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: EC FP7 ProteomeXchange project grant agreement number 260558, Ghent University, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences fund BOF/FGE B/00559/01, FWO Vlaanderen research fund G.0353.11. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Overview of currently available tools/software dedicated to wound healing-like workflow</figDesc><table>Expermental 
design, 
annotation 

Experimental 
set-up a 

Image 
processing: 
area 
measurement 
(*¼free) 

Data analysis 
Data storage, 
management and 
sharing; potential 
for meta-analysis 
Multiple 
conditions 

Time series 
Replicates= 
condition 
Quality 
control 
replicates 
Graphical 
presentation 

area velocity 
Statistics 
Report 
SQLbased 

CellMissy 

Wound healing assay 
(scratch b , photo-ab-
lation, electrical 
wounding (ECIS)) 

WimScratch 
WimScratch – 
þ 
þ 
v 
– 
csv 
– 

CellMissy 

2D cell exclusion 
zone assay b,c 

Image-Pro Plus 
Software 
2D fence assay 
TScratch* d 
2D microcarrier 
bead/spheroid 
assay 

CellProfiler (wound 
healing tool)* 

TScratch e 
þ 
þ þ 
þ 
a 
þ 
csv 
– 

Capillary tube mi-
gration assay 
(microfluidics) 
3D cell exclusion 
zone assay 
(Platypus) 

ImageJ tools b * 
C e l l M i s s y 
þ 
þ þ 
þ 
þ 
a,v þþ pdf csv þ 

3D spheroid assay 
Home-made tools b 

Note: The table headers show the typical steps in a wound healing-like workflow; within gray are those to which CellMissy contributes. 
The first column under 'Data analysis' gives the software; '–', 'þ' or 'þþ' indicates absence or level of presence of the listed feature; file format of report is indicated. 

a 

Common conditional feature: migration of (confluent) cell layer followed in time (Kramer et al., 2013). 

b 

used as input in current work, but any of these set-ups can provide input to CellMissy. 

c 

various set-ups (from Platypus, Ibidi, Cell Biolabs). 

d 

Geba¨ckGeba¨ck et al., 2009. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">P.Masuzzo et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Established and novel methods of interrogating two-dimensional cell migration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Ashby</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Zijlstra</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Integr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1338" to="1350" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Icy: an open bioimage informatics platform for extended reproducible research</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>De Chaumont</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="690" to="696" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective cell migration in morphogenesis, regeneration and cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Friedl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="457" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TScratch: a novel and simple software tool for automated analysis of monolayer wound healing assays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Geba¨ckgeba¨ck</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechniques</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A quantitative, facile, and high-throughput image-based cell migration method is a robust alternative to the scratch assay</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Gough</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biomol. Screen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cell migration and invasion assays as tools for drug discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Hulkower</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmaceutics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vitro cell migration and invasion assays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Kramer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mutat. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">752</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vitro scratch assay: a convenient and inexpensive method for analysis of cell migration in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Liang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="333" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proteomics databases and repositories</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Martens</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">694</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="227" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reanalysis of phosphoproteomics data uncovers ADPribosylation sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Matic</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="771" to="772" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open tools for storage and management of quantitative image data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Moore</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="555" to="570" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advances in wound-healing assays for probing collective cell migration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Riahi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Lab. Autom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>