
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:48+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Change-O: a toolkit for analyzing large-scale B cell immunoglobulin repertoire sequencing data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Namita</forename>
								<forename type="middle">T</forename>
								<surname>Gupta</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Interdepartmental Program in Computational Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>06511</postCode>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jason</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Vander Heiden</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Interdepartmental Program in Computational Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>06511</postCode>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mohamed</forename>
								<surname>Uduman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>06511</postCode>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Daniel</forename>
								<surname>Gadala-Maria</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Interdepartmental Program in Computational Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>06511</postCode>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gur</forename>
								<surname>Yaari</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Bioengineering Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Bar-Ilan University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ramat Gan 52900</settlement>
									<country key="IL">Israel</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Steven</forename>
								<forename type="middle">H</forename>
								<surname>Kleinstein</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Interdepartmental Program in Computational Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>06511</postCode>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>06511</postCode>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Change-O: a toolkit for analyzing large-scale B cell immunoglobulin repertoire sequencing data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv359</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 17, 2014; revised on April 30, 2015; accepted on June 5, 2015</note>
					<note>Sequence analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Associate Editor:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Advances in high-throughput sequencing technologies now allow for large-scale characterization of B cell immunoglobulin (Ig) repertoires. The high germline and somatic diversity of the Ig repertoire presents challenges for biologically meaningful analysis, which requires specialized computational methods. We have developed a suite of utilities, Change-O, which provides tools for advanced analyses of large-scale Ig repertoire sequencing data. Change-O includes tools for determining the complete set of Ig variable region gene segment alleles carried by an individual (including novel alleles), partitioning of Ig sequences into clonal populations, creating lineage trees, inferring somatic hypermutation targeting models, measuring repertoire diversity, quantifying selection pressure , and calculating sequence chemical properties. All Change-O tools utilize a common data format , which enables the seamless integration of multiple analyses into a single workflow. Availability and implementation: Change-O is freely available for non-commercial use and may be downloaded from http://clip.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Large-scale characterization of immunoglobulin (Ig) repertoires is now feasible due to dramatic improvements in high-throughput sequencing technology. Repertoire sequencing is a rapidly growing area, with applications including detection of minimum residual disease, prognosis following transplant, monitoring vaccination responses, identification of neutralizing antibodies and inferring B cell trafficking patterns (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Robins, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Stern et al., 2014</ref>). We previously developed the repertoire sequencing toolkit (pRESTO) for producing assembled and error-corrected reads from high-throughput lymphocyte receptor sequencing experiments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Vander Heiden et al., 2014</ref>), which may then be fed into existing methods for alignment against V(D)J germline databases [e.g. IMGT/HighV-QUEST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alamyar et al., 2012</ref>), IgBLAST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Ye et al., 2013</ref>), iHMMune-align (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gaëta et al., 2007)]</ref>. However, extracting measures of biological and clinical interest from the resulting germline-annotated repertoire remains a time-consuming and error-prone process that is often dependent upon custom analysis scripts. Here, we introduce ChangeO, a suite of utilities that cover a range of complex analysis tasks for Ig repertoire sequencing data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Features</head><p>The Change-O suite is composed of four software packages: a collection of Python commandline tools (changeo-ctl) and three separate R (R Core<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Team, 2015</ref>) packages (alakazam, shm, and tigger)<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>). Data are passed to Change-O utilities in the form of a tab-delimited text file. Each utility identifies the relevant input data based on standardized column names and adds new columns to the file with the output information to be carried through to the next analysis step. Change-O provides tools to import data from the frequently used IMGT/HighV-QUEST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alamyar et al., 2012</ref>) tool as well as a set of utilities to perform basic database operations, such as sorting, filtering and modifying annotations. The more computationally expensive components have built-in multiprocessing support. Each utility includes detailed help documentation and optional logging to track errors. Example workflow scripts are provided on the website, which can easily be modified by adding, removing or reordering analysis steps to meet different analysis goals. As detailed later, several repertoire analyses may be carried out, depending on the nature of the study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Inference of novel alleles and individual genotype</head><p>Germline segment assignment tools, such as IMGT/HighV-QUEST, work by aligning each sequence against a database of known alleles. However, this process is inaccurate for sequences that utilize previously undetected alleles. In this case, the sequence will be assigned to the closest known allele and any polymorphisms will be incorrectly identified as somatic mutations. To address this problem, the Tool for Immunoglobulin Genotype Elucidation (TIgGER) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Gadala-Maria et al., 2015</ref>) has been implemented as an R package for inclusion in Change-O. TIgGER determines the complete set of variable region gene segments carried by an individual and identifies novel alleles, yielding a set of germline alleles personalized to an individual. The germline variable region allele assignments are then adjusted based on this individual Ig genotype. This process significantly improves the quality of germline assignments, thus increasing the confidence of downstream analysis dependent upon mutation profiles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Partitioning sequences into clonally related groups</head><p>Identifying sequences that are descended from the same B cell (clonal groups) is important to virtually all Ig repertoire analyses. Clonal group sizes and lineage structures provide information on the underlying response, and clonally related sequences cannot be treated independently in statistical analyses and models. Change-O provides several methods for partitioning sequences into clones. Along with published methods based on hierarchical clustering (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ademokun et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chen et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Glanville et al., 2009</ref>), users also have the option to employ several published somatic hypermutation (SHM) hot/cold-spot targeting models as distance metrics in the clustering methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Smith et al., 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Yaari et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Stern et al., 2014</ref>). Users may alter the clustering thresholds, and Change-O also includes tools to tune the thresholds based on distance patterns in the repertoire (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Glanville et al., 2009</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Quantification of repertoire diversity</head><p>To assess repertoire diversity, Change-O provides an implementation of the general diversity index ( q D) proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hill (1973)</ref>, which encompasses a range of diversity measures as a smooth curve over a single varying parameter q. Special cases of this general index of diversity correspond to the most popular diversity measures: species richness (q ¼ 0), the exponential Shannon-Weiner index (as q ! 1), the inverse of the Simpson index (q ¼ 2), and the reciprocal abundance of the largest clone (as q ! 1). Resampling strategies are also provided to perform significance tests and allow comparison across samples with varying sequencing depth (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Wu et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Stern et al., 2014</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Generation of B cell lineage trees</head><p>Lineage trees provide a means to trace the ancestral relationships of cells within a clone. This information has been used to estimate mutation rates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kleinstein et al., 2003</ref>), infer B cell trafficking patterns (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Stern et al., 2014</ref>) and trace the accumulation of mutations that drive affinity maturation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Uduman et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Wu et al., 2012</ref>). Change-O provides a tool for generating lineage trees using PHYLIP's maximum parsimony algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Felsenstein, 1989</ref>), with modifications to meet the requirements of an Ig lineage tree (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Barak et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Stern et al., 2014</ref>). Trees may be viewed and exported into different file formats using the igraph (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Csardi and Nepusz, 2006</ref>) R package.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Somatic hypermutation hot/cold-spot motifs</head><p>SHM is a process that operates in activated B cells and introduces point mutations into the DNA coding for the Ig receptor at a very high rate (%10 À3 per base-pair per division) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kleinstein et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">McKean et al., 1984</ref>). Accurate background models of SHM are critical, since SHM displays intrinsic hot/cold-spot biases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Yaari et al., 2013</ref>). Change-O provides utilities for estimating the mutability and substitution rates of DNA motifs from large-scale Ig sequencing data to construct hot/cold-spot motif models. Furthermore, models may be generated based solely on silent mutations, thereby avoiding the confounding influence of selection pressures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Yaari et al., 2013</ref>). These tools can be used to build models of SHM targeting and gain insight into the relative contributions of different error-prone repair pathways in SHM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">Analysis of selection pressure</head><p>For quantifying selection pressure in Ig sequences, Change-O includes the BASELINe (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Yaari et al., 2012</ref>) method, which has been implemented as an R package for inclusion in the suite. BASELINe quantifies deviations in the frequency of replacement mutations compared with a background model of SHM. Users may choose between published background models (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Smith et al., 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Yaari et al., 2013</ref>) or infer the background from their own data using the SHM model building tools described above. communication between the utilities and can easily be viewed using any spreadsheet application. This format also allows research groups the flexibility to incorporate other analysis tools into their in-house analysis pipelines by simply adding additional columns of information to the central file. Change-O, along with pRESTO (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Vander Heiden et al., 2014</ref>), provides key components of an analytical ecosystem that enables sophisticated analysis of high-throughput Ig repertoire sequencing datasets.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 3356 Bioinformatics, 31(20), 2015, 3356–3358 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv359 Advance Access Publication Date: 10 June 2015 Applications Note (</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> Conclusion Change-O is a suite of utilities implementing a wide range of B cell repertoire analysis methods. Together these tools allow researchers to quickly implement advanced analysis pipelines for large datasets generated by repertoire sequencing experiments. A simple tabdelimited file with standardized column names allows for Table 1. Summary of Change-O features Package Analysis tasks changeo-clt Parsing of V(D)J assignment output Basic database manipulation Multiple alignment of sequence records Assignment of sequences into clonal groups Calculation of CDR3 physiochemical properties alakazam Clonal diversity analysis Lineage reconstruction shm SHM hot/cold-spot modeling Quantification of selection pressure tigger Inference of novel germline alleles Construction of personalized germline genotype Change-O</note>

			<note place="foot">N.T.Gupta et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors thank the Yale University Biomedical High Performance Computing Center<ref type="bibr">[</ref></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vaccination-induced changes in human B-cell repertoire and pneumococcal IgM and IgA antibody at different ages</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ademokun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aging cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="922" to="930" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IMGT(V R ) tools for the nucleotide analysis of immunoglobulin (IG) and T cell receptor (TR) V-(D)-J repertoires, polymorphisms, and IG mutations: IMGT/V-QUEST and IMGT/HighV-QUEST for NGS</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Alamyar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">882</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="569" to="604" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IgTree: creating immunoglobulin variable region gene lineage trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Barak</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">338</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustering-based identification of clonally-related immunoglobulin gene sequence sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The igraph software package for complex network research. InterJournal, Complex Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Csardi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Nepusz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page">1695</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PHYLIP-Phylogeny inference package (Version 3.2)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Felsenstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cladistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="164" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automated analysis of high-throughput B-cell sequencing data reveals a high frequency of novel immunoglobulin V gene segment alleles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Gadala-Maria</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">iHMMune-align: hidden Markov model-based alignment and identification of germline genes in rearranged immunoglobulin gene sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Gaëta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1580" to="1587" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Precise determination of the diversity of a combinatorial antibody library gives insight into the human immunoglobulin repertoire</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Glanville</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20216" to="20221" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diversity and evenness: a unifying notation and its consequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Hill</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="427" />
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating hypermutation rates from clonal tree data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Kleinstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4639" to="4649" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generation of antibody diversity in the immune response of BALB/c mice to influenza virus hemagglutinin</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Mckean</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3180" to="3184" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R Core</forename>
				<surname>Team</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<pubPlace>Vienna, Austria</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunosequencing: applications of immune repertoire deep sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Robins</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="646" to="652" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Di-and trinucleotide target preferences of somatic mutagenesis in normal and autoreactive B cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">156</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2642" to="2652" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">B cells populating the multiple sclerosis brain mature in the draining cervical lymph nodes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N H</forename>
				<surname>Stern</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Transl. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating B cell lineage information into statistical tests for detecting selection in Ig sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Uduman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">192</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="867" to="874" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">pRESTO: a toolkit for processing highthroughput sequencing raw reads of lymphocyte receptor repertoires</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Vander Heiden</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1930" to="1932" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Age-related changes in human peripheral blood IGH repertoire following vaccination</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y.-C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="0193" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Influence of seasonal exposure to grass pollen on local and peripheral blood IgE repertoires in patients with allergic rhinitis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y.-C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Allergy Clin. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="604" to="612" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantifying selection in high-throughput immunoglobulin sequencing data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Yaari</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">134</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Models of somatic hypermutation targeting and substitution based on synonymous mutations from high-throughput immunoglobulin sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Yaari</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">358</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IgBLAST: an immunoglobulin variable domain sequence analysis tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Ye</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Web. Server Issue</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>