
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:54+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology ChemoPy: freely available python package for computational biology and chemoinformatics</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dong-Sheng</forename>
								<surname>Cao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Research Center of Modernization of Traditional Chinese Medicines</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Central South University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>410083</postCode>
									<settlement>Changsha</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P. R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Qing-Song</forename>
								<surname>Xu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mathematics and Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Central South University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>410083</postCode>
									<settlement>Changsha</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P. R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Qian-Nan</forename>
								<surname>Hu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Ministry of Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Combinatorial Biosynthesis and Drug Discovery (Wuhan University)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430071</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P. R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yi-Zeng</forename>
								<surname>Liang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Research Center of Modernization of Traditional Chinese Medicines</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Central South University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>410083</postCode>
									<settlement>Changsha</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P. R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology ChemoPy: freely available python package for computational biology and chemoinformatics</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1092" to="1094"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt105</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on November 27, 2012; revised on February 22, 2013; accepted on February 25, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Martin Bishop/p/pychem/downloads/list, and it runs on Linux and MS-Windows. Contact: yizeng_liang@263.net Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Molecular representation for small molecules has been routinely used in QSAR/SAR, virtual screening, database search, ranking , drug ADME/T prediction and other drug discovery processes. To facilitate extensive studies of drug molecules, we developed a freely available, open-source python package called chemoinformatics in python (ChemoPy) for calculating the commonly used structural and physicochemical features. It computes 16 drug feature groups composed of 19 descriptors that include 1135 descriptor values. In addition , it provides seven types of molecular fingerprint systems for drug molecules, including topological fingerprints, electro-topological state (E-state) fingerprints, MACCS keys, FP4 keys, atom pairs fingerprints, topological torsion fingerprints and Morgan/circular fingerprints. By applying a semi-empirical quantum chemistry program MOPAC, ChemoPy can also compute a large number of 3D molecular descrip-tors conveniently. Availability: The python package, ChemoPy, is freely available via</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Molecular features for small molecules have frequently been used in the development of machine learning in QSAR/QSPR, virtual screening, database search, similarity search, ranking, drug ADME/T prediction and other drug discovery processes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cao et al., 2010</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cao et al., , 2011</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Cao et al., , 2012a</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Dea-Ayuela et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Du et al., 2005</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Du et al., , 2008a</ref><ref type="bibr">Du et al., , b, 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Gola et al., 2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">, Gonzaíez-Dıáz et al., 2005</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Prado-Prado et al., 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">van de Waterbeemd et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wang et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wei et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Yan et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Zhu et al., 2011</ref>). These descriptors capture and magnify distinct aspects of molecular topology to investigate how molecular structure affects molecular property. Currently, these features were widely used to characterize ligand molecules in the protein–ligand network and predict new protein–ligand associations to identify potential drug targets (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Campillos et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cao et al., 2012a, b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Chou et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Izrailev et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Keiser et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Prado-Prado et al., 2011a, b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Vinã et al., 2009</ref>), following the spirit of chemogenomics. Several programs for computing molecular descriptors have been developed, such as MARCH-INSIDE, TOPS-MODE, TOMO-COMD, Dragon, CODESSA, Molconn-Z (http://www. edusoft-lc.com/molconn/), Chemistry Development Kit (CDK), Indigo (http://ggasoftware.com/opensource/indigo), JOELib, RDKit (http://www.rdkit.org/) and Avogadro (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Gonzaíez-Dıáz et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hanwell et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Katritzky et al., 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Marrero-Ponce et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Pe´rezPe´rez-Gonzaíez et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Steinbeck et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Todeschini et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Wegner, 2005</ref>). Unfortunately, some of these tools are not comprehensive, or are limited to only a certain kind of features. Additionally, some are not freely and easily accessible. We implemented a selection of sophisticated molecular features and provided them as a package for the free and open-source software environment python. The ChemoPy package aims at providing the user with comprehensive implementations of these descriptors in a unified framework to allow easy and transparent computation. To our knowledge, ChemoPy is the first opensource package computing a large number of molecular features based on the MOPAC optimization. We recommend ChemoPy to analyse and represent the drugs or ligand molecules under investigation. Further, we hope that the package will be helpful when exploring questions concerning drug activity, drug ADME/T and drug–target interactions in the context of computational biology. After accomplishing the previous goal, we expect that our/other groups may use the free code of ChemoPy and the new QSAR models to implement public web servers, such as MIND-BEST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Gonzaíez-Dıáz et al., 2011</ref>). The users can run predictions of libraries of compounds using SMILES codes as input.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">CHEMOPY FEATURES</head><p>The ChemoPy package contains several functions and modules manipulating drug molecules. To obtain molecular structures easily, ChemoPy provides a download module, by which the user could easily get molecular structures from four databases (i.e. KEGG, PubChem, DrugBank and CAS) by providing IDs.<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>(see also detailed descriptor list in Supplementary Material S1). There are two means to compute these molecular descriptors from small molecules. One is to use the built-in modules. There exist 19 modules responding to the calculation of descriptors from 16 feature groups. The instruction for each module is provided in the form of HTML in ChemoPy (see Supplementary Material S2). We could import related functions to compute these features. For example, the topology module includes a number of functionalities used for calculating various topological descriptors. The user could conveniently use them as need.The other is to call the PyChem2d or PyChem3d class by importing the pychem module, which encapsulates commonly used descriptor calculation methods. PyChem2d and PyChem3d are responsible for the calculation of 2D and 3D molecular descriptors, respectively. We could construct a PyChem2d or PyChem3d object with a molecule input and then call corresponding methods to calculate these features.4 4 4 All3D ¼ des2.GetAllDescriptor() In ChemoPy, molecular structures are optimized by the AM1 method in MOPAC. MOPAC input file is directly prepared by Pybel and OpenBabel. The detailed introductions for all descriptors are provided in the ChemoPy manual (see Supplementary Material S3). A user guide for the use of ChemoPy is included to guide how the user uses it to calculate the needed features (see Supplementary Material S4). ChemoPy is written by the pure python language. We chose to use python because it is open source, and there already exist packages to handle small molecules [e.g. Pybel (O'<ref type="bibr">Boyle et al., 2008b</ref>), PyMol and Cinfony (O'<ref type="bibr">Boyle et al., 2008a)]</ref>. It is convenient for ChemoPy to analyse drug molecules processed by Cinfony or RDKit. ChemoPy is available for two operating systems: Linux and Windows. ChemoPy depends on Pybel, RDKit, OpenBabel (O'<ref type="bibr">Boyle et al., 2011</ref>) and MOPAC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Stewart, 1990</ref>). Moreover, it needs the support of scientific library for python (SciPy).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">from pychem.pychem import PyChem2d, PyChem3d</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DISCUSSION</head><p>ChemoPy contains a selection of molecular descriptors to analyse, classify and compare complex molecular network. They facilitate to exploit machine-learning techniques to drive hypothesis from complex molecular datasets. The usefulness of these molecular descriptors covered by ChemoPy for representing structural features of small molecules has been sufficiently demonstrated by a number of published studies of the development of machine-learning classification systems. The ChemoPy implementation of each of these algorithms was extensively tested by using a number of test molecules. The computed descriptor values were compared with the known values for these molecules to ensure that our computation is accurate. Owing to the modular structure of ChemoPy, extensions or new functionalities can be implemented easily without complex and time-consuming alterations of the source code. In future work, we plan to apply the integrated features on various biological research questions, and extending the range of functions with new promising descriptors for the coming versions of ChemoPy.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>ChemoPy</head><figDesc>can compute a large number of 2D and 3D descriptors. A list of structural and physicochemical features covered by ChemoPy is summarized in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. List of ChemoPy computed features for small molecules</figDesc><table>Feature group 
Features 
Number of 
descriptors 

Constitution 
Constitutional descriptors a 
30 
Topology 
Topological descriptors a 
35 
Connectivity 
Connectivity indices a 
44 
E-state 
E-state descriptors 
245 
Kappa 
Kappa shape descriptors a 
7 
Basak 
Basak information indices 
21 
Burden 
Burden descriptors 
64 
Autocorrelation 
Moreau-Broto autocorrelation 
32 
Moran autocorrelation 
32 
Geary autocorrelation 
32 
Charge 
Charge descriptors 
25 
Property 
Molecular property a 
6 
MOE-type 
MOE-type descriptors b 
60 
Geometric 
Geometric descriptors 
12 
CPSA 
CPSA descriptors 
30 
RDF 
RDF descriptors 
180 
MoRSE 
MoRSE descriptors 
210 
WHIM 
WHIM descriptors 
70 
Fingerprints 
Topological fingerprints b 
2048 
MACCS keys b 
166 
FP4 keys c 
307 
E-state fingerprints b 
79 
Atom pairs fingerprints b 
— 
Topological torsions b 
— 
Morgan fingerprints b 
— 

a 

Some of these features are from RDKit. 

b 

These features are from RDKit. 

c 

These features are from OpenBabel. </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">ChemoPy at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">D.-S.Cao et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank three anonymous referees for their constructive comments, which greatly helped improve on the original version of the manuscript.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict</head><p>of Interest: none declared.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug target identification using side-effect similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Campillos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">321</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of aqueous solubility of druglike organic compounds using partial least squares, back-propagation network and support vector machine</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Cao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chemometr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="584" to="595" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In silico classification of human maximum recommended daily dose based on modified random forest and substructure fingerprint</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Cao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">692</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computer-aided prediction of toxicity with substructure pattern and random forest</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Cao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chemometr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale prediction of drug-target interactions using protein sequences and drug topological structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Cao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">752</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting networking couples for metabolic pathways of Arabidopsis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Chou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EXCLI J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HP-Lattice QSAR for dynein proteins: experimental proteomics (2D-electrophoresis, mass spectrometry) and theoretic study of a Leishmania infantum sequence</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Dea-Ayuela</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioorg. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7770" to="7776" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heuristic molecular lipophilicity potential (HMLP): a 2D-QSAR study to LADH of molecular family pyrazole and derivatives</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Du</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="461" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple field three dimensional quantitative structure-activity relationship (MF-3D-QSAR)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Du</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent advances in QSAR and their applications in predicting the activities of chemical molecules, peptides and proteins for drug design</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Du</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Protein Pept. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="259" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fragment-based quantitative structure-activity relationship (FB-QSAR) for fragment-based drug design</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Du</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="304" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ADMET property prediction: the state of the art and current challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Gola</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">QSAR Comb. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1172" to="1180" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting multiple drugs side effects with a general drug-target interaction thermodynamic Markov model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Gonzaíez-Dıáz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioorg. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1119" to="1129" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting antimicrobial drugs and targets with the MARCH-INSIDE approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Gonzaíez-Dıáz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Top. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1676" to="1690" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MIND-BEST: web server for drugs and target discovery; design, synthesis, and assay of MAO-B inhibitors and theoretical experimental study of G3PDH protein from Trichomonas gallinae</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Gonzaíez-Dıáz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1698" to="1718" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Avogadro: an advanced semantic chemical editor, visualization, and analysis platform</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hanwell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chemoinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enzyme classification by ligand binding</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Izrailev</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="711" to="724" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">CODESSA Comprehensive Descriptors for Structural and Statistical Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Katritzky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Reference. manual</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relating protein pharmacology by ligand chemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Keiser</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">TOMOCOMD software, version 1.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Marrero-Ponce</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cinfony—combining open source cheminformatics toolkits behind a common interface</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Boyle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Cent. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pybel: a Python wrapper for the OpenBabel cheminformatics toolkit</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Boyle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Cent. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open babel: an open chemical toolbox</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Boyle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cheminform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TOPS-MODE based QSARs derived from heterogeneous series of compounds. Applications to the design of new herbicides</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Pe´rezpe´rez-Gonzaíez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Comput. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1192" to="1199" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unified QSAR approach to antimicrobials Part 3: first multi-tasking QSAR model for input-coded prediction, structural back-projection, and complex networks clustering of antiprotozoal compounds</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Prado-Prado</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioorg. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5871" to="5880" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unified QSAR approach to antimicrobials. 4. Multi-target QSAR modeling and comparative multi-distance study of the giant components of antiviral drug-drug complex networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Prado-Prado</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioorg. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="569" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-target spectral moment QSAR versus ANN for antiparasitic drugs against different parasite species</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Prado-Prado</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioorg. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2225" to="2231" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using entropy of drug and protein graphs to predict FDA drug-target network: theoretical-experimental study of MAO inhibitors and hemoglobin peptides from Fasciola hepatica</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Prado-Prado</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1074" to="1094" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2D MI-DRAGON: a new predictor for protein-ligands interactions and theoretic-experimental studies of US FDA drug-target network, oxoisoaporphine inhibitors for MAO-A and human parasite proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Prado-Prado</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5838" to="5851" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The chemistry development kit (CDK): an open-source java library for chemo-and bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Steinbeck</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Comput. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="493" to="500" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MOPAC: a semiempirical molecular orbital program</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Stewart</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Aided Mol. Des</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Molecular Descriptors for Chemoinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Todeschini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<publisher>Wiley-VCH GmbH &amp; Co</publisher>
			<pubPlace>KGaA, Weinheim</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ADMET in silico modelling: towards prediction paradise?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Van De Waterbeemd</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Drug Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="192" to="204" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alingment-free prediction of a drug-target complex network based on parameters of drug connectivity and protein sequence of receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Vinã</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Pharm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="825" to="835" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent advances on aqueous solubility prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comb. Chem. High Throughput Screen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="328" to="338" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">JOELib: Graph/Data Mining and Clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Wegner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>ACS Meeting</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigation into adamantane-based M2 inhibitors with FB-QSAR</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Wei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="317" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of quantitative structure-retention relationship models on four stationary phases with different polarity for a diverse set of flavor compounds</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Yan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chromatogr. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1223" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent developments of in silico predictions of oral bioavailability</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Zhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comb. Chem. High Throughput Screen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="362" to="374" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>