
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:43+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Chimira: analysis of small RNA sequencing data and microRNA modifications</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dimitrios</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Vitsios</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">European Molecular Biology Laboratory—European Bioinformatics Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1SD</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anton</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Enright</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">European Molecular Biology Laboratory—European Bioinformatics Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1SD</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Chimira: analysis of small RNA sequencing data and microRNA modifications</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv380</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 13, 2015; revised on June 12, 2015; accepted on June 16, 2015</note>
					<note>Sequence analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Ivo Hofacker Contact: aje@ebi.ac.uk Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Chimira is a web-based system for microRNA (miRNA) analysis from small RNA-Seq data. Sequences are automatically cleaned, trimmed, size selected and mapped directly to miRNA hairpin sequences. This generates count-based miRNA expression data for subsequent statistical analysis. Moreover, it is capable of identifying epi-transcriptomic modifications in the input sequences. Supported modification types include multiple types of 3 0-modifications (e.g. uridylation, adenylation), 5 0-modifications and also internal modifications or variation (ADAR editing or single nucleotide polymorphisms). Besides cleaning and mapping of input sequences to miRNAs, Chimira provides a simple and intuitive set of tools for the analysis and interpretation of the results (see also Supplementary Material). These allow the visual study of the differential expression between two specific samples or sets of samples, the identification of the most highly expressed miRNAs within sample pairs (or sets of samples) and also the projection of the modification profile for specific miRNAs across all samples. Other tools have already been published in the past for various types of small RNA-Seq analysis, such as UEA workbench, seqBuster, MAGI, OASIS and CAP-miRSeq, CPSS for modifications identification. A comprehensive comparison of Chimira with each of these tools is provided in the Supplementary Material. Chimira outperforms all of these tools in total execution speed and aims to facilitate simple, fast and reliable analysis of small RNA-Seq data allowing also, for the first time, identification of global microRNA modification profiles in a simple intuitive interface. Availability and implementation: Chimira has been developed as a web application and it is accessible here: http://www.ebi.ac.uk/research/enright/software/chimira.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Small RNA sequencing data are among the most straightforward types of NGS data to analyse. However many laboratories that generate such data still struggle to develop or adapt computational pipelines for the analysis and interpretation of these data. Additionally, in recent years, it has been reported that many miRNAs go through post-transcriptional alterations that modify their 3 0 end, mainly via mono/poly-Uridylation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Heo et al., 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Heo et al., , 2012</ref>) or polyAdenylation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Shanfa et al., 2009</ref>). Such modifications are believed to impart significant functional changes to the miRNA. Indeed, other modifications and/or editing have also been observed to occur in several other instances (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Burroughs et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sung-Chou et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Yu and Chen, 2010</ref>). Hence, it is imperative to explore the full profile of all modifications and/or edits that can be identified in small RNA-Seq data. The functional roles of small RNAs in different conditions may be greatly influenced by such modifications. This can be accomplished by aligning small RNA sequences against their hairpin precursors. The alignment region spanning each V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3365</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited., 5 0 and internal miRNA modifications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bioinformatics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Input</head><p>Chimira accepts FASTQ/FASTA files as input, containing adapter and/or barcode stripped small RNA-Seq data. The user is provided with a simple system for uploading each sample and replicate and selecting among the available run options. Additionally, Chimira provides a limited 3 0 adapter cleaning functionality using reaper (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Davis et al., 2013</ref>) supporting different adapters for each input sample. Finally, the system provides a simple interface for computationally determining likely 3 0 sequencing adapters in case the user does not have this information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Usage notes</head><p>In its current release (v1.0), Chimira supports mapping of small RNA-Seq data against 209 genomes registered in miRBase (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Griffiths-Jones et al., 2008</ref>). In order to optimize and speed-up the analysis, tally (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Davis et al., 2013</ref>) is being used for de-duplicating the sequence fragments. Tally dramatically reduces the size of input sequence files by collapsing identical sequences into a single one while storing the total read depth. When input sequence files are uploaded and the appropriate genome is selected, the user is able to launch a new queued job. Every job is submitted to a highperformance computing cluster and the user can follow its progress via an analysis console. Notification via e-mail upon completion of each job is also available, provided the user has supplied a valid e-mail address before launching the job.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Methods</head><p>Two types of miRNAs identification are provided: Plain Counts and Modifications. Plain Counts refers to the quantification of the miRNA molecules that are expressed in any form (template or modified) in each of the input samples. The input sequences are mapped against miRBase using BLASTn (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Boratyn et al., 2013</ref>) allowing up to two mismatches for each sequence. BLASTn output is filtered so that antisense matches are discarded. The extracted counts are normalized across all samples using DESeq2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Love et al., 2014</ref>) and basic QC plots are provided together with plots for the total counts per sample and the top-10 miRNAs expression levels across all samples. In cases where a small RNA sequence identically matches more than one precursor sequences (i.e. miRNA paralogues) the user can choose between calling only the first optimal alignment hit or assigning counts fractionally with equal weights between the paralogues. Apart from the quantification of miRNA counts and the prevalence of modifications, Chimira integrates basic functionality for comparative analysis of input samples. Specifically, differential expression (of plain counts) between two samples or sets of samples can be visualized through an interactive scatterplot that allows the user to view the miRNA identifier and the different expression levels at each point of the plot (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). Moreover, the user can display the 10, 20 or 50 most highly expressed miRNAs in two samples (or sets of samples) side by side. Secondly, 'modifications' refers to the quantification of any sequence segments that are part of the input sequences and cannot be explained by genomic sequence. In the example shown (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>), uridylation and adenylation are the most prevalent modification types in the 1 nt after the 3 0 end of the miRNAs, while C modifications are highly enriched exactly at the 3 0 end. ADAR editing is the predominant modification type in the internal modifications followed by a moderately expressed C-SNP, 11 nt upstream of the 3 0 end (index position: 11). The types of modifications being identified include: @BULLET 3 0-modifications: any non-templated sequences in a window that starts at the 5th nt upstream of the 3 0 end of each miRNA and ends at the 6th nt downstream of the 3 0 end. @BULLET 5 0-modifications: any non-templated sequences in a window that starts at the 8th nt upstream of the 5 0 end of each miRNA and ends at the 5th nt downstream of the the 5 0 end. @BULLET Internal modifications: SNPs and ADAR edits. In order for a modification to be classified as a SNP, an arbitrary 70% value is used as a threshold for the ratio of the modified counts to the overall counts. It is worth noting that the window lengths being used for identification of 3 0 and 5 0 modifications include nucleotide positions also within the original miRNA sequence to better distinguish all possible modifications from multiple miRNA variants originating from the same precursor but with different length mature products. Modification types are inferred from BLAST alignments of input sequences to their hairpin precursors and then examining the content of alignment mismatches returned. In order to decipher the correct modification position a reference database has been built initially for all supported genomes, containing canonical alignments between mature miRNAs and their hairpin precursors. Based on these data each of the identified modification patterns is assigned a position index (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>) in order to build the full depth-wise modification profile. Chimira also allows the display of the modification profiles across all samples for a specific miRNA, defined byon the x-axis is at index '0' (5 0 end) while its end is at index '22' (3 0 end) the user. Finally, all counts (plain and modifications) can be downloaded for further analysis as separate files as soon as the processing of a set of samples is complete.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusion</head><p>Chimira has been specifically developed for fast analysis of simple small RNA datasets with a user-friendly interface. It complements our previous pipeline sequenceImp, which was designed for command-line level analysis of larger-scale experiments with complex designs. Chimira is a fast and robust system for the cleaning, filtering, QC and mapping of small RNA-Seq data aiming to simplify the process of small RNA NGS analysis to a straightforward online workflow. Additionally, it allows the extraction of global modification profiles across and within each of the input samples thus allowing the inference of correlations between certain modification patterns and any conditions indicated by the input samples. We hope the system will prove useful to the small RNA community. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Modification profile from 12 Heart, Liver and Brain tissue samples in H. sapiens, as detected by Chimira: (a) Global profile (b) 3 0-Modifications (c) 5 0Modifications (d) Internal modifications (ADAR edits and SNPs) (e) Internal modifications (SNPs). The x-axis corresponds to the index positions across a miRNA molecule. They y-axis corresponds to the raw counts of the identified modification patterns. The start of a miRNA on the x-axis is at index '0' (5 0 end) while its end is at index '22' (3 0 end)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>, 31(20), 2015, 3365–3367 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv380</figDesc><table>Advance Access Publication Date: 20 June 2015 
Applications Note miRNA is analysed to detect bases in the miRNA sequence that 
could not possibly have derived from the precursor it aligns to. 
These unalignable nucleotides are likely either: (i) base-calling 
errors, (ii) single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), (iii) ADAR edits 
or (iv) post-transcriptional miRNA modifications (e.g. via 
TUTases). Base-calling errors are pseudo-random depending on the 
platform used and usually more likely to occur towards the 3 0 end of 
sequences. In order to study this diverse pool of possible miRNA 
post-transcriptional modifications, we have developed Chimira. 
This is a cohesive platform for the processing and analysis of small 
RNA NGS data allowing simultaneous detection of 3 0 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">D.M.Vitsios and A.J.Enright at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BLAST: a more efficient report with usability improvements</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Boratyn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comprehensive survey of 3 0 animal miRNA modification events and a possible role for 3 0 adenylation in modulating miRNA targeting effectiveness</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Burroughs</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1398" to="1410" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kraken: a set of tools for quality control and analysis of high-throughput sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Davis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">mirbase: tools for microrna genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TUT4 in concert with Lin28 suppresses microRNA biogenesis through pre-microRNA uridylation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Heo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="696" to="708" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mono-uridylation of pre-microRNA as a key step in the biogenesis of group II let-7 microRNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Heo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">151</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="532" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Love</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">550</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adenylation of plant miRNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Shanfa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1878" to="1885" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MicroRNA 3&apos; end nucleotide modification patterns and arm selection preference in liver tissues</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of miRNA modifications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Yu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">592</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Analysis of small RNA sequencing data and microRNA modifications</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>