
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:50+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression cisASE: a likelihood-based method for detecting putative cis-regulated allele-specific expression in RNA sequencing data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zhi</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">CAS-MPG Partner Institute for Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200031</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Tuantuan</forename>
								<surname>Gui</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">CAS-MPG Partner Institute for Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200031</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zhen</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">CAS-MPG Partner Institute for Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200031</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hong</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yunhe</forename>
								<surname>Fu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">CAS-MPG Partner Institute for Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200031</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Biochemistry and Cell Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Systems Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200031</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xiao</forename>
								<surname>Dong</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Albert Einstein College of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10461</postCode>
									<settlement>Bronx</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yixue</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">CAS-MPG Partner Institute for Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200031</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">School of Life Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Shanghai Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200240</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Shanghai Center for Bioinformation Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Shanghai Industrial Technology Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>201203</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Collaborative Innovation Center for Genetics and Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fudan University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200438</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression cisASE: a likelihood-based method for detecting putative cis-regulated allele-specific expression in RNA sequencing data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw416</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 27, 2015; revised on May 16, 2016; accepted on June 24, 2016</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Ziv Bar-Joseph Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Allele-specific expression (ASE) is a useful way to identify cis-acting regulatory variation , which provides opportunities to develop new therapeutic strategies that activate beneficial alleles or silence mutated alleles at specific loci. However, multiple problems hinder the identification of ASE in next-generation sequencing (NGS) data. Results: We developed cisASE, a likelihood-based method for detecting ASE on single nucleotide variant (SNV), exon and gene levels from sequencing data without requiring phasing or parental information. cisASE uses matched DNA-seq data to control technical bias and copy number variation (CNV) in putative cis-regulated ASE identification. Compared with state-of-the-art methods, cisASE exhibits significantly increased accuracy and speed. cisASE works moderately well for datasets without DNA-seq and thus is widely applicable. By applying cisASE to real datasets, we identified specific ASE characteristics in normal and cancer tissues, thus indicating that cisASE has potential for wide applications in cancer genomics. Availability and Implementation: cisASE is freely available at http://Iifecenter.sgst.cn/cisASE.Contact:
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Allele-specific gene expression (ASE) refers to the differential expression of two alleles in a diploid genome. ASE is primarily a result of the associated cis-element variation and allele-specific epigenetic modifications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Pastinen, 2010</ref>). Germline ASEs are usually associated with the existence of regulatory elements, which exert a pronounced effect on human phenotypic polymorphism and common diseases. Somatic ASEs (ASEs of somatic mutations) in tumors are often genetically linked to tumor drivers. Thus, ASE studies provide an opportunity for the development of new therapeutic strategies that activate beneficial alleles or silence mutated alleles at specific loci (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Huang et al., 2012</ref>). Next-generation sequencing (NGS) allows for the genome-wide identification of ASE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Heap et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Lee et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Smith, 2013</ref>); however, several problems exist. The first problem is technical and intrinsic allele bias, which we and others have previously demonstrated (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Degner et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Liu et al., 2014</ref>). For example, reads carrying single nucleotide variants (SNVs) are less likely to be correctly mapped than those carrying reference genotype (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Degner et al., 2009</ref>). Another example is that, a large proportion of previously identified ASEs, especially in tumor samples, have been found a result of copy number variations (CNVs) rather than cis-regulation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Tuch et al., 2010</ref>). The second problem is that gene-level ASE detection usually requires phased-SNVs or parental genomes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Montgomery et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Rozowsky et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Skelly et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Zhang et al., 2009</ref>), which are usually not available. Although methods to phase singlenucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) into individual haplotypes exist (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Browning and Browning, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Howie et al., 2009</ref>), these methods cannot be applied to somatic mutations in tumors. The third problem relates to testing ASE with statistical confidence. Two simple statistical methods, i.e. binomial and chi-square tests, have been frequently used in SNV-level ASE detection (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Ge et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Heap et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Zhang et al., 2009</ref>); however, these methods do not make full use of the information of these complex sequencing datasets. Although several tools have been developed for ASE detection, none has addressed all of these concerns (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Mayba et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Pandey et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Rozowsky et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Skelly et al., 2011</ref>). To overcome the problems outlined above, we proposed a new computational method and developed a software tool, cisASE, based on a likelihood ratio test. cisASE uses DNA-seq data to make site-by-site adjustments for RNA allele imbalance assessment to reduce the effects of technical bias and CNV, and reports ASE putatively caused by cis-regulation. cisASE also considers the base quality of each base to reduce the influence of sequencing error. We tested cisASE on both simulated and real datasets, and compared it with other methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Mayba et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Skelly et al., 2011</ref>). cisASE exhibits significantly improved accuracy and computational speed compared with existing methods. We applied cisASE to public colon tumor datasets, and observed several important features, i.e. germline ASE hotspots of human leukocyte antigen (HLA) loci, cancer somatic ASE genes in focal adhesion and extracellular matrix (ECM)–receptor interaction pathways. These findings revealed a landscape of germline and somatic ASE in colon tumors and highlighted broad applications of our cisASE method in ASE detection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Materials and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Simulated data</head><p>We selected normal tissue data (n ¼ 46) of a human colon dataset (n ¼ 92) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Seshagiri et al., 2012</ref>) as the basis for generating a simulated dataset (Supplementary Material) because this dataset contains high-quality matched DNA-seq and RNA-seq data with high sequencing depth. The dataset was also used to test our method (described in the following sections). First, fold changes of adjusted RNA allele counts of the real data were calculated using the following equation,</p><formula>fc ¼ X n i¼1 RNAref = X n i¼1 RNAalt i X n i¼1 DNAref = X n i¼1 DNAalt i (1)</formula><p>where n is the number of SNVs for a specific feature (SNV, exon or gene). The distributions of log2 fc and log2 DNA depth were then modeled using Laplace (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>) and normal distributions, respectively. For each simulated SNV, its DNA sequencing depth was drawn from the normal distribution, and its RNA sequencing depth was sampled from the real data. Both DNA and RNA reference allele counts were assumed to exhibit a binomial distributionr $ Bðn; pÞ, where n is the sequencing depth of DNA-seq or RNA-seq, and p is the frequency of reference allele. To simulate data without CNV (non-CNV data), DNA reference allele counts were subjected to a binomial distribution with parameter p estimated from real DNA-seq data. To mimic the proportion of ASEs in real data, we sampled fc for each SNV from the above Laplace distribution. When the sampled fc exceeded a certain cutoff (1.5, 2, 3, 4 or 5), we generated a true positive ASE SNV, whose RNA reference allele count was subject to a binomial distribution with parameter p determined as the fraction of DNA reference allele after adjustment by the sampled fc (illustrated in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S2</ref>). Otherwise, we generated a true negative site with the parameter p of the binomial distribution setting as its DNA reference allele fraction. We simulated 1000 genes for each fc cutoff, and the number of SNVs in each gene was also sampled from the real data. To simulate data carrying CNV (CNV data), DNA reference allele count of each SNV was assumed to have a binomial distribution, with a DNA ratio of reference (R) and alternative (A) alleles n(R):n(A)¼2, 3 or 4, for DNA copy numbers of 2, 3 and 4, respectively. Next, to assess the performance of cisASE at different sequencing depths, we simulated another non-CNV dataset with fixed depth (10–20, 20–30, 30–40 and 40–50) and fixed number of SNVs per gene (1, 2, 3, 4 or 5), resulting in datasets with 125 strata (Supplementary Material).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Real sequencing datasets</head><p>We collected three real sequencing datasets to test cisASE. First, we obtained RNA and Exon sequencing data of 46 pairs of matched human colon tumor-normal samples from the European Genome-Phenome Archive (EGA) under accession number EGAS00001000288 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Seshagiri et al., 2012</ref>). Second, RNA-seq and DNA-seq data for a well-studied individual NA12878 were obtained from the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) under accession number GSE30401 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Rozowsky et al., 2011</ref>) and the ENA with accession number ERR194147, respectively. The phased genomic variants of individual NA12878 in hg19 coordinates were obtained from Rozowsky et al. (2011). Additionally, a mouse dataset including exon and RNA sequencing data was downloaded from the European Nucleotide Archive (ENA) under accession numbers PRJEB5321 and PRJEB5320, respectively (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Castle et al., 2014</ref>). DNA-seq and RNA-seq reads were mapped to the reference genome using bowtie2, and all duplicated reads were removed to avoid the effects of polymerase chain reaction (PCR) duplication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Methods</head><p>The allele ratios of reference and alternative alleles in normal samples deviate from expected value (1:1) (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. S3</ref>) because of technical bias in strand capture, sequencing process and mapping. Additionally, in cancer samples, because of somatic structure variations, e.g. CNV, the bias is more severe (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. S3</ref>). To detect putative cis-regulated ASE regardless of bias and CNV, we use DNA-seq data for site-by-site adjustment based on the assumption of<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Zhang et al. (2009)</ref>that technical bias in the measurement of the allele ratio for DNA is the same for RNA. cisASE pipeline is illustrated in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>, including following steps:</p><p>(1) pileup files are generated from DNA-seq and RNA-seq data (mapped bam files after duplication removal) using samtools (Supplementary Material) (<ref type="bibr">Li et al., 2009). (2)</ref>The pileup files are submitted to cisASE, and log-likelihood ratio score (LLR) for each feature (SNV, exon or gene) is calculated. (3) For each input sample, the null distribution of LLRs is simulated from the input itself, and the LLR cutoffs corresponding to alpha levels of 0.05 and 0.01 are determined from the null distribution. (4) The LLRs are compared with a cutoff at a specific alpha level to determine whether the features are ASEs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1">Model for SNV-level LLR calculation</head><p>We take standard pileup files as input and calculate the probability of observing base b i on read i (i ¼ 1.. .d, where d is the coverage of base b i ) at each SNV following<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cibulskis et al. (2013)</ref>,</p><formula>Pðb i jf ; e i ; r; aÞ ¼ f : e i 3 þ ð1 À f Þð1 À e i Þ if b i ¼ r f ð1 À e i Þ þ ð1 À f Þ: e i 3 if b i ¼ a e i 3 otherwise 8 &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; :</formula><formula>(2)</formula><p>where r and a refer to the reference and alternative allele respectively. f refers to the fraction of the alternative allele. e i is the probability of errors in that base call (each base has an associated Phred-like quality score, q i , where e i ¼ 10 Àq i =10 ). We assume that the sequencing errors are independent for each read and that substitution errors are uniformly distributed and occur with probability e i /3. To assess allelic imbalance, we explain the observations with the following two hypotheses,</p><formula>H 0 : f ¼ DNAalt=ðDNAref þ DNAaltÞ H 1 : f ¼ RNAalt=ðRNAref þ RNAaltÞ (3)</formula><p>where DNAref/alt and RNAref/alt represent the allele read counts of the reference and alternative alleles in the DNA and RNA sequencing data, respectively. ASE detection is performed by comparing the likelihoods of two hypotheses. When the LLR, as defined below, exceeds a decision threshold, we identify the SNV as an ASE.2.3.2 Model for gene/exon-level LLR calculation For genes harboring n informative heterozygous SNVs, the hypotheses are modified as follows,</p><formula>H 0 : f ¼ X n i¼1 DNAhap2 X n i¼1 ðDNAhap1 þ DNAhap2Þ ; H 1 : f ¼ X n i¼1 RNAhap2 X n i¼1 ðRNAhap1 þ RNAhap2Þ</formula><formula>(5)</formula><p>where DNAhap1/2 and RNAhap1/2 represent the allele counts of the haplotype 1/2 allele. We implemented the pseudo-phasing process applied by<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Mayba et al. (2014)</ref>in cisASE. This process estimates the major and minor haplotypes by assigning SNV-level alleles with higher RNA read counts to the 'major' haplotype (hap1) and those with lower RNA read counts to the 'minor' haplotype (hap2). This process is applied to both gene-level and exon-level ASE detection when no phasing information is provided. Alternatively, users can provide their own phasing information to cisASE. One problem in gene-level ASE detection is that alternative splicing can affect the ASE identification when skip efficiency differs between two haplotypes. cisASE can accept annotation files containing labels for constitutive exons (parameter – C1) and considers only SNVs within constitutive exons when measuring gene-level ASE. A chi-square test is applied to check the consistency of the allele ratios for all SNVs within a gene. For multi-SNV genes, a small P-value from the chi-square test indicates that individual SNVs differ significantly in their allelic ratios. This inconsistency can arise because of differences in ASE between various transcript isoforms of a gene or counting errors for SNVs prone to technical bias. Candidate ASE genes with this inconsistency (e.g. P-value of the chi-square test &lt;0.05) should be filtered out by users.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3">Generating a null distribution</head><p>To determine a decision threshold to reject the null hypothesis, we perform the following simulation to calculate the threshold for a specific significance level a. For each input dataset, we simulate paired DNA and RNA data from the dataset itself. The simulated DNA and RNA sequencing depths are randomly sampled from the input. Read counts of both the simulated DNA and RNA reference alleles are assumed to follow a binomial distributionr $ Bðn; pÞ, where p is the average DNA or RNA reference allele frequency of the input. Base qualities and the number of SNVs in each feature (i.e. SNV, exon or gene) are also sampled from the input, and sequencing errors (0.001 errors per base) are added to the simulated reads. The LLR of each simulated feature is calculated according to Equation (4).<ref type="figure">1</ref>. Overview of cisASE algorithm. Mapped RNA-seq and DNA-seq data are piled up using samtools. LLR of the null and alternative models is calculated for each feature, i.e. SNV, exon or gene. Simulated DNA and RNA allele counts are generated from the data to produce a null distribution of the LLR, which is used to define an LLR cutoff with respect to a particular significance level. The LLR of each measured feature is compared to the LLR cutoff to determine whether it is an ASE</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Applications of cisASE in RNA sequencing data</head><p>By repeating the simulation S times, we estimate a null distribution of the LLR and determine a cutoff corresponding to significance level a according to Equation (6),</p><formula>PðKðXÞ gjH 0 Þ ¼ a (6)</formula><p>The default simulation repeat time S is set to 2000, which is reasonable for obtaining a robust cutoff (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. S4</ref>; discussed in the Supplementary Material), and the LLR cutoffs at alpha levels of 0.05 and 0.01 are provided.cisASE can also be applied to datasets without parallel DNA-seq data. In this situation, the preexisting DNA bias can be set by users; otherwise, the pre-existing DNA bias is assumed to be the same as the mean of the RNA bias. In addition, when simulation is disabled by users, we recommend SNV-level LLR cutoffs of 0.85 and 1.47 and gene-level LLR cutoffs of 0.82 and 1.50 for alpha levels of 0.05 and 0.01, respectively, based on a simulation of 92 sets of high-quality sequencing data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Seshagiri et al., 2012</ref>). To test the robustness of the recommended LLR cutoff, we applied it to Seshagiri's data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Seshagiri et al., 2012</ref>) and NA12878, and used the recommended LLR and the LLR calculated from the dataset itself as the cutoff to define ASE genes. This process revealed 4.2 and 2.3% differences in the Seshagiri's data and NA12878, respectively (see the Supplementary Material for details), indicating that, with the recommended LLR, cisASE has acceptable performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.4">Implementation of the chi-square test</head><p>We also implemented chi-square test, a widely used test that uses count information of both DNA and RNA for ASE identification (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Heap et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Zhang et al., 2009</ref>), in cisASE. We adjust the DNA and RNA counts for the chi-square test using base qualities. The adjusted counts for each base is defined as 1 À e i , where e i is the error rate of base i. In the absence of DNA input, we simulate the DNA reference and alternative allele counts for each SNV from the RNA sequencing depth and assume a DNA bias as mentioned in the Section 2.3.3. The allelic counts are summed for each haplotype for multi-SNV genes and exons for testing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Method evaluation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Evaluation in simulated data</head><p>To evaluate the effectiveness of taking DNA-seq data as a reference for reducing bias, we ran cisASE with the following four settings, using simulated non-CNV data and compared the performance (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>): A. cisASE default (adopt site-by-site bias adjustment with DNAseq data); B. set no DNA bias; C. set DNA bias as the mean reference allele fraction of all SNVs in the DNA-seq data; and D. set DNA bias as the mean reference allele fraction of all SNVs in the RNA-seq data. The highest performance was achieved when using setting A. The performances of cisASE with settings B and C were similar (overlapping in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>) and inferior to that obtained with setting A. These results suggest that bias is a local event and global adjustment does not perform better than no adjustment. The performance was worst when we estimated DNA bias from RNA-seq data (setting D). Because of overdispersion (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Skelly et al., 2011</ref>) and uneven sequencing depth of RNA-seq data, allele bias in a small percentage of highly expressed transcripts may shift the mean bias away from 0.5, resulting in higher false positive and false negative rates. Therefore, we recommend running cisASE with setting B, in which the DNA reference allele fraction is set to the expected value (0.5), for experiments without matched DNA-seq data. Of note, in this case, users cannot distinguish between cis-regulated ASE and CNV-resulted ASE. We compared cisASE with MBASED (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Mayba et al., 2014</ref>), which, to the best of our knowledge, is the only currently published ASE-detection method that allows for gene-level ASE detection without phasing information (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S2</ref>). We applied MBASED to our simulated data with its default settings. For simulated CNV data, cisASE substantially outperformed MBASED (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 3a</ref>). As illustrated in the table in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3a</ref>, when a SNV is located in a CNV region with a DNA ratio of 3:1 and its RNA allele ratio is 1:1, MBASED produced a false negative result, whereas for an RNA allele ratio of 3:1, MBASED produced a false positive result. cisASE also performed better with simulated non-CNV data (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 3b</ref>). Additionally, the computational speed of cisASE was faster than that of MBASED. On average, for a sample with 3500 SNVs, the running time for MBASED was 460 min, and cisASE was seven times faster, i.e. 68 min. Next, we compared our method with the chi-square test. The results showed that, although the two methods exhibited comparable specificity, the sensitivity of cisASE was much higher than that of the chi-square test (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S5</ref>). We also measured the accuracy of the chi-square test relative to that of cisASE. cisASE outperformed the chi-square test in each stratum of the simulated data, especially when the fold change threshold of the simulated data was low (fc ¼ 1.5), indicating its superior performance in detecting mildly biased ASE and ASE at low sequencing depth (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 4</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Evaluation in real data</head><p>We assessed the performance of cisASE in paired human colon tumor-normal samples (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Seshagiri et al., 2012</ref>). We randomly selected 16 of the 46 pairs of paired data to compare the methodsbecause some of the methods have speed limitations. Ideally, without technical and assessment bias, we would expect a balanced proportion of ASE SNVs over-expressing reference allele and alternative allele (0.5 versus 0.5). For ASE SNVs identified in the data, the proportion of ASEs over-expressing reference alleles was 0.50 when using cisASE and 0.67 when using MBASED (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Mayba et al., 2014</ref>) (<ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>). We also compared the performance of cisASE with and without DNA-seq data as an input for bias adjustment (<ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>). These results indicate that cisASE efficiently decreased the false positive results caused by pre-existing bias, especially bias toward the reference allele. Next, we applied cisASE to a mouse colon carcinoma cell line (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Castle et al., 2014</ref>). We identified 43 ASE SNVs with cisASE, covering all 31 SNVs identified by chi-square test at the same significance level (P-value ¼ 0.01). As demonstrated in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S5</ref>, for the SNV-level ASE detection, even for the most biased SNVs (fc ¼ 5), sensitivity of the chi-square test was not as high as that of cisASE until the sequencing depth increased to 40. Of the 12 ASE SNVs only detected by cisASE, 10 had sequencing depths less than 40 for DNA or RNA, and one had a sequencing depth less than 60. The remaining one had a chi-square P-value that fell slightly short of the chosen cutoff of 0.01 (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S3</ref>). These results were consistent with our conclusions based on the simulated data, suggesting that cisASE has higher sensitivity, especially in cases of low sequencing coverage. We further applied cisASE to a high-quality phased individual, NA12878, from the 1000 Genomes Project. First, we assessed the performance of cisASE with and without known phasing information. RNA and DNA sequencing data were pre-processed analogously to our previous dataset (Supplementary Material). Overall 2295 genes were tested, including 963 (42%) with &gt;1 heterozygous locus. In total, 274 and 291 genes (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S4</ref>) were classified as ASE genes at a significance level of 0.05 with and without the known haplotype as input, respectively. Among these genes, 273 were shared. Similar to previous reports (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Mayba et al., 2014</ref>), pseudo-phasing had a high recovery rate of the true haplotype, and 98.0% (950/963) of the multi-SNV genes were correctly classified by cisASE when no phasing information was supplied. These results indicated that cisASE is an accurate method, even without phasing information. We then compared cisASE with MBASED(<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Mayba et al., 2014</ref>) and Skelly's method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Skelly et al., 2011</ref>) (see the Supplementary Material for details). Skelly's method requires known haplotype data as input and incorporates DNA-seq information as the overall adjustment for bias. In this comparison, haplotypes were supplied to all three methods. A total of 274 (significance level ¼ 0.05, adjusted MAF ! 0.7), 114 (P 0.05, MAF ! 0.7) and 137 [posterior P(ASE) &gt;0.95, posterior median MAF ! 0.7] ASE genes were detected by cisASE, MBASED and Skelly's method, respectively (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S5</ref>). cisASE identified 85% ASE genes reported<ref type="figure">5</ref>. Distribution of the percentage of ASE overexpressing reference alleles in a real dataset. For each cancer (N ¼ 16) and normal sample (N ¼ 16), we calculated the percentage of ASE specific to the reference allele (ASE with overexpressed reference allele)Applications of cisASE in RNA sequencing databy MBASED and 64% of those identified by Skelly's method but was more sensitive (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 6</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. S6</ref>). Additionally, cisASE required much less computation time, i.e. 90 min compared to 360 min for Skelly's method and 660 min for MBASED.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Recurrent germline ASE and ASE hotspots in normal and tumor samples</head><p>In the human colon dataset, we found that most ASE SNVs are sample-specific (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. S7</ref>). Low-frequency ASEs in the population randomly distribute across chromosomes. However, some hotspots exist (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S8</ref>and<ref type="figure">Table S6</ref>), e.g. HLA regions (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S7</ref>). MHC loci are some of the most genetically variable coding loci in mammals, including humans (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Parham and Ohta, 1996</ref>). In normal tissues, polymorphisms in the HLA loci have been found to be associated with a large number of human phenotypic traits and common diseases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Shiina et al., 2009</ref>). In tumors, HLA is frequently altered in comparison to the tissue from which it originates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Yip et al., 2000</ref>). Our identification of ASE hotspots in HLA loci indicated that the HLA loci are enriched with regulatory polymorphisms, which contribute to phenotypic polymorphism and disease in humans.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Highly overexpressed somatic mutant alleles in tumor samples</head><p>Somatic ASEs, which are caused by linked somatic events in the regulatory regions of genes or the somatic mutation itself, may contribute to tumor progression. Because of the high genetic heterogeneity of tumors, matched DNA-seq data are required to identify somatic ASEs with high accuracy. We observed that 75% of the somatic ASEs overexpressed their mutant alleles. The significantly up-regulated expression level of the mutant alleles (Fisher exact test P-value &lt; 2.2e-16, odds ratio ¼ 2.99) suggests the existence of widespread selective pressure to produce more mutant proteins in tumors. Of the 25% somatic ASEs, which underexpressed their mutant alleles, 73% lost the mutant allele expression completely. This is possibly because potential tumor suppressors are involved in suppressing the expression of these somatic mutations. By mapping somatic mutations to genes, we found that genes with underexpressed mutant alleles are significantly enriched in focal adhesion and ECM-receptor interaction pathways (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S8</ref>). Abnormal behaviors of these two pathways have been reported to play important roles in cancer progression in many cancer types (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Lu et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Nagano et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Stewart et al., 2004</ref>), including colon cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Lascorz et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Peng et al., 2015</ref>). Our ASE study reveals detailed information about how somatic mutations in these genes affect gene expression and identifies possible therapeutic targets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Discussion</head><p>In this work, we present a novel flexible computational method, cisASE, to detect ASE at the SNV, exon and gene levels. cisASE makes full use of information from DNA-seq and RNA-seq data to achieve an unbiased estimation of ASE. By default, cisASE adopts a site-by-site adjustment for ASE identification by using the DNA allele ratio. This procedure reduces the artifacts from technical and mapping bias (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Degner et al., 2009</ref>) and CNVs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Mayba et al., 2014</ref>), making cisASE efficient for detecting putative cis-regulated ASEs. In the absence of matched DNA-seq data, cisASE performed moderately well. Additionally, the implementation of a pseudo-phasing function in cisASE allows the incorporation of unphased SNV data into an individual exon, gene or isoform. To evaluate the performance of cisASE for ASE detection, we performed extensive analyses based on both simulated and real data from multiple resources, i.e. human and mouse colon tumor celllines and a phased 1000 Genomes Project individual. cisASE outperformed the chi-square test in terms of accuracy, especially for genes with low sequencing depth. Additionally, cisASE exhibits greatly increased accuracy and computation speed compared with other previous methods based on complex models. By applying cisASE to a panel of paired tumor-normal human colon samples, we identified HLA loci as the most significant 'hotspot' of germline ASEs in both tumor and normal samples. In tumor samples, somatic ASE showed widespread overexpression of mutant alleles, indicating oncogenic roles of the mutant genes. These results confirmed the ability of cisASE to detect tumorassociated ASEs.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Overview of cisASE algorithm. Mapped RNA-seq and DNA-seq data are piled up using samtools. LLR of the null and alternative models is calculated for each feature, i.e. SNV, exon or gene. Simulated DNA and RNA allele counts are generated from the data to produce a null distribution of the LLR, which is used to define an LLR cutoff with respect to a particular significance level. The LLR of each measured feature is compared to the LLR cutoff to determine whether it is an ASE</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. The performance of cisASE in simulated data with four different settings. We applied cisASE to simulated data with four different settings for pre-existing DNA bias. (A) site-by-site bias calculated from DNA-seq; (B) no bias; (C) mean bias of the DNA-seq data; and (D) mean bias of the RNA-seq data. B and C are overlapped</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Comparison of cisASE with the chi-square test in simulated data. The colors represent accuracy of the chi-square test relative to that of cisASE</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. Distribution of the percentage of ASE overexpressing reference alleles in a real dataset. For each cancer (N ¼ 16) and normal sample (N ¼ 16), we calculated the percentage of ASE specific to the reference allele (ASE with overexpressed reference allele)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Comparison of cisASE with MBASED in simulated data. cisASE performs better than MBASED in each stratum of the simulated data with (a) and without (b) CNV</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.6.</head><figDesc>Fig. 6. Comparison of cisASE with other methods in individual NA12878</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig.7.</head><figDesc>Fig. 7. Comparison of ASE in paired tumor and normal samples</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> Applications To demonstrate the application of cisASE, we applied it to a panel of 46 paired tumor-normal samples (Seshagiri et al., 2012). 4. 1 Higher cis-regulated ASE level in tumor samples For methods that do not use DNA-seq as a reference for bias adjustment, a high rate of CNV in tumor tissues (Shlien and Malkin, 2009) distorts the ASE detection results. For example, according to Mayba et al. (2014), the ASE genes identified by MBASED in tumor samples are mainly driven by large-scale genomic alterations, especially CNVs. However, the ASEs reported by cisASE should be unaffected by CNV. Applying cisASE to colon samples revealed that only 1% of the ASE genes in tumor samples are located within CNV regions (Fig. 7) and that the CNV genes are not significantly enriched in ASE genes (Fisher test P-value ¼ 0.273). This result validates the effectiveness of cisASE in identifying cis-regulated ASEs. By comparing tumor and normal samples, we found that tumor samples exhibited 1.8-fold-higher ASE rates than normal samples (P ¼ 9.961e-06). This result indicates that the cis-regulation of gene expression is more extensive in tumors.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors thank Mr. Jie Bi of Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences for useful advice on web development and Dr. Guoqing Zhang of Shanghai Center for Bioinformation Technology for managing the websites.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid and accurate haplotype phasing and missing-data inference for whole-genome association studies by use of localized haplotype clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Browning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Browning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1084" to="1097" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunomic, genomic and transcriptomic characterization of CT26 colorectal carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Castle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="0190" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sensitive detection of somatic point mutations in impure and heterogeneous cancer samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Cibulskis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of read-mapping biases on detecting allelespecific expression from RNA-sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Degner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3207" to="3212" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global patterns of cis variation in human cells revealed by high-density allelic expression analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Ge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1216" to="1222" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide analysis of allelic expression imbalance in human primary cells by high-throughput transcriptome resequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Heap</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mol. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A flexible and accurate genotype imputation method for the next generation of genome-wide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Howie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000529</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topoisomerase inhibitors unsilence the dormant allele of Ube3a in neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">481</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="189" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus pathways implicated in prognosis of colorectal cancer identified through systematic enrichment analysis of gene expression profiling studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Lascorz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18867</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale profiling and identification of potential regulatory mechanisms for allelic gene expression in colorectal cancer cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">512</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The sequence alignment/map format and SAMtools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2078" to="2079" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparing computational methods for identification of allele-specific expression based on next generation sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="591" to="598" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The extracellular matrix: a dynamic niche in cancer progression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Lu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">196</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="406" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MBASED: allele-specific expression detection in cancer tissues and cell lines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Mayba</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">405</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptome genetics using second generation sequencing in a Caucasian population</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Montgomery</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">464</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="773" to="777" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Turnover of focal adhesions and cancer cell migration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nagano</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">310616</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Allelic imbalance metre (Allim), a new tool for measuring allele-specific gene expression with RNA-seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Pandey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ecol. Resour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="740" to="745" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Population biology of antigen presentation by MHC class I molecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Parham</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Ohta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">272</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide allele-specific analysis: insights into regulatory variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Pastinen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="533" to="538" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptome profiling of the cancer and adjacent nontumor tissues from cervical squamous cell carcinoma patients by RNA sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Peng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tumour Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3309" to="3317" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AlleleSeq: analysis of allele-specific expression and binding in a network framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Rozowsky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">522</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recurrent R-spondin fusions in colon cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Seshagiri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">488</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="660" to="664" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The HLA genomic loci map: expression, interaction, diversity and disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Shiina</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Copy number variations and cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Shlien</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Malkin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">62</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A powerful and flexible statistical framework for testing hypotheses of allele-specific gene expression from RNA-seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Skelly</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1728" to="1737" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole transcriptome RNA-Seq allelic expression in human brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">571</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in extracellular matrix (ECM) and ECMassociated proteins in the metastatic progression of prostate cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Stewart</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reprod. Biol. Endocrinol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tumor transcriptome sequencing reveals allelic expression imbalances associated with copy number alterations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Tuch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9317</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunomodulation therapy in colorectal carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Yip</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Treat. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital RNA allelotyping reveals tissue-specific and allele-specific gene expression in human</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="618" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applications of cisASE in RNA sequencing data</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>