
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:32+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology CMGRN: a web server for constructing multilevel gene regulatory networks using ChIP-seq and gene expression data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Daogang</forename>
								<surname>Guan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hong Kong Baptist University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hong Kong</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jiaofang</forename>
								<surname>Shao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hong Kong Baptist University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hong Kong</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Youping</forename>
								<surname>Deng</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Internal Medicine and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Rush University Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Panwen</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">HKU-SIRI</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zhongying</forename>
								<surname>Zhao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hong Kong Baptist University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hong Kong</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yan</forename>
								<surname>Liang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hong Kong Baptist University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hong Kong</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Junwen</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">HKU-SIRI</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Genomic Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">LKS Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Hong Kong</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hong Kong</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bin</forename>
								<surname>Yan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hong Kong Baptist University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hong Kong</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Key Laboratory of Acupuncture and Medicine Research of Minister of Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanjing University of Chinese Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210046</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<region>Jiangsu</region>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology CMGRN: a web server for constructing multilevel gene regulatory networks using ChIP-seq and gene expression data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1190" to="1192"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt761</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 3, 2013; revised on November 12, 2013; accepted on December 25, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Gunnar Ratsch Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>ChIP-seq technology provides an accurate characterization of transcription or epigenetic factors binding on genomic sequences. With integration of such ChIP-based and other high-throughput information, it would be dedicated to dissecting cross-interactions among multilevel regulators, genes and biological functions. Here, we devised an integrative web server CMGRN (con-structing multilevel gene regulatory networks), to unravel hierarchical interactive networks at different regulatory levels. The newly developed method used the Bayesian network modeling to infer causal interrelationships among transcription factors or epigenetic modifications by using ChIP-seq data. Moreover, it used Bayesian hierarchical model with Gibbs sampling to incorporate binding signals of these regulators and gene expression profile together for reconstructing gene regulatory networks. The example applications indicate that CMGRN provides an effective web-based framework that is able to integrate heterogeneous high-throughput data and to reveal hierarchical &apos;regulome&apos; and the associated gene expression programs.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The combinational performance of transcriptional and epigenetic factors is central regulatory mechanisms to control gene expression networks. A fundamental challenge in post-genome era is to dissect such complex regulation associations underlying biological functions. ChIP-seq technology allows high-fidelity mapping of different regulators, such as transcription factors (TFs) or epigenetic modifications to genomic locations, thus providing a basis for profiling transcriptional or epigenetic regulatory relationships. Accurate binding features of these factors on the genomic sequences can also be used to identify regulatory modules and reconstruct gene regulatory networks (GRNs). Various algorithms and computational methods have been proposed to investigate gene regulation promoted by cooperation of TFs and epigenetic alterations. Some online tools or servers were designed to build GRNs derived from ChIP-seq data, for instance, Cscan (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Zambelli et al., 2012</ref>) and ChIP-Array (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Qin et al., 2011</ref>). Although the existing web-based software can predict potential target genes of the multiple regulators, they are not able to discover hierarchical organizations formed by cross-interactions between the regulators and genes simultaneously. Currently, there is a lack of effective web resources to generate the topology of networks controlled by the interacting factors at transcriptional, post-transcriptional and epigenetic layers. To provide an easy-to-use bioinformatics tool to interpret these ChIP-seq high-throughput data, we devised an integrative web server, constructing multilevel gene regulatory networks (CMGRN) to unveil interrelationships between TFs or epigenetic modifications and to robustly construct hierarchical regulatory network structures in biological complex systems. It is system wide and enables biologists to analyze the mixture information of ChIP-seq and gene expression levels, using standard data formatted with minimal need of bioinformatics skills.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Overview</head><p>The schematic procedure and layout of CMGRN are illustrated in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. Our server provides a web-based framework with two main tasks: (i) inference of causal relationships between TFs or epigenetic modifications by using Bayesian network-based methodology. One input is required: gene counts of TFs or epigenetic modifications based on ChIP-seq BED data mapped to genomic regions. (ii) Construction of GRNs coordinated by the multilevel factors. Two types of input are required: regulatory signal of TFs, epigenetic modifications or microRNAs and gene expression data. The regulatory signal represents binding/modification activities of TFs or epigenetic factors identified by calling peaks of ChIP-seq or binding targets of microRNAs. Through the integrated analysis, CMGRN would establish hierarchical regulatory network organizations at multiple levels, which quantify the interactions among regulators and genes by using Bayesian hierarchical model and Gibbs sampling. Thus, CMGRN can generate two outputs following the two procedures and also provides an option for network reconstruction *To whom correspondence should be addressed. depending on what are the types of input data (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). The first one will obtain a causal network linking TFs or epigenetic factors if only ChIPseq gene counts are provided. The second one will construct a final network exploring interactions of both regulator–regulator and regulator– gene if all three types of input are satisfied. The output tables and figures will be displayed via a user-friendly web interface and be easily downloaded. Usage of our service is simple and does not need user's knowledge on specific algorithm. The detailed information for the web tool implementation is explained in supplementary information and help page of the Web site.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Algorithms and statistical methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1">Inference of causal relationships between regulators We</head><p>used a Bayesian network-based model to infer causal interactions among regulators (TFs or epigenetic modifications) and examine how these regulators influence or associate with each other. The basic algorithm of Bayesian network structure searching for possibility of dependence between two nodes was described by<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Heckerman et al. (1995)</ref>. There are two challenges to overcome, high posterior probability and the compelled edges in the network. In particular, compelled edge identification is critical because these edges indicate causal relationships when certain assumptions hold. A series of optimization is needed for such 'causeeffect' network structures with high posterior probability. In this study, we adopted BD metric (Bayesian metric with Dirichlet prior) strategy proposed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Heckerman et al. (1995)</ref>to find the high likelihood of posterior probability. First, we set a Bayesian network of regulators as follows: B ¼ D,</p><formula>f g, D ¼ ðx i ,. .. , x n Þ, E k È É , D</formula><p>is an acyclic-directed graph (DAG); x i represents nodes (regulators) of the DAG, E k is set of edges of DAG and contains the set of conditional probability distributions that correspond to D. To find likelihood structures, the probability can be calculated by the following formula:</p><formula>log p D, B h s j À Á ¼ X n i¼1 log s x i j i ð Þ¼ X n i¼1 w x i , i ð Þþ X n i¼1 log s x i j ð Þ</formula><p>where i is the (possibly) null parent of x i. For edge x j ! x i , the strategy is to associate with a weight w x i , x j À Á ¼ log s x i jx j À Á À log s x i j ð Þ, is a node set without edges. A weight is defined for edge x i to x j as</p><formula>! x i , x j À Á ¼ logG x i jx j À Á À logG x i j' ð Þ.</formula><p>To search for the best network structure, we used maximal value for P n i¼1 w x i , i ð Þ: The aforementioned algorithm uses greedy strategy, so the next step is to identify compelled edges as potential network structures. Chickering developed mathematical algorithm for identifying compelled edges between two nodes to determine their causal relationship (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chickering, 1995</ref>).<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Yu et al. (2008)</ref>applied a similar methodology to predict causal relationships between histone modifications and gene expression in human T cells. The ChIP-seq reads in BED format were mapped to genomic regions and were then transferred to gene counts or signals of TFs or epigenetic modifications that could be detected. CMGRN used the gene count of ChIP-seq as input for inferring the causal relationships between regulators. First, the input gene counts will be discretized by using k-meansþþ algorithm. The k-means method is a widely used clustering technique that seeks to minimize the average and squared distance between points in the same cluster. Although its simplicity and speed are appealing in practice, it offers no accuracy guarantees for discretization. One reason is that k-means usually chooses initial k centers in an arbitrary way. If the centers are not properly taken, the resulting clusters will be also arbitrary and thus leading to generation of unstable 'cause-effect' relationships. In this study, we adopted a k-meansþþ method, which proposes a specific approach to choose centers like 'D 2 weighting' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arthur and Vassilvitskii, 2007</ref>). The main step of k-meansþþ is as follows:</p><p>(i) take one center k 1 , chosen uniformly at random from ; (ii) take a new center k i , choosing x 2 with probability</p><formula>DðxÞ 2 P x2 DðxÞ 2 ;</formula><p>(iii) repeat the second step until we take k centers altogether; and (iv) do the k-means algorithm. The strategy used by the k-meansþþ is able to improve both speed and accuracy of k-means. We have also demonstrated that the k-meansþþ method can increase the stability of the inferred causal relationships (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2">GRNs construction We used Bayesian hierarchical model with</head><p>Gibbs sampling implementation to identify correct sets of regulator–gene interactions that explore underlying network structures. This method will combine two types of data, regulatory signals of multifactors and gene expression profile. The ChIP-seq binding peaks of TFs and epigenetic modifications on the promoters were used as their regulatory signals. The regulatory signals of microRNAs were expressed by their binding targets based on both known and predicted sites on 3 0-untranslated regions. The main aim of this method is to incorporate the heterogeneous data, to capture essential regulatory features behind high-throughput data and to provide a basis for reconstructing GRNs. An integrated model COGRIM using the similar algorithm showed its capacity of identifying potential regulatory interactions between TFs and genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Chen et al., 2007</ref>). Previously, we successfully used this statistical model to identify target regulons of oncogenic TF family of NF-B in different cell types of head and neck cancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Yan et al., 2008</ref>). Here, we assign the gene expression profile and binding data of regulators to Bayesian hierarchical with an extensible linear model as following:</p><formula>e it ¼ i þ X j j¼1 j Pr ij f jt þ it p Pr ij j;, e it , b ij À Á / Y t t¼1 p e it jPr ij , ; À Á Á Y j j¼1 p Pr ij jb ij À Á</formula><p>Where it $ Normalð0, 2 Þ, e it is the log expression of gene i (i ¼ 1. .. N) in experiment t (t ¼ 1. .. T). The i is baseline expression for gene i in absence of known regulators. The f jt is the regulation activity estimated by log expression of TF gene j (j ¼ 1. .. J) in experiment t. Pr ij refers to the probability of gene i regulated by regulator j. Prior Pr ij $ Bernoulli h b ij À Á À Á where b ij means regulator j physically binds in proximity to gene i. In this study, this parameter can be considered as the regulatory signal from ChIP-seq binding peaks, or targets contain binding sites of microRNAs. ; represents parameter set ( i , j , 2 ). Both Pr ij and ; can be estimated one set given the other by Gibbs<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. An overview of data-integrated analysis and regulatory network construction. The triangle nodes represent TFs (pink), epigenetic regulators (red) and cofactors (blue), whereas the V-type nodes represent microRNAs (yellow). Target genes were indicated by using the circle nodes sampling, one of Markov chain Monte Carlo algorithm that is able to iteratively sample new values for each set of unknown parameters conditional on the current values of all other parameters. This process can be described as follows: estimating ; given Pr ij , e it and b ij , estimating Pr ij given ;, e it and b ij. To test the performance of CMGRN, we compared it with other three methods by using four different types of cancer gene expression data. The result showed that our method could improve the reliability of TF target identification from the cancer datasets (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Implementation</head><p>CMGRN was implemented with PHP and pascal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">SAMPLES TEST</head><p>We applied CMGRN to address the complex structures of regulatory networks underlying mouse embryonic stem cell pluripotency and differentiation. Our analysis provides computational proof that three pluripotent TFs (Oct4, Sox2 and Nanog), active histone methylations and microRNAs form a hierarchical 'regulome' that downregulates gene expression related to transcriptional processes and upregulates developmental genes facilitating differentiation. The hierarchical regulatory feature also works in an estrogen-stimulated breast cancer cell line and reveals that estrogen receptor is a driving factor that links to other TFs and cofactors that control estrogen-associated gene expression programs (see Supplementary Figs S3 and S4).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: Grant of Science Faculty of Hong Kong Baptist University (Grant no: FRG2/12-13/066), National Nature</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">kmeansþþ: the advantages of careful seeding</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Arthur</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Vassilvitskii</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Eighteenth Annual ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms</title>
		<meeting>the Eighteenth Annual ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms<address><addrLine>Philadelphia, PA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1027" to="1035" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustering of genes into regulons using integrated modelingCOGRIM</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A transformational characterization of equivalent bayesian network structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Chickering</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 11th Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<editor>Besnard,P. and Hanks,S.</editor>
		<meeting>11th Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence<address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="98" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning Bayesian networks: the combination of knowledge and statistical data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Heckerman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mach. Learn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="243" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ChIP-Array: combinatory analysis of ChIP-seq/chip and microarray gene expression data to discover direct/indirect targets of a transcription factor</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Qin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="430" to="436" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology-defined NF-kappaB regulons, interacting signal pathways and networks are implicated in the malignant phenotype of head and neck cancer cell lines differing in p53 status</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Yan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">53</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inferring causal relationships among different histone modifications and gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Yu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1314" to="1324" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cscan: finding common regulators of a set of genes by using a collection of genome-wide ChIP-seq datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Zambelli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="510" to="515" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Guan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>