
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:40+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies CoDNaS: a database of conformational diversity in the native state of proteins</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">19 2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alexander</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Miguel</forename>
								<surname>Monzon</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad Nacional de Quilmes</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>B1876BXD</postCode>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ezequiel</forename>
								<surname>Juritz</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad Nacional de Quilmes</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>B1876BXD</postCode>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">María</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Silvina</forename>
								<surname>Fornasari</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad Nacional de Quilmes</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>B1876BXD</postCode>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Gustavo</forename>
								<surname>Parisi</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>gusparisi@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad Nacional de Quilmes</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>B1876BXD</postCode>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies CoDNaS: a database of conformational diversity in the native state of proteins</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2512" to="2514"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">19 2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt405</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 25, 2013; revised on June 18, 2013; accepted on July 5, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Conformational diversity is a key concept in the understanding of different issues related with protein function such as the study of catalytic processes in enzymes, protein-protein recognition , protein evolution and the origins of new biological functions. Here, we present a database of proteins with different degrees of conformational diversity. Conformational Diversity of Native State (CoDNaS) is a redundant collection of three-dimensional structures for the same protein derived from protein data bank. Structures for the same protein obtained under different crystallographic conditions have been associated with snapshots of protein dynamism and consequently could characterize protein conformers. CoDNaS allows the user to explore global and local structural differences among confor-mers as a function of different parameters such as presence of ligand, post-translational modifications, changes in oligomeric states and differences in pH and temperature. Additionally, CoDNaS contains information about protein taxonomy and function, disorder level and structural classification offering useful information to explore the underlying mechanism of conformational diversity and its close relationship with protein function. Currently, CoDNaS has 122 122 structures integrating 12 684 entries, with an average of 9.63 confor-mers per protein. Availability: The database is freely available at http://www.codnas. com.ar/.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>It is well established that the native state of a protein is represented by an ensemble of conformers in equilibrium (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Tsai et al., 1999</ref>). Different factors, such as ligands, post-translational modifications or pH variations could shift this equilibrium toward a given conformer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kumar et al., 2000</ref>). Following conformational selection theory, the change in the dynamic landscape and the re-distribution of conformer population is a key feature to understand protein function (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Nussinov and Ma, 2012</ref>). It has been shown that different structures for the same protein obtained under different conditions represent snapshots of protein dynamism and then characterize putative structural conformers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Best et al., 2006</ref>). Here, we describe the design, development and use of a database of proteins showing different degrees of conformational diversity. Conformational Diversity of Native State (CoDNaS) is a collection of redundant structures, obtained from different experimental protocols, for the same protein. CoDNaS is a database of complete proteins, linked with Protein Conformational DataBase (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Juritz et al., 2011</ref>), a previous development from our group oriented to the analysis of conformational diversity in protein domains. The database is extensively linked with physicochemical and biological information, and it is designed to allow the user to explore how different parameters could modulate protein conformational diversity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>Using the BlastClust application (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Altschul et al., 1990</ref>) on protein data bank database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Berman, 2000</ref>), for every protein deposited, we obtained all available clusters with 100% of sequence identity. We only considered clusters with more than two structures for each protein and structures with resolutions 54 A ˚. Structural similarity measures were performed using MAMMOTH (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Ortiz et al., 2002</ref>), ProFit (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">McLachlan, 1982</ref>) and TM-score (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Zhang and Skolnick, 2004</ref>) for all the structures retrieved for each protein. The maximum C-alpha root-mean-square deviation (RMSD) value for every entry was registered as a measure of the conformational diversity extension. Each structure in CoDNaS is characterized by the conditions of its experimental determination: presence of ligands, mutations, post-translational modifications, oligomeric state, pH, loop regions and temperature. According to the conformational selection theory, these factors could be used to study conformational changes and to correlate them with biological information. In addition, proteins were linked with other databases, such as UniProt (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Jain et al., 2009</ref>), gene ontology (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ashburner et al., 2000</ref>), enzyme commission (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kotera et al., 2004</ref>), CATH (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Greene et al., 2007</ref>), SIFTS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Velankar et al., 2005</ref>) and MobiDB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Di Domenico et al., 2012</ref>), to obtain a broad spectrum of biological and physicochemical information such as taxonomy, source organism, protein function, degree of protein disorder and structural class, among others. Structures (putative conformers) for a given protein were clustered using two algorithms: hierarchical clustering and affinity propagation clustering. C-alpha RMSD per position values were also derived to complement global similarity measures together with additional parameters characterizing conformational change (such as degree of protein disorder, loopy residues content and solvent-exposed area). The web application server is implemented on HTML, PHP and Java languages, connected with a MySQL-based database. CoDNaS search is based on dynamics SQL queries generated in PHP. *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">USAGE</head><p>CoDNaS database can be searched and browsed using different global structural measures between conformers. This structural information is linked with physicochemical and biological parameters. The user can define and combine different parameters to limit the search such as C-alpha RMSD extension, causes of conformational diversity or taxonomy, among others. A typical query, for example, could involve the search for those proteins showing a conformational diversity 41 A ˚ of C-alpha RMSD owing to the presence of ligands. This query will retrieve all entries containing at least one pair of conformers presenting a C-alpha RMSD 41 A ˚ where the unique difference in the structure estimation (NMR or XRD) is the presence or absence of ligands. An example of that search is shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, where five conformational states are observed for the protein lysine, arginine and ornithine-binding protein (LAO protein) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1A</ref>). One of these structures (2LAO) has no ligand bound, whereas the other four (1LAH, 1LAF, 1LAG and 1LST) have arginine, lysine or ornithine bound. Maximum conformational diversity is obtained when the conformer with unbound ligand is compared with any of the other conformers containing a ligand. The conformers containing a ligand are structurally similar to each other as derived from the clustering analysis shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1A</ref>. Global and local structural differences are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1B</ref>and C. The pair of conformers with maximum structural diversity is shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1B</ref>with a C-alpha RMSD of 4.71 A ˚ .<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1C</ref>represents the z-scores derived from per position C-alpha RMSD showing the local differences between bound and unbound forms of the protein. Similar information is provided for all the aligned pairs of conformers for each protein at the web server. For each entry in CoDNaS, structural alignments, sequence-derived alignment and structural and physicochemical comparisons between conformers are available to download. Other parameters besides the presence of ligands can be used to search CoDNaS database, such as differences in pH and temperature, change in oligomeric structure (e.g. the occurrence of transient oligomers for a given protein), presence of mutations, presence of disordered and/or loopy regions and the presence of post-translational modifications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>Conformational diversity is a key feature to understand protein function and evolution (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Juritz et al., 2013</ref>), enzyme catalysis and molecular recognition (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Boehr et al., 2010</ref>). Recently, it has been shown that explicit consideration of conformational diversity improves prediction of disease-related mutations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Juritz et al., 2012</ref>) and protein-protein interactions and molecular docking (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kuzu et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Osguthorpe et al., 2012</ref>). As computational prediction of large conformational changes could be challenging [e.g. using molecular dynamics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Petruk et al., 2013)]</ref>, CoDNaS database could provide a useful dataset to test new tools to predict and explore possible causes of conformational diversity in proteins.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. (A) Example of a protein entry retrieved from CoDNaS showing conformational diversity. In this case, we show the LAO-binding protein exhibiting five different putative conformers. Hierarchical clustering using C-alpha RMSD as distance measure is shown. (B) Maximum conformational diversity is obtained when bound and unbound conformers are compared [C-alpha RMSD ¼ 4.71 1LAH with bound ligand represented as space-filled model and 2LAO_A ]. (C) Per position C-alpha RMSD z-score showing local structural differences between conformers displayed in (B)</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Database of conformational diversity of the native state in proteins at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">A.M.Monzon et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basic local alignment search tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">215</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="410" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The protein data bank</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Berman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relation between native ensembles and experimental structures of proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Best</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10901" to="10906" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of dynamic conformational ensembles in biomolecular recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Boehr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="789" to="796" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MobiDB: a comprehensive database of intrinsic protein disorder annotations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Di</forename>
				<surname>Domenico</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2080" to="2081" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The CATH domain structure database: new protocols and classification levels give a more comprehensive resource for exploring evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Greene</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="297" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Infrastructure for the life sciences: design and implementation of the UniProt website</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Jain</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">136</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the effect of protein conformation diversity in discriminating among neutral and disease related single amino acid substitutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Juritz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 4</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein conformational diversity modulates sequence divergence</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Juritz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PCDB: a database of protein conformational diversity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Juritz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="475" to="479" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational assignment of the EC numbers for genomicscale analysis of enzymatic reactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kotera</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16487" to="16498" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Folding and binding cascades: dynamic landscapes and population shifts</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kumar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploiting conformational ensembles in modeling protein-protein interactions on the proteome scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Kuzu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2641" to="2653" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid comparison of protein structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Mclachlan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Crystallogr. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="871" to="873" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein dynamics and conformational selection in bidirectional signal transduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Nussinov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Ma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MAMMOTH (matching molecular models obtained from theory): an automated method for model comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Ortiz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2606" to="2621" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generation of receptor structural ensembles for virtual screening using binding site shape analysis and clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Osguthorpe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem Biol Drug Des</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular dynamics simulations provide atomistic insight into hydrogen exchange mass spectrometry experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Petruk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Theory Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="658" to="669" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Folding funnels, binding funnels, and protein function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Tsai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1181" to="1190" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">E-MSD: an integrated data resource for bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Velankar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scoring function for automated assessment of protein structure template quality</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Skolnick</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="702" to="710" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>