
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:36+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology DA 1.0: parameter estimation of biological pathways using data assimilation approach</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chuan</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Hock</forename>
								<surname>Koh</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">NUS Graduate School for Integrative Sciences and Engineering</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>117597</postCode>
									<country key="SG">Singapore</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National University of Singapore</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Computing Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>117417</postCode>
									<country key="SG">Singapore</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Human Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Medical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">the University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>4-6-1 Shirokanedai, Minato-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>108-8639</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Masao</forename>
								<surname>Nagasaki</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Human Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Medical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">the University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>4-6-1 Shirokanedai, Minato-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>108-8639</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ayumu</forename>
								<surname>Saito</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Human Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Medical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">the University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>4-6-1 Shirokanedai, Minato-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>108-8639</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Limsoon</forename>
								<surname>Wong</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National University of Singapore</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Computing Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>117417</postCode>
									<country key="SG">Singapore</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Satoru</forename>
								<surname>Miyano</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Human Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Medical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">the University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>4-6-1 Shirokanedai, Minato-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>108-8639</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Olga</forename>
								<surname>Troyanskaya</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology DA 1.0: parameter estimation of biological pathways using data assimilation approach</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1794" to="1796"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq276</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on January 19, 2010; revised on April 21, 2010; accepted on May 23, 2010</note>
					<note>[17:26 18/6/2010 Bioinformatics-btq276.tex] Page: 1794 1794–1796 Associate Editor:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Data assimilation (DA) is a computational approach that estimates unknown parameters in a pathway model using time-course information. Particle filtering, the underlying method used, is a well-established statistical method that approximates the joint posterior distributions of parameters by using sequentially generated Monte Carlo samples. In this article, we report the release of Java-based software (DA 1.0) with an intuitive and user-friendly interface to allow users to carry out parameters estimation using DA. Availability and Implementation: DA 1.0 was developed using Java and thus would be executable on any platform installed with JDK 6.0 (not JRE 6.0) or later. DA 1.0 is freely available for academic users and can be launched or downloaded from http://da.csml.org.Contact:
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Simulating and modeling of biological pathways have been gaining popularity in an attempt to better understand complex biological relationships (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Fisher and Henzinger, 2007</ref>). However, before a pathway model can be simulated, all parameters in the model must be known. Unfortunately, some parameters are usually either unknown or do not agree in literature. To address this problem, we previously introduced a computational method called Data assimilation (DA) to estimate unknown parameters in a pathway model using the time-course information based on a well-established statistical method, particle filtering (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Nagasaki et al., 2006</ref>). This method has been successfully used to do parameter estimation for the circadian clock model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Nagasaki et al., 2006</ref>) and phosphotyrosine-dependent signaling networks in the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) pathway (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Tasaki et al., 2006</ref>). Furthermore, in a recent paper, it has also been shown that particle filtering can be deployed to utilize parallel computing infrastructure that makes it scalable for large, complex models (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Nakamura et al., 2009</ref>). * To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint first authors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">DA</head><p>DA is an approach widely used especially in the field of geophysics. It combines observations and numerical simulation models to estimate the unknown parameters. Two advantages of DA are its compatibility with parallelism and its ability to reveal the posterior distributions of unknown parameters. The approach in brief is as follows; given a pathway model, the list of parameters to be estimated and N observed time points, a set of M particles is drawn either randomly or through user-specified distribution. At each time point N, the M particles will be resampled with a probability directly proportional to a fitness score. The fitness score is computed as a function of difference between the simulated and observed data at each time point. A higher score is given to particles with simulated results closer to the observed results. At the end of the algorithm, users are given the distribution plots of the M particles' values. It is recommended that the mode of the distribution be chosen as the estimated value for downstream applications. For more details on the algorithm, please refer to<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Nagasaki et al. (2006)</ref>. The power of DA largely depends on two factors: (i) the number of observed time points and (ii) size of particles and number of parameters to be estimated. From a statistical point of view, the more time points observed (higher frequency and longer duration), the higher the accuracy would be. However, time points are often limited by current experimental techniques. The size of particles should also be exponentially proportional to the number of parameters to be estimated in order to obtain a high accuracy. However, if the number of particles is large, it is likely to cause either out of memory error or slow running time on standard desktop computers. In the next section, we will describe practical ways to work around the two limitations above in order to obtain an accurate estimation of parameters in a normal desktop environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">SOFTWARE FEATURES</head><p>DA 1.0 contains implementation of the particle filter methodology and several other features for ease of use, including a drawing utility that will be particularly useful when observed data is limited. The user interface is deliberately minimalistic so that the usage would be intuitive (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>, main dialog). The required inputs include a pathway model, observed data and the range of the parameters to estimate. The output consists of a distribution plot of the particles, simulation results of the fitted models and Cell System Markup Language (CSML) format (http://www.csml.org) of the fitted models.This step is needed to pair the model entities with observed data. An auto-map function is available to match corresponding entities and observed data with same names. (d) A variety of settings for the particle filter and simulation are enabled to allow for flexibility based on the user's needs. (e) After running the particle filter algorithm, the simulation runs results using estimated parameters will be plotted for ease of comparison between the original and fitted models. The parameters' distribution plot is also displayed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Inputs</head><p>The required format for the pathway model is CSML as DA 1.0 is built to run particle filtering on hybrid functional Petri net with extension (<ref type="bibr">HFPNe;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Nagasaki et al., 2004</ref>), which uses the CSML format. However, support has also been extended to another format, Systems Biology Markup Language (SBML) in the form of a SBML2CSML converter. Thus, it is possible to input the pathway model in either CSML or SBML (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1a</ref>). If the latter is being provided, it will be automatically converted into CSML format. As for observed data, EDF (expression data format) would be required. EDF (http://da.csml.org) was developed in our laboratory for the ease of representing time series expression data that usually include replicates and annotation data. Similarly, to support the commonly used tab (or comma) separated format, a convertor to convert tab (or comma) separated format into EDF is included. Finally, users would have to set the range for the parameters they wish to estimate (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1a</ref>). This need not be precise. It would be sufficient to simply give it a rough range that is biologically possible.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Outputs</head><p>Unlike parameter estimation methods based on using optimization method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Yoshida et al., 2008</ref>), particle filtering gives a distribution plot of the possible values for the parameter. This information is particularly useful for repeat runs to obtain a better estimation. The simulation results of the original model, observed data and fitted model are also plotted on one graph for ease of comparison (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1e</ref>). Finally, users can save the fitted models in CSML format, which can be displayed and replayed on Cell Illustrator Player that is available for free. Direct launch of the fitted models in Cell Illustrator Player from DA 1.0 is also possible. Additionally, users can run Cell Illustrator to apply more comprehensive downstream analysis. Cell Illustrator (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Nagasaki et al., 2003</ref>) is available for free as a 1 month trial at https://cionline.hgc.jp. Users also have the freedom to utilize other software of their choice, and they can obtain the estimated values from the distribution plot (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1e</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Tips to improve estimation accuracy</head><p>As mentioned in the previous section, observed time points are often limited, which could potentially reduce the estimation accuracy. To overcome this limitation, we have added the ability to increase time points' frequency by means of smoothing and re-sampling (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1b</ref>). In some cases, it is possible that users do not have any experimental data but have an idea of how a particular biological entity would behave with respect to time, either gleaned from literature or simply testing out a hypothesis. To handle such cases, we have also made it simple to draw expression plots within DA 1.0.Another important factor that affects estimation accuracy is the seed size (number of particles). However, setting a large seed size causes the program to run slowly. Therefore, we suggest for users to do repeat runs using medium seed size (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1d</ref>) and to adjust the possible range after each run using the distribution plot of the parameters (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1e</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Page: 1796 1794–1796</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.H.Koh et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">PERFORMANCE</head><p>To give users a gauge of the performance of DA 1.0, we have performed some experiments using the circadian clock model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Nagasaki et al., 2006</ref>) with 17 parameters in total, on a contemporary desktop machine (Intel Core i7 CPU at 3.2 GHz). We focused on the influence of seed size on time used, space needed and estimation power. With respect to the memory needed, every one million seeds require ∼1 GB of RAM (data not shown). From<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2a</ref>, we can see that the time used increases with the seed size linearly and is able to finish in reasonable time (&lt;80 s for 2 million seeds).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2b</ref>demonstrates how the coverage on the search space would affect the estimation power. The standard deviation of the score is large because the seeds are randomly generated. If a 'good' seed is randomly generated, the score would be low. Naturally, with increased coverage, the chance of generating a 'good' seed increases. However, in the case of a large search space, having good coverage would require a huge amount of memory that might not be available. In such cases, users are encouraged to follow the strategy suggested in Section 3.3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">FUTURE WORK</head><p>As mentioned, one important factor that affects the estimation power is the size of particles. To empower users with the ability to significantly increase the size of particles yet still be able to complete the estimation within reasonable time, we are currently working on adding the ability to utilize remote computing infrastructure easily using remote method invocation (RMI). One advantage of DA is that it gives a distribution instead of a single optimal value for each parameter. However, currently only the mean, mode, median or best seed can be used for simulation on Cell Illustrator. Hence, we are now working to further increase the compatibility of Cell Illustrator and DA 1.0 to take full advantage of the DA approach.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. (a) This step is to load the model file (CSML or SBML) and define the distribution and range for parameters that users wish to estimate. (b) This step is to input the observed time-series data. Accepted formats include EDF, CSV and TSV. Functions such as smoothing and sampling are included to improve the quality of observed data for better estimation results. (c) This step is needed to pair the model entities with observed data. An auto-map function is available to match corresponding entities and observed data with same names. (d) A variety of settings for the particle filter and simulation are enabled to allow for flexibility based on the user's needs. (e) After running the particle filter algorithm, the simulation runs results using estimated parameters will be plotted for ease of comparison between the original and fitted models. The parameters' distribution plot is also displayed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. (a) Time versus seed size plot. (b) Score versus coverage. Scores close to 1 or &lt;1 indicates a very good match between observed data and simulation results. (Please see supplementary data for experiments details.)</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Executable cell biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Fisher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Henzinger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1239" to="1249" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic Object Net: I. A platform for modeling and simulating biopathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nagasaki</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="184" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A versatile Petri net based architecture for modeling and simulation of complex biological processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nagasaki</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="180" to="197" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic data assimilation for estimating hybrid functional Petri net from time-course gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nagasaki</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parameter estimation of in silico biological pathways with particle filtering towards a petascale computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Nakamura</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pac. Symp. Biocomput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling and estimation of dynamic EGFR pathway by data assimilation approach using time series proteomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Tasaki</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="226" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian learning of biological pathways on genomic data assimilation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Yoshida</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2592" to="2601" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>