
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:29+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression Discovering relational-based association rules with multiple minimum supports on microarray datasets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yu-Cheng</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Information Engineering</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chun-Pei</forename>
								<surname>Cheng</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Information Engineering</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Vincent</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Tseng</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Information Engineering</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Janet</forename>
								<surname>Kelso</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Medical Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Cheng Kung University</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>R.O.C</region>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression Discovering relational-based association rules with multiple minimum supports on microarray datasets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="3142" to="3148"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr526</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 18, 2011; revised on August 29, 2011; accepted on September 3, 2011</note>
					<note>[14:36 19/10/2011 Bioinformatics-btr526.tex] Page: 3142 3142–3148 Associate Editor: Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Association rule analysis methods are important techniques applied to gene expression data for finding expression relationships between genes. However, previous methods implicitly assume that all genes have similar importance, or they ignore the individual importance of each gene. The relation intensity between any two items has never been taken into consideration. Therefore, we proposed a technique named REMMAR (RElational-based Multiple Minimum supports Association Rules) algorithm to tackle this problem. This method adjusts the minimum relation support (MRS) for each gene pair depending on the regulatory relation intensity to discover more important association rules with stronger biological meaning. Results: In the actual case study of this research, REMMAR utilized the shortest distance between any two genes in the Saccharomyces cerevisiae gene regulatory network (GRN) as the relation intensity to discover the association rules from two S.cerevisiae gene expression datasets. Under experimental evaluation, REMMAR can generate more rules with stronger relation intensity, and filter out rules without biological meaning in the protein–protein interaction network (PPIN). Furthermore, the proposed method has a higher precision (100%) than the precision of reference Apriori method (87.5%) for the discovered rules use a literature survey. Therefore, the proposed REMMAR algorithm can discover stronger association rules in biological relationships dissimilated by traditional methods to assist biologists in complicated genetic exploration. Availability: The source code in Java and other materials used in this study are available at http://websystem.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Formerly, biologists were constrained to performing laboratory experiments to clarify gene expressions; however, manipulation of multiple genes is very costly, in both time and money. Microarray technology is a useful tool for gaining the expression value of many genes in the cell environment while simultaneously tackling * To whom correspondence should be addressed. the manipulation problem. At present, how to explain the cell's inner working with efficiency has become another challenge for the biologist. Data mining technologies are ideal for discovering information from large datasets. Thus, a growing number of researchers are applying data mining technologies for efficient elucidation of genetic information. Recently, various types of analysis methods were proposed to analyze gene expression data, such as clustering analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Cheng and Church, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Jiang et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Madeira and Oliveira, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Pei et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Prelic et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Thalamuthu et al., 2006</ref>), association rule analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Creighton and Hanash, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Georgii et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Martinez et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">McIntosh and Chawla, 2007</ref>), classification analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bhasin and Raghava, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Liu and Xu, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Martella, 2009</ref>), among others. These methods equip biologists to extract biological knowledge quickly for different analysis purposes. Association rule analysis is used to find and describe relationships between genes. Every rule indicates whether a given gene is expressed (↑) or repressed (↓) to describe expression relationships in a cellular environment. Suppose that we discover the rule {gene x ↑} =&gt; {gene y ↓,gene z ↑} from a gene expression dataset. This rule states that when gene x is expressed, gene y is repressed and gene z is expressed together in this dataset. Two important thresholds exist to measure the significance of a rule, support and confidence. The support of a rule is the frequency that gene x ↑, gene y ↓ and gene z ↑ together in a sample. The confidence of a rule is the frequency that gene y ↓, gene z ↑ occurs when gene x ↑ occurs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Creighton and Hanash, 2003</ref>). Although various types of association rule analysis methods were proposed to analyze gene expression data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Creighton and Hanash, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Georgii et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Martinez et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">McIntosh and Chawla, 2007</ref>), not all of the proposed methods fit with the goal of our work in exploring the regulatory relations of genes from microarray datasets.<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Georgii et al. (2005)</ref>adopted the half-space technique to discover quantitative association rules on numeric microarray datasets without requiring a discretization process. However, their approach cannot mine a complete set of relevant rules when applying the method on microarray profile.<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Martinez et al. (2008)</ref>proposed the GenMiner method to mine association rules from a set of gene expression profiles and the publicly available gene ontology (GO) terms. However, the main purpose of their approach is different from ours since they were in an attempt to extract relationships between certain genes and its annotated GO terms. Finally,<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">McIntosh and Chawla (2007)</ref>proposed an association rule mining algorithm called MaxConf, which was developed with a row-enumeration method. However, it did not consider the constraint<ref type="bibr">[14:36 19/10/2011 Bioinformatics-btr526.tex]</ref>Page: 3143 3142–3148 REMMAR of minimum support threshold. Moreover, the results of applying the algorithm on microarray dataset can only show high confidence gene regulations. Nevertheless, MaxConf may fail in discovering the longer rules with the context containing many items. However, the longer rules are usually more important than the rules that are shorter in size in the real applications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Alves et al., 2010</ref>). On the other hand, the rules with low support would also be mined using their algorithm. These rules are likely to be regarded as false positive as long as they appear infrequently over all samples. Differentiated with the previous works as described above, our method proposed in this article is effective for mining putative gene regulations from microarray profiles. However, the traditional association rule analysis implicitly assumes that all items have similar importance without considering their significance in the data. Regardless, this is often not the case in real-life applications. Therefore, a number of researchers have proposed weight-based (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Cai et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Ramkumar et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Tao et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Tseng et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Wang et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Yun and Leggett, 2005</ref>) or multiple support-based (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Liu et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Su et al., 2008</ref>) association rule mining to engage this problem in a transaction database. Nevertheless, traditionally weighted or multiple supportbased association rule mining techniques only take into account the importance of each item. In a number of real-life case, the degree of importance is dependent on relationships between items. Both techniques never consider the relation intensity between any two items. For this reason, we propose the REMMAR (RElationalbased Multiple Minimum supports Association Rules) algorithm, which adjusts the minimum relation support (MRS) for each paired item dependent on the relation intensity, to discover the rules that have stronger biological meaning. In a real case study, we used the shortest distance between any two genes in the gene regulatory network (GRN) as the relation importance. Two real S.cerevisiae microarray datasets were used to evaluate the comparison results between the traditional association rule mining method and the proposed algorithm. The remainder of this article is organized as follows: Section 2 provides a brief review of traditional association rule mining and presents the proposed method; Section 3 consists of the application of the approach to S.cerevisiae datasets, to study the significance of the discovered rules. Finally, in Section 4, we present a conclusion regarding our findings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>In this section, we first describe the reference Apriori algorithm and research using the Apriori framework to discover gene interaction rules from gene expression data. Before we utilize the REMMAR algorithm to discover association rules, microarray data must undergo a transformation into transactional data format. Thereafter, the problem in the research must be defined. Finally, Section 2.3 shows the proposed REMMAR algorithm in detail.<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Agrawal et al. (1993</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Agrawal et al. ( , 1994</ref>) first proposed association rule analysis. It was used as the Apriori algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Agrawal et al., 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Agrawal and Srikant, 1994</ref>) to analyze databases, to discover valuable relationships between items. The support of an itemset is defined as the frequency that occurs in all transactions. If the support of an itemset was not less than the user-specified minimum support, it would be recognized as a large itemsetThe main concept of all Apriori-based methods is that any subitemsets of a large itemset is surely also a large itemset. In other words, an itemset is not required to be revised if it exceeds minimum support as long as any one of subitemsets of the itemset is not a large itemset. For example, if a large itemset generated by an Apriori-based algorithm contains k items, all of the subitemsets involving 1 to k −1 items are certainly large itemsets. In contrast, with a brute force method, an itemset needs to be verified even if it contains an item whose frequency does not exceed the minimum support. Taken together, using an Apriori-based method can reduce the overhead in examining whether the produced itemsets are large ones. For this reason, the Apriori-based methods are more efficient since the verification of ineligible itemsets is not required. When all large itemsets are identified, any large itemset possessing more than one item can be divided into two itemsets, S x and S y. An association rule is described as S x =&gt; S y , where S x and S y are the left-hand side (LHS) and right-hand side (RHS) of this rule, respectively. This rule means that S y can possibly occur where S x exists. The confidence of a candidate rule is the frequency that S y occurs when S x exists. If the confidence of this candidate rule is not less than a user-specified minimum confidence, it would be defined as an association rule in this data. In 2003,<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Creighton and Hanash (2003)</ref>used the Apriori method to discover numerous gene interaction rules from gene expression data, many of which are biologically sensible. Every rule can indicate whether a given gene is expressed (↑) or repressed (↓), to describe the expression relationship in a cellular environment. Suppose that the user discovers the rule {gene x ↑} =&gt; {gene y ↓,gene z ↑} from the gene expression dataset. This rule states that if gene x is expressed, then gene y is repressed and gene z is expressed together in this dataset.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Traditional association rule mining</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Gene expression data transformation and basic definitions of our method</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1">Transformation of gene expression data As with the model</head><p>Creighton and Hanash (2003) proposed, which consists of applying the association-based method on gene expression data analysis, each sample can be recognized as a transaction. Each expression value in the data can be transformed as up (↑; expressed; readings are &gt; 0.2 for the log base 10 of fold change 1.58 as upper bound), down (↓; repressed; readings are lower than −0.2 for the log base 10 of fold change −1.58 as lower bound) or normal</p><p>(neither expressed nor repressed). For the threshold value of ±0.2, it is set in a reasonable range (fold change from 1.5 to 2.0) based on most microarray analysis studies in identifying the differentially expressed probes. The up or down notation suffices in displaying whether a gene is significant and has the probability to influence other genes. For this reason, only the expression value for each gene can be transformed as up or down in transactional data format, as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. After gene expression data transformation, gene x ↑ and gene x ↓ will be defined in different items. Thus, the number of items would be increased when either decreasing the upper bound or increasing lower bound, whereas that of items would be decreased when either increasing upper bound or decreasing lower bound.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2">Initial minimum support</head><p>The support of an itemset S x is the frequency of S x occurrence in all transactions (Samples). The initial minimum support (IMS) is a user-specified baseline threshold to judge the support of each item. Items greater than, or equal to, IMS are called large 1-itemsets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3">Initial minimum confidence</head><p>The confidence of an association rule S x =&gt; S y is the frequency of S y occurrence when S x occurs. The initial minimum confidence (IMC) is a user-specified baseline threshold to judge the confidence of each rule.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.4">Minimum relation support</head><p>In the real case study of this research, we used the shortest distance between any two genes in the GRN as the relational importance. As an example,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>is a GRN. For any pair of neighboring genes (physical interaction) in the network, the distance between them will be defined as 1. Hence, the shortest distance between G2 and G4 is 1, and that between G1 and G2 is 3. In theory, two genes are more likely to involve the same pathways or biological functions if they have a shorter distance.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref>is the gene shortest distance matrix retrieved from the GRN of<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>., because G2 and G4 have a stronger relation intensity (with smaller shortest distance) than others in the GRN. Furthermore, if the itemset S has more than two items, based on the second equation, the MRS of S will be the maximum MRS of each item-pair in S. A large itemset would be generated as long as the support value of the itemset (contains at least two items) is not less than its corresponding MRS.</p><formula>MRS(x,y) = ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ IMS+ IMS * Dist(x,y)−Avg_Dist Max_Dist-Min_Dist 2 (Dist(x,y)−Avg_Dist) &gt; 0 IMS− IMS * Dist(x,y)−Avg_Dist Max_Dist-Min_Dist 2 Otherwise (1)</formula><p>MRS(S) = Max{MRS(x,y)|x,y ∈ S and x = y, where S is an itemset containing more than one item} (2)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.5">Minimum relation confidence As Creighton and Hanash (2003)</head><p>proposed, this study focused on the rule S x =&gt; S y , where S x has a single item, as to limit the search space of candidate rules. In the Minimum relation confidence (MRC), we also used the shortest distance between any two genes in the GRN as the relation importance. Based on Equations (3)</p><p>and</p><p>(4), the MRC of rule S x =&gt; S y will be the maximum MRC of each item-pair between S x and S y. Suppose the user-specified IMC is 45% and the MRC({G2↑} =&gt; {G4↑, G5↓}) = Max{MRC(G2↑, G4↑), MRC(G2↑, G5↓)} = Max{39.4875, 46.0125} = 46.0125. Therefore, in this example, if the confidence value of the rule ({G2↑} =&gt; {G4↑, G5↓}) is not less than its corresponding MRC (46.0125), the rule would be an eligible association rule.</p><formula>MRC(S x ⇒ S y ) = Max{MRC(x,y)|x ∈ S x and y ∈ S y , where S x and S y are itemsets} (3) MRC(x,y) = ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ IMC+ IMC * Dist(x,y)−Avg_Dist Max_Dist−Min_Dist 2 (Dist(x,y)−Avg_Dist) &gt; 0 IMC− IMC * Dist(x,y)−Avg_Dist Max_Dist−Min_Dist 2 Otherwise (4)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Relational-based multiple minimum supports association rules mining</head><p>The REMMAR algorithm was proposed to discover gene interaction rules from the gene expression database on relation intensity. As stated above in Section 2.1, REMMAR utilizes the main concept of Apriori to improve the efficiency of mining association rules compared with the brute force method. The REMMAR algorithm is shown below:The main process of the REMMAR algorithm is described as follows:</p><p>(1) Count the support of each item in Database D (all samples). If the support of the item is greater than, or equal to, the IMS, it is called large 1-itemsets in L 1 (the set that includes all the large 1-itemsets).</p><p>(2) Utilize the candidate-gen function to generate candidate k-itemsets in C k (the set that includes all the candidate k-itemsets) based on large k−1-itemsets in L k−1 .</p><p>(3) Utilize the subset function to count the support of each candidate k-itemset in D.</p><p>(4) If the support of the candidate k-itemset in C k is greater than, or equal to, the MRS of this itemset, it is called large k-itemsets in L k .</p><p>(5) Increment k by 1 and repeat the procedure from Stage 2 to Stage 4 until candidate itemsets can no longer be generated.</p><p>After the process of REMMAR, the algorithm can generate all large itemsets that satisfy the MRS. In the next phase, for each set of large itemset L and each possible subset A of L, they can generate the association rule A → (L–A) that satisfies the MRC themselves. Following the proposal of<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Agrawal et al. (1994)</ref>, REMMAR have two important functions similar to other Apriori-based algorithms; the candidategen function and the subset function. The candidate-gen function is used to generate the</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS AND DISCUSSIONS</head><p>This section compares the association rules discovered from the proposed REMMAR algorithm to the reference Apriori method, and whether the former is superior at satisfying the biological meaning. The first part presents a brief introduction of the gene regulatory (GR) data, the protein–protein interaction (PPI) data and two yeast-related datasets that were utilized. The second part offers a comparison of the significance of rules REMMAR discovered, against of reference Apriori method, to verify with the PPI network. The third part displays the discovered rules that are verified with biological literatures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Datasets</head><p>The GR and PPI data of S.cerevisiae were obtained from the Saccharomyces Genome Database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Cherry et al., 1998</ref>). The GRN is composed of 5331 genes interacting with one another via 143 668 transcriptional regulation interactions. The protein–protein interaction network (PPIN) comprises 5603 proteins interacting with one another via 85 622 protein physical interactions. To the best of our knowledge, the microarray profile can be conducted in the three major experiments involving temporal, duplicate and perturbation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">McIntosh and Chawla, 2007</ref>). In this study, we applied our proposed method on two microarrays involving individual datasets performed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Gasch et al. (2000) and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Brem et al. (2002)</ref>. The former is a S.cerevisiae gene expression dataset on different stress in perturbation experiment, which contains a collection of 173 different stress conditions and a selection of 2993 genes. The latter is a S.cerevisiae gene expression dataset in duplicate on yeast segregation experiment. The dataset contains 6229 genes and 40 segregates with dye swap are included.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Evaluation with PPIN</head><p>In the real case study, the shortest distance between any two genes in the GRN was used as the relation importance to discover association rules. The distances of proteins that have physical interactions are defined as 1 in PPIN. Moreover, the average shortest distance (ASD) between any two proteins is 2.771 in PPIN. This section shows that the rules discovered with REMMAR have stronger biological meanings (has the shorter ASD in the PPIN) than those discovered with the reference Apriori algorithm. The focus on rules was on position where the LHS possesses only a single item, as<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Creighton and Hanash (2003)</ref>proposed, to limit the search space of candidate rules in this study. Therefore, if the rules represent their items with {gene x ↑} =&gt; {gene y ↓,gene z ↑}, the rule length (RL) is defined as 3 (RL3). In addition, if the shortest distance between gene x and gene y in PPIN is 2, then the shortest distance between gene x and gene z in PPIN is 4. Based on Equation (5), the ASD of this rule in PPIN is 3.</p><formula>Average_Shortest_Distance(S x ⇒ S y ) = 1 n n i=1 distance(x,y i )|x ∈ S x and y ∈ S y ,</formula><p>where S x and S y are itemsets, n is the number of items in S y</p><formula>(5)</formula><p>We conducted a novel method named REMMAR, which automatically adjusted two arguments involving IMC and IMS. To prove that our improvement is significant, we set IMC of our method as 80%, which is same as the minimum confidence value introduced in the primitive Apriori algorithm of a previous approach (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Creighton and Hanash, 2003</ref>). On the other hand, we empirically set the values of IMS and minimum support since the aim of this research is to manually evaluate the mined rules by either REMMAR or Apriori with literature. By decreasing the values (lower threasholds) of IMS for REMMAR and minimum support for Apriori, a large number of satisfied rules will be mined. This arises a big problem that comprehensive evaluations of these massive rules would be beyond our ability. On the contrary, few rules will be mined when we increased the parameter values (higher threasholds). In facing this trade-off, in this study, we set both the IMS value for REMMAR and the minimum support value for Apriori as 60% in the first dataset (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Gasch et al., 2000</ref>) and 92% in the second dataset (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Brem et al., 2002</ref>).<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>indicates the resultant rule numbers under different methods (Apriori and REMMAR) and different RLs in the first dataset. Here 'Common' represents the intersection of the results produced by Apriori and REMMAR algorithms. 'Apriori (no common)' and 'REMMAR (no common)' represent the respective results without the common intersection. In other words, all rules within the respective results are unique. From RL2 to RL7, both Apriori and REMMAR generated 42 739 (including common) and 53 616 (including common) rules, respectively. In all, 37 771 of the discovered rules appear in both generated rule sets. From RL2 to RL7, only a difference of 4968 and 15 845 rules exists. Furthermore,<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>indicates the ASD under different methods and different RLs in the first dataset. In this table, REMMAR (no common) can discover shorter ASD rules in PPIN under any RL in contrast with Apriori (no common). The ASD (2.173) of a total number of association rules mined by REMMAR (no common) is better than</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Y.-C.Liu et al.</head><p>that (2.288) of the Apriori (no common). Therefore, in the result of this dataset, REMMAR can evidently mine not only more rules, but also rules of more importance in real biological significance than traditional association rule mining methods.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>indicates the result rule numbers under different methods (Apriori and REMMAR) and different RLs in the second dataset. From RL2 to RL14, Apriori and REMMAR generated 613 799 (including common) and 541 165 (including common) rules, respectively. However, 541 133 rules are shared in both generated rule sets. Hence, from RL2 to RL14, only 72 666 and 32 rules are different. Moreover,<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>indicates the ASD under different methods and different RLs in the second dataset. In this table, REMMAR (no common) can discover shorter ASD rules in PPIN under any RL than Apriori (no common). The ASD (2.467) of a total number of association rules mined by REMMAR (no common) is better than that (2.873) of the Apriori (no common). The ASD 2.873 of Apriori (no common) is inferior to the ASD 2.771 between any two proteins in PPIN. Therefore, in the result of this dataset, REMMAR was evidently not generating many rules that have no real biological meanings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Evaluation with literature</head><p>After evaluating the correlation of associated rules with ASD in PPIN, REMMAR, proposed in this study, has a lower ASD compared with the Apriori method. Genes involved in association rules have a high probability for representing an interaction at protein level, which includes three main types: positive regulation, negative regulation or physical interaction. However, the PPIN does not contain this information. This study applied REMMAR on two yeastrelated datasets, composed of differentially expressed values ofprobes. Upregulation and downregulation of a gene in different conditions are represented as two items within a transaction database (see Section 2). Both Apriori and REMMAR algorithms generated numerous rules from these two datasets, as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Tables 1</ref>and 3. Verifying all these rules with literature is a difficult task. Therefore, if our identified rules have physical interactions in PPIN (ASD = 1), the rules whose regulations involve positive or negative regulations would be further verified with the literature. We showed the results in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_5">Table 5</ref>. In this table, we want to test whether these association rules are highly informative, especially in the biological domain. In previous studies, an increasing amount of literature has reported enormous critical regulations for gene pairs in certain conditions. These published papers were manually collected as ground truth for validating rules identified from these two datasets. In the Supplementary Material, the rules in each dataset in the beginning will be disassembled into a length of two as relations for verifying with the literature. For example, {YLL039C_Up} =&gt; {YDR074W_Up, YHR089C_Down} will be disassembled into {YLL039C_Up} =&gt; {YDR074W_Up} and {YLL039C_Up} =&gt; {YHR089C_Down} two disassembled relations. If prior studies have reported a disassembled relation, a positive serial number of corresponding papers will be assigned in its entry in the References column. On the contrary, the serial numbers in negative represent an opposite way between the relations and the statement of literature. For instance, for the first dataset results, we illustrate two relations: {YJL164C_Up} =&gt; {YPL203W_Up} and {YPL203W_Up} =&gt; {YJL164C_Up}. The former states that the overexpressed gene YPL203W is dependent on the upregulation of gene YJL164C, and</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>REMMAR</head><p>vice versa for the latter. In terms of this bidirectional regulation, these two genes may have a high cooperation or a similar function in a bioprocess. Interestingly,<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Toda et al. (1987)</ref>had identified that these two candidates can encode catalytic subunits of cAMPdependent protein kinases, and be encoded by the TPK genes in 1987. A similar result showed that these two genes play critical roles for the maintenance of iron levels (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Robertson et al., 2000</ref>). For biologists, the most important issue is how these relations provide valuable information. The REMMAR method identified a novel relation between a pair of genes; {YCR057C_Down} =&gt; {YGL171W_Down}. To date, the relation has not been reported. To check the reliability of the novel regulation relation '{YCR057C_Down} =&gt; {YGL171W_Down}' discovered in this study, we get insights into the biological functions of these two genes through a literature survey. Both proteins, YCR057C and YGL171W, have been reported in the assembly of the 90S preribosomal particle to drive the process of ribosome biosynthesis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dosil and Bustelo, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Grandi et al., 2002</ref>). Moreover, it has also been reported that they played functional roles involved in rRNA biogenesis in the nucleolus (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Dragon et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Venema and Tollervey, 1999</ref>). However, to the best of our knowledge, it has yet been reported that both proteins directly regulate each other even though they would colocalize with ribosomes and nucleolus. Therefore, we can provide biologists with this kind of gene regulation relation with high reliance in validation. Moreover, it has been reported that YCR057C could predominantly accumulate in a complex with YJL069C (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dosil and Bustelo, 2004</ref>). This relation can also be found in our results. Hence, this study provides a novel relation for gene pairs among a total number of 34 disassembled relations. All remaining relations in the two datasets coincided with previous studies in certain conditions of yeast species. Therefore, when comparing to the reference algorithm in this study, the advantages of applying REMMAR to automatically adjust MRS yield a precision of 100% (33/33, without considering the novel one), rather than Apriori's 87.5% (7/8). We can find an incorrect disassembled relation, {YPL154C_Up} =&gt; {YMR174C_Up}, which does not correspond to the contents of previous literature because Pai3p (YMR174C) was reported as a specific Pep4p (YPL154C) inhibitor (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Phylip et al., 2001</ref>). However, since a pair of genes with long distance may involve in different pathways or play entirely different roles in a cell, we only verified the part of both methods that identified distinctive rules, whose ASD values are equal to 1 in PPIN. If the ASD of an identified rule is &gt;1, this rule would not be considered for verification in this study. Definitely, there exist putative gene regulations that have yet been identified. Besides, all the rules and disassembled relations evaluated with literature are unique, as shown in the Supplementary Material. In fact, we found 33 verified disassembled relations that did not appear in the results by the reference Apriori algorithm. The results of this study suggest that the REMMAR method has a significant improvement, which can identify more association genes from microarray data.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Example of transforming gene expression data into transaction data format.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. An example of GRN.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. An example of gene shortest distance matrix retrieved from the GRN of Figure 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>2.</head><figDesc>Average shortest distance of rules in PPIN under different methods and RL in the first dataset RL2 RL3 RL4 RL5 RL6 RL7 Total Apriori (no common) 2.384 2.292 2.311 2.271 2.222 2.178 2.288 Common 2.271 2.181 2.149 2.112 2.087 2.089 2.160 REMMAR (no common) 2.256 2.218 2.176 2.149 2.110 2.102 2.173</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>(frequent itemset), because strong relationships exist between items in this itemset.</figDesc><table>G1 
G2 
G3 
G4 
G5 
Sample 1 
-0.21 
0.04 
0.02 
-0.01 
-0.23 
Sample 2 
0.02 
-0.07 
0.22 
0.01 
0.07 
Sample 3 
0.03 
-0.25 
0.01 
-0.08 
0.33 
Sample 4 
0.08 
0.05 
-0.03 
0.03 
-0.06 

G1 G2 G3 G4 G5 G1 G2 G3 G4 G5 
Sample 1 0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
1 
0 
0 
0 
1 
Sample 2 0 
0 
1 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
Sample 3 0 
0 
0 
0 
1 
0 
1 
0 
0 
0 
Sample 4 0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>The maximum shortest distance (Max_Dist), minimum shortest distance (Min_Dist) and average shortest distance (</figDesc><table>Avg_Dist) of this matrix are 3, 1 and 1.7, respectively. Suppose the 
user-specified IMS is 20%, and the shortest distance between G2 and G4 is 1 
[Dist(G2↑,G4↑) = Dist(G2↑,G4↓) = Dist(G2↓,G4↑) = Dist(G2↓,G4↓) = 1]. 
Depending on Equation (1), G2 and G4 can get the MRS to 17.55% 
[MRS(G2↑,G4↑) = MRS(G2↑,G4↓) = MRS(G2↓,G4↑) = MRS(G2↓,G4 ↓) 
= 17.55%]</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><figDesc>=candidate-gen(L k−1 ) 8. for all transactions t in D do 9. C t =subset(C k ,t) 10. for all candidates c in C t do</figDesc><table>Algorithm REMMAR 
1. for(k = 1;L k−1 = φ;k ++) do 
2. if (k = 1) then 
3. 
for all transactions t in database D do 
4. 
L 1 ={c in C 1 |c.count&gt;=c.IMS} 
5. 
end 
6. else 
7. 
C k 11. 
c.count++ 
12. 
end 
13. 
end 
14. end 
15. L k ={c in C k |c.count&gt;=c.MRS} 
16. end 
17. Answer=U k L k 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><figDesc>candidate k-itemsets in C k based on the large k −1itemsets in L k−1. Page: 3145 3142–3148 REMMAR candidate-gen insert into C k select p.item 1 , p.item 2 , …, p.item k−1 , q.item k−1 from L k−1 p, L k−1 q where p.item 1 =q.item 1 , …, p.item k−2 =q.item k−2 , p.item k−1 &lt;q.item k−1 The subset function will utilize the candidate itemsets generated from the candidate-gen function, to count the support of each candidate k-itemset. If the candidate itemsets from C k are the subset of a transaction t, it will be defined as C t (candidate itemsets in transaction t). The support of itemsets from C t will then be incremented by 1. Each transaction t will be scanned once to measure the support of C k dependent on the Subset function when each level of C k has been generated. Subset 1. Subset_collection=φ 2. for each itemset c in C k 3. if c is subset of t 4. Subset_collection= Subset_collection Uc 5. return Subset_collection</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1.</figDesc><table>Rule number comparison under different methods and RL in the 
first dataset 

RL2 RL3 
RL4 
RL5 RL6 RL7 Total 

Apriori (no common) 
242 
668 1813 1679 522 44 
4968 
Common 
3307 11 519 14 438 7062 1372 73 37 771 
REMMAR (no common) 281 3476 6078 4611 1253 146 15 845 </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="false"><figDesc>Table</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 5. Rule number comparison under different methods and RLs in the first and second datasets</figDesc><table>First dataset 
Second dataset 

RL2 RL3 RL4 RL5 Total RL2 Total 

Apriori (no common) 
8 
0 
0 
0 
8 0 
0 
Common 
104 34 
8 
2 
148 2 
2 
REMMAR (no common) 14 14 
5 
0 
33 2 
2 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 3.</figDesc><table>Rule number comparison under different methods and RLs in the second dataset 

RL2 
RL3 
RL4 
RL5 
RL6 
RL7 
RL8 
RL9 
RL10 
RL11 RL12 RL13 RL14 Total 

Apriori (no common) 
140 
1059 
3620 
7895 
12 366 
14 651 13 568 
9999 
5820 2574 
804 156 
14 
72 666 
Common 
1524 11 001 40 200 87 520 124 086 121 121 84 976 44 739 18 400 5940 1404 208 
14 
541 133 
REMMAR (no common) 
32 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
3 2 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 4. Average shortest distance of rules in PPIN under different methods and RLs in the second dataset</figDesc><table>RL2 
RL3 
RL4 
RL5 
RL6 
RL7 
RL8 
RL9 
RL10 
RL11 
RL12 
RL13 
RL14 
Total 

Apriori (no common) 
2.636 
2.741 
2.791 
2.834 
2.865 
2.886 
2.896 
2.897 
2.890 
2.878 
2.867 
2.856 
2.846 
2.873 
Common 
2.694 
2.724 
2.744 
2.760 
2.774 
2.787 
2.799 
2.808 
2.816 
2.821 
2.825 
2.829 
2.835 
2.780 
REMMAR (no common) 
2.467 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
2.467 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>In this study, we proposed the REMMAR algorithm to tackle the inefficiency of previous methods, which never took into account the importance of each item. Moreover, for discovering more meaningful rules in biology, the proposed REMMAR would adjust the MRS for each individual gene pair according to the intensities of two neighboring genes in the PPIN. Not only did we improve the traditional association algorithm with a multiple support mechanism called REMMAR, but it was also applied on two yeast datasets for mining association genes in different conditions. The shortest distance between any two genes in the GRN was used as the relation importance in this study. In the first part of the result evaluation, the proposed method not only generated more rules with stronger relation intensity, but also filtered rules without biological meaning in the PPIN. In the second part of the evaluation, the part of the discovered rules was verified with biological literature. The proposed method has a precision of 100%, whereas the reference Apriori method exhibits a precision of 87.5%. Therefore, the proposed method is more effective in helping biologists explore the relationships of biological activities.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mining association rules between sets of items in large databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Agrawal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data</title>
		<meeting>the ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data<address><addrLine>Washington, D.C., USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="216" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast algorithms for mining association rules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Agrawal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Srikant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on Very Large Data Bases</title>
		<meeting>the 20th International Conference on Very Large Data Bases<address><addrLine>Santiago de Chile, Chile</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="487" to="499" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene association analysis: a survey of frequent pattern mining from gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Alves</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="210" to="224" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SVM based method for predicting HLADRB1*0401 binding peptides in an antigen sequence</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Bhasin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P S</forename>
				<surname>Raghava</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="421" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic dissection of transcriptional regulation in budding yeast</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Brem</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">296</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="752" to="755" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mining association rules with weighted items</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Cai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Database Engineering and Applications Symposium</title>
		<meeting>the International Database Engineering and Applications Symposium<address><addrLine>Cardiff, Wales, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="68" to="77" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biclustering of expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Cheng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Church</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology</title>
		<meeting>the 8th International Conference on Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology<address><addrLine>Menlo Park, California, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>AAAI Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="103" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SGD: Saccharomyces Genome Database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Cherry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mining gene expression databases for association rules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Creighton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hanash</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional characterization of Pwp2, a WD family protein essential for the assembly of the 90 S pre-ribosomal particle</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Dosil</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Bustelo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37385" to="37397" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A large nucleolar U3 ribonucleoprotein required for 18S ribosomal RNA biogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Dragon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">417</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="967" to="970" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic expression programs in the response of yeast cells to environmental changes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Gasch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4241" to="4257" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing microarray data using quantitative association rules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Georgii</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">90S pre-ribosomes include the 35S pre-rRNA, the U3 snoRNP, and 40S subunit processing factors but predominantly lack 60S synthesis factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Grandi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cluster analysis for gene expression data: a survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Jiang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Knowl. Data Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1370" to="1386" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mining association rules with multiple minimum supports</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Fifth ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining</title>
		<meeting>the Fifth ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="341" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A genetic programming-based approach to the classification of multiclass microarray datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Xu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="337" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biclustering algorithms for biological data analysis: a survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Madeira</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Oliveira</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Comput. Biol. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classification of microarray data with factor mixture models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Martella</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="202" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1410</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3148" to="3142" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y.-C</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GenMiner: mining non-redundant association rules from integrated gene expression data and annotations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Martinez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2643" to="2644" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High confidence rule mining for microarray analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Mcintosh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Chawla</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Trans. Comput. Biol. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="611" to="623" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MaPle: a fast algorithm for maximal pattern-based clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Pei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 3rd IEEE International Conference on Data Mining</title>
		<meeting>the 3rd IEEE International Conference on Data Mining<address><addrLine>Melbourne, Florida, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="266" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The potency and specificity of the interaction between the IA3 inhibitor and its target aspartic proteinase from Saccharomyces cerevisiae</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Phylip</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">276</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2023" to="2030" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic comparison and evaluation of biclustering methods for gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Prelic</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1122" to="1129" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Weighted association rules: model and algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Ramkumar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Fifth ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining</title>
		<meeting>the Fifth ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The yeast A kinases differentially regulate iron uptake and respiratory function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Robertson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5984" to="5988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effective ranking and recommendation on web page retrieval by integrating association mining and Pagerank</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Su</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Workshop on Optimization-Based Data Mining and Web Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the Workshop on Optimization-Based Data Mining and Web Intelligence<address><addrLine>Sydney, NSW, Australia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="455" to="458" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Weighted association rule mining using weighted support and significance framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Tao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Ninth ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining</title>
		<meeting>the Ninth ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining<address><addrLine>Washington, DC, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="661" to="666" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation and comparison of gene clustering methods in microarray analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Thalamuthu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2405" to="2412" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three different genes in S. cerevisiae encode the catalytic subunits of the cAMP-dependent protein kinase</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Toda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="287" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UP-Growth: an efficient algorithm for high utility itemsets Mining</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Tseng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 16th ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining</title>
		<meeting>the 16th ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining<address><addrLine>Washington, DC, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="262" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ribosome synthesis in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Venema</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Tollervey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="261" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient mining of weighted association rules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the sixth ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining</title>
		<meeting>the sixth ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining<address><addrLine>Boston, MA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="270" to="274" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WFIM: weighted itemset mining with a weight range and a minimum weight</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<surname>Yun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Leggett</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the SIAM International Data Mining Conference. Society of Industrial and Applied Mathematics</title>
		<meeting>the SIAM International Data Mining Conference. Society of Industrial and Applied Mathematics<address><addrLine>Newport Beach, California, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="270" to="274" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>