
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:54+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Drug-set enrichment analysis: a novel tool to investigate drug mode of action</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Francesco</forename>
								<surname>Napolitano</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Systems and Synthetic Biology Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Telethon Institute of Genetics and Medicine (TIGEM)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>80078</postCode>
									<settlement>Pozzuoli</settlement>
									<region>NA</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Francesco</forename>
								<surname>Sirci</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Systems and Synthetic Biology Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Telethon Institute of Genetics and Medicine (TIGEM)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>80078</postCode>
									<settlement>Pozzuoli</settlement>
									<region>NA</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Diego</forename>
								<surname>Carrella</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Systems and Synthetic Biology Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Telethon Institute of Genetics and Medicine (TIGEM)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>80078</postCode>
									<settlement>Pozzuoli</settlement>
									<region>NA</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Diego</forename>
								<surname>Di Bernardo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Systems and Synthetic Biology Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Telethon Institute of Genetics and Medicine (TIGEM)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>80078</postCode>
									<settlement>Pozzuoli</settlement>
									<region>NA</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering and Information Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Naples Federico II</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>80125</postCode>
									<settlement>Naples</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Drug-set enrichment analysis: a novel tool to investigate drug mode of action</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv536</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 27, 2015; revised on July 28, 2015; accepted on September 3, 2015</note>
					<note>Systems biology *To whom correspondence should be addressed Associate Editor: Janet Kelso Contact: dibernardo@tigem.it Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Automated screening approaches are able to rapidly identify a set of small molecules inducing a desired phenotype from large small-molecule libraries. However, the resulting set of candidate molecules is usually very diverse pharmacologically, thus little insight on the shared mechanism of action (MoA) underlying their efficacy can be gained. Results: We introduce a computational method (Drug-Set Enrichment Analysis—DSEA) based on drug-induced gene expression profiles, which is able to identify the molecular pathways that are targeted by most of the drugs in the set. By diluting drug-specific effects unrelated to the phenotype of interest, DSEA is able to highlight phenotype-specific pathways, thus helping to formulate hypotheses on the MoA shared by the drugs in the set. We validated the method by analysing five different drug-sets related to well-known pharmacological classes. We then applied DSEA to identify the MoA shared by drugs known to be partially effective in rescuing mutant cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR) gene function in Cystic Fibrosis. Availability and implementation: The method is implemented as an online web tool publicly available at http://dsea.tigem.it.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Large collections of small-molecules can be automatically screened against a desired phenotypic effect. Automated experimental screening approaches include high-content screening (HCS) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bickle, 2010</ref>) and high-throughput screening (HTS) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bajorath, 2002</ref>), with different advantages and limitations, and a screening capacity that ranges from thousands to millions of compounds per assay. Screening assays can be performed either to identify lead compounds binding a specific molecular target, or inducing a specific phenotype of interest. A common drawback of automated molecular screening is the opacity of the hit compound selection mechanism. Indeed, the set of positive hits following an HTS or HCS typically includes small-molecules with unknown mode-of-action (MoA) or whose MoA are so different from each other, that no hint on the shared molecular mechanisms underlying their efficacy can be gained (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Sams-Dodd, 2005</ref>). The difficulty in characterizing a set of screening hits resides in the complexity of their interactions within the cell. Molecules binding the same molecular target can induce different phenotypes caused by unknown off-targets. On the contrary, molecules binding different targets can induce the same phenotype, when they act in the same pathway (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Sams-Dodd, 2005</ref>). Nonetheless, among the heterogeneous effects induced by the hit compounds in the cell, there could exist a common mechanism responsible for their efficacy in the screening selection. Here, we introduce a new method, named drug-set Enrichment Analysis (DSEA), that aims at identifying the mechanism(s) of action shared by a set of compounds in terms of the molecular pathways targeted by all, or most of them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>235</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com<ref type="bibr">Bioinformatics, 32(2), 2016, 235</ref>–241 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv536</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Advance Access Publication Date: 28 September 2015 Original Paper</head><p>We define a pathway as a set of genes. We collected a large database of pathways by merging nine different publicly available collections, including generic gene sets (co-localized genes, co-regulated genes, protein complex subunits, etc.) and disease-related gene sets. DSEA looks for shared pathways in a set of drugs by analysing transcriptional responses induced by each of the compounds of interest in one or more cell lines. To this end, we exploited the Connectivity Map (cMap,<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lamb et al., 2006</ref>) dataset consisting of about 7000 microarrays following treatment of four different cell lines with 1309 drugs. The main hypothesis underlying DSEA is that if pharmacologically different drugs induce the same phenotype of interest, then some of the molecular pathways they target must be shared by most of them. Although this is not necessarily true in general, it is a reasonable assumption. DSEA is designed to search transcriptional responses of different, but phenotypically-related, drugs for shared pathways whose genes are upregulated (or downregulated) by most of the drugs in the set. In this way, pathways relevant for the phenotype of interest should emerge, while drug-specific pathways, which are unrelated to the phenotype of interest, should cancel out. To validate the method, we thoroughly tested the ability of DSEA in identifying the shared pathways for five different drug-sets whose MoA has already been well characterized: Histone Deacetylase Inhibitors (HDIs), Cyclin Dependent Kinase Inhibitors (CDKIs), Heat Shock Protein 90 Inhibitors (HSP90Is), Topoisomerase Inhibitors (TIs), Cardiac Glycosides (CGs). Finally, we applied DSEA to a set of eleven drugs, belonging to different pharmacological classes, that have been shown to act as (weak) correctors of the mutant CFTR protein defect (DF508) causative of cystic fibrosis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data preparation</head><p>We downloaded raw data files from the cMap (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lamb et al., 2006</ref>), a compendium of 7056 Affymetrix microarrays (.CEL files) obtained with three different chipsets (HG-U133A, HT_HG-U133A, HT_HG-U133A_EA). Expression values for all the samples were computed using the R package affy v.1.40.0 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gautier et al., 2004)</ref>with MAS5 normalization. The probes of each chipset were re-annotated to 12 012 genes using the Brainarray CDF packages v.16.0.0 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dai et al., 2005</ref>). The combined matrix (12 012 Â 7056), after removing non-common (control) probes, was quantile-normalized (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1a</ref>). Fold change (FC) values were obtained as log-ratios between the values of the treatment samples and the corresponding control samples (averaged over replicates) thus reducing the data matrix to size 12 012 Â 6100. After converting FC values to ranks, we built Prototype Ranked Lists (PRLs) by merging all the samples corresponding to the same drug, as described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Iorio et al. (2010)</ref>, thus obtaining a 12 012 genes Â 1309 drugs matrix of PRLs (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">A Pathway-based connectivity map</head><p>We collected set of genes (pathways) from nine publicly available databases (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>): Biological Processes (GO-BP), Molecular Function (GO-MF) and Cellular Component (GO-CC) from BioMart (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Durinck et al., 2009</ref>), excluding pathways with less than 5 or more than 500 genes, KEGG, Reactome, Biocarta, Canonical Pathways, Genetic and Chemical Perturbation (as collected in<ref type="bibr">MSigDB, Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>) and MIPS Corum (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Ruepp et al., 2010</ref>). For each gene set, we removed the genes not included in the set of 12012 Affymetrix probe-mapped genes. In addition, we defined a gene-based collection (Single-Gene Sets, SGS) by building 12 012 fictitious gene sets containing only one gene. We provided this addition database just as a resource for the user who wishes to perform DSEA analysis in a gene-wise fashion, although we discourage its use being DSEA designed to work with gene-sets rather than single genes. To convert the 12 012 genes Â 1309 drugs PRL matrix to a pathway-oriented matrix, we proceeded as follows: given a pathway database of interest, for each pathway i in the database, and each PRL j, we computed a signed Enrichment Score ES ij and a p-value using the Kolmogorov–Smirnov (KS) test (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>). The two-sample KS statistic is defined as the maximum distance between two empirical distribution functions. Along the lines of the Gene Set Enrichment Analysis method (GSEA,<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>), we apply a signed version of the KS statistic to compare gene ranks. The ES associated with the KS statistic is thus defined as follows:</p><formula>ES ¼ supjF 1 À F 2 j Á sðF 1 ; F 2 Þ (1)</formula><p>where F 1 and F 2 are the two empirical distribution functions corresponding to the ranks of the genes included in a set of interest (F 1 ) against those that are not included (F 2 ), and s is a function returning – 1 or þ 1 according to the sign of F 1 À F 2 at the point where their absolute difference is maximal. Note that a P-value for the KS test can be computed analytically without resorting to random permutations. In particular, we used our signed variant (available online at https:// github.com/franapoli/signed-ks-test) of the R function ks.test tocompute the signed KS statistic (and the corresponding p-values, used in the next Subsection). We thus obtained, for each database, one Enrichment Score matrix ES whose rows correspond to pathways and whose columns correspond to drugs (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1c</ref>). In the rest of the paper, we will make two other different uses of the KS test: to compute the DSEA itself in Section 2.3, and to validate it in Section 3.2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Drug-set enrichment analysis</head><p>DSEA quantifies the extent at which a set of drugs consistently upregulates (or downregulates) one or more pathways. Starting from the ES matrix, we first sorted each row i according to the Enrichment Scores ES ij of the pathway i across the j ¼ 1. .. l drugs (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1d</ref>), obtaining a rank-based matrix R. Each element R ij in R represents the rank of drug j when sorting drugs according to their effect on pathway i. The significance of a drug-set for each pathway is assessed by applying the same procedure showed previously to compute the ES ij scores, but comparing drug ranks (distributed across the row corresponding to a given pathway) as opposed to gene ranks (distributed across the column corresponding to a given drug). In this case, the sign of the ES indicates whether a pathway is activated or inhibited by the drugs in the set. DSEA can be thought of as the dual of GSEA: if in GSEA a druginduced expression profiles can be represented as a ranked list of differentially expressed genes, in DSEA we modeled a pathway as a ranked list of drugs. From a methodological point of view, DSEA is able to highlight pathways that are significantly modulated by most of the drugs in the input drug-set relative to the other drugs in the database. This means that if drugs in a drug-set tend to modulate the same pathway more than the other drugs in the database, this pathway will be found by DSEA, even if the modulation exerted by the single drugs on the pathway is weak. This mechanism is key to identify a shared mode of action, even when it is not apparent when considering the individual drugs in the set.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Drug-set enrichment analysis (DSEA)</head><p>We developed the Drug-Set Enrichment Analysis (DSEA) algorithm in order to identify the shared molecular pathways modulated by all, or most of, the compounds in a given set. DSEA exploits a compendium (the cMap,<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lamb et al., 2006</ref>) of Gene Expression Profiles (GEPs) following treatment with 1309 small molecules (mostly FDA approved drugs). DSEA works by applying the following steps: (i)<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1a</ref>,b—GEPs for each small molecule are merged into ranked lists of differentially expressed genes (following treatment of multiple cell-lines and at different dosages) into a unique Prototype Ranked List (PRL,<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Iorio et al., 2010</ref>); (ii)<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1c—each</ref>gene-wise PRL is converted to a pathway-wise PRL, by computing the Enrichment Score (ES) of each pathway through a GSEA approach (see Section 2), using the list of genes in the pathway as the gene-set, and the gene-wise PRL as the ranked list of genes. (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>). Each pathway thus has a specific ES for each small-molecule; (iii)<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1d—the</ref>resulting pathway-by-small-molecule matrix is then sorted row-wise, so that each pathway is now associated to a ranked list of small-molecules: from the one most activating the pathway to the one most inhibiting it. Given a query-set of small-molecules, DSEA checks for each pathway whether small-molecules tend to be significantly ranked at the top (or the bottom) of the list, by applying a Kolmogorov-Smirnov (KS) test, as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>. An Enrichment Score for the drug-set and a p-value can thus be computed for each pathway exactly, without the need of random permutations. The final output of DSEA is a list of pathways ranked by the KS P-value, which are significantly modulated by the majority of the small-molecules in the drug-set.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Validation</head><p>To validate the method, we applied DSEA to five drug-sets consisting of compounds belonging to five distinct pharmacological classes, as summarized in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. Prior knowledge about each drug-set allowed us to assess whether the shared pathways found by DSEA within each class were correct.We also added a collection of fictitious sets each containing a single gene from the 12012 obtained after probe reannotation of the cMap raw data. We collected existing gene sets from a number of publicly available databases.DSEA performs a statistical test to assess whether the drugs in a set are significantly ranked at top (or bottom) of the row corresponding to a given pathway. Each row is ranked according to how much the drug in the column upregualtes (or downregulates) the genes in the pathway. The toy example shows how a set of three drugs is found to consistently downregulate one pathway (top arrow), while upregulating another one (bottom arrow)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Drug-set enrichment analysis</head><p>To this end, we defined a golden standard for each drug-set as follows: we selected the known target gene for each drug-set (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). For drugs with more than one known target, we chose the first member (alphabetical order) of the target protein family. In the case of Topoisomerase Inhibitor (TI) drug-set, we chose TOP2 because six out of nine drugs in the set were TOP2 inhibitors. For the Histone Deacetylase Inhibitor (HDI) drug-set, we chose HAT1 in addition to HDAC1. For each drug-set, we then added to the golden-standard all the Gene Ontology (GO) pathways containing the chosen drug target. A summary of the golden standard for each drug-set is reported in Suppl.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>. To evaluate the performance of DSEA, we checked whether the golden-standard pathways were significantly enriched at the top of the ranked list of pathways given as output by DSEA by applying again a KS test. As shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>, for each drug-set, DSEA ranked the golden-standard pathways significantly at least in one GO database. Suppl.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table S3</ref>shows the same type of validation for each of the 10 pathway databases. Interestingly for the HDI drug-set, when using HDAC1 as the target gene for the golden standard pathways, we did not find any significant enrichment, however when using the dual enzyme, HAT1, we did find the golden standard pathways to be significantly shared by the drugs in the drug-set (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>). These pathways are related to the process complementary to deacetylation, that is acetylation. The acetylation-deacetylation balance is known as acetylation homeostasis and the existence of a HAT-HDAC coupling through a common signal has been suggested (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Dokmanovic et al., 2007</ref>). In order to exclude that the results obtained in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>were due to a hidden bias in the golden standard pathways, we generated for each of the 5 drug-sets, 1000 random drug-sets with the same size as the corresponding original drug-set. We then ran DSEA on each random drug-set and checked whether the golden-standard pathways of the original drug-set were significantly enriched at the top of the resulting ranked list of pathways. Since these random drug-sets consist of unrelated drugs, the golden standard pathways should not be significantly enriched and the corresponding KS P-values should be uninformative. The results are summarized in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>. Observe that in this significance analysis, we treated p-values as random variables, thus their expected value should be close to 0.5 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Sackrowitz and Samuel-Cahn, 1999</ref>, and Suppl.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S14</ref>). It is clear from<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>that using random drug-sets, DSEA ranks the golden-standard pathways at random positions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Robustness and convergence</head><p>Hit compounds selected from automated drug screening techniques may contain false-positive hits, exhibiting a mode of action inconsistent with the other compounds in the selected set. For this reason, we investigated the effects of adding noise to the drug-sets used for validation before running DSEA. In order to assess the robustness of the method with respect to varying degrees of false-positive hits included in the drug-set, we added 1–10 random drugs to each of the 5 drug-sets and run DSEA on the resulting augmented drug-sets. More precisely, we repeated this process 1000 times thus producing a total of 5 x 10 x 1000 ¼ 50 000 perturbed drug-sets and ran DSEA on each of them. As before, we used the golden standard to evaluate the p-values for the enrichment of golden standard pathways in the ranked list given as output by DSEA. As shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>adding up to 3 random drugs to the HSP90I drug-set, i.e. 75% of the initial set size, the golden standard pathways are still significant showing the robustness of DSEA to false positives.The P-values assess if the golden-standard pathways within the GO-BP, GO-MF and GO-CC databases are ranked significantly at the top by DSEA. P-values &lt; 0.005 are highlighted in bold.Similar results were obtained for the other drug-sets: HSP90I and CG show robustness up to 75% false positives, CDKI and HDI, up to 250% and 167%, respectively. Only in the case of TIs adding a single false positive will cause the result to become not significant (refer Supplementary Figs S4–S8). We hypothesize that the sub-set of drugs in the TI drug-set not targeting TOP2 (3 out of 9 in the set) may partly contribute to decrease the robustness of DSEA in this case. To test the convergence properties of DSEA, we ran the analysis by varying the number of drugs in the drug-sets, in order to understand how many drugs were needed in order for the golden standard pathways to become significant. Specifically, for each of the five drug-sets, we generated all the possible combinations of subsets of one drug, two drugs and so on, up the total number of drugs in the drug-set, and then ran DSEA on each subset.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref>shows the results for the HDI drug-set. It can be observed how the P-value of the golden-standard pathways exponentially decreases when more drugs are included in the drug-set, thus demonstrating the power of DSEA in finding pathways shared in common by multiple drugs. We also demonstrated that the same convergence property holds across the other four drug-sets (Supplementary Figs S9–S13).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Example of application to antineoplastic agents</head><p>The cMap data were generated from experiments on cancer cell lines. The multi-factorial nature of cancer is reflected by the heterogeneity of the pharmacological approaches to its treatment. The World Health Organization (WHO) defined 5 main categories of antineoplastic agents: Alkylating agents, damaging DNA to impair replication; Antimetabolites, interfering with cancer cell metabolism; Alkaloids, causing metaphase arrest; Cytotoxic antibiotics and related substances, mainly affecting the function or synthesis of nucleic acids; other, with different known or unknown mode of action. We tested the ability of the DSEA in finding a common effect across all the drugs in the cMap that have been annotated as antineoplastic agents (code L01) by the WHO. The drug-set includes 23 drugs unevenly distributed across the five different subclasses. DSEA ranked in the GO-BP database as the most significant pathway (out of 3262): DNA damage response, signal transduction by p53 class mediator resulting in cell cycle arrest. This result is in line with the common mode of action of antineoplastic drugs, particularly alkylating agents, which are the most enriched class of drugs in this drug-set. The result of the analysis for all of the pathways is available as Supplementary Data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Application to cystic fibrosis: correctors of DF508-CFTR trafficking defects</head><p>CF is one of the most common genetic diseases among people of Caucasian origin (O'<ref type="bibr">Sullivan and Freedman, 2009</ref>). It mostly affects lungs causing inflammation, tissue scarring and severe breathing difficulties, thus substantially impacting the patient life-span and quality of life. CF is caused by mutations in the gene coding for the CFTR (CF transmembrane conductance regulator) protein. The most frequent mutation is the deletion of phenylalanine 508 (DF508). Wild-type CFTR translocates to the plasma membrane where it acts as a chloride channel. Mutant DF508CFTR is unable to fold correctly and, although partially functional, it is tagged for degradation (O'<ref type="bibr">Sullivan and Freedman, 2009</ref>). No therapeutic treatment is currently available for this disorder. Nevertheless, thanks to world-wide efforts of the academic and industrial research community, some drugs with a mild 'corrector' activity for DF508CFTR have been found, largely by HTS studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hanrahan et al., 2013</ref>). However, each of these compounds has a different known MoA, completely unrelated to CFTR function. Hence, the mechanism by which these drugs are able to correct DF508CFTR function are unknown. To test the usefulness of DSEA in a 'real-life' scenario, we applied DSEA to a drug-set consisting of drugs reported to act as DF508-CFTR correctors in Cystic Fibrosis (CF). We included 11 drugs in the drug-set (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>) according to the following criteria: (i) a DF508CFTR corrector activity is reported in</p><formula>0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1.0</formula><p>Number of random drugs added (ratio to initial size) Ranks of target pathways (p value)</p><formula>0 ( 0 .0 0 ) 1 ( 0 .2 5 ) 2 ( 0 .5 0 ) 3 ( 0 .7 5 ) 4 ( 1 .0 0 ) 5 ( 1 .2 5 ) 6 ( 1 .5 0 ) 7 ( 1 .7 5 ) 8 ( 2 .0 0 ) 9 ( 2 .2 5 ) 1 0 ( 2 .5 0 )</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HSP90 Inhibitors (GO BP)</head><p>Fig. 4. DSEA Robustness. Golden-standard pathways' significance (P-values on the y-axis) for the HSP90I drug-set with an increasing number of random drugs (reported on the x axis) added to the drug-set. The horizontal line indicates the 0.05 significance threshold. DSEA correctly identifies the goldenstandard pathways even when up to three random drugs are added to the drug-set (75% of the drug-set)Drug-set enrichment analysisliterature, and (ii) GEPs were available in the cMap dataset. As expected these drugs are very heterogenous and no obvious relation to the correction of the DF508CFTR trafficking defects exists. DSEA results for the GO-BP, GO-MF, GO-CC databases are reported in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_5">Table 5</ref>and for all the other pathway databases in online Supplementary Data. Strikingly the most significant pathway ranked in the GO-CC database according to DSEA is the chloride channel complex. This gene-set comprises 38 genes, including CFTR itself. Hence, DSEA predicts that one mode of action shared in common by the 11 drugs is the upregulation of chloride channel genes' expression (since the ES score associated to chloride channel complex for the drug-set is positive as reported in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_5">Table 5</ref>). Note that this effect would have never been detected by analysing GEPs of each individual drug separately, as the median rank of the chloride channel complex across the 11 drugs is 196. The 11 drugs belong to very different pharmacological classes, therefore the effect on the chloride channel gene expression is detected by DSEA only because it is a common 'side-effect' shared by most of them. To assess whether the DSEA-predicted shared MoA, i.e. up regulation of chloride channel genes is reasonable, we searched the literature of each of these drugs for evidence of chloride channel gene upregulation. Known effects on CFTR expression have been reported for cardiac glycosides (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Srivastava et al., 2004</ref>, Strophanthidin in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_5">Table 5</ref>), HDAC inhibitors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hutt et al., 2010</ref>, Entinostat, Scriptaid, Tricostatin-A) and Doxorubicin, a topoisomerase inhibitor (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Maitra et al., 2001</ref>). These observations support the results of the DSEA analysis. Additional signalling pathways, which are known regulators of ion channels activity, are also notable in the DSEA results, such as hormone activity, insulin receptor substrate binding, cytokine activity, which are ranked 2, 5, 9, in GO-CC; and signal recognition particle, ranked 4 in GO-CC. We also investigated expected pathways which were not found by DSEA. Of interest is the absence of references to protein folding<ref type="bibr">et al., 2007</ref>) Antibiotics Inhibits bacterial protein synthesis by preventing peptidyl transferase activity. Chlorzoxazone (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Carlile et al., 2007</ref>) Muscle Relaxants Inhibits degranulation of mast cells and prevents the release of histamine and slow-reacting substance of anaphylaxis. Dexamethasone (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Caohuy et al., 2009</ref>) Glucocorticoid Agonists Its anti-inflammatory properties are thought to involve phospholipase A2 inhibitory proteins, lipocortins. Doxorubicin (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Maitra et al., 2001</ref>) Topoisomerase Inhibitors DNA intercalator stabilizing the DNA-topoisomerase II complex. Glafenine (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Robert et al., 2010</ref>) NSAID Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory. An anthranilic acid derivative with analgesic properties. Liothyronine (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Carlile et al., 2007</ref>) Synthetic hormones Increases the basal metabolic rate, affect protein synthesis and increase the body's sensitivity to catecholamines. Entinostat (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hutt et al., 2010</ref>) HDAC Inhibitors Inhibits preferentially HDAC 1, also HDAC 3. Scriptaid (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hutt et al., 2010</ref>) HDAC Inhibitors Inhibits HDAC1, HDAC3 and HDAC8. Strophanthidin (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Carlile et al., 2007</ref>) Cardiac Glycosides Inhibits Na þ /K þ ATPase. Also known to inhibit the interaction of MDM2 and MDMX. Thapsigargin (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Egan et al., 2002</ref>) Calcium Channel Blockers Inhibits non-competitively the sarco/endoplasmic Ca 2þ ATPase. Trichostatin-A (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hutt et al., 2010</ref>) HDAC Inhibitors Inhibits HDAC1, HDAC3, HDAC8 and HDAC7.The top-ranking GO-CC gene set, chloride channel complex, clearly identifies the main common feature of the chosen drug-set. The top 10 enriched pathways according to DSEA for each GO category resulting from the analysis of the 11 small molecules reported as DF508CFTR-correctors. and ER quality control pathways, which seems to exclude a direct role of these 11 drugs as chemical chaperons. Experimental validations would certainly help in confirming the validity of our hypothesis. However, a more in-depth experimental analysis of these drugs falls out of the scope of our work. Overall these results confirm the usefulness of this new approach when investigating the shared MoA among a set of unrelated drugs resulting from automated screening efforts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusions</head><p>We introduced DSEA, a computational approach to help elucidating the mechanism of action of a set of drugs resulting from automated screening techniques, also available online at http://dsea.tigem.it. Hit compounds are selected from automated screening if they are able to induce a phenotype of interest. Usually, these selected drugs belong to different pharmacological classes, therefore the molecular mechanisms mediating their effectiveness on the screened phenotype is not immediately obvious. DSEA aims at identifying these mechanisms by looking for recurrent pathways modulated by most of drugs in the set. This is achieved by analysing the transcriptional response elicited by drugs, as available in the cMap database. With DSEA, we present a new perspective in which drugs represent features of pathways (or genes). The most relevant pathway is thus the one that is most dysregulated by the drugs in the set, as compared with the other drugs in the database. The DSEA analysis is thus able to highlight pathways that are targeted by most of the drugs in the set. Applying DSEA after an automated screening study can thus support the formulation of hypotheses explaining the efficacy of the positive hits. Beyond High Content Screening, a broad range of drug set generating applications that could take advantage of the DSEA can be imagined. Similarity based methods, like Transcriptional Drug Networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Carrella et al., 2014</ref>) or Virtual Screening (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bajorath, 2002</ref>) could exploit DSEA to provide additional biological insights about a drug neighbourhood. Prior knowledge about drugs can be another method to define drug sets. In fact, it is the method we used to define the drug sets for the cancer and cystic fibrosis examples. In particular, for the cancer application, we defined a set by simply using ATC codes. Although a very heterogeneous class of drugs was analyzed, the DSEA highlighted, as top in GO-BP, a pathway that is very related to mechanisms of action commonly used by antineoplastic agents. In the case of the cystic fibrosis application, instead, we derived the set of DF508CFTR correctors by searching relevant literature. DSEA provided a possible explanation of their corrective effect as mediated by overexpression of CFTR and other chloride channel genes. It is worth observing that expression profiles in cMap were mostly obtained in MCF7 cells, which are very different from bronchial epithelial cells where CFTR is active. Nevertheless, also in this case DSEA was able to detect a strong signal related to the chloride channel complex, which was ranked as the first most significant pathway in the GO-CC category. The DSEA method was developed and has been validated in a pharmacological context. However, it can be used to analyse any biological condition inducing a measurable transcriptional phenotype, including different cell types, diseases and genetic perturbations. Moreover, the method can be easily applied to other experimental techniques, such as RNA-seq. The DSEA web site provides all the raw and processed data used by the tool, together with pointers to external gene set databases. Moreover, relevant code is maintained on GitHub (https://github.com/franapoli/signed-ks-test). These resources are meant to facilitate the expansion of the DSEA database of pathways and profiles, to encourage further development of the methods and to ensure replicability of our results.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Data preparation pipeline. (a) Raw genome wide expression profiles are collected from the cMap and preprocessed. (b) Control-treatment fold change values are computed and converted to ranks. Profiles referring to the same small molecule in different experimental conditions are merged together. (c) Gene expression ranks are converted to pathway Enrichment Scores. (d) The ESs are converted to row-wise ranks</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. The DSEA method. Pathways are defined as ranked lists of drugs. DSEA performs a statistical test to assess whether the drugs in a set are significantly ranked at top (or bottom) of the row corresponding to a given pathway. Each row is ranked according to how much the drug in the column upregualtes (or downregulates) the genes in the pathway. The toy example shows how a set of three drugs is found to consistently downregulate one pathway (top arrow), while upregulating another one (bottom arrow)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Golden-standard pathways significance for random drug-sets. The box-plots show DSEA validation against the golden-standard when using 1000 random drug-sets containing the same number of drugs as in the original drug-sets. The horizontal line indicates the 0.05 significance threshold. The P-value obtained by chance is close to 0.5, as expected (black segment in each box shows the median P-value)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. DSEA Convergence. Golden-standard pathways' significance (P-values on the y axis) for subsets of the HDI drug-set (subset size on the x axis). The horizontal line indicates the 0.05 significance threshold. For HDI subsets greater than 3, DSEA ranks the golden-standard pathways significantly (P &lt; 0.05)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1. Gene set databases currently supported by DSEA</figDesc><table>Source 
Name 
Description 
</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2. Drug-sets chosen to validate the DSEA method Column 1: Pharmacological class; column 2: molecular processes known to be targeted by the drugs; column 3: Drugs in the set; column 4: targets chosen for the validation process (see main text). A golden-standard was designed for each pharmacological class by collecting all the pathways containing the corresponding gene shown in the last column.</figDesc><table>Drug-set 
Affected activity 
Phrmacological class 
Validation target 

Histone deacetylase inhibitors (HDI) 
Transcription 
Scriptaid, trichostatin A, valproic acid, vorinostat, HC toxin, 
bufexamac 

HAT1 

Cyclin dependant kKinase inhibitors (CDKI) 
Cell cycle 
Alsterpaullone, GW-8510, H-7, staurosporine 
CDK1 
Heat shock protein 90 inhibitors (HSP90I) 
Protein folding 
Geldanamycin, monorden, tanespimycin, alvespimycin 
HSP90AA1 
Topoisomerase inhibitors (TI) 
Cell cycle 
Doxorubicin, etoposide, camptothecin, irinotecan, genistein, 
ofloxacin, Mitoxantrone, flumequine, luteolin 

TOP2A/B 

Cardiac glycosides (CG) 
Na þ -K þ pump 
Digitoxigenin, digoxigenin, digoxin, ouabain 
ATP1A1 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 3.</figDesc><table>Validation results 

GO-BP 
GO-MF 
GO-CC 

CDKI 
1:34E À6 
0.2834 
0.1407 
HDI 
0.3483 
0:0007 
0.5182 
HSP90I 
0:0065 
0.64 
0.1582 
TI 
0:03868 
0.1556 
0.6597 
CG 
0:002 
0.3764 
0.2673 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 4. Drugs with a DF508CFTR corrector activity according to the literature</figDesc><table>Drug 
Class 
Use / MoA 

Chloramphenicol (Carlile </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 5.</figDesc><table>Top 10 enriched pathways for DF508CFTR-correctors 

GO-BP 
GO-MF 
GO-CC 
# 
Term 
ES 
P 
Term 
ES 
P 
Term 
ES 
P 

1 
Natural killer cell activation 
0.68 7 Á 10 À5 Metallocarboxypepti-
dase activity 

0.62 5 Á 10 À4 Chloride channel complex 
0.62 4 Á 10 À4 

2 
Potassium ion export 
0.68 8 Á 10 À5 Hormone activity 
0.60 8 Á 10 À4 Dendrite membrane 
0.59 8 Á 10 À4 
3 
Smooth muscle contraction 
0.67 1 Á 10 À4 4 Iron, 4 sulfur cluster 
binding 

À0.59 1 Á 10 À3 mRNA cleavage factor 
complex 

À0.58 1 Á 10 À3 

4 
Positive regulation of IL-8 
biosynthetic process 

0.65 2 Á 10 À4 Heparin binding 
0.57 1 Á 10 À3 Signal recognition particle 
0.57 2 Á 10 À3 

5 
Positive regulation of cAMP-
mediated signaling 

0.62 4 Á 10 À4 Insulin receptor 
substrate binding 

À0.57 2 Á 10 À3 Axonemal dynein complex 
0.56 2 Á 10 À3 

6 
Keratinocyte differentiation 
0.62 5 Á 10 À4 Exonuclease activity 
À0.57 2 Á 10 À3 Nuclear membrane 
À0.56 2 Á 10 À3 
7 
Potassium ion transport 
0.61 5 Á 10 À4 DNA N-glycosylase 
activity 

À0.55 2 Á 10 À3 Transcription factor TFIIIC 
complex 

À0.56 2 Á 10 À3 

8 
Regulation of pH 
0.61 5 Á 10 À4 Mitogen-activated 
protein kinase 
kinase binding 

À0.55 3 Á 10 À3 Cell surface 
0.55 3 Á 10 À3 

9 
Interferon-gamma 
production 

0.61 6 Á 10 À4 Cytokine activity 
0.55 3 Á 10 À3 Voltage-gated potassium 
channel complex 

0.54 3 Á 10 À3 

10 
GABA signaling pathway 
0.60 7 Á 10 À4 Spindle 
À0.55 3 Á 10 À3 Integrin complex 
0.54 4 Á 10 À3 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">F.Napolitano et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgement</head><p>The authors would like to thank Ramanath Hegde for providing the referenced list of CFTR correctors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This study has been funded by: the Italian Ministry of Health (GR-20091596824), Fondazione Telethon Grant (TGM11SB1) and the EU FP7 Grant NANOSOLUTIONS (FP7/2007-2013 309329).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict</head><p>of Interest: none declared.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integration of virtual and high-throughput screening</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Bajorath</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Drug Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="882" to="894" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The beautiful cell: high-content screening in drug discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Bickle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Bioanal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">398</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rescue of DeltaF508-CFTR by the SGK1/Nedd4-2 signaling pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Caohuy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25241" to="25253" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correctors of protein trafficking defects identified by a novel high-throughput screening assay. Chembiochem Eur</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Carlile</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1012" to="1020" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mantra 2.0: an online collaborative resource for drug mode of action and repurposing by network analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Carrella</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1787" to="1788" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolving gene/transcript definitions significantly alter the interpretation of GeneChip data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Dai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Histone deacetylase inhibitors: overview and perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Dokmanovic</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="981" to="989" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping identifiers for the integration of genomic datasets with the r/bioconductor package biomaRt</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Durinck</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protocols</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1184" to="1191" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calcium-pump inhibitors induce functional surface expression of F508-CFTR protein in cystic fibrosis epithelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Egan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="485" to="492" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">affy–analysis of affymetrix GeneChip data at the probe level</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Gautier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel pharmacological strategies to treat cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Hanrahan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Pharmacol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="125" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reduced histone deacetylase 7 activity restores function to misfolded CFTR in cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Hutt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovery of drug mode of action and drug repositioning from transcriptional responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Iorio</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14621" to="14626" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The connectivity map: using gene-expression signatures to connect small molecules, genes, and disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Lamb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="1929" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased functional cell surface expression of CFTR and DeltaF508-CFTR by the anthracycline doxorubicin</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Maitra</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Physiol. Cell Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">280</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1031" to="1037" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Sullivan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Freedman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">373</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1891" to="1904" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correction of the Delta phe508 cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator trafficking defect by the bioavailable compound glafenine</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Robert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="922" to="930" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CORUM: the comprehensive resource of mammalian protein complexes–</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ruepp</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="497" to="501" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">P values as random variables expected P values</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Sackrowitz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Samuel-Cahn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="331" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Target-based drug discovery: is something wrong? Drug Dis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Sams-Dodd</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Today</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digitoxin mimics gene therapy with CFTR and suppresses hypersecretion of IL-8 from cystic fibrosis lung epithelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Srivastava</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7693" to="7698" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledgebased approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Subramanian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15545" to="15550" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Drug-set enrichment analysis</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>