
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:46+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Enrich: software for analysis of protein function by enrichment and depletion of variants</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Douglas</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Fowler</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>dfowler@uw.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genome Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Carlos</forename>
								<forename type="middle">L</forename>
								<surname>Araya</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genome Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wayne</forename>
								<surname>Gerard</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genome Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Stanley</forename>
								<surname>Fields</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>fields@uw.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genome Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Howard Hughes Medical Institute</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Washington</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>98195</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>WA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Enrich: software for analysis of protein function by enrichment and depletion of variants</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">24</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="3430" to="3431"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr577</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 8, 2011; revised on October 5, 2011; accepted on October 11, 2011</note>
					<note>[12:51 12/11/2011 Bioinformatics-btr577.tex] Page: 3430 3430–3431 Associate Editor: Burkhard Rost Availability and Implementation: Enrich is implemented in Python and is available under a FreeBSD license at http://depts .washington.edu/sfields/software/enrich/. Enrich includes detailed documentation as well as a small example dataset. Contact: Supplementary Information: Supplementary data is available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Measuring the consequences of mutation in proteins is critical to understanding their function. These measurements are essential in such applications as protein engineering, drug development, protein design and genome sequence analysis. Recently, high-throughput sequencing has been coupled to assays of protein activity, enabling the analysis of large numbers of mutations in parallel. We present Enrich, a tool for analyzing such deep mutational scanning data. Enrich identifies all unique variants (mutants) of a protein in high-throughput sequencing datasets and can correct for sequencing errors using overlapping paired-end reads. Enrich uses the frequency of each variant before and after selection to calculate an enrichment ratio, which is used to estimate fitness. Enrich provides an interactive interface to guide users. It generates user-accessible output for downstream analyses as well as several visualizations of the effects of mutation on function, thereby allowing the user to rapidly quantify and comprehend sequence–function relationships.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Understanding how variations in protein sequence relate to function is of fundamental importance. Measurement of protein activity is critical to engineer protein function, to understand how mutations relate to disease and to gain insight into catalytic mechanisms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alper et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kato et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Weiss et al., 2000</ref>). Efforts to parallelize measurement of protein activity rely on selection for a desired function present within a library of variants of a protein of interest using a display-based system that directly links a protein's activity to its encoding DNA sequence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Levin and Weiss, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Pal et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Sidhu and Koide, 2007</ref>). Selection for function (e.g. ligand binding, catalytic activity or stability) alters the population of displayed proteins, and thus their associated DNA molecules. DNA sequences encoding highly functional variants</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">APPROACH</head><p>Enrich is implemented in Python. Enrich requires ∼2 h to run on a typical dataset on a desktop computer. To facilitate the analysis of multiple datasets in parallel, Enrich can function in a highperformance computing environment managed by the Oracle Grid Engine. Enrich uses the DRMAA distributed resource management API to facilitate extension to other environments (http://drmaa.org/). Enrich supports command line execution and an interactive mode that guides users through the configuration and execution of Enrich runs. Enrich takes as input FASTQ-formatted high-throughput sequencing data files acquired from an unselected and a selected library (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cock et al., 2010</ref>). Enrich can use reads from any sequencing platform, provided they are FASTQ-formatted. If overlapping paired-end reads have been acquired, Enrich corrects each read pair for sequencing error by examining agreement between the reads. At positions where the reads disagree, the nucleotide with the higher quality score is used. If both reads have identical quality scores at the position in question, the read pair is removed. More robust error models could improve error correction, particularly when overlapping paired-end reads are not available (e.g. ShoRAH) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Zagordi et al., 2011</ref>). Variant sequences are identified and enumerated within the unselected and selected libraries. Variants containing insertions and deletions are removed. An enrichment ratio (selected/unselected)is calculated for each variant. Enrichment ratios are evaluated using a two-sided Poisson exact test to calculate a P-value for the significance of enrichment or depletion for each variant. Multiple testing correction is performed using false discovery rates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Storey and Tibshirani, 2003</ref>). The resulting q-values enable the user to identify subsets of variants whose frequency is significantly altered by selection. To accomplish these tasks, the Enrich workflow is divided into seven modules that can run independently or all together (for a more detailed description, see the Supplementary Material). Enrich uses matplotlib to produce any of three visualizations as a starting point for further analyses (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). The visualizations show an estimation of library diversity, the position-averaged mutation enrichment and an all-residue enrichment ratio scan. In addition to providing these visualization options, Enrich produces easy to use output files that can be carried forward into project-specific analyses. Enrich can take advantage of high-performance computing to conduct many analyses in parallel. Enrich's Python-based modular, extensible design enables users to customize the software. Enrich facilitates deep mutational scanning, which can be widely applied to the breadth of disciplines that depend on understanding protein sequence–function relationships.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Enrich</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head><p>We thank Alan Rubin, Michael Hoffman and William Noble for helpful discussion and advice.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Enrich visualizations. Enrich produces three visualizations; examples from the dataset included with Enrich are shown here. (a) The diversity within a library is illustrated by a heatmap of the frequency of each position– mutation combination. (b) The position-averaged change in mutational frequency between two libraries is shown. (c) The log 2-scaled enrichment ratio for each position–mutation combination is plotted, individually organized both by position and by amino acid (a single amino acid, serine, is shown). Blue dots indicate the enrichment or depletion of substitutions. Red squares correspond to wild-type residues. Grey squares correspond to unobserved mutations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: National Institutes of Health (P41RR11823 to S.F. and F32GM084699 to D.M.F.). S.F. is an investigator of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. are enriched, whereas DNA sequences encoding poorly functional variants are depleted. Sanger sequencing of library members after selection can reveal a few hundred highly functional variants. Recently, high-throughput sequencing has been used to significantly increase the number of variants assessed (Di Niro et al., 2010; Dias-Neto et al., 2009; Ernst et al., 2010; Fowler et al., 2010; Hietpas et al., 2011; Hinkley et al., 2011; Ravn et al., 2010). Such &apos;deep mutational scanning&apos; (Araya and Fowler, 2011) experiments engender significant analysis challenges. Here, we present Enrich, a tool to address these challenges. Enrich identifies and enumerates unique protein sequences within high-throughput sequencing data. It calculates an enrichment ratio between unselected and selected libraries for each unique variant, and it creates a number of visualizations. Enrich is open-source, freely available and modular, creating easy-to-manipulate output files. Thus, users can customize Enrich and perform project-specific analysis.</note>

			<note place="foot">© The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from [12:51 12/11/2011 Bioinformatics-btr577.tex]</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3431"> at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Engineering yeast transcription machinery for improved ethanol tolerance and production</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Alper</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">314</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1565" to="1568" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deep mutational scanning: assessing protein function on a massive scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Araya</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Fowler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Sanger FASTQ file format for sequences with quality scores, and the Solexa/Illumina FASTQ variants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Cock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1767" to="1771" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid interactome profiling by massive sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Di</forename>
				<surname>Niro</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">110</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Next-generation phage display: integrating and comparing available molecular tools to enable cost-effective high-throughput analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Dias-Neto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8338</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coevolution of PDZ domain-ligand interactions analyzed by high-throughput phage display and deep sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ernst</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biosyst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1782" to="1790" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-resolution mapping of protein sequence-function relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Fowler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="741" to="746" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From the cover: experimental illumination of a fitness landscape</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Hietpas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7896" to="7901" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systems analysis of mutational effects in HIV-1 protease and reverse transcriptase</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Hinkley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="487" to="489" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding the function-structure and function-mutation relationships of p53 tumor suppressor protein by high-resolution missense mutation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kato</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8424" to="8429" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimizing the affinity and specificity of proteins with molecular display</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Levin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Weiss</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biosyst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive and quantitative mapping of energy landscapes for protein-protein interactions by rapid combinatorial scanning</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Pal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">281</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22378" to="22385" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">By-passing in vitro screening–next generation sequencing technologies applied to antibody display and in silico candidate selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<surname>Ravn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">193</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phage display for engineering and analyzing protein interaction interfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Sidhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Koide</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="481" to="487" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical significance for genomewide studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Storey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Tibshirani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9440" to="9445" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid mapping of protein functional epitopes by combinatorial alanine scanning</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Weiss</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8950" to="8954" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ShoRAH: estimating the genetic diversity of a mixed sample from next-generation sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Zagordi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>