
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:29+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics eSBMTools 1.0: enhanced native structure-based modeling tools</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Benjamin</forename>
								<surname>Lutz</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Steinbuch Centre for Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76128</postCode>
									<settlement>Karlsruhe</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Claude</forename>
								<surname>Sinner</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Steinbuch Centre for Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76128</postCode>
									<settlement>Karlsruhe</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Geertje</forename>
								<surname>Heuermann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Steinbuch Centre for Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76128</postCode>
									<settlement>Karlsruhe</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Abhinav</forename>
								<surname>Verma</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Steinbuch Centre for Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76128</postCode>
									<settlement>Karlsruhe</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alexander</forename>
								<surname>Schug</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Steinbuch Centre for Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76128</postCode>
									<settlement>Karlsruhe</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics eSBMTools 1.0: enhanced native structure-based modeling tools</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2795" to="2796"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt478</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 23, 2013; revised on July 22, 2013; accepted on August 9, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Availability: http://sourceforge.net/projects/esbmtools/ Contact: alexander.schug@kit.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Molecular dynamics simulations provide detailed insights into the structure and function of biomolecular systems. Thus, they complement experimental measurements by giving access to experimentally inaccessible regimes. Among the different molecular dynamics techniques, native structure-based models (SBMs) are based on energy landscape theory and the principle of minimal frustration. Typically used in protein and RNA folding simulations, they coarse-grain the biomolecular system and/or simplify the Hamiltonian resulting in modest computational requirements while achieving high agreement with experimental data. eSBMTools streamlines running and evaluating SBM in a comprehensive package and offers high flexibility in adding experimental-or bioinformatics-derived restraints. Results: We present a software package that allows setting up, modifying and evaluating SBM for both RNA and proteins. The implemented workflows include predicting protein complexes based on bioinformatics-derived inter-protein contact information, a standardized setup of protein folding simulations based on the common PDB format, calculating reaction coordinates and evaluating the simulation by free-energy calculations with weighted histogram analysis method or by phi-values. The modules interface with the molecular dynamics simulation program GROMACS. The package is open source and written in architecture-independent Python2.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Energy landscape theory and the principle of minimal frustration stipulate that biomolecular evolution results in an effective overall bias of a macromolecule's energy landscape being funnelshaped toward its global minimum at the native folded state (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Onuchic and Wolynes, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Schug and Onuchic, 2010</ref>). Native structure-based models (SBMs, also often referred to as G " o-models) realize an idealized minimally frustrated folding funnel devoid of any energetic traps by a simple Hamiltonian (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Clementi et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Whitford et al., 2009</ref>) that allows molecular dynamics simulations to reach biologically relevant timescale. The SBM potential is based on the native folded structure and native contact information. The number of formed native contacts in a structure is the dominant reaction coordinate typically called Q. The Q value can be used as a reaction coordinate to investigate folding paths or as an order parameter for the weighted histogram analysis method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kumar et al., 1992</ref>). The SBM can be combined with coarse-graining approaches. Proteins can be represented by single beads at the positions of their C atoms. Accordingly, there exist formulations of the SBM at an all-atom (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Whitford et al., 2009</ref>) and C (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Clementi et al., 2000</ref>) graining level (see Supplementary Information). Bioinformatics-derived contact information (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Schug et al., 2009</ref>) or experimental measurements (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Whitford et al., 2011</ref>) can be added as restraints to SBM. Eventually, the SBM defines a force field that results in computationally tractable simulations that facilitate simulations on the effective timescale of seconds (for small proteins even on single CPUs) in combination with extensive sampling. Existing web-based solutions like the SMOG-server (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Noel et al., 2010</ref>) allow a straightforward setup and evaluation of standard SBM. Our open source eSBMTools extends the customization options enabling the setup of automatized workflows and strong modifications of SBM by, e.g. adding arbitrary additional contacts, protein/RNA structures, novel ligand topologies or manipulating force field parameters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">FUNCTIONALITY</head><p>eSBMTools is organized in modules that can be loaded into Python projects. The modules and their input and output files interface with tools that are part of the standard GROMACS software package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Hess et al., 2008</ref>). It can be used at all stages in the context of SBM simulations: from generating the SBM itself, over manipulations of the model and configuration file generation, to extensive post-processing of simulation data. Several examples can be found in the Supplementary Information. The SBM is generated starting from a PDB structure with the help of an XML-based topology definition that introduced the bonded interactions via bonds, angles and dihedral angles. eSBMTools provides topology definitions for DNA/RNA or protein systems in an all-atom or a C formulation. The XML format allows the user to easily extend the existing topology definitions by custom additions of arbitrary ligands or experimental markers (for example FRET-fluorosphores). The nonbonded interactions via inter-atomic contacts are implemented by a simple cut-off formulation. Two atoms are considered to form a contact when the distance between the atoms is below *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com a certain threshold. A contact map represents every contact between two atoms by an entry, as in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. The generated SBM can be modified according to the requirements of the user's system of interest. The contact information can be manipulated to include, e.g. predicted contacts (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Dago et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Morcos et al., 2011</ref>) or the energetics of all contacts can be re-weighted by, e.g. by amino acid interaction matrices (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Miyazawa and Jernigan, 1996</ref>), shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. Two SBMs can be merged to set up combined systems for, e.g. complex formation simulations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Schug et al., 2009</ref>). Once all the files that describe the system of interest are prepared, eSBMTools generates the required configuration files for GROMACS simulations. This generation can be customized within Python to adjust simulation parameters, e.g. temperature, duration or resolution to steer simulations within a workflow. The simulation output by GROMACS can be processed in various ways depending on the desired evaluation protocol. The root-mean-square deviations along the trajectory of the simulation can be generated and included in further postprocessing. Similarly, the Q values (the number of formed native contacts) can be generated from a trajectory. The Q values can be used to generate time-depending contact maps or filtered by certain ranges to follow the folding process of substructures within the system of interest. Based on histograms of Q values, it is possible to calculate values (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Fersht and Sato, 2004</ref>) that give a measure for a residue's stability in the transition state. eSBMTools can also be used to perform a more demanding analysis of Q value and energy histograms: the weighted histogram analysis method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kumar et al., 1992</ref>). This method yields the free-energy landscape ÁGðQ, TÞ over the sampled Q values and a chosen temperature range, based on a finite number of simulations at distinct temperatures, preferably around the folding temperature. In addition, it is possible to calculate the heat capacity over the temperature range, which allows the user to determine the folding temperature.<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. Contact maps of protein HigA in the standard homogeneous formulation and the Miyazawa–Jernigan formulation. Each square stands for a contact between residue i and j in the native structure of HigA. The upper left contact map represents the homogeneous energetics of the standard SBM formulation. However, the lower right contact map illustrates the possibility of weighting each native contact by Miyazawa– Jernigan factors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Miyazawa and Jernigan, 1996)</ref></p></div>
			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> CONCLUSIONS We present the full release version of our Python2-based software package for SBM simulation pre-and post-processing. The package provides a comprehensive tool box to perform and evaluate simulations in the field of SBMs. The open source package interfaces with a standard build of the GROMACS software suite, which is a state-of-the-art software for molecular dynamics simulations. The combination of a high-performance simulation software with a user-defined Python2 framework makes eSBMTools versatile yet compact. Computationally tractable SBM can be set up in a platform-independent manner as workflows for extensive sampling on both HPC systems and local computers. Funding: AS recognizes support from the Helmholtz Association within the &apos;Impuls-und Vernetzungsfond&apos;. Conflict of interest: none declared.</note>

			<note place="foot">B.Lutz et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topological and energetic factors: what determines the structural details of the transition state ensemble and &apos;&apos;en-route&apos;&apos; intermediates for protein folding? An investigation for small globular proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Clementi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">298</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="937" to="953" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural basis of histidine kinase autophosphorylation deduced by integrating genomics, molecular dynamics, and mutagenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Dago</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1733" to="1742" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phi-value analysis and the nature of protein-folding transition states</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Fersht</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Sato</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7976" to="7981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GROMACS 4: algorithms for highly efficient, load-balanced, and scalable molecular simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Hess</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Theory Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="447" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The weighted histogram analysis method for free-energy calculations on biomolecules. I. The method</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kumar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1011" to="1021" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Residue-residue potentials with a favorable contact pair term and an unfavorable high packing density term, for simulation and threading</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Miyazawa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Jernigan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">256</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="623" to="644" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct-coupling analysis of residue coevolution captures native contacts across many protein families</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Morcos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1293" to="1301" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SMOG@ctbp: simplified deployment of structure-based models in GROMACS</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Noel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="657" to="661" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theory of protein folding</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Onuchic</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Wolynes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From protein folding to protein function and biomolecular binding by energy landscape theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Schug</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Onuchic</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="709" to="714" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-resolution protein complexes from integrating genomic information with molecular simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Schug</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22124" to="22129" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An all-atom structure-based potential for proteins: bridging minimal models with all-atom empirical forcefields</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Whitford</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="430" to="441" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Excited states of ribosome translocation revealed through integrative molecular modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Whitford</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18943" to="18948" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>