
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:58+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Exact quantification of cellular robustness in genome-scale metabolic networks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matthias</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Gerstl</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Austrian Centre of Industrial Biotechnology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biotechnology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country>Austria,</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Steffen</forename>
								<surname>Klamt</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Dynamics of Complex Technical Systems</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Magdeburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christian</forename>
								<surname>Jungreuthmayer</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Austrian Centre of Industrial Biotechnology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biotechnology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country>Austria,</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jü</forename>
								<surname>Rgen Zanghellini</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Austrian Centre of Industrial Biotechnology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biotechnology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country>Austria,</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Exact quantification of cellular robustness in genome-scale metabolic networks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv649</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 5, 2015; revised on October 6, 2015; accepted on October 28, 2015</note>
					<note>Systems biology *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Igor Jurisica Availability and implementation: Source code is available under the GNU General Public License at https://github.com/mpgerstl/networkRobustnessToolbox. Contact: juergen.zanghellini@boku.ac.at Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Robustness, the ability of biological networks to uphold their functionality in spite of perturbations, is a key characteristic of all living systems. Although several theoretical approaches have been developed to formalize robustness, it still eludes an exact quantification. Here, we present a rigorous and quantitative approach for the structural robustness of metabolic networks by measuring their ability to tolerate random reaction (or gene) knockouts. Results: In analogy to reliability theory, based on an explicit consideration of all possible knockout sets, we exactly quantify the probability of failure for a given network function (e.g. growth). This measure can be computed if the network&apos;s minimal cut sets (MSCs) are known. We show that even in genome-scale metabolic networks the probability of (network) failure can be reliably estimated from MSCs with lowest cardinalities. We demonstrate the applicability of our theory by analyzing the structural robustness of multiple Enterobacteriaceae and Blattibacteriaceae and show a dramatically low structural robustness for the latter. We find that structural robustness develops from the ability to proliferate in multiple growth environments consistent with experimentally found knowledge. Conclusion: The probability of (network) failure provides thus a reliable and easily computable measure of structural robustness and redundancy in (genome-scale) metabolic networks.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>A major characteristic of biological systems is their 'robustness', i.e. the ability to perform normally under the presence of perturbations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Kitano, 2002</ref>). Despite its fundamental importance, robustness is hard to quantify and a comprehensive, quantitative understanding of robustness has yet to be developed (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kitano, 2007</ref>). The problem is augmented by the fact that robustness is an extremely general concept which obstructs efforts for an exact definition (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Stelling et al., 2004</ref>). Clearly, robustness arises as a consequence of the interactions between the components in a system. It therefore requires a network-based approach for its analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Larhlimi et al., 2011</ref>). In the following, we study a key aspect of cellular robustness, namely structural robustness in metabolic networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Wilhelm et al., 2004</ref>), which is a measure of the apparent redundancy in metabolic networks. Redundancy is one reason why specific (network) functions may persist in spite of changes in the networks' topologies. Metabolic networks are particularly suitable to study structural robustness as their topologies are either well known or can be reliably reconstructed by well-established protocols (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Thiele and Palsson, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Vlassis et al., 2014</ref>). An unbiased way to characterize all topologically feasible flux distributions in a metabolic network can be achieved in terms of elementary flux modes (EFMs) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Schuster et al., 2000</ref>). EFMs are steady-state pathways that use a minimal set of reactions (enzymes) in the appropriate thermodynamic directions. Biologically, they can be interpreted as simple, indivisible functional building blocks, which represent all feasible metabolic capabilities of the organism. Thus, EFMs are likely candidates to be used in a definition of structural robustness. In fact,<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Wilhelm et al. (2004)</ref>were the first to define structural robustness by counting the number of EFMs in different situations. An alternative approach to EFMs is minimal cut sets (MCSs) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Klamt and Gilles, 2004</ref>). These are minimal sets of reaction (enzyme) knockouts that completely disable a particular network functionality. MCSs are intimately connected to EFMs. Any network function can be represented by a set of EFMs. Thus, MCSs can equivalently be defined as the minimal set of reaction knockouts that prevent a set of target EFMs from carrying a steadystate flux. An MCS is therefore a so-called minimal hitting set of the target EFMs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Klamt, 2006</ref>). If the EFMs or the MCSs are known, the respective other can be calculated. Mathematically, this relationship is known as duality (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Berge, 1989</ref>). While EFMs describe the possibilities to achieve a particular function, MCSs describe the effort it takes to remove that function from the network. Thus, the size distribution of the MCSs provides a measure for the structural fragility of a network (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Klamt and Gilles, 2004</ref>). One major disadvantage for both measures, the EFM-based structural robustness measure as well as the MCS-based structural fragility measure, is that they presuppose the availability of the complete set of EFMs and MCSs, respectively. This is a computationally intractable problem in genome-scale metabolic models (GSMMs). Here, we present a novel method that overcomes the computational limitations and allows one for the first time to estimate the structural robustness even in GSMMs. We use MCSs to calculate the exact (structural) probability of failure (PoF) of a network. This puts the estimation of structural robustness on a theoretically sound fundament.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Theory</head><p>We consider a metabolic network made up of m (internal) metabolites and r reactions. The network contains n EFMs. We use the support representation E ¼ suppðeÞ to uniquely characterize an EFM, e. E is the set of all (reaction) indices i for which the EFM vector e carries any flux, i.e. suppðeÞ ¼ fije i 6 ¼ 0g; with 1 i r. We collect all EFMs in the set E ¼ fE 1 ;. .. ; E n g. If we delete d reactions, several EFMs will get disabled. We represent a set of d deleted reactions by a cut set (CS) C d of cardinality d. C d contains the set of (reaction) indices that get deleted. A CS C d disables all EFMs involving any of the d deleted reactions. To study the impact of a deletion strategy, C d , on the network, we collect all EFMs not affected by C d in the set of the remaining EFMs,</p><formula>E C d ¼ fE 2 EjC d \ E ¼ ;g.</formula><p>The complement of E C d is denoted by H C d and contains all EFMs that are disabled by C d : H C d ¼ E n E C d. A minimal (irreducible) set of reaction (enzyme) deletions that completely disables a given set of target EFMs, T, is called an MCS, M (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Klamt and Gilles, 2004</ref>). For any target set T we collect all l MCSs in the set of MCSs, M ¼ fM 1 ;. .. ; M l g. Finally, we collect all 1 i b ¼ r d ! possible CSs C d i of cardinality d in the set of CSs, C d ¼ fC d 1 ;. .. ; C d b g.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Structural robustness: RðdÞ</head><p>For a given number d of deletions, Behre et al. (2008) defined the network's structural robustness RðdÞ as the average ratio of the number of remaining EFMs to the total number of EFMs over all possible combinations of exactly d knockouts, i.e.</p><formula>RðdÞ :¼ 1 jC d j X jC d j i¼1 jE C d i j jEj : (1)</formula><p>We show in the Supplementary material that the network's structural robustness only depends on the cardinality of the network's EFMs and can easily be calculated for any number of deletions d by</p><formula>RðdÞ ¼ 1 n r d ! À1 X n i¼1 r À jE i j d ! : (2)</formula><p>Thus, network structural robustness is merely determined by the EFMs' length.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">PoF: F(d)</head><p>For a given number of deletions, d, we define the network's PoF, F(d), as the ratio of the number of CSs that disable a particular network objective, obj, to the total number of all possible combinations of exactly d knockouts, i.e. F obj ðdÞ :¼ jC d obj j jC d j :</p><formula>(3)</formula><p>CSs that disable a particular objective (i.e. the elements of C d obj ) are either MCSs or supersets of MCSs disabling 'obj'. We show in the Supplementary material that the PoF can be calculated bywhere M J ¼ [ j2J M j and J is a (multi)-index over all power sets of the indices f1;. .. ; lg of the set M of MCSs blocking 'obj'. Note that the definition of the PoF requires specification of an objective, that can be the operation of the whole system or of a particular function. A typical cellular function is the production of biomass (BM). Thus, F BM ðdÞ measures the probability that the deletion of d reactions is lethal. In what follows we will drop the index for the objective and implicitly assume that the production of BM is targeted, unless stated otherwise.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exact quantification of cellular robustness</head><p>2.3 Overall structural robustness R and overall PoF (OPoF) F Both RðdÞ and F(d) are defined for a specific number of reaction deletions. Following<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Behre et al. (2008)</ref>, we define the overall structural robustness, R, if at most (all) r reactions are knocked out, as the weighted sum of all possible RðdÞ (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Behre et al., 2008</ref>),</p><formula>R :¼ X r d¼1 w R d RðdÞ:</formula><formula>(5)</formula><p>Analogous to the structural robustness we define the OPoF, F as</p><formula>w R d :¼ r d ! p d with p ¼ ffiffiffi 2 r p À1: (7)</formula><p>However, their choice is difficult to interpret in terms of a probability distribution. That is why we opted for an appropriately selected probability distribution function for the calculation of F. w F d may be naturally modeled by a binomial distribution,</p><formula>w F d :¼ r d ! p d ð1 À pÞ rÀd ; (8)</formula><p>which estimates the number of loss-of-function mutations with exactly d reaction deletions assuming a constant (reaction) mutation rate p. In typical metabolic networks, the number of reactions r is large and the mutation rate is small. We therefore approximate the binomial distribution with the simpler Poisson distribution, w F d :¼ k d expðÀkÞ=ðd!Þ;</p><formula>(9)</formula><p>with k ¼ rp. RðdÞ; R; FðdÞ and F all range between 0 and 1. However, while R ¼ 1 indicates a totally robust network, F ¼ 1 denotes the reverse, a completely fragile network.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Implementation and computation</head><p>The computation of the structural robustness RðdÞ according to Equation (2) is straight forward as long as the complete set of EFMs is known. The computation of the PoF is computationally more demanding as the number of summands in the sum of Equation (4) explodes combinatorially. In the following, we will outline countermeasures to estimate the PoF even in GSMMs.. Aerobic growth for Enterobacteriaceae was simulated on minimal medium with glucose or melibiose as sole carbon source and for Blattibacteriaceae with full medium (for media compositions see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). All reactions that could not carry a steady state flux under any circumstances for the given growth media were removed from the original models. m and r refer to the (remaining) number of internal metabolites and reactions, respectively, for fully consistent models (represented by the respective internal stoichiometric matrix, S). n and n BM refer to the total number and the number of BM producing EFMs in the respective models. An EFM analysis was not applicable (n/a) for GSMMs.</p><p>Algorithm 1 implements Equation (4) by calculating the total number of CSs for given deletions d in a recursive way. The number of reactions in the model, as well as all mcs with a cardinality up to the current number of reaction deletions are needed for the calculation. The algorithm calculates the number of all possible CSs for a single MCS by the function CHOOSE, which computes the binomial coefficient for r À combCd d À combCd ! , where combCd is the number of deletions resulting from the combination of MCSs. In order to avoid the consideration of a CS multiple times those CSs that have already been calculated by other MCS, indicated by their index, are subtracted. This is done by creating an intermediate CS by a logical OR operation and then following the inclusion–exclusion principal (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ryser, 1963</ref>) in a recursive procedure. Algorithm 1 was implemented as multi-threaded C program which is available at https://github.com/mpgerstl/networkRobustnessToolbox.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Results</head><p>In the following analysis, we used k ¼ 0:5, unless stated otherwise.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">F reliably identifies structural fragility</head><p>We used a medium-scale metabolic model (MSMM) that describes the core metabolism of Escherichia coli (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>for an overview of the topological properties of the models used) to study the influence of the carbon source on the structural robustness and the PoF (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). In all cases, a complete EFM and MCS analysis was feasible. We found that both measures indicated a strong impact of the carbon sources although with opposing trends. The OPoF was lowest for growth on glucose and highest for growth on acetate. We observed that in all three growth environments the PoFs F(d) could be well approximated (coefficient of determination, R 2 &gt; 0:999) by a½1 À bexpðÀcdÞ with three free parameters a, b and c (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S1</ref>). R however ranked growth on acetate to be most robust and growth on glucose or glycerol similarly robust but far behind growth on acetate. According to Equation (2) this implied that for acetate EFMs were on average shorter then for glucose (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. S2</ref>). Finally, the simple ratio between the number of BM producing EFMs and the total number of EFMs revealed yet another ranking with the highest ratio for growth on glycerol and the lowest ratio for growth on acetate (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table  S2</ref>). Comparing the different measures, we found that only the OPoF scored the (lack of) structural robustness in E. coli consistently to previous analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Klamt and Gilles, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Stelling et al., 2002</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">R and F can be calculated exactly in MSMMs</head><p>Judged by the number of EFMs, the three growth models significantly differed in size (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). Yet all structural robustnessvalues were calculated within few seconds for any number of reaction deletions. As the number of summands in Equation (4) grew excessively for high number of reaction deletions, d, the calculation of F(d) was more demanding. We found an exponential increase in the number of recursions for Algorithm 1 (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1</ref>). Our optimized implementation scaled consistently better than that and allowed us to evaluate F(d) in the largest model, EColi_core þ glc, up to d ¼ 9 in &lt; 10 min using 10 threads on an Intel</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">R and F are determined by the first few deletions</head><p>We analyzed the contribution of higher-order deletions to the overall structural robustness and OPoF, respectively. In the best case higher-order terms RðdÞ and F(d) vanish for d &gt; d 0 causing no error in the sums of Equations (5) and (6). In the worst case higher-order<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. Structural robustness and PoF in a core metabolic model of E. coli growing on minimal media (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>) and three different carbon sources (glc, glucose; gly, glycerol; ac, acetate)We used all EFMs for the calculation of R and all synthetic lethals of groups of up to d 0 ¼ 9 reactions for the estimation ofExact quantification of cellular robustnessterms maximally contribute to the sums. Thus, the maximum error e is easily calculated by setting RðdÞ ¼ FðdÞ ¼ 1 for all terms d &gt; d 0 ,</p><formula>model ID R(1) R(2) R F (1) F(2) F</formula><formula>eðd 0 Þ ¼ X r d¼d0þ1 w ðiÞ d ¼ 1 À X d0 d¼0 w ðiÞ d ; (10)</formula><p>where the last sum represents the cumulative distribution function of w ðiÞ d with i 2 fF; Rg. We found that the resulting maximum error dropped quickly with d 0 even in huge GSMMs (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 2</ref>). For instance, for k 1 the e drops below 10 À4 if all MCSs up to cardinality six are known. Thus, we conclude that for practical means the overall structural robustness R and the OPoF F can be approximated by the first few terms in their respective sums</p><formula>R % X d0 d¼1 w R d RðdÞ; and F % X d0 d¼1 w F d FðdÞ:</formula><formula>(11)</formula><p>For fixed k the OPoF F depends only on the d 0 smallest MCS and consistently converges toward its true value with increasing MCS cardinality. In the E. coli example used above (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>), all MCSs up to cardinality 4 were sufficient to estimate F within an error of 0.02 percentage points. However, a similar argument for the overall structural robustness R is not available. The knowledge of the d 0 shortest EFMs does not allow one to accurately estimate R. Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S5</ref>illustrates the error in the overall structural robustness as function of the d 0 shortest EFMs for the E. coli model used above. In that case, &gt;55% of all EFMs were required to get within a 10% error margin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">For small k, F is well approximated in GSMMs</head><p>According to Equation (11), the OPoF could be estimated if all low cardinality MCSs were known. Recently, von Kamp and<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Klamt (2014)</ref>showed that it is in fact possible to enumerate the smallest MCSs in GSMMs. In the following, we used their approach to calculate low cardinality MCSs. We calculated all lethal MCSs up to a cardinality of 4 in GSMMs of three E. coli strains growing on minimal medium and glucose or melibiose as the sole carbon source and estimated the OPoF (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>). The models represented E. coli K-12 MG1655 (iJO1366), the pathogenic enterohemorrhagic E. coli O157:H7 Sakai (iECs_1301) and the Shigella flexneri 2a 2457T (iS_1188). Comparing the three organisms against each other revealed that growth on glucose is more failsafe than growth on the alternative carbon source melibiose. In fact, growth on glucose (and glucose 1phosphate) was found to be more robust than on any other single, nitrogen-free carbon source (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S4</ref>). The two E. coli were similarly robust (with a small advantage for E. coli K-12 MG1655), while the S. flexneri was most fragile. Although the difference in the OPoF was small, it is indicative as the difference in F for any two models is larger than eð4Þ. We observed the same trend not only for F but also for F(d) for all tested cardinalities d 4, as well. The GSMMs were also found to be more robust than the E. coli core model. Again, in all models, F(d) could be nicely approximated by a½1 À bexpðÀcdÞ (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table S4</ref>). Finally, we calculated all synthetic lethal reactions in groups of up to d 0 ¼ 6 reaction deletions and evaluated the OPoF in the GSMMs of the endosymbiotic Blattabacterium cuenoti Bge (iCG238 þ full) and B. cuenoti Pam (iCG230 þ full), see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>, for full growth media containing all nutrients that were possibly taken up, see Supplementary Table S1 for detailed media compositions. Both strains were found to be extremely fragile with OPoFs &gt; 26% and a maximal inaccuracy of 1 Â 10 À4 percentage points. Any three reaction deletions almost certainly killed these two strains (with a small chance of survival of &lt;5%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Gene–centric PoFs showed same behavior as reaction–centric PoFs</head><p>For simplicity so far we analyzed structural robustness from a reaction–centric (RC) viewpoint. However, it is possible to change from an RC to a gene–centric (GC) viewpoint while retaining our formalism for the PoF calculation. PoF only requires the calculation of MCSs. These can be calculated in an RC model as well as in a GC model provided that a gene–reaction mapping is available as Boolean function of the genes (as it is typically the case). GC MCSs consider the effect of gene knock-outs on reactions based on the evaluation of the provided Boolean rules. If the complete set of EFMs is known, GC MCSs can be calculated using an established integer programming procedure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Jungreuthmayer and Zanghellini, 2012</ref>). In GSMMs, where the complete set of EFMs is unavailable, the dual systems approach (von<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kamp and Klamt, 2014</ref>) can beThe OPoF was estimated by considering all synthetic lethals of groups of up to d 0 ¼ 4 reactions and k ¼ 0:5. All values are listed in %The OPoF was estimated by considering all synthetic lethals of groups of up to d 0 ¼ 6 reactions and k ¼ 0:5. All values are listed in %For the GSMMs the OPoFs were estimated by considering all synthetic lethals of groups of up to d 0 ¼ 4 reactions and k ¼ 0:5. For these settings the estimation error was &lt; 0.02 percentage points. All values are listed in % adopted to compute GC MCSs. The common dual approach calculates RC MCSs (ordered by ascending cardinality) by iteratively solving a mixed integer linear program (MILP) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">De Figueiredo et al., 2009</ref>). In order to obtain a GC MCS instead of an RC MCS the gene–reaction association has to be integrated into the MILP, which can be achieved by means of the so-called indicator constraints. These concepts are provided by modern MILP solvers, which allow for the Boolean coupling of reactions and their associated genes. We evaluated GC PoFs for models listed in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>and compared them against the corresponding RC PoFs (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_5">Table 5</ref>). We found comparable (O)PoF values except for the MSMM of E. coli, where we observed larger differences. Yet the absolute ranking of the organisms with respect to structural robustness remained unchanged no matter if the GC or RC PoF was used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Discussion</head><p>Here, we developed a new general measure to quantify the structural robustness (or fragility) of metabolic networks based on the (O)PoF. Both, PoF F(d) as well as OPoF F are based on MCSs and share analogies with the previously defined structural robustness measures R(d) and R which rely on EFMs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Behre et al., 2008</ref>). In contrast to R, the OPoF remains computationally feasible even in GSMMs for two reasons: (i) the OPoF can be well estimated from the shortest MCSs with up to d 0 reaction cuts; and (ii) these d 0 shortest MCSs can be calculated with a MILP even in GSMMs (von<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kamp and Klamt, 2014</ref>). Previously, it was shown that MCSs in the (primal) network are EFMs in a network dual to the original network (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ballerstein et al., 2012</ref>). Thus, finding the shortest EFMs in this dual network is equivalent to finding the low cardinality MCSs in the primal GSMM (von<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kamp and Klamt, 2014</ref>). A high performance computing infrastructure is not required for this task. Thus, the OPoF is in principle an easily computable measure. However, due to the combinatorial explosion of the number of summands in F(d), see Equation (4), the evaluation is practically limited to low cardinalities. This does not cause practical problems for the OPoF F as the impact of high-cardinality MCSs on F quickly decreases (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 2</ref>). The slope of this decrease depends on the selected probability density that models the number of deletions that occur per mutation. Here, we used a Poisson distribution which is typically used for the study of rare events, like mutations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lee et al., 2012</ref>, and references therein). We were able to show that up to k 1 our analysis is computationally feasible on standard computer infrastructure. This is sufficient for the study of naturally occurring mutations. For instance, in E. coli a mutation rate of about 10 À3 per genome and generation was found (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lee et al., 2012</ref>), which is far below our limit of k 1, as we can assume that not all mutations lead to a loss of function of metabolic enzymes. All our conclusions remained valid (data not shown) if we used other probability densities like a binomial distribution or the one used by<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Behre et al. (2008)</ref>, see Equation (7). Previously, MCSs were already used to compute a so-called fragility coefficient which characterized the sensitivity of a metabolic network to deletions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Klamt, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Klamt and Gilles, 2004</ref>). Fragility was defined for each reaction as the inverse of the average cardinality of all MCSs that were supported by that reaction. Upon averaging the reaction-specific fragility over all reactions one obtained a measure for the overall network fragility. In contrast to the here introduced concept of the OPoF, network fragility lacks a rigorous probabilistic definition and more importantly requires the complete set of MCSs for its calculation. Network fragility is therefore not applicable to GSMMs. A clear difference between the PoF and structural robustness is that the former is function oriented while the latter characterizes the network. F is calculated with respect to some particular function that fails. Typically, networks perform multiple functions at the same time, which may be differentially robust. Thus, the OPoF is not only a topological property but also a property of the associated function. For instance, it is interesting to ask (and scope of further analysis) whether two essential functions like cellular energy production and BM production are similarly robust. R on the other hand characterizes the network topology by essentially measuring the proportion of short EFMs in a network. This definition is independent of any functions performed by the network. R counterintuitively identified growth on acetate to be more robust than growth on glucose which indicates that the length of EFMs may not be an appropriate proxy for structural robustness. Even if we selected only those EFMs that support a particular target function (like BM production), and calculated R for the reduced set of EFMs, we had misidentified growth on acetate as the most robust growth environment as growth supporting EFMs on acetate were on average 'shorter' than on glucose (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. S2</ref>). For better understanding we illustrated this effect in a toy network in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure S3</ref>. Thus, we propose to use the complement of the OPoF: R new ¼ 1 À F as a new measure for structural robustness in metabolic networks. PoFs can be calculated equally well on the basis of reaction deletions as well as on the basis of gene deletions. Some reactions in an organism are not associated with a gene (e.g. non-catalyzed reactions, reactions with unknown annotations) and can therefore not be knocked out. Other reactions are catalyzed by several different enzymes and are therefore more difficult to knock-out. However, our analysis indicates that the question if an organism or a growth condition is more robust than another can be identically answered in both approaches. It was criticized that structural robustness (as defined by<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Behre et al., 2008</ref>) lacks the ability to identify critical enzymes, such as knot enzymes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Min et al., 2011</ref>). This is true for the OPoF as well. For instance, according to our measure, network A in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 3</ref>was correctly identified to be more robust than network B. The cause for the lack of structural robustness is not apparent from the numerical value of the OPoF.<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Min et al. (2011)</ref>proposed to solve this dilemma by considering the number of independent (i.e. non-overlapping) EFMs, which are not available in GSMMs. However, by measuring the specific PoF f R ðdÞ for each individual reaction (enzyme) R we are at least able to identify critical enzymes. For this purpose, we define the (reaction) specific PoF f R ðdÞ</p><formula>f R ðdÞ :¼ jc d R j jC d j (12)</formula><p>to be the ratio between all specific CSs, c d R , that are supported by reaction R and the number of all possible CSs, C d (and similarly for f R ). By ranking reactions according to their impact on the network we are able to identify critical reactions which may be useful drug targets. We calculated OPoFs in MSMMs and GSMMs of multiple Enterobacteriaceae growing on minimal media to illustrate our concept. Among these, the ordinary lab strain E. coli K-12 MG1655 growing on glucose was found to be most robust. This was consistently observed in MSMMs and GSMMs in agreement with expectations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Stelling et al., 2002</ref>). Moreover, catabolite repression mechanisms support this observation of glucose as a preferential growth source. Escherichia coli K-12 MG1655 was also found to be more robust than the pathogenic E. coli O157:H7 Sakai, and the least Exact quantification of cellular robustnessrobust S. flexneri 2a 2457T. While the difference between K-12 MG1655 and O157:H7 Sakai was small (but larger than the possible error), S. flexneri was clearly set apart. Due to its adaption to a specific growth niche, S. flexneri has lost many catabolic pathways for various nutrient sources (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bliven and Maurelli, 2012</ref>). It was demonstrated computationally as well as experimentally that the number of growth-supporting conditions is larger for E. coli K-12 MG1655 than for E. coli O157:H7 Sakai than for S. flexneri 2a 2457T (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Monk et al., 2013</ref>). In contrast we here investigated the OPoF as a measure of structural robustness for these organisms in a single growth condition. Yet we found the same ranking as obtained from counting the number of growth-supporting conditions. Structural robustness is thought to come about from the need to survive in multiple environments. Many of these adaptations occur through rewiring of existing enzymes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Wagner, 2013</ref>), thus increasing the connectivity in the network, and—as a byproduct—also introducing many alternative routes. These topological alternatives can be exploited for other growth sources as well and were mirrored in our analysis in low OPoFs. The two strains of the highly specialized endosymbiont B. cuenoti, which for millions of years have lived in the relatively constant environment provided by specialized cells of cockroaches (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Lo et al., 2007</ref>), were found to be extremely sensitive to loss-of-function mutations (<ref type="bibr">González-Domenech et al., 2012</ref>). This was confirmed by an extremely high OPoF of &gt;26%. B. cuenoti was more than three times less robust than E. coli. It is known that B. cuenoti grows only on an extremely limited palette of metabolic substrates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Sabree et al., 2009</ref>), which results in their low structural robustness as documented here. Consistent with our findings above on S. flexneri this lack of structural robustness is thought to be shaped by massive gene loss (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Sabree et al., 2010</ref>). A characteristic difference between B. cuenoti Pam and Bge is a defunct TCA cycle in the former due to the absence of the first three enzymatic steps (<ref type="bibr">González-Domenech et al., 2012</ref>). This fact was mirrored in a lower structural robustness of B. cuenoti Pam compared with Bge. Thus, we conclude that the OPoF is indeed an appropriate measure to correctly assess the structural robustness of cells.</p><p>Here, we analyzed the structural robustness of multiple organisms in several growth environments. Consistent with previous findings our results confirm that structural robustness is correlated with the ability to utilize multiple carbon sources (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Papp et al., 2004</ref>). They concluded that structural robustness is not a trait selected by evolution but a byproduct of environmental flexibility. However, very recently<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Yang et al. (2015)</ref>showed that structural redundancy also impacts a cell factory's ability to produce a product of interest in the presence of perturbations. Based on predictions from GSMMs, they argue that pathway diversification leads to robust production capabilities under large perturbations. For instance, we show in Supplementary Table S5 two strain designs with different OPoFs but identical production/growth characteristics. Thus, calculating the OPoF will identify promising designs for cell factories. Interestingly, we found that the raise in F(d) with increasing d was well approximated by an exponential function in all investigated models and independent of the investigated organism. Whether this is an expression of some general topological properties of metabolic networks or a coincidence will be scope of further work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Conclusion</head><p>We developed a consistent theory of cellular redundancy based on a rigorous probabilistic definition of failure in metabolic networks. The new measure, called OPoF, allows quantification of the structural robustness of biochemical reaction networks with respect to certain functionalities. OPoF can be reliably estimated—even in GSMMs—from low cardinality MSCs. In contrast to other measures, the OPoF quantifies structural robustness and fragility of cellular metabolism concurrent with current biological paradigms and experimental findings. More specifically we showed that the number of growth-supporting nutrients indirectly correlates with the organisms' OPoF. As the OPoF is easily computable, we expect that it will be useful in increasing our understanding of key properties of metabolic networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Behre</head><figDesc>et al. (2008) suggested to use the following weights</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>F with k ¼ 0:5. All values are listed in %</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Number of recursions in Algorithm 1 as function of the number of reaction deletions, d evaluated for the model EColi_coreþglc in different computation scenarios. In addition, we plotted the number of MCS (dotted line) as function of their cardinality for the model used</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Maximum error, e, as function of the expansion length, d 0 , for various k values. Note that according to Equation (10) the maximum error only depends on k and is independent of the specific topology and size of the metabolic model</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Two differently robust networks (panel A, F ¼ 6:48%; panel B, F ¼ 15:32%) and their overall specific PoF, f with k ¼ 0:5 (panel C)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Major topological properties of the MSMMs and GSMMs for the investigated Enterobacteriaceae and Blattibacteriaceae</figDesc><table>Model ID 
Organism 
Medium 
M 
r 
RankðSÞ 
n 
n BM 

EColi_core þ glc (Gerstl et al., 2015) 
E. coli K-12 MG1655 
Glucose 
70 
90 
65 
169 916 
121 753 
EColi_core þ gly (Gerstl et al., 2015) 
E. coli K-12 MG1655 
Glycerol 
71 
91 
66 
60 495 
48 944 
EColi_core þ ac (Gerstl et al., 2015) 
E. coli K-12 MG1655 
Acetate 
69 
88 
64 
1299 
736 
iJO1366 þ glc (Monk et al., 2013) 
E. coli K-12 MG1655 
Glucose 
1165 
1726 
1131 
n/a 
n/a 
iJO1366 þ mel (Monk et al., 2013) 
E. coli K-12 MG1655 
Melibiose 
1163 
1718 
1128 
n/a 
n/a 
iECs_1301 þ mel (Monk et al., 2013) 
E. coli O157:H7 Sakai 
Melibiose 
1098 
1666 
1057 
n/a 
n/a 
iS_1188 þ mel (Monk et al., 2013) 
S. flexneri 2a 2457T 
Melibiose 
1 026 
1 517 
982 
n/a 
n/a 
iCG230 þ full (Gonzá lez-Domenech et al., 2012) 
B. cuenoti Pam 
Full 
299 
342 
292 
n/a 
n/a 
iCG238 þ full (Gonzá lez-Domenech et al., 2012) 
B. cuenoti Bge 
Full 
306 
350 
299 
n/a 
n/a 

Models were taken from Gerstl et al. (2015), Monk et al. (2013) and González-Domenech et al. (2012)</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 3. PoFs in GSMMs of different Enterobacteriaceae growing on minimal media (see Supplementary Table S1) and glucose (glc) or melibiose (mel)</figDesc><table>Model ID 
F(1) 
F(2) 
F(3) 
F(4) 
F 
eð4Þ 

iJO1366 þ glc 
16.74 
30.71 
42.35 
52.06 
8.02 
0.02 
iJO1366 þ mel 
17.17 
31.42 
43.24 
53.04 
8.22 
0.02 
iECs_1301 þ mel 
17.59 
32.11 
44.10 
53.98 
8.41 
0.02 
iS_1188 þ mel 
19.97 
35.99 
48.83 
59.12 
9.51 
0.00 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 4. PoFs in GSMMs of B. cuenoti Bge (iCG238 þ full) and B. cuenoti Pam (iCG230 þ full) growing on full media (see Supplementary Table S1)</figDesc><table>Model ID 
F(1) F(2) F(3) F(4) F(5) F(6) F 
eð6Þ 

iCG230 þ full 64.62 87.68 95.81 98.61 99.55 99.86 27.63 10 À4 
iCG238 þ full 62.57 86.36 95.16 98.31 99.43 99.81 26.89 10 À4 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 5. GC and RC PoF for various MSMMs and GSMMs</figDesc><table>Model ID 
F(1) 
F(2) 
F 

GC 
RC 
GC 
RC 
GC 
RC 

EColi_core þ glc 
5.00 21.11 10.01 40.45 
2.50 10.31 
EColi_core þ gly 
5.71 31.87 11.46 54.63 
2.86 14.84 
EColi_core þ ac 
15.00 42.05 29.10 67.42 
7.38 19.06 
iJO1366 þ glc 
16.94 16.74 31.03 30.71 
8.11 
8.02 
iJO1366 þ mel 
17.55 17.17 32.05 31.42 
8.39 
8.22 
iECs_1301 þ mel 19.14 17.59 34.65 32.11 
9.12 
8.41 
iS_1188 þ mel 
21.82 19.97 38.92 35.99 10.33 
9.51 
iCG230 þ full 
66.34 64.62 88.96 87.68 28.24 27.63 
iCG238þfull 
62.26 62.57 86.33 86.36 26.79 26.89 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.P.Gerstl et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimal cut sets in a metabolic network are elementary modes in a dual network</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Ballerstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural robustness of metabolic networks with respect to multiple knockouts</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Behre</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">252</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="441" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Combinatorics of Finite Sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Berge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<publisher>North Holland</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1st. edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antivirulence genes: insights into pathogen evolution through gene loss</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Bliven</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Maurelli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infect. Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4061" to="4070" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computing the shortest elementary flux modes in genome-scale metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">De</forename>
				<surname>Figueiredo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3158" to="3165" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolomics integrated elementary flux mode analysis in large metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Gerstl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8930</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolic stasis in an ancient symbiosis: genome-scale metabolic networks from two Blattabacterium cuenoti strains, primary endosymbionts of cockroaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Gonzá Lez-Domenech</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Microbiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Designing optimal cell factories: integer programming couples elementary mode analysis with regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Jungreuthmayer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Zanghellini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology: a brief overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Kitano</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">295</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1662" to="1664" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a theory of biological robustness</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Kitano</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">137</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized concept of minimal cut sets in biochemical networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Klamt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biosystems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="247" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimal cut sets in biochemical reaction networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Klamt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Gilles</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="226" to="234" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robustness of metabolic networks: a review of existing definitions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Larhlimi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biosystems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rate and molecular spectrum of spontaneous mutations in the bacterium Escherichia coli as determined by whole-genome sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2774" to="2783" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cockroaches that lack Blattabacterium endosymbionts: the phylogenetically divergent genus Nocticola</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Lo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="327" to="330" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathway knockout and redundancy in metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Min</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">270</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-scale metabolic reconstructions of multiple Escherichia coli strains highlight strain-specific adaptations to nutritional environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Monk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20338" to="20343" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolic network analysis of the causes and evolution of enzyme dispensability in yeast</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Papp</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">429</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="661" to="664" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Ryser</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1963" />
			<publisher>Combinatorial Mathematics. Mathematical Association of America</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Washington</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nitrogen recycling and nutritional provisioning by Blattabacterium, the cockroach endosymbiont</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Sabree</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19521" to="19526" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chromosome stability and gene loss in cockroach endosymbionts</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Sabree</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4076" to="4079" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general definition of metabolic pathways useful for systematic organization and analysis of complex metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Schuster</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="332" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolic network structure determines key aspects of functionality and regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Stelling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">420</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robustness of cellular functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Stelling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="675" to="685" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A protocol for generating a high-quality genome-scale metabolic reconstruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Thiele</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Ø</forename>
				<surname>Palsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimal Escherichia coli cell for the most efficient production of ethanol from hexoses and pentoses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Trinh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3634" to="3643" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast reconstruction of compact context-specific metabolic network models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Vlassis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003424</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enumeration of smallest intervention strategies in genome-scale metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Von Kamp</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Klamt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003378</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Chapter 13—genotype networks and evolutionary innovations in biological systems Handbook of Systems Biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Wagner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Walhout, A. J. M. et al.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="264" />
			<pubPlace>San Diego</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of structural robustness of metabolic networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Wilhelm</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEE Proc. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing metabolic pathway diversification in the context of perturbation size</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metab. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="122" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Exact quantification of cellular robustness</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>