
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:35+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining FILTUS: a desktop GUI for fast and efficient detection of disease-causing variants, including a novel autozygosity detector</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Magnus</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Vigeland</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Oslo University Hospital and University of Oslo</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>N-0424</postCode>
									<settlement>Oslo</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kristina</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Gjøtterud</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Cancer Registry of Norway</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>N-0304</postCode>
									<settlement>Oslo</settlement>
									<country key="NO">Norway</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kaja</forename>
								<forename type="middle">K</forename>
								<surname>Selmer</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Oslo University Hospital and University of Oslo</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>N-0424</postCode>
									<settlement>Oslo</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining FILTUS: a desktop GUI for fast and efficient detection of disease-causing variants, including a novel autozygosity detector</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw046</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on 19 August 2015; revised on 17 January 2016; accepted on 20 January 2016</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Inanc Birol Automatic installation is available via PyPI (e.g. pip in-stall filtus). Contact: magnusdv@medisin.uio.no Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>FILTUS is a stand-alone tool for working with annotated variant files, e.g. when searching for variants causing Mendelian disease. Very flexible in terms of input file formats, FILTUS offers efficient filtering and a range of downstream utilities, including statistical analysis of gene sharing patterns, detection of de novo mutations in trios, quality control plots and autozygosity mapping. The autozygosity mapping is based on a hidden Markov model and enables accurate detection of autozygous regions directly from exome-scale variant files. Availability and implementation: FILTUS is written in Python and runs on Windows, Mac and Linux. Binaries and source code are freely available at https://peroxibase.toulouse.inra.fr/geca_input_demo.php
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Recent years have seen a revolution in Mendelian disease gene identification thanks to high-throughput sequencing (HTS) methods, in particular whole-exome sequencing (WES). Most of the released software for downstream analysis is aimed at bioinformatically trained users, thus posing a challenge for many medical researchers wanting to do hands-on analysis of HTS data. To accommodate this, we introduce a program (FILTUS) offering advanced tools for identifying disease-causing variants in an easy-to-use graphical environment. Several programs for manipulating variant files have been published, including VarSifter (<ref type="bibr">Teer et al., 2012</ref>) and the web-based EVA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Coutant et al., 2012</ref>). In addition to efficient browsing and filtering, FILTUS offers several specialized analysis tools aimed at Mendelian disease projects. These include statistical evaluation of variant sharing among patients, de novo detection in trios and autozygosity mapping. FILTUS accepts virtually any variant files, in contrast to most existing programs which are limited to Variant Call Format (VCF) or other specific input formats. Typical examples of non-standard formats are VCF files with additional columns, and files produced by Annovar (<ref type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</ref>). Although FILTUS is primarily intended for WES-scale data, whole-genome data can be analyzed by using the built-in prefiltering functionality. Some countries have strict regulations requiring offline handling of all human sequencing data, thus making it impossible to use webbased tools or to download information during analysis. FILTUS is ideal for such working conditions, requiring no installation, being completely self-contained and offline. In summary, the main features of FILTUS include:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods and results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Statistical evaluation of gene sharing</head><p>A common strategy for Mendelian disease gene identification is to compare WES data from unrelated patients with the same phenotype. The basic idea is to apply strict filters, leaving only potentially disease-causing variants compatible with the inheritance model, and then look for genes where these variants are enriched among the patients. In many cases this method produces a long list of genes with no obvious ranking. FILTUS implements a statistical model (<ref type="bibr">Zhi and Chen, 2012</ref>) for evaluating the significance of each gene in the output (Supplementary Material S1).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Detection of de novo mutations</head><p>There is an emerging understanding that de novo mutations are a major cause of Mendelian disorders. As a result, trio sequencing has become a popular design when faced with an isolated patient with healthy parents (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Chong et al., 2015</ref>). To overcome the practical challenge of false positives and negatives, Bayesian methods are typically used, as in DeNovoGear (<ref type="bibr">Ramu et al., 2013</ref>). FILTUS implements a similar approach, computing posterior de novo probabilities from the genotype likelihoods provided by the variant caller (Supplementary Material S2). We compared FILTUS with DeNovoGear by applying both to a publically available trio data set. The results were very similar, particularly when using filters typical in clinical settings (Supplementary Material S3). In addition to posterior probabilities, FILTUS computes ALT allele percentages for each trio member, facilitating ranking and filtering.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Autozygosity mapping: the AutEx algorithm</head><p>Autozygosity (or homozygosity) mapping (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Lander and Botstein, 1987</ref>) is a powerful method for mapping recessive disorders. Traditional sliding-window approaches as offered by PLINK (<ref type="bibr">Purcell et al., 2007</ref>) are designed for dense, evenly distributed SNPs and are not optimal for exome data. Better methods have recently been proposed, e.g. H3M2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Magi et al., 2014</ref>), and the-roh command of BCFtools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Li et al., 2009</ref>), but these require skillful bioinformatic handling of sequence data. As an alternative, we introduce the AutEx algorithm for detecting autozygous regions directly from variant files. Our approach is based on a hidden Markov model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Leutenegger et al., 2003</ref>) described in Supplementary Material S4. The user specifies an approximate parental relationship and a column with allele frequencies (if available). The output provides details of each estimated autozygous segment, and can be directly used for filtering. Zoomable plots show the detected regions with surrounding variants. An example of a disease gene identification aided by AutEx is given in Supplementary Material S5. We compared AutEx with traditional homozygosity mapping to validate its performance, using data from a child of first cousin parents for which both dense SNP genotypes and WES data were available. Taking the SNP-based homozygous segments (as detected by PLINK) as the true segments, AutEx applied to the WES variants exceeded 95% for both true positive and true negative rates (Supplementary Material S6).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Visualizations</head><p>FILTUS offers various plots to aid QC of the variant files: gender estimation (based on X-chromosomal heterozygosity levels), private variants (compared with the other samples) and autosomal heterozygosity level (examples given in Supplementary Material S7). In addition histograms and scatter plots can be made from any numerical columns.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Purcell,S.</head><figDesc>et al. (2007) PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses. Am. J. Hum. Genet., 81, 559–575. Ramu,A. et al. (2013) DeNovoGear: de novo indel and point mutation discovery and phasing. Nat. Methods, 10, 985–987. Teer,J.K. et al. (2012) VarSifter: visualizing and analyzing exome-scale sequence variation data on a desktop computer. Bioinformatics, 28, 599–600. Wang,K. et al. (2010) ANNOVAR: functional annotation of genetic variants from high-throughput sequencing data. Nucleic Acids Res., 38, e164. Zhi,D. and Chen,R. (2012) Statistical guidance for experimental design and data analysis of mutation detection in rare monogenic mendelian diseases by exome sequencing. PLoS One, 7, e31358.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. Bioinformatics, 32(10), 2016, 1592–1594 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw046 Advance Access Publication Date: 27 January 2016 Applications Note at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> Discussion FILTUS has been used in many successful disease gene identifications, some of which are published (Baroy et al., 2015; Fjaer et al., 2015; Hansen et al., 2015; Pedurupillay et al., 2015) and others currently in preparation. FILTUS runs on Windows, Mac and Linux (see Supplementary Material S8 for supported versions) and is actively maintained and developed. We believe it to be a valuable contribution to the computer toolset of researchers and clinicians working with HTS variant data, especially those without access to specialized bioinformatics resources.</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.D.Vigeland et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank all the people who tested and gave feedback on early versions of FILTUS, in particular Tuva Barøy, Øyvind Busk, Morten C. Eike, Roar Fjaer, Asbjørn Holmgren, Christeen R. Pedurupillay, Aina Rengmark, Ying Sheng and Hanne S. Sorte. We also thank Robert Lyle for valuable comments on the article.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work has been supported by the South-Eastern Norway Regional Health Authority (2012066). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel type of rhizomelic chondrodysplasia punctata, RCDP5, is caused by loss of the PEX5 long isoform</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Baroy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mol. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5845" to="5854" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genetic basis of mendelian phenotypes: discoveries, challenges, and opportunities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">X</forename>
				<surname>Chong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EVA: Exome Variation Analyzer, an efficient and versatile tool for filtering strategies in medical genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Coutant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. 14</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized epilepsy in a family with basal ganglia calcifications and mutations in SLC20A2 and CHRNB2</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Fjaer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Med. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="624" to="628" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel POLE mutation associated with cancers of colon, pancreas, ovaries and small intestine</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Hansen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fam. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="448" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homozygosity mapping: a way to map human recessive traits with the DNA of inbred children</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Lander</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Botstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">236</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1567" to="1570" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of the inbreeding coefficient through use of genomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Leutenegger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="516" to="523" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2078" to="2079" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">H3M2: detection of runs of homozygosity from wholeexome sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Magi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2852" to="2859" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome in sisters with novel compound heterozygous mutation in UBE3B</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Pedurupillay</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Med. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">167</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="657" to="663" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">FILTUS: a desktop GUI for detection of disease-causing variants</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>