
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:48+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">FishingCNV: a graphical software package for detecting rare copy number variations in exome-sequencing data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yuhao</forename>
								<surname>Shi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">McGill University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>H3A 1B1</postCode>
									<settlement>Montreal</settlement>
									<region>Quebec</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jacek</forename>
								<surname>Majewski</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">McGill University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>H3A 1B1</postCode>
									<settlement>Montreal</settlement>
									<region>Quebec</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Genome Quebec Innovation Centre</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>H3A 0G1</postCode>
									<settlement>Montreal</settlement>
									<region>Quebec</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">FishingCNV: a graphical software package for detecting rare copy number variations in exome-sequencing data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1461" to="1462"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt151</idno>
					<note type="submission">Sequence analysis Advance Access publication March 28, 2013 Received on December 20, 2012; revised on March 2, 2013; accepted on March 25, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Rare copy number variations (CNVs) are frequent causes of genetic diseases. We developed a graphical software package based on a novel approach that can consistently identify CNVs of all types (homozygous deletions, heterozygous deletions, heterozygous duplications) from exome-sequencing data without the need of a paired control. The algorithm compares coverage depth in a test sample against a background distribution of control samples and uses principal component analysis to remove batch effects. It is user friendly and can be run on a personal computer. Availability and implementation: The main scripts are implemented in R (2.15), and the GUI is created using Java 1.6. It can be run on all major operating systems. A non-GUI version for pipeline implementation is also available. The program is freely available online: https://sourceforge.net/projects/fishingcnv/</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Many sporadic and Mendelian disorders are caused by exonic mutations that alter the amino acid sequence of the affected gene. Exome sequencing has so far shown great utilty in elucidating single nucleotide mutations that contribute to these diseases. However, using exome sequencing to detect rare copy number variations (CNVs) that contribute to diseases remain a challenge. We developed FishingCNV, a graphical software package for comprehensive analysis of CNVs in exome-sequencing data. We included a matched case/control analysis feature adapted from ExomeCNV, but more importantly, we implemented a new CNV detection algorithm that prioritizes rare variants for nonmatched sample analysis. Many sequencing centers have by now accumulated large internal sets of exome samples that can be used as controls for CNV detection in new unmatched samples. Our method relies on pooling such a control set, comparing the exonic read depth of the test sample against the distribution of read depths in the control set. To remove batch-to-batch variations in the control set, we applied principal component analysis (PCA) and removed the top contributing principal components (2–10) from the data. We bundled GATK (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">McKenna et al., 2010</ref>) into our program to extract coverage information. Read depth information is then converted to Reads Per Kilobase per Million mapped reads (RPKM) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Mortazavi et al., 2008</ref>), and the test sample is segmented into regions of similar RPKM ratios using circular binary segmentation (CBS) before comparison against the control distribution (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Olshen et al., 2004</ref>). The output is a file that contains segmented CNV calls ranked by statistical confidence (See Supplementary Materials for details on method). We tested our algorithm on simulated and actual exome data and show that it is effective in identifying homozygous as well as heterozygous CNVs of varying length. We also show that principal component removal is effective in reducing false positives. A summary of the program workflow is presented in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>. We compared our algorithm against ExomeCNV (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Sathirapongsasuti et al., 2011</ref>) and Conifer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Krumm et al., 2012</ref>) and show that FishingCNV consistently outperforms previous approaches (See Supplementary Materials for data).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Simulation and performance</head><p>We created test files with presumably no CNVs by averaging the RPKM values of a subset of samples from the control set. In each file, we simulated heterozygous deletions, heterozygous duplications and homozygous deletions of length 1 exon, 2 exons, 5 exons and 10 exons by changing the RPKM data within the file. An FDR-adjusted P-value of 0.05 was used as the threshold of detection. Our results show that our algorithm is effective in detecting homozygous deletions, as well as heterozygous deletions and duplications at the resolution of a single exon (See Supplementary Materials). Sensitivity increases as the size of the affected locus increases. Homozygous CNVs are detected with higher sensitivity. We compared our algorithm against ExomeCNV (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Sathirapongsasuti et al., 2011</ref>) and Conifer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Krumm et al., 2012</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">CNV detection—two validated examples</head><p>We tested our program on two patients suffering from metaphyseal dysplasia with maxillary hypoplasia and brachydactyly (MDMHB), and it identified a 4 exon amplification spanning SUPT3H and RUNX2 as the sixth most confident call (P51.06e-11). This CNV was verified as the causal variant in a previous study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Moffatt et al., 2013</ref>). In addition, we analyzed a sample from a study on mandibulofacial dysostosis with microcephaly (MFDM), which was previously shown to harbor a deleterious heterozygous deletion in the last 9 exons of the EFTUD2 gene (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Lines et al., 2012</ref>). The known deletion was the highest ranked call produced by our algorithm, with a P-value of 4.38e-12. FishingCNV determines it to be a 12 exons long deletion that spans the last 9 exons of EFTUD2 and the first 3 exons of the neighboring gene HIGD1B. The analysis of the MFDM illustrates some of the problems that may be encountered in real-life analysis. We note that the MFDM sample is an outlier, as identified by PCA, and produces many more CNV calls than is expected. However, our results demonstrate the power of our approach because after the ranking of CNV calls according to the P-values (even in cases where the normal approximation does not hold well), the true variants can be identified within the top ranking calls, despite the nonideal input.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSION</head><p>We believe that looking for rare CNVs in exome-sequencing data can be a powerful way of detecting new disease-causing mutations.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Until now, efforts on this front have been largely limited by the computational tools available to us, but here we presented a new graphical software package for easy detection of CNVs and showed that it is effective in identifying causal CNVs in rare diseases. This program should have vast applications in genomics research, and will aid in the ever-expanding scientific efforts to identify the genetic causes of rare diseases, such as the Finding of Rare Disease Genes in Canada (FORGE) and Rare Disease Consortium for Autosomal Loci (RaDiCAL) projects.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Summary of the workflow of FishingCNV. (A) RPKM values are extracted from each test or control sample. (B) PCA-based method is used to remove batch-to-batch variations in the data. (C) The test sample is segmented into regions of similar read depth ratio (with respect to the average of the controls) and tested against the read depth distribution of all the controls</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>) using the same simulated dataset. We show that ExomeCNV is not effective in detecting heterozygous variants or larger sized CNVs and Conifer is unsuccessful when CNVs are small (one to two exons long), but FishingCNV performed well for all CNV types and lengths. The performance of Conifer for larger sized CNVs is similar to FishingCNV. Overall, FishingCNV outperforms previous approaches to CNV detection. *To whom correspondence should be addressed ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Y.Shi and J.Majewski at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We would like to thank the FORGE Canada Consortium for allowing us to use exome data to test the algorithm and Kevin Ha for providing the initial ideas that gave rise to this project.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Copy number variation detection and genotyping from exome sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Krumm</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1525" to="1532" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Haploinsufficiency of a spliceosomal GTPase encoded by EFTUD2 causes mandibulofacial dysostosis with microcephaly</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Lines</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="377" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genome analysis toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Mckenna</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1297" to="1303" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metaphyseal dysplasia with maxillary hypoplasia and brachydactyly is caused by a duplication in RUNX2</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Moffatt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="252" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Mortazavi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="621" to="628" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circular binary segmentation for the analysis of arraybased DNA copy number data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Olshen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="557" to="572" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exome sequencing-based copy-number variation and loss of heterozygosity detection: ExomeCNV</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Sathirapongsasuti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2648" to="2654" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>