
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:37+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">&apos;Flatten plus&apos;: a recent implementation in WSxM for biological research</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alejandro</forename>
								<surname>Gimeno</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Física de la Materia Condensada</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratorio de Nuevas Microscopías</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad Autó noma de Madrid</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2 WSxM solutions, C Jú piter, 7</addrLine>
									<postCode>E-28049, E-28042</postCode>
									<settlement>Madrid, Madrid</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pablo</forename>
								<surname>Ares</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Física de la Materia Condensada</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratorio de Nuevas Microscopías</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad Autó noma de Madrid</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2 WSxM solutions, C Jú piter, 7</addrLine>
									<postCode>E-28049, E-28042</postCode>
									<settlement>Madrid, Madrid</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ignacio</forename>
								<surname>Horcas</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Adriana</forename>
								<surname>Gil</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Nanotec Electró nica S.L</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ronda de Poniente 12</addrLine>
									<postCode>E-28760</postCode>
									<settlement>Tres Cantos, Madrid</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">José</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Gó Mez-Rodríguez</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Física de la Materia Condensada</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratorio de Nuevas Microscopías</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad Autó noma de Madrid</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2 WSxM solutions, C Jú piter, 7</addrLine>
									<postCode>E-28049, E-28042</postCode>
									<settlement>Madrid, Madrid</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jaime</forename>
								<surname>Colchero</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departamento de Física</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Facultad de Química</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Murcia</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E-30100</postCode>
									<settlement>Murcia</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Julio</forename>
								<surname>Gó Mez-Herrero</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Física de la Materia Condensada</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratorio de Nuevas Microscopías</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad Autó noma de Madrid</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2 WSxM solutions, C Jú piter, 7</addrLine>
									<postCode>E-28049, E-28042</postCode>
									<settlement>Madrid, Madrid</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">&apos;Flatten plus&apos;: a recent implementation in WSxM for biological research</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv278</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 3, 2015; revised on April 15, 2015; accepted on April 24, 2015</note>
					<note>Bioimage informatics *To whom correspondence should be addressed Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Availability</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Scanning probe microscopy (SPM) is already a relevant tool in biological research at the nanoscale. We present &apos;Flatten plus&apos;, a recent and helpful implementation in the well-known WSxM free software package. &apos;Flatten plus&apos; allows reducing low-frequency noise in SPM images in a semi-automated way preventing the appearance of typical artifacts associated with such filters.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Since the introduction of scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) by<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Binnig et al. (1982)</ref>and later atomic force microscopy (AFM) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Binnig et al., 1986</ref>), Scanning Probe Microscopy (SPM), the general denomination for these techniques, has become a very relevant tool for the life sciences research. SPM can be used to obtain atomically resolved images in different media including ultrahigh vacuum, ambient air and liquids. SPM allows the possibility to study biological systems (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baro et al., 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Gould et al., 1988</ref>) even in their native environment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hansma et al., 1992</ref>) with unprecedented results. SPM is best known for its ability to acquire images; but in reality SPM also allows many other features, as for instance manipulation of matter at the atomic/nanometer scale (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Eigler and Schweizer, 1990</ref>), spectroscopy measurement of tip–sample interactions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Burnham et al., 1993</ref>) or the characterization of mechanical properties of relevant biological entities including proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Rief et al., 1997</ref>), cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Radmacher et al., 1996</ref>) and virus particles (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ivanovska et al., 2004</ref>). SPM images are acquired by scanning a very sharp tip on a region of interest. The distance between the tip and the sample surface is in the nanometer range. As in many other techniques there are a number of artifacts that are commonly present even in the best acquired images: noise due to different sources (mechanical, electrical, environmental, etc.), visible slopes in the main plane of an image or tip–sample dilations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Villarrubia, 1997</ref>). Thus, the development and improvement of the available processing tools becomes of great importance to ease the visualization and interpretation of SPM images. Biological samples studied by SPM typically consist of the biological specimens immobilized to an atomically flat, texture-free surface (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Wagner, 1998</ref>). The way an SPM is operated can make variations from scan line-to-scan line difficult to be avoided (changes in the average height, tilts or low-frequency noise) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Fogarty et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Schouterden et al., 1996</ref>). Thus, processing filters such as plane and flatten filters are very common when analyzing SPM images. Plane filters fit the raw data image to a general plane or parabolic surface, which is then subtracted from the original image. However, some issues in SPM images such as vertical scanner drift, scanner non-linearities, areas with different slopes or very different heights, etc., cannot be adequately corrected by plane filters. Flattenfeatures, and therefore, different heights. If a line is basically flat, and its average is subtracted, the whole line will change the same way, therefore, it will remain uniform (for example, area within the gray rectangle in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>). When a line contains very different heights and the average is subtracted, the originally lower parts will be even lower. This causes 'artificial' negative contrast regions (shadowing effects) around the higher parts of the filtered image (area within the black rectangle in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>). There are some standard tools to avoid these effects: discard regions, draw master paths, etc. However, these processes can be tedious for images with a large number of features or are hard to put to practical use. There are a good number of high-impact journal publications where, without discussing here the quality of the results there presented, some of the published images show these shadowing effects. Some very recent examples can be found in the following references (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Endo et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Fisicaro et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Jaksa et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kim et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Marchi et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Miles and Frankel 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Moon et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Uprety et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wang et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Yamamoto et al., 2014</ref>). WSxM is a free software devoted to the control of SPM systems and processing of images and data acquired with such microscopes. It was initially created at the New Microscopies Lab, in the Universidad Autonoma de Madrid (UAM). Then it continued growing at Nanotec Electronica SL, and now it is maintained and developed by WSxM solutions (www.wsxmsolutions.com). A detailed view of WSxM can be found in<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Horcas et al. (2007)</ref>. Here, we explain in some detail the features of 'Flatten plus', an option recently developed in WSxM that is particularly beneficial for biological data, enabling in a semi-automated way to remove typical artifacts when applying common filters to process SPM images.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Implementation</head><p>Consider the unfiltered image shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1b</ref>(left). Just by visual inspection one can easily find the general background. As usual, this simple task is very difficult to identify by a computer. Conventional flatten algorithms consider the lower points of an image as the flat substrate. 'Flatten plus' uses successive approximation algorithms using the information provided by the user through the Substrate area (%) parameter. This information can be just an ocular estimation of the percentage of background area as a share of total image area or can include regions to discard. Successive approximation algorithms discard the highest points in the image and apply a flatten process. This is similar to the method of discarding regions defined by the user but in this case the regions are automatically defined and they are free in shape and in number. Each iteration discards additional points over the results of the previous step and the remaining points are considered as the flat substrate. This iterative process is repeated until the Substrate area value is reached.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1a</ref>presents a flow chart of the various steps of the 'Flatten plus' routine.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1b</ref>and c shows an example of the difference between usual flatten filters (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>right) and 'Flatten plus' (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1c</ref>right) when applied to a typical DNA image. Whereas filtered image in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1b</ref>presents shadowing effects around the higher parts, they are not present in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1c</ref>.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1d</ref>shows height profiles after usual flatten (dashed blue line in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>) and 'Flatten plus' (solid green line in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1c</ref>). The background of both images shows the same roughness, but in the center part of the usual flatten profile it can be clearly distinguished a depression coming from an 'artificial' dark region in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1b</ref>. Since mica is atomically smooth over relatively large (often micrometer sized) areas, these dark regions correspond to artifacts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Conclusion</head><p>We have introduced a relevant implementation in software techniques for SPM. 'Flatten plus' provides a semi-automated filter to eliminate low-frequency noise reflected as slopes, bows and/or bands in images preventing the appearance of undesired shadowing effects which is common in conventional flatten procedures.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. 'Flatten plus' operation. (a) Routine flow chart. (b) Usual flatten filter on SMC protein particles co-adsorbed with DNA molecules on a mica substrate. Low-frequency noise of the original image (left) is eliminated after filtering (right). Typical shadowing artifacts are induced. Black rectangle: different heights are present causing shadowing effects. Gray rectangle: region without relevant height differences. Conventional flatten works correctly. (c) 'Flatten plus' filter. Low-frequency noise is eliminated with no shadowing effects even in the presence of relevant height differences. (d) Height profiles along vertical lines in (b) and (c)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 2918 Bioinformatics, 31(17), 2015, 2918–2920 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv278 Advance Access Publication Date: 29 April 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table>works by subtracting a function from each scan line in the raw data 
image. The simplest function is a zero-order function: the average of 
each line. Other common possibilities are a first-order function 
(a straight line) or a second-order function (a parabola). Flatten 
filters can be used to eliminate slopes, bows and/or bands in the 
images coming from low-frequency noise. 
A raw data image presents different </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determination of surface topography of biological specimens at high-resolution by scanning tunnelling microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Baro</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="253" />
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface studies by scanning tunneling microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Binnig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic force microscope</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Binnig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="930" to="933" />
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interpretation of force curves in force microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Burnham</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nanotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positioning single atoms with a scanning tunneling microscope</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Eigler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Schweizer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">344</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="524" to="526" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Helical DNA Origami tubular structures with various sizes and arrangements</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Endo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Angew. Chem. Int. Ed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7484" to="7490" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonviral gene delivery: gemini bispyridinium surfactant-based DNA nanoparticles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Fisicaro</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13183" to="13191" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimizing image-processing artifacts in scanning tunneling microscopy using linear-regression fitting</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Fogarty</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Sci. Instrum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">126104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular resolution images of amino-acid crystals with the atomic force microscope</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Gould</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">332</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="332" to="334" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reproducible imaging and dissection of plasmid DNA under liquid with the atomic force microscope</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Hansma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">256</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1180" to="1184" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WSXM: a software for scanning probe microscopy and a tool for nanotechnology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Horcas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Sci. Instrum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13705</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bacteriophage capsids: tough nanoshells with complex elastic properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Ivanovska</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. US A</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. US A</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7600" to="7605" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of different solvents on the morphology of APTMS-modified silicon surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Jaksa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">315</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="516" to="522" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ternary and senary representations using DNA doublecrossover tiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nanotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward larger DNA Origami</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Marchi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nano Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5740" to="5747" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lipid directed assembly of the HIV capsid protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Miles</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Frankel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soft Matter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9562" to="9567" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nanoscale topographical replication of graphene architecture by artificial DNA nanostructures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Moon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">231904</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring the viscoelastic properties of human platelets with the atomic force microscope</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Radmacher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="556" to="567" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reversible unfolding of individual titin immunoglobulin domains by AFM</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Rief</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">276</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1109" to="1112" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal filtering of scanning probe microscope images for wear analysis of smooth surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Schouterden</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3445" to="3451" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Site-specific metallization of multiple metals on a single DNA Origami template</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Uprety</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Langmuir</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1134" to="1141" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithms for scanned probe microscope image simulation, surface reconstruction, and tip estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Villarrubia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Res. Natl Inst. Stand. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="454" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immobilization strategies for biological scanning probe microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Wagner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEBS Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">430</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="112" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single molecular investigation of DNA looping and aggregation by restriction endonuclease BspMI</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5897</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single molecule visualization and characterization of Sox2-Pax6 complex formation on a regulatory DNA element using a DNA Origami frame</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Yamamoto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nano Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2286" to="2292" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>