
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:39+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics FRODOCK 2.0: fast protein–protein docking server</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Erney</forename>
								<surname>Ram Irez-Aportela</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Chemical Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Rocasolano Physical Chemistry Institute C.S.I.C</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>28006</postCode>
									<settlement>Madrid</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Centro de Investigaciones Biol ogicas</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CSIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E-28040</postCode>
									<region>Madrid</region>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">José</forename>
								<surname>Ram On L Opez-Blanco</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Chemical Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Rocasolano Physical Chemistry Institute C.S.I.C</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>28006</postCode>
									<settlement>Madrid</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pablo</forename>
								<surname>Chac</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Chemical Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Rocasolano Physical Chemistry Institute C.S.I.C</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>28006</postCode>
									<settlement>Madrid</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics FRODOCK 2.0: fast protein–protein docking server</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw141</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on December 9, 2015; revised on February 19, 2016; accepted on March 9, 2016</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The prediction of protein–protein complexes from the structures of unbound components is a challenging and powerful strategy to decipher the mechanism of many essential biological processes. We present a user-friendly protein–protein docking server based on an improved version of FRODOCK that includes a complementary knowledge-based potential. The web interface provides a very effective tool to explore and select protein–protein models and interactively screen them against experimental distance constraints. The competitive success rates and efficiency achieved allow the retrieval of reliable potential protein–protein binding conformations that can be further refined with more computationally demanding strategies. Availability and Implementation: The server is free and open to all users with no login requirement at http://</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Protein–protein interactions are involved in every cellular process, and their characterization is therefore critical to understanding the underlying molecular mechanisms. The computational prediction of protein–protein complexes from the unbound 3D structures is a successful complementary alternative to ongoing structural and proteomic endeavors. A great variety of computational ab initio docking approaches have been developed to predict protein complexes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Huang, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ritchie, 2008</ref>). These algorithms employ a variety of efficient search strategies and energy-based scoring strategies, usually beginning with an exhaustive six-dimensional search to generate many potential predictions, followed by a detailed and more computationally demanding refining stage. However, despite the significant progress in improved scoring functions and the integrative use of biochemical and biophysical information, current algorithms are still limited. In a recent independent comprehensive assessment of current exhaustive docking programs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Huang, 2015)</ref>, the best three docking approaches succeed in identifying acceptable protein–protein solutions in 21–31, 40–52 and 60–79% of the cases within the top 10components in only a few minutes. The user-friendly interface permits the interactive exploration of the docking models, including additional screening filters with experimental distance constraints to enhance the success of identifying near-native docking solutions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Benchmarking and implementation</head><p>The docking algorithm is detailed elsewhere (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Garzon et al., 2009</ref>). FRODOCK's competitive efficiency depends on the spherical harmonic (SH) formulation to accelerate the rotational part of the search. Compared with classical 3D grid-based FFT correlation algorithms, the use of SH has proven to be a faster alternative in protein–protein docking (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ritchie, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Ritchie and Kemp, 2000</ref>). Moreover, linear speed-up is obtained by performing parallel efficient rotational searches of independent docking translational positions. The original docking fitness score as defined in pyDock (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Cheng et al., 2007</ref>) was approximated as a correlation between soft van der Waals, electrostatics, and desolvation 3D grid potential maps conveniently transformed into SH radial (volumetric) representations. Here, we improve this scoring function by adding a complementary coarse-grained knowledge-based protein-docking potential (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Tobi, 2010</ref>). We employed the ADPs-II atomic potential variant derived from known protein–protein and decoy (misdocked) complexes using a linear programming technique. This two-step contact potential fitted very well to our approximation because of its efficiency and good performance, as shown in a recent survey of protein–protein scoring functions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Moal et al., 2013</ref>). To optimize the relative weights of all potential terms, we followed the same procedure described in (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Garzon et al., 2009</ref>). We also have optimized the potential weights for the three types of interaction disclosed in the benchmark (enzyme–substrate, antigen–antibody and others). However, compared with the addition of the pairwise potential the gain was quite reduced in terms of docking success (less than 5% in the best case scenario). The new version, FRODOCK 2.0, obtained 35–45% enhancement in the top rank solution regions using the standard benchmark 3.0 (results available on the web server). Results obtained on the 176 targets of the benchmark 4.0 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Hwang et al., 2010</ref>) confirm the excellent relative docking performance of FRODOCK 2.0 (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>and<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>). The success rates to find an acceptable solution based on CAPRI criteria are 10, 29, 61 and 82% when the top 1, 10, 100 and 1000 predictions are considered, respectively. The accuracy reported for ZDOCK3.02 in (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Huang, 2015</ref>), is slightly higher for the top solutions (10 versus 12) but slightly lower if more predictions are considered (61% versus 52% for the top 100 and 82% versus 79% for the top 1000). Outside this independent comparison, SwarmDock (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Torchala et al., 2013</ref>) also reported slightly better rates for top solutions with the same benchmark (10, 36 and 65% for the top 1, 10, 100 solutions) but considering additional costly refinement procedures, including rescoring and minimization. It is important to note that, in contrast with other methods, our success rates include the docking dependence on the starting orientation as they are computed using 50 runs per case starting from distinct initial relative orientations. The method is quite robust, and we only found relative small ranking variations of the best prediction found depending of the FRODOCK's docking sensitivity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Description of the web server</head><p>The web interface is highly intuitive and responsive to all major browsers. The server performs automatic protein–protein docking of two uploaded input protein structures (in PDB format). Alternatively the user can also select the type of interaction to slightly improve the docking success rates. In only a few minutes, a results page is shown, including a graphical interface to interactively explore the predictions or retrieve the generated models (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). The user can inspect and compare the highly scored poses and visualize docking hot spots. Moreover, a practical interface is included to add multiple distance constraints within a user-specified tolerance, providing an effective way to narrow down the exhaustive docking search. This information is known to significantly enhance docking success rates and is often available from various biophysical and biochemical techniques such as chemical cross-linking, FRET, nuclear or electron magnetic resonances, mass spectrometry, or mutagenesis experiments. Finally, the server is completed with an extensive gallery of examples including all the benchmark test cases presented here to illustrate the quality and limitations of the approach. One of the major advantages of the server is its efficiency. The average docking running time for the benchmark 4.0 test cases is 2 min. FRODOCK 2.0 is a faster alternative to state-of-the-art servers such as ZDOCK (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Pierce et al., 2014</ref>) (11 min) or SwarmDock (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Torchala et al., 2013</ref>) (36 h) with similar predictive performance. Moreover, the user can test different constraints and thresholds on the fly without re-running the docking protocol as in other servers because the constraint module is implemented as a post-docking procedure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusions</head><p>Overall, the server quickly provides reliable potential protein–protein binding conformations that can be further refined and validated by more computationally demanding post-docking procedures. The docking accuracy achieved by adding a complementary knowledgebased protein-docking potential is comparable to the results of existing global docking tools but significantly faster. Future developments include the incorporation of additional experimental constraints (e.g. low resolution information from electron microscopy maps or SAXS) and the integration with docking refinement tools.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.FRODOCK 2.0Funding</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Sample results page. In this example, the high score docking solution (spheres) of the ligand is displayed together with the protein receptor (dark ribbons). The spheres correspond to translational hot spots where the docking scoring was higher than 30%. The user can interactively load and represent different docking solutions with the help of JSmol (Color version of this figure is available at Bioinformatics online.)</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="100"> and 1000 first solutions, respectively. Our approach, FRODOCK (Garzon et al., 2009), which combine 3D grid-based potentials with the efficiency of spherical harmonics (SH) approximations, ranked 4th of the 18 docking/scoring functions tested. Although its success rates were slightly lower than the best three methods for the top 10 predictions (19%), FRODOCK yielded competitive success rates of 46 and 76% for the top 100 and 1000 predictions, respectively. In fact, the authors of this review considered FRODOCK to be a good docking choice if more predictions can be evaluated, which is often the case in a post-docking approach. Interestingly, top ranked methods such as ZODOCK (Pierce et al., 2014) include knowledge-based energy terms that FRODOCK lacks. Here, we present a further update of FRODOCK that includes an extra knowledge-based potential. This new version significantly improves the docking success rate to the levels of existing state-of-the-art approaches but achieves superior efficiency. With integration into a new web framework, users can now predict protein–protein complexes from the unbound V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 2386 Bioinformatics, 32(15), 2016, 2386–2388 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw141 Advance Access Publication Date: 12 March 2016 Applications Note at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">E.Ram ırez-Aportela et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PyDock: electrostatics and desolvation for effective scoring of rigid-body protein–protein docking</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M K</forename>
				<surname>Cheng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins: Struct. Funct. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="503" to="515" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FRODOCK: a new approach for fast rotational protein–protein docking</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Garzon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2544" to="2551" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Search strategies and evaluation in protein–protein docking: principles, advances and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Drug Discov. Today</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1081" to="1096" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the potential of global protein–protein docking: an overview and critical assessment of current programs for automatic ab initio docking</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Drug Discov. Today</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="969" to="977" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein–protein docking benchmark version 4.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Hwang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins: Struct. Funct. Bioinf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3111" to="3114" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The scoring of poses in protein–protein docking: current capabilities and future directions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Moal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="286" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ZDOCK server: interactive docking prediction of protein– protein complexes and symmetric multimers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Pierce</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1771" to="1773" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent progress and future directions in protein–protein docking</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Ritchie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Protein Pept. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein docking using spherical polar Fourier correlations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Ritchie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J L</forename>
				<surname>Kemp</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins: Struct. Funct. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="194" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Designing coarse grained-and atom based-potentials for protein–protein docking</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Tobi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">40</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SwarmDock: a server for flexible protein–protein docking</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Torchala</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="807" to="809" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>