
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">geiger v2.0: an expanded suite of methods for fitting macroevolutionary models to phylogenetic trees</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matthew</forename>
								<forename type="middle">W</forename>
								<surname>Pennell</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>mwpennell@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences and Institute for Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jonathan</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Eastman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences and Institute for Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Graham</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Slater</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Paleobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">National Museum of Natural History</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Smithsonian Institution</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20013</postCode>
									<settlement>Washington</settlement>
									<region>DC</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
								<forename type="middle">W</forename>
								<surname>Brown</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences and Institute for Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>48109</postCode>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Josef</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Uyeda</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences and Institute for Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Richard</forename>
								<forename type="middle">G</forename>
								<surname>Fitzjohn</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Macquarie University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2109</postCode>
									<settlement>Sydney</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Alfaro</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>90095</postCode>
									<settlement>Los Angeles, Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Luke</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Harmon</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences and Institute for Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">geiger v2.0: an expanded suite of methods for fitting macroevolutionary models to phylogenetic trees</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2216" to="2218"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu181</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 24, 2014; revised on March 31, 2014; accepted on April 1, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: David Posada Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Phylogenetic comparative methods are essential for addressing evolutionary hypotheses with interspecific data. The scale and scope of such data have increased dramatically in the past few years. Many existing approaches are either computationally infeasible or inappropriate for data of this size. To address both of these problems , we present geiger v2.0, a complete overhaul of the popular R package geiger. We have reimplemented existing methods with more efficient algorithms and have developed several new approaches for accomodating heterogeneous models and data types. Availability and implementation: This R package is available on the CRAN repository http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/geiger/. All source code is also available on github http://github.com/mwpen-nell/geiger-v2. geiger v2.0 depends on the ape package. Contact:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>In the past few decades, phylogenetic trees have become a key component of evolutionary research. This development has been fueled by the increased availability of robust time-calibrated phylogenies for many groups, in addition to an expanding number of statistical techniques for inferring patterns and processes from comparative data (reviewed in<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Pennell and Harmon, 2013</ref>). Among the many R packages developed for phylogenetic and comparative data (e.g.,<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Paradis et al., 2004</ref>), geiger (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Harmon et al., 2008</ref>) has been a primary utility for making macroevolutionary inferences from phylogenetic trees. However, in the 6 years since the initial release of geiger, the data available for comparative biology have changed substantially. For some groups, we now have phylogenies and corresponding trait data with thousands (and even tens of thousands) of species (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Jetz et al., 2012</ref>). geiger v2.0 is a complete overhaul of the previous release (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Harmon et al., 2008</ref>), designed to scale up comparative methods to large datasets. To do so, we have taken two complementary tacks. The first is to improve algorithms and implementations to increase computational efficiency of existing methods. The second is to expand the suite of statistical approaches to allow for heterogeneity in both models and data types across the phylogeny. In this applications note, we briefly describe the methods now in geiger, with a particular focus on novel implementations and algorithms. Most of these methods have been previously published elsewhere in some form, and we refer readers to the relevant publications for full explanations (for an overview of the main features of the package, see Appendix 1 in Supplementary Material). the function fitDiscrete. We have rewritten this function for geiger v2.0, again using an alternative, more efficient algorithm for calculating the likelihood of observing trait values under a model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">FitzJohn et al., 2009</ref>). In the new version of fitDiscrete, the computational time required for the likelihood calculation scales approximately linearly with the number of character states, whereas the previous version scaled superlinearly (see Appendix 2 in Supplementary Material for details). This improvement allows for more complex models to be efficiently fit to large phylogenies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Bayesian methods for fitting models of character evolution</head><p>A major addition to geiger is the implementation of several Bayesian methods for fitting models of trait evolution to comparative data. These include the Accomodating Uncertainty in Trait Evolution Using R (AUTEUR) approach of<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Eastman et al. (2011)</ref>, which uses reversible jump Markov chain Monte Carlo machinery (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Green, 1995</ref>) to move across multirate models of various complexities. The implementation of this method in geiger v2.0 improves on the original by allowing model partitions to be constrained a priori and alternate models to be compared (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Eastman et al., 2013b</ref>). Additionally, geiger now includes the following: a method for fitting models to phylogenies including unresolved clades using<ref type="bibr">, 2013</ref>). These types of approaches, which allow for greater complexity both in models and data, will be essential to make robust evolutionary inferences from large comparative datasets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Inferring shifts in the rate of lineage diversification</head><p>Alfaro et al. (2009) developed an approach, Modeling Evolutionary Diversification Using Stepwise-AIC (MEDUSA), to detect shifts in diversification rates from molecular phylogenies using a stepwise-Akaike Information Criteria (AIC) algorithm. A single-rate birth–death model is fit to the entire tree, and then the tree is partitioned into two rate classes, breaking the tree at all possible nodes. The partition that improves the fit of the model is then fixed and the process is repeated, breaking the tree into three partitions and so on, until a stopping criterion is reached. MEDUSA can be applied to both fully bifurcating and unresolved trees. For this release of geiger, the MEDUSA algorithm has been improved in a number of ways. First, it has been recoded so that it is now orders of magnitude faster and scales well to large trees; this version of MEDUSA has already been applied to a phylogeny of all 9,993 extant bird species (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Jetz et al., 2012</ref>). Second, we used simulations to develop a threshold-AIC value as a stopping criterion (see Appendix 3 in Supplementary Material for details) to correct for multiple comparisons—the larger the phylogeny, the greater the threshold for accepting a new partition to the model [a similar approach was developed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Thomas and Freckleton (2012)</ref>for studying variation in rates of phenotypic evolution]. Last, we have developed tools for summarizing MEDUSA analyses across a distribution of trees, such as from a Bayesian posterior or from non-parametric bootstrapping, so that uncertainty in both topology and branch lengths can be accomodated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSION</head><p>In this note we provide a broad overview of the methods now available in geiger. We have not discussed some methods implemented in geiger (e.g. 'Congruification' for time-scaling large trees;<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Eastman et al., 2013a</ref>) and many of the nuances of the methods described here have been left out. We refer readers to associated publications and the package documentation for more information. It is an exciting time for macroevolutionary research. We now have access to datasets of unparalleled size and a wide variety of new statistical approaches with which to analyze them. We hope that the software presented here will help researchers address some fundamental and long-standing questions in macroevolution.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Approximate Bayesian Computation (Modeling Evolution of Continuous Characters using Approximate Bayesian Computation, MECCA; Slater et al., 2012b); a method for including fossil information as priors on node states (Slater et al., 2012a); and a posterior predictive simulation approach for assessing the adequacy of common models of trait evolution (Slater and Pennell</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> METHODS 2.1 Fitting simple models of character evolution using maximum likelihood Fitting and comparing models of trait evolution can provide insight into many macroevolutionary questions (Pennell and Harmon, 2013). The two &apos;workhorse&apos; functions in geiger for fitting models of trait evolution using maximum likelihood, fitContinuous and fitDiscrete, have both been completely reimplemented. The previous version of fitContinuous calculated the likelihood of a set of continuous characters (e.g. body size) having evolved under a model using a variance–covariance (vcv) matrix approach. This involves inverting the vcv matrix, which is extremely computationally intensive, making the method infeasible for large trees. FitzJohn (2012) demonstrated that using a &apos;pruning&apos;-based algorithm (Felsenstein, 1973) allows for much more efficient likelihood calculations. This algorithm is used in the diversitree package (FitzJohn, 2012). [For related algorithms, see Freckleton (2012) and the phylolm package (Ho and Ane´,Ane´, 2014)]. The approach has now been extended to all the models in fitContinuous. In addition to improving the efficiency of the algorithm, we have improved numerical optimization procedures and implemented a novel method to simultaneuously estimate model parameters and an additional term to account for measurement error. For the case of modeling discrete characters, the most commonly used models are the Mk models (Pagel, 1994), which can be fit to data with *To whom correspondence should be addressed. y The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors.</note>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">geiger v2.0 at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.W.Pennell et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors are grateful to the large community of researchers— both method developers and users—who have been so generous with their time and expertise. The authors specifically thank Brian O'Meara, Liam Revell, Dan Rabosky, Carl Boettiger, Jeremy Beaulieu, Dan Wegmann and Simon Uribe-Convers who gave numerous helpful insights in the development of this work. The auhtors thank David Posada, Daniele Silvestro and two anonymous reviewers for comments on this note.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nine exceptional radiations plus high turnover explain species diversity in jawed vertebrates</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Alfaro</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13410" to="13414" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel comparative method for identifying shifts in the rate of character evolution on trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Eastman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3578" to="3589" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Congruification: support for time scaling large phylogenetic trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Eastman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="688" to="691" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Simpsonian &apos;evolution by jumps&apos; in an adaptive radiation of anolis lizards</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Eastman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximum-likelihood estimation of evolutionary trees from continuous characters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Felsenstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="471" to="492" />
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diversitree: comparative phylogenetic analyses of diversification in R</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Fitzjohn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1084" to="1092" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating trait-dependent speciation and extinction rates from incompletely resolved phylogenies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Fitzjohn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="595" to="611" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast likelihood calculations for comparative analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Freckleton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="940" to="947" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reversible jump Markov chain Monte Carlo computation and bayesian model determination</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Green</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="711" to="732" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geiger: investigating evolutionary radiations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Harmon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A linear-time algorithm for gaussian and non-gaussian trait evolution models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S T</forename>
				<surname>Ho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Ane´</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Ane´</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="408" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The global diversity of birds in space and time</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Jetz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">491</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="444" to="448" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting correlated evolution on phylogenies: a general method for the comparative analysis of discrete characters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Pagel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. R. Soc. Lon. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">255</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ape: analyses of phylogenetics and evolution in R language</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Paradis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrative view of phylogenetic comparative methods: connections to population genetics, community ecology, and paleobiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Pennell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Harmon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1289</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating fossils with molecular phylogenies improves inference of trait evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Slater</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3931" to="3944" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fitting models of continous trait evolution to incompletely sampled comparative data using approximate Bayesian computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Slater</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="752" to="762" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust regression and posterior predictive simulation increase power to detect early bursts of trait evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Slater</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Pennell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="308" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motmot: models of trait macroevolution on trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Thomas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Freckleton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>