
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:34+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis Genevar: a database and Java application for the analysis and visualization of SNP-gene associations in eQTL studies</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">19 2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Tsun-Po</forename>
								<surname>Yang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1HH</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Claude</forename>
								<surname>Beazley</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1HH</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Stephen</forename>
								<forename type="middle">B</forename>
								<surname>Montgomery</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1HH</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetic Medicine and Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Geneva Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CH-1211</postCode>
									<settlement>Geneva</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Antigone</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Dimas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1HH</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetic Medicine and Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Geneva Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CH-1211</postCode>
									<settlement>Geneva</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Wellcome Trust Centre for Human Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>OX3 7BN</postCode>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Maria</forename>
								<surname>Gutierrez-Arcelus</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetic Medicine and Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Geneva Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CH-1211</postCode>
									<settlement>Geneva</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Barbara</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Stranger</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1HH</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Brigham and Women&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Panos</forename>
								<surname>Deloukas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1HH</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Emmanouil</forename>
								<forename type="middle">T</forename>
								<surname>Dermitzakis</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>emmanouil.dermitzakis@unige.ch</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB10 1HH</postCode>
									<settlement>Hinxton, Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Genetic Medicine and Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Geneva Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CH-1211</postCode>
									<settlement>Geneva</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis Genevar: a database and Java application for the analysis and visualization of SNP-gene associations in eQTL studies</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2474" to="2476"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">19 2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq452</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 12, 2010; revised on July 22, 2010; accepted on August 4, 2010</note>
					<note>[13:57 28/8/2010 Bioinformatics-btq452.tex] Page: 2474 2474–2476 Associate Editor: Martin Bishop Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Genevar (GENe Expression VARiation) is a database and Java tool designed to integrate multiple datasets, and provides analysis and visualization of associations between sequence variation and gene expression. Genevar allows researchers to investigate expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) associations within a gene locus of interest in real time. The database and application can be installed on a standard computer in database mode and, in addition, on a server to share discoveries among affiliations or the broader community over the Internet via web services protocols.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) mapping, where gene expression profiling is treated as a phenotypic trait in genome-wide association studies (GWAS), has successfully been employed to uncover genetic variants that influence expression variation in recent studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Dixon et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Stranger et al., 2007a</ref>). Single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)–gene associations from eQTL analysis can be investigated in populations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Stranger et al., 2007b</ref>) or among tissue types (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Dimas et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Heinzen et al., 2008</ref>). In addition to genome-wide eQTL identification, combinations of eQTLs and lead SNPs identified by GWAS have been provided to interrogate the mechanisms underlying disease susceptibility at specific loci (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Grundberg et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Nica et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Zeller et al., 2010</ref>). However, an analytical and visualization tool, together with a structured repository for multiple datasets, is still needed to facilitate the investigation of loci of interest and to share data publicly and among collaborators. Here, we present Genevar, a database and Java tool designed to provide: (i) data warehousing; (ii) real-time computation of correlation significance; (iii) visualization of mapping results in a user-friendly interface; and (iv) an added web services platform * To whom correspondence should be addressed. that is implemented as a bridge between the server and multiple users. Genevar allows published data to be visually accessible in a secure fashion, without the need for users to download raw data. Through interactive analysis pipelines, researchers are able to rapidly investigate, for instance, cis-acting eQTLs at the locus of interest. Complementing already available standalone tools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Chen et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Ge et al., 2008</ref>), a database-centric architecture enables Genevar to perform complex queries on-the-fly and does not have a high memory requirement for prior reading in large-scale datasets. Furthermore, exploiting the convenience of web-based (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Wang et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Zou et al., 2007</ref>) and web-launch (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Mueller et al., 2005</ref>) tools, a Java interface was developed that connects to both database and web services. The main advantage of this system design is that users can switch between public services and local data on the same interface. Default services at the Sanger Institute currently contain gene expression profiling and genotypic data from the following two datasets: lymphoblastoid cell lines from eight HapMap3 populations (824 individuals, unpublished data); and three cell types derived from umbilical cords of 75 Geneva GenCord individuals (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Dimas et al., 2009</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">FEATURES</head><p>Genevar has two main functionalities in cis-eQTL analysis:</p><p>(i) identifying eQTLs in genes of interest, and (ii) observing SNP–gene associations surrounding SNPs of interest (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). Additional features include SNP–probe association plots and external links to three major genome browsers. Either cis-or transeQTLs can be plotted in the SNP–probe association plot module. Mapping results are listed in tree nodes in a structural manner, and information can be saved as PNG diagrams or exported as tab-delimited lists for further use in presentations or publications. Genevar is compatible with PLINK (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Purcell et al., 2007</ref>) genotype data formats and any tab-delimited expression/genotyping file in our format. After uploading datasets onto the database, Genevar presents expression profiling data and individual genotypes in two cataloged management panels. Once a group of datasets is selected in the follow-up analysis pipelines, the software automatically prompts available expression–genotype pairs for the user to choose from.Spearman's rank correlation coefficient is performed to estimate the strength of relationship between alleles and gene expression intensities, linear regression is also used to model the relationship between the two variables. To test the significance of the relationship, a t-statistic is employed with n−2 degrees of freedom for both correlation and regression analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Stranger et al., 2007b</ref>). The software allows the user to adjust the window size centering on the gene/SNP of interest (e.g. 2 Mb) and userdefined P-value threshold (e.g. P &lt; 0.001) for the featured cis-eQTL analysis. Alternatively, non-parametric permutation P-values are also provided in the subsequent association plot module to further evaluate the significance of nominal P-values. In order to construct a distribution of the test statistic, under the null hypothesis of no SNP–probe associations, expression intensities are randomly re-assigned to individuals' genotypes, then correlation coefficient and statistical significance are re-computed for the relabeled traits, and this procedure is repeated 10 000 times (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Stranger et al., 2005</ref>). We recommend users to launch Genevar via Java Web Start from our homepage for the most up-to-date version. After launching, Genevar is initially in web services mode connecting to the Sanger Institute. The user can then make another services connection to affiliated institutes, or switch to database mode connecting directly to user's local database. Genevar can be run completely offline in database mode as there is no communication between the Java interface and Sanger server. Future work will include modified visualization for displaying next-generation sequence data, e.g. RNA-Seq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Montgomery et al., 2010</ref>); and implementation of methylation modules to interrogate epigenomic data.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Results of Genevar: a scatter plot represents observed eQTLs in a 2 Mb window centering the GBP3 locus in HapMap3 CHB (A), and a line chart illustrates observed SNP–gene associations in a 2 Mb region surrounding rs13277113 SNP in eight HapMap3 populations (B).</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> IMPLEMENTATION This approach to relational database design is an attempt to systematically decompose traditional flat files, which are one record per line and have no structural relationships between the records, into grouped dimension tables and to reduce data redundancy. A normalized and structured repository is suitable to warehouse all kinds of data format regardless of the file size and field numbers. Most importantly, the advantage of using database indexing on expression and genotype fact tables highly stabilize retrieval performance with the subsequent but reasonable cost of slower uploads and increased disk space. The only limitation when the datasets grew would be the storage space as this is a trade-off for query speed. To maximize the potential of Genevar as a platform shared among affiliations, Genevar has been extended to interact with web services protocols to enhance data security; the database schema will be deployed behind and protected by the firewall, whereas only a secure frontend webpage acting as a middle layer will be accessible to the user over the Internet. Genevar uses Hibernate library (http://www.hibernate.org) to map object-oriented models onto MySQL relational database tables (http://www.mysql.com) in the back-end, and acquires Apache CXF framework (http://cxf.apache.org) to wrap up database queries and business logics into middle-layer services. Finally, a Tomcat server (http://tomcat.apache.org) is used to provide services in the front-end. For a standalone database-mode Genevar, only a MySQL database is required to be installed on user&apos;s local machine. Association results are visualized in genomic views by JFreeChart library (http://www.jfree.org/jfreechart/). A gene-centered scatter plot represents observed SNP–gene associations around genes of interest, and a SNP-centered line chart illustrates observed eQTLs surrounding SNPs of interest (Fig. 1). Tested on a 1.6 GHz Pentium Centrino laptop with 1 GB of RAM, Genevar was able to upload a 75×23k expression dataset onto the database and built up indexes in 1 min; another 23 min were required for the 75×400k genotype file. Once it is uploaded, Genevar can fetch per SNP–probe pairs from these 75 individuals in &lt;0.0257 s from the database, and calculates Spearman&apos;s rhos and nominal P-values for 486 SNP–probe pairs in 3 s.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2476"> at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>btq452. .tex]</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2476" to="2474" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T.-P</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Webteam) and Andrew Bryant (Database Team) for helpful support on this project</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">James</forename>
				<surname>Jeffs</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Paul</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Bevan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Sanger</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Funding: Wellcome Trust and Louis-Jeantet Foundation. Conflict of Interest: none declared</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">REFERENCES</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GWAS GUI: graphical browser for the results of wholegenome association studies with high-dimensional phenotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="284" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Common regulatory variation impacts gene expression in a cell type-dependent manner</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Dimas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">325</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1246" to="1250" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A genome-wide association study of global gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Dixon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1202" to="1207" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WGAViewer: software for genomic annotation of whole genome association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Ge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="640" to="643" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Population genomics in a disease targeted primary cell model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Grundberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1942" to="1952" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tissue-specific genetic control of splicing: implications for the study of complex traits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Heinzen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2869" to="2879" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptome genetics using second generation sequencing in a Caucasian population</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Montgomery</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">464</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="773" to="777" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">eQTL Explorer: integrated mining of combined genetic linkage and expression experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Mueller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Candidate causal regulatory effects by integration of expression QTLs with complex trait genetic associations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Nica</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000895</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and populationbased linkage analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Purcell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="559" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide associations of gene expression variation in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Stranger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">78</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relative impact of nucleotide and copy number variation on gene expression phenotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Stranger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">315</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="848" to="853" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Population genomics of human gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Stranger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1217" to="1224" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WebQTL: web-based complex trait analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="308" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and beyond–the transcriptome of human monocytes and disease susceptibility</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Zeller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10693</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">eQTL Viewer: visualizing how sequence variation affects genomewide transcription</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Zou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>