
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:37+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">genomation: a toolkit to summarize, annotate and visualize genomic intervals</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Altuna</forename>
								<surname>Akalin</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>altuna.akalin@fmi.ch, or aakalin@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Friedrich Miescher Institute for Biomedical Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4058</postCode>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Vedran</forename>
								<surname>Franke</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Bioinformatics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Zagreb</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10000</postCode>
									<settlement>Zagreb, Croatia</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kristian</forename>
								<surname>Vlahoviček</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Bioinformatics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Zagreb</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10000</postCode>
									<settlement>Zagreb, Croatia</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oslo</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>NO-0316</postCode>
									<settlement>Oslo</settlement>
									<country>Norway ‡</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christopher</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Mason</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physiology and Biophysics and the Institute for Computational Biomedicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Weill Cornell Medical College</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10021</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dirk</forename>
								<surname>Schü Beler</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>dirk.schubeler@fmi.ch, chm2042@med.cornell.edu,</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Friedrich Miescher Institute for Biomedical Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4058</postCode>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4051</postCode>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">genomation: a toolkit to summarize, annotate and visualize genomic intervals</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu775</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 14, 2014; revised on November 14, 2014; accepted on November 17, 2014</note>
					<note>Genome analysis Present address: Bioinformatics platform, Berlin Institute for Medical Systems Biology (BIMSB), Max Delbrück Center (MDC), Robert-Rö ssle-Straße 10, 13125 Berlin, Germany. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: John Hancock Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Biological insights can be obtained through computational integration of genomics data sets consisting of diverse types of information. The integration is often hampered by a large variety of existing file formats, often containing similar information, and the necessity to use complicated tools to achieve the desired results. We have built an R package, genomation, to expedite the extraction of biological information from high throughput data. The package works with a variety of genomic interval file types and enables easy summarization and annotation of high throughput data sets with given genomic annotations. Availability and implementation: The software is currently distributed under MIT artistic license and freely available at http://bioinformatics.mdc-berlin.de/genomation, and through the Bioconductor framework.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Genomic intervals are the basis of genome annotation and are widely used in short-read alignments, where an interval represents the location of an aligned read. In addition, intervals can contain a variety of scores, with different scales, such as conservation, percent methylation and ChIP-seq enrichment. Summarization of these information-rich intervals over different sub-genomic contexts (promoters, exons, enhancers, etc.) is the necessary first step in making inference about the biological importance of the data. Throughout the text we use the phrase 'genomic annotation' to refer to the regions of the genome associated with a potential function or regions of interest, which do not necessarily have a score (examples: CpG islands, genes, enhancers, promoter, exons, etc.). These genomic annotations provide anchor points, and the general distribution of genomic intervals at and in vicinity to these annotations can assist in biological interpretation of the data.In order to facilitate the extraction of knowledge from genomic intervals, we have developed the R package genomation. This package is a toolkit for annotation and bulk summarization, and visualization of genomic intervals over predefined genomic annotations. genomation is designed to work with genomic intervals stored either in (i) arbitrarily formatted text files containing minimal information about the chromosome, start and end, or (ii) in compressed formats such as BAM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Li et al., 2009</ref>) and BigWig (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Kent et al., 2010</ref>). The package provides functions for computing fast summary statistics about the level of association of genomic intervals with the desired annotation and enables simultaneous visualization of multiple highthroughput experiments over regions of interest through parallel heatmaps, meta-region (meta-gene, meta-promoter, etc.) plots, coverage distribution profiles and pie charts for overlap with annotation (features summarized in<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). In addition, the data structures used in the package can easily be integrated to other analysis in R/Bioconductor (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Gentleman et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">R Core Team, 2013</ref>), which provides a multitude of possibilities for downstream analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Software features</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data import</head><p>The readGeneric() function can read any tabular file containing minimal information about chromosome, start and end positions in addition to any meta-data that can be associated with those genomic locations. In addition to that, readBed() and readGFF() can read BED and GFF formatted files. The genomic intervals contained in the flat files will be represented in memory as Granges objects from GenomicRanges package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Lawrence et al., 2013</ref>). These functions can be used to read both the genomic intervals to be summarized, and the genomic annotations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Annotation of genomic intervals</head><p>Searching for association between different genomic data sets is a standard exploratory method in computational genomics. Typically, we would like to know whether our genomic intervals overlap with previously known annotation and the amount of overlap between those sets. annotateWithFeature() and annotateWithGene Parts() annotate a genomic interval set of interest with a known annotation set such as ChIP-seq peaks or exon/intron/promoter structure of the genes. These results can be visualized with plotGeneAnnotation() or plotTargetAnnotation().</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Summary and visualization of genomic intervals over pre-defined regions</head><p>similarity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Hartigan and Wong, 1979</ref>). In addition, users can provide their own ordering or clustering for the heatmaps.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Conclusion</head><p>genomation is a versatile toolkit for interrogating diverse types of genomic intervals with or without scores. It significantly reduces the time needed for data processing and biological inference by providing a multitude of convenience functions for annotation, summarization and visualization of genomic intervals. Complementing and extending capabilities of similar tools written in other languages (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Ramírez et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Ye et al., 2011</ref>), we believe this R package will be a welcome addition to a bioinformaticians' toolbox. In addition, the data structures used in the package can easily be integrated to other analysis in R/Bioconductor (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Gentleman et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">R Core Team, 2013</ref>). A comprehensive overview of the capabilities is included in package vignette available at http://goo.gl/vHTExn.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Bioinformatics, 31(7), 2015, 1127–1129doi:10.</head><figDesc>1093/bioinformatics/btu775 Advance Access Publication Date: 21 November 2014 Applications Note</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">V C The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">One of the fundamental functionalities of genomation is the ability to summarize genomic intervals over predefined regions. These summaries represent matrices of scores or coverage values for each predefined region. The predefined regions do not have to have the same length. If that is the case, each region will be binned to equal number of bins and a summary statistic (such as mean or median) will be calculated for each bin, keeping the result in a rectangular matrix format in a package-specific object format. The basic functions for constructing matrices are ScoreMatrix() and ScoreMatrix Bin(). The functions have two main mandatory arguments: first is the list of genomic intervals (with or without a score) in the format of GRanges objects, BAM or BigWig files and the second is the list of pre-defined regions such as GRanges objects. These functions will return a ScoreMatrix object or a ScoreMatrixList object that contains multiple matrices, representing the enrichment of multiple experiments over the same sub-genomic set. Such matrices can be visualized in multiple ways. A simpler way of visualization is to construct meta-region plots by taking the average values of the columns and plotting those averages as line plots. The second approach is to make heatmaps for each average profile and stack them on top of each other (Stadler et al., 2011). We have implemented these possibilities in genomation as metaPlot() and metaHeat() functions. Lastly, we can visualize whole matrices as heatmaps (see Fig. 1). We also implemented functions to visualize the score matrices and score matrix lists as a heatmap or a set of heatmaps (heatMatrix() and multiHeatMatrix()) using low-level graphics functions, entirely re-writing heatmap to be able to visualize high-dimensional data efficiently. These functions can also employ Kmeans clustering to plot the rows of the matrices ordered by their Fig. 1. Diagram outlining capabilities of the genomation package, where raw data are summarized, annotated and visualized. The raw data can be in multiple formats such as BED, GFF, BAM and BigWig, as wells as GRanges objects</note>

			<note place="foot">A.Akalin et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Toolkit to summarize, annotate and visualize genomic intervals</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>The research in the laboratory of D.S. was supported by the Novartis Research Foundation, the European Union<ref type="bibr">[</ref></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bioconductor: open software development for computational biology and bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Gentleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">80</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A k-means clustering algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Hartigan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Wong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JSTOR Appl. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BigWig and BigBed: enabling browsing of large distributed datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Kent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2204" to="2207" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Software for computing and annotating genomic ranges</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Lawrence</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The sequence alignment/map format and SAMtools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2078" to="2079" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R Core</forename>
				<surname>Team</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">deepTools: a flexible platform for exploring deepsequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Ramírez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA-binding factors shape the mouse methylome at distal regulatory regions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Stadler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">480</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="490" to="495" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">seqMINER: an integrated ChIP-seq data interpretation platform</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Ye</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>