
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:48+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">GenomeLaser: fast and accurate haplotyping from pedigree genotypes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wenzhi</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">First Affiliated Hospital of Medical School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xi&apos;an Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>710061</postCode>
									<settlement>Xi&apos;an, Shaanxi, China</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Cardiovascular Research Institute and Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Morehouse School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3 4DGENOME Inc</addrLine>
									<postCode>30310, 30033</postCode>
									<settlement>Atlanta, Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>GA, GA</region>
									<country>USA, USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Guoxing</forename>
								<surname>Fu</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Weinian</forename>
								<surname>Rao</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wei</forename>
								<surname>Xu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Cardiovascular Research Institute and Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Morehouse School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3 4DGENOME Inc</addrLine>
									<postCode>30310, 30033</postCode>
									<settlement>Atlanta, Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>GA, GA</region>
									<country>USA, USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Li</forename>
								<surname>Ma</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Cardiovascular Research Institute and Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Morehouse School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3 4DGENOME Inc</addrLine>
									<postCode>30310, 30033</postCode>
									<settlement>Atlanta, Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>GA, GA</region>
									<country>USA, USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Shiwen</forename>
								<surname>Guo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">First Affiliated Hospital of Medical School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xi&apos;an Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>710061</postCode>
									<settlement>Xi&apos;an, Shaanxi, China</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Qing</forename>
								<surname>Song</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Cardiovascular Research Institute and Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Morehouse School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3 4DGENOME Inc</addrLine>
									<postCode>30310, 30033</postCode>
									<settlement>Atlanta, Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>GA, GA</region>
									<country>USA, USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Center of Big Data and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">First Affiliated Hospital of Medical School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xi&apos;an Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Xi&apos;an</addrLine>
									<postCode>710061</postCode>
									<settlement>Shaanxi</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">GenomeLaser: fast and accurate haplotyping from pedigree genotypes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv452</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 24, 2015; revised on July 21, 2015; accepted on July 28, 2015</note>
					<note>Genome analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Associate Editor: John Hancock Contact: qsong@msm.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present a software tool called GenomeLaser that determines the haplotypes of each person from unphased high-throughput genotypes in family pedigrees. This method features high accuracy, chromosome-range phasing distance, linear computing, flexible pedigree types and flexible genetic marker types. Availability and implementation:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Haplotype refers to a group of alleles inherited together on a single chromosome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Browning and Browning, 2011</ref>). Haplotype is essential for mapping disease signals, finding functional cis-acting loops among non-coding elements, imputing the missing values in big data. Genotypes can be obtained directly from high-throughput genotyping or next-generation sequencing, but haplotypes cannot be obtained directly. Given that current high-throughput haplotyping technologies are still expensive (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Fan et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kirkness et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kitzman et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Kuleshov et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Ma et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Rao et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Selvaraj et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Suk et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Yang et al., 2011</ref>) and statistical haplotyping approach suffers from ambiguities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Browning and Browning, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Li et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Liu et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Niu et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Qin et al., 2002</ref>), phasing by pedigrees is the most cost-effective and accurate approach for haplotype determination whenever pedigree genotypes are available (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chen et al., 2013</ref>). Most of the phasing programs by pedigrees assume zero or minimal recombinations and difficult for large complicated and looping pedigrees (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abecasis et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Georges, 2010, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Gao et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kong et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Kruglyak et al., 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Li and Li, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">O'Connell, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">O'Connell et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Sobel and Lange, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Zhang et al., 2005</ref>). The lack of efficient and accurate methods for long-range haplotype determination has hampered the functional interpretation of non-coding cis-acting elements in human genome. Here, we present a computational tool, GenomeLaser, to reconstruct personal haplotypes from unphased genotypes, it can also handle the looped pedigrees and missing genotype data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Features</head><p>Pedigree dissection is the central switchboard throughout the entire procedure (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>). Large pedigrees will be first dissected to nuclear families. If a person is shared by two nuclear families, he/she will be included in both nuclear family units. In the algorithm of Laser I, each nuclear family will be further dissected into trios (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>). A nuclear family with n children will be dissected into n trios. If only one parent is recruited in a study, the parent–child pair will be used. Then the child haplotypesGenomeLaserresolved in Laser I will be sent back to the pedigree dissection algorithm, in which children's haplotypes inherited from the same parent will be grouped (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>) and sent to the Laser II algorithm. In case that a person has children in more than one nuclear family, all of his/her children in different nuclear family units will be grouped together. The algorithm of GenomeLaser is based on the Mendelian Law of Inheritance (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hodge et al., 1999</ref>). It is composed of four components, pedigree dissection, Laser I, Laser II and Laser III (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>). Laser I resolves child haplotypes. It first determines the allele origins of the child using parental genotypes (Supplementary Tables S1 and S2) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hodge et al., 1999</ref>). For example, when a child is AG, his/ her mother is AA and father is AG, under the Mendelian Law of Inheritance, the G allele must come from father and thus the A allele must be inherited from mother. After Laser I determines the parental origin of each allele, all maternally originated alleles will be grouped together and constitute the haplotype of the chromosome inherited from his/her mother and all paternally originated alleles will be grouped and constitute the haplotype of the chromosome inherited from his/her father. If all three members (mother, father, child) of a trio are heterozygous at a single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) locus, Laser I will output XX at the triple-heterozygous SNP site on the child haplotypes of this trio. Laser II resolves parental haplotypes. It first groups the child haplotypes inherited from the same person and then compares the nucleotide sequences among these child haplotypes. A zebra pattern will appear in which identical parts (all alleles are the same) and non-identical segments (all alleles are different) will separate each other along a chromosome. The boundary between an identical segment and an opposite segment will indicate a crossover breakpoint occurred in either gamete of these two children. Laser II then cut the children's haplotypes into pieces at these boundaries and reassemble them into two chromosomal haplotypes (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). After Laser II, there are some loci (8.7 6 5.9% of all SNPs) that are still labeled as NN or XX due to missing data or tripleheterozygotes. Laser III will impute all of those NN and XX sites with an additional input, the reference panel, using the phaseresolved loci by Laser I and II as seeds into Laser III. The algorithm for Laser III was the same as HiFi, whose algorithm was described in a previous publication (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Rao et al., 2013</ref>). The Laser program is coded in Python. The input files include the pedigree relationship, genotypes and an imputation reference panel. The output will be two haplotypes of each person. To examine the performance of the Laser program, we created a simulated dataset containing 30 nuclear families (150 individuals, 116 415 SNPs) in a pedigree structure of two parents and three children (Supplementary Methods) and resolved the haplotypes of all members in this pedigree dataset. Missing data (NN) was introduced into the simulated genotypes at randomly selected loci. The results showed that accuracy was &gt;99.99%, and the error rate was 0.003% on parental haplotypes and 0.0009% on child haplotypes (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S3</ref>). We then created two simulated complicated pedigrees and resolved the haplotypes of all members (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>). The results showed that accuracy was 99.99%, and the error rate was 0.002% (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S4</ref>). Its accuracy is substantially higher compared with other software for phasing pedigrees. We further examined the computing speed on a regular desktop computer (Intel Core i7-2600K CPU at 3.40 GHzx8, 31.3 GB RAM). The computing time of Laser is linear to the number of Trios (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S4</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Conclusion</head><p>GenomeLaser provides an efficient computational tool for determination of molecular haplotypes from unphased genotype data in pedigrees. Accurate chromosome-range personal haplotypes will be extremely useful to explore those long-distance cis-regulatory networks and epigenetic controls of chromosome function. It is not suitable for those scenarios (such as very small genomic regions) in which pedigree information are not available. Briefly, Laser III may be affected by admixture. Laser I and Laser II are based on the Mendelian Law of Inheritance and they will not be affected by genetic admixtures, but Laser III is a reference-based imputation, it will be affected by the admixture. The performance may be improved by the following operations. First, locus-specific ancestry may be determined in parallel with GenomeLaser to monitor the admixtures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Ma et al., 2014</ref>). Second, the reference panels should be either chosen according to the admixture background or based on the pooled reference panels (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Huang et al., 2009</ref>). The statistical haplotyping approaches also use similar strategies to improve imputation performance for admixed samples by either improving the algorithm or careful selecting reference panels (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Huang and Tseng, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Krithika et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Liu et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Zhang et al., 2011</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health (R21HG006173, R43HG007621, HL117929, MD007602, RR003034, U54MD07588). The research was conducted in a facility constructed with support from Research Facilities Improvement Grant 1 C06 RR07571 from the National Center for Research Resources, National Institutes of Health. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 3984 Bioinformatics, 31(24), 2015, 3984–3987 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv452 Advance Access Publication Date: 18 August 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table>Fig. 1. The GenomeLaser principle. (a) Resolving children's haplotypes including red, all-three heterozygotes; blue, misinheritance and gray, missing data. (b) Resolving parental haplotypes. To simplify this figure, we focus 

only on the q arm of maternally derived chromosomes 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Merlin—rapid analysis of dense genetic maps using sparse gene flow trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Abecasis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Haplotype phasing: existing methods and new developments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Browning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Browning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="703" to="714" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genotype calling and haplotyping in parent-offspring trios</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A hidden Markov model combining linkage and linkage disequilibrium information for haplotype reconstruction and quantitative trait locus fine mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Druet</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Georges</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">184</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="789" to="798" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LINKPHASE3: an improved pedigreebased phasing algorithm robust to genotyping and map errors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Druet</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Georges</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="1677" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole-genome molecular haplotyping of single cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Fan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Haplotyping methods for pedigrees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Gao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Hered</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Loss of information due to ambiguous haplotyping of SNPs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Hodge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="360" to="361" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genotype imputation accuracy with different reference panels in admixed populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Tseng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Proc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">64</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genotype-imputation accuracy across worldwide human populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="250" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequencing of isolated sperm cells for direct haplotyping of a human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Kirkness</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="826" to="832" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Haplotype-resolved genome sequencing of a Gujarati Indian individual</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Kitzman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of sharing by descent, long-range phasing and haplotype imputation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Kong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1068" to="1075" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of the imputation performance of the program IMPUTE in an admixed sample from Mexico City using several model designs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Krithika</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Med. Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parametric and nonparametric linkage analysis: a unified multipoint approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Kruglyak</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1347" to="1363" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole-genome haplotyping using long reads and statistical methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Kuleshov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="261" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An almost linear time algorithm for a general haplotype solution on tree pedigrees with no recombination and its extensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bioinform. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="545" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MaCH: using sequence and genotype data to estimate haplotypes and unobserved genotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="816" to="834" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MaCH-admix: genotype imputation for admixed populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Haplotype-association analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="405" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct determination of molecular haplotypes by chromosome microdissection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Ma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate inference of local phased ancestry of modern admixed populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Ma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5800</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian haplotype inference for multiple linked singlenucleotide polymorphisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Niu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general approach for haplotype phasing across the full spectrum of relatedness</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Connell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1004234</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Zero-recombinant haplotyping: applications to fine mapping using SNPs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Connell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Partition-ligation-expectation-maximization algorithm for haplotype inference with single-nucleotide polymorphisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Qin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1242" to="1247" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-resolution whole-genome haplotyping using limited seed data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Rao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="7" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole-genome haplotype reconstruction using proximity-ligation and shotgun sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Selvaraj</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1111" to="1118" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Descent graphs in pedigree analysis: applications to haplotyping, location scores, and marker-sharing statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Sobel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Lange</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1323" to="1337" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comprehensively molecular haplotype-resolved genome of a European individual</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Suk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1672" to="1685" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Completely phased genome sequencing through chromosome sorting</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="17" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Practical consideration of genotype imputation: sample size, window size, reference choice, and untyped rate</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Interface</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="352" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HAPLORE: a program for haplotype reconstruction in general pedigrees without recombination</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>