
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:54+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies GO-Module: functional synthesis and improved interpretation of Gene Ontology patterns</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011 . 2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xinan</forename>
								<surname>Yang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Section of Genetic Medicine and Center for Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jianrong</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Section of Genetic Medicine and Center for Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Younghee</forename>
								<surname>Lee</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Section of Genetic Medicine and Center for Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yves</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Lussier</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Section of Genetic Medicine and Center for Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute for Translational Medicine and Institute for Genomics and Systems Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Ludwig Center for Metastasis Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Computation Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">the University of Chicago</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies GO-Module: functional synthesis and improved interpretation of Gene Ontology patterns</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Bioinformatics BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">27 10</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="64"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011 . 2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr142</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 6, 2010; revised on December 28, 2010; accepted on March 13, 2011</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Availability: http://lussierlab.org/GO-Module Contact: ylussier@bsd.uchicago.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>GO-Module is a web-accessible synthesis and visualization tool developed for end-user biologists to greatly simplify the interpretation of prioritized Gene Ontology (GO) terms. GO-Module radically reduces the complexity of raw GO results into compact biomodules in two distinct ways, by (i) constructing biomodules from significant GO terms based on hierarchical knowledge, and (ii) refining the GO terms in each biomodule to contain only true positive results. Altogether, the features (biomodules) of GO-Module outputs are better organized and on average four times smaller than the input GO terms list (P = 0.0005, n = 16).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Gene Ontology (GO;<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ashburner et al., 2000</ref>) is a standardized representation of biological gene attributes organized in a directed acyclic graph structure, where nodes are GO terms and edges are the hierarchical relationships between them. Prioritized GO terms are routinely computed in functional analyses of genomic studies such as gene expression profiles and high-throughput sequencing. Enrichment and gene set analyses have been implemented to identify significant GO terms from large prioritized gene lists, such as DAVID (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dennis et al., 2003</ref>), Onto-express (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Draghici et al., 2003a</ref>), Global test (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Draghici et al., 2003b</ref>), GOstats (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Falcon and Gentleman, 2007</ref>), etc. However, when presented with the resulting extensive list of GO terms, biologists cannot readily synthesize their relationships and rigorously prioritize hypotheses. Two approaches have generally been used for refining overabundant GO terms resulting from genomic studies. The first approach reduces the number of GO terms studied thus decreasing the total prioritized ones. For instance, GOSlim (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Harris et al., 2004</ref>) contains a small list of 127 key terms (2010 August version) curated a priori by expert biologists, while GOPaD dynamically calculates the most informative subset of GO terms from a prioritized gene list by disregarding other statistically significant GO terms * To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p><p>(<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alterovitz et al., 2007</ref>). These approaches are designed to eliminate a massive number of GO terms deemed as significant by statistics, thus severely limiting the expressiveness of the resulting list of GO terms. A second group of approaches removes falsely prioritized GO terms that are computational artifacts attributable to the inheritance of genes (signal) in the GO hierarchy occurring in enrichment studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Rhee et al., 2008</ref>). For example, a bottom-up conditional hypergeometric test can conservatively remove inherited genes annotated to statistically significant descendants nodes before testing the parent GO nodes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Falcon and Gentleman, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Grossmann et al., 2007</ref>). However, this test also eliminates true-positive GO nodes such as those whose child nodes are all significant. We developed an approach that only prunes a parent node if its inherited signal is equal or worse to that of its most statistically significant child (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lee et al., 2010</ref>). This approach retains key parent GO terms whose increased statistical significance is amplified by inheriting multiple children's signals indicating an overarching systems property, a key GO term, emerging from subsumed GO terms. We hypothesized that grouping prioritized GO terms in biomodules could further improve their interpretation by biologists, and would thus allow for the synthesis and reduction of the overall number of biological features while explicitly encapsulating subsumed GO terms. This approach focuses on biomodules of GO terms rather than of individual genes. While prioritized gene lists have been shown to aggregate in biomodules associated to GO terms in co-expression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Wolfe et al., 2005</ref>) and protein interaction studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Cho et al., 2007</ref>), software designed to group gene lists into gene biomodules using GO knowledge produce large numbers of GO terms for interpretation without any coherent organization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">GO BIOMODULE ONLINE TOOL: GO-MODULE</head><p>Here we described GO-Module, a user-friendly, parameter-free and web-accessible synthesis and visualization tool developed for enduser biologists to improve their analysis of prioritized GO terms by removing false-positive GO terms and organizing the remaining ones as GO biomodules. We previously described the algorithm as a hierarchical refinement of a prioritized list of GO terms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lee et al., 2010</ref>). Three characters are used to annotate the results where 'K' refers to the key terms of GO biomodules, 'T' refers to the truly significant hierarchical descendents of the key terms and 'F' refers to the false positive prioritized GO terms among the input. This</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GO-Module</head><p>algorithm follows the steps described below and is illustrated in more detail in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S1</ref>(1) Annotates a node as 'K' (key GO term) if every one of its children or parents is less prioritized than itself. To allow for straightforward interpretation of the key GO terms as 'local minima in a directed acyclic graph', these key terms are locally prioritized within contiguous relationships (e.g. parent and child).</p><p>(2) As long as contiguous descendents of a 'K' node are not themselves new 'K' nodes, GO-Module annotates them as 'T' (subsumed true-positive GO terms as a member of the biomodule).</p><p>(3) Assigns 'F' (false positive) to the remaining GO terms.</p><p>(4) Assigns a unique numerical label to each 'K' GO term and to all its 'T' descendants. Note that this assignment is a number that has no bearing on the rank and that a 'T' node may have more than one biomodule label. Output: GO-Module provides three alternative output formats of identified terms and their relationships in biomodules: (i) an online table, (ii) a downloadable text file with five columns containing two input columns following by labels of significance, full names of the GO IDs and identified GO biomodules or (iii) a fixed graphic vector network visualization of resultant IDs or their terms (pdf format) preferably for lists of up to 500 GO terms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>Example data: To demonstrate the efficacy of GO-Module, we examined prioritized GO lists reported in the literature (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). Results: GO-Module significantly reduces the features as measured by the ratio of 16 literature reported GO lists to their number of resultant biomodules (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>, #K/#GO ranging from 28 to 91%; P = 0.0005, n = 16, Wilcoxon's signed rank test compared with theoretical median of 100%). Specifically, we report that on average 28% of input terms were found to be false positives (F), and among the remaining K and T terms, 33% are linked together in GO-Module of two or more terms (data not shown). Relatively general terms were rejected in several of the independently published GO lists because their P-values were larger than that of their children terms. In two cases in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>, 'regulation of tumor necrosis factor biosynthetic process' (GO:0042534) was rejected, while its child term 'positive regulation of tumor necrosis factor biosynthetic process' (GO:0042535) was retained (<ref type="bibr">Heinig et al., 2010 in Fig. 1;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Marcucci et al., 2008</ref>), demonstrating that this feature reduction eliminated redundant GO terms, while retaining useful informative ones. Self-evident uninformative terms such as 'positive regulation of biological process' (GO:0048518) are also annotated as false positive by GO-Module in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>. Conclusively, by synthesizing significant GO outputs and constructing biomodules, GO-Module better facilitates the biological understanding and interpretation of genetic analyses. Additionally, GO-Module can refine GO signatures found using conventional methods without requiring that the user revisit any gene expression or GO databases. By requiring prioritized GO<ref type="bibr">et al., 2000</ref>) version 1.7 were used as the input for GO-Module.terms rather than gene lists as its input, GO-Module prunes and modularizes results of conventional enrichment studies (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>) while remaining remarkably simple for end-users such as biologists and translational scientists.</p><p>Page: 1446 1444–1446</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>X.Yang et al.</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>[17:46 18/4/2011 Bioinformatics-btr142.tex] Page: 1445 1444–1446</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Visualization of GO-Module output from the online portal. The key terms are seen as octagons, descendants of identified key terms as circles and false positive terms as dash lined circles. The contiguous hierarchical terms are linked together by lines. GO list from Heinig et al., 2010.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>. Inputs: GO-Module requires a table containing: (i) a list of prioritized GO IDs and (ii) their corresponding rankable qualifiers, such as P-values or simply ordinal numbers.</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. GO-Module applied to lists of prioritized GO terms a</figDesc><table>Retained 
features 
(#K/#GO) 
(%) 

Input Output 
Journal (author year) 

#GO #K #T #F 

53 
15 b 
8 
2 
5 Oncogene (Yamaguchi et al., 2010) 
63 
24 
15 
4 
5 Nature (Burke et al., 2010) 
28 
162 
46 63 53 Nature (Heinig et al., 2010) 
57 
65 b 37 
8 20 Cell (Smukalla et al., 2008) 
41 
189 b 76 47 64 Cell (Smukalla et al., 2008) 
50 
16 
8 
2 
6 N. Engl. J. Med. (Marcucci et al., 2008) 
45 
20 
9 
0 11 Genome Res. (Swanson-Wagner et al. 2010) 
91 
23 
21 
2 
0 Genome Res. (Mortazavi et al. 2010) 
86 
35 b 30 
2 
3 Genome Res. (Somel et al. 2010) 
90 
21 b 19 
1 
1 Genome Res. (Vinuela et al. 2010) 
70 
30 
21 
2 
7 Genome Res. (Atanur et al. 2010) 
46 
13 
6 
2 
5 Genome Res. (Hoffman et al. 2010) 
40 
20 b 
8 
6 
2 Genome Res. (Hoffman et al. 2010) 
44 
9 
4 
3 
2 Genome Res. (Hoffman et al. 2010) 
50 
10 
5 
1 
4 Genome Res. (Hoffman et al. 2010) 
50 
10 
5 
0 
5 Genome Res. (Liu et al. 2010) 

a Twelve scientific papers (16 GO lists) were selected in the following way: the first five 

were prioritized by a Google search for 'significant GO terms'and each of four renowned 
journal names and the remaining seven were sequentially found in the journal Genome 
Research by manually searching from 12/2010 back to 5/2010 for GO lists containing 
more than eight prioritized terms. 
b Only the reported terms with trackable official GO IDs using AmiGO (Ashburner 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank Ellen Rebman and Yang Liu for their advice and review.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GO PaD: the Gene Ontology partition database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Alterovitz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="322" to="327" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genome sequence of the spontaneously hypertensive rat: analysis and functional significance</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Atanur</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="791" to="803" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide analysis of a long-term evolution experiment with Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Burke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">467</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="587" to="590" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semantic integration to identify overlapping functional modules in protein interaction networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Cho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">265</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DAVID: Database for annotation, visualization, and integrated discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Dennis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Jr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Onto-Tools, the toolkit of the modern biologist: OntoExpress, Onto-Compare, Onto-Design and Onto-Translate</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Draghici</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3775" to="3781" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global functional profiling of gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Draghici</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="98" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using GOstats to test gene lists for GO term association</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Falcon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Gentleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved detection of overrepresentation of Gene-Ontology annotations with parent child analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Grossmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3024" to="3031" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Gene Ontology (GO) database and informatics resource</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Harris</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="258" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A trans-acting locus regulates an anti-viral expression network and type 1 diabetes risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Heinig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">467</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="460" to="464" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An effective model for natural selection in promoters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Hoffman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Birney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="685" to="692" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network modeling identifies molecular functions targeted by mir-204 to suppress head and neck tumor metastasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000730</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of copy number variations among diverse cattle breeds</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="693" to="703" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MicroRNA expression in cytogenetically normal acute myeloid leukemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Marcucci</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N. Engl. J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">358</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1919" to="1928" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scaffolding a Caenorhabditis nematode genome with RNAseq</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Mortazavi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1740" to="1747" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use and misuse of the gene ontology annotations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Rhee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="515" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FLO1 is a variable green beard gene that drives biofilm-like cooperation in budding yeast</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Smukalla</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="726" to="737" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MicroRNA, mRNA, and protein expression link development and aging in human and macaque brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Somel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1207" to="1218" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pervasive gene content variation and copy number variation in maize and its undomesticated progenitor</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Swanson-Wagner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1689" to="1699" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide gene expression regulation as a function of genotype and age in C.elegans</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Vinuela</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="929" to="937" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic survey reveals general applicability of &quot; guilt-byassociation &quot; within gene coexpression networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Wolfe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">227</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of an ovarian clear cell carcinoma gene signature that reflects inherent disease biology and the carcinogenic processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncogene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1741" to="1752" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>