
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:59+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis GREVE: Genomic Recurrent Event ViEwer to assist the identification of patterns across individual cancer samples</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">. 22 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jean-Baptiste</forename>
								<surname>Cazier</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Wellcome Trust Centre for Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Roosevelt Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>OX3 7BN</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chris</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Holmes</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Wellcome Trust Centre for Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Roosevelt Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>OX3 7BN</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<surname>Broxholme</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Wellcome Trust Centre for Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Roosevelt Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>OX3 7BN</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 South Parks Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>OX1 3TG</postCode>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis GREVE: Genomic Recurrent Event ViEwer to assist the identification of patterns across individual cancer samples</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2981" to="2982"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">. 22 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts547</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 11, 2012; revised on August 3, 2012; accepted on September 2, 2012</note>
					<note>Associate Editor:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>GREVE has been developed to assist with the identification of recurrent genomic aberrations across cancer samples. The exact characterization of such aberrations remains a challenge despite the availability of increasing amount of data, from SNParray to next-generation sequencing. Furthermore, genomic aberrations in cancer are especially difficult to handle because they are, by nature, unique to the patients. However, their recurrence in specific regions of the genome has been shown to reflect their relevance in the development of tumors. GREVE makes use of previously characterized events to identify such regions and focus any further analysis. Availability: GREVE is available through a web interface and open-source application (http://www.well.ox.ac.uk/GREVE).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Genomic aberrations have been the subject of much interest in the past decade with variable degrees of success. Two categories have to be distinguished: exactly matching germline and unique, often somatic, aberrations. There has been much effort to identify and catalogue the former in order to treat them like regular markers such as SNPs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Iafrate et al., 2004</ref>). The first difficulty lies in the exact characterization of the breakpoints. Furthermore, such inventory is impossible for somatic events that are by definition unique. Still, the recurrence of overlapping regions can indicate a key controlling area, e.g. a small deletion on 9p in adolescent acute lymphoblastic leukemia (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Paulsson et al., 2008</ref>). Current approaches are essentially based on either the integration into a general-purpose browser to provide context, but no measure of overlap, or the creation of a heatmap where the copy number itself is used as a metric across all types of events to characterize the recurrence (Cancer Genome WorkBench, https://cgwb.nci.nih.gov/cgi-bin/heatmap;<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Mermel et al., 2011</ref>). This single continuous value is then used to construct a score at every location. GREVE is designed to look into further details by allowing the user to define further subgroups such as copy neutral LOH that would be ignored otherwise. Furthermore, GREVE provides a highly configurable interface and specific statistics on recurrent events. GREVE has been successfully used in numerous cancer studies where the cohort size varied from a handful (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Langemeijer et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Olsson et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Paulsson et al., 2010</ref>) to hundreds (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Gupta et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">O'Shea et al., 2009</ref>). Highly flexible, GREVE provides the ability to statistically explore a given dataset and to present results in a ready-to-publish format.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">FEATURES</head><p>The purpose of GREVE is to enable a flexible view of aberrations across the genome, or per chromosome, and score their recurrence. Therefore, the default usage is very simple with the input of the sole list of events being sufficient, while it is highly configurable with further optional input to help the inspection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Key features</head><p>GREVE transforms a list of events into a genomic representation, summarizes and scores their recurrence across samples:</p><p>Read flat or Excel input files containing a list of event per individual and type, with build 35, 36 or 37 location (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1b</ref>). Plot all events genome-wide and per chromosome with cytobands. The views can either sort all the events or overlay them with a fixed set of individuals (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1c</ref>). Calculate, tabulate and plot recurrence within any given type of events (e.g. Gain, Loss and LOH), score each overlapping segment across multiple statistics (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1c</ref>). Generate publication-ready figures in several graphical formats (EPS, PDF, PNG, JPG or TIFF;<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1c</ref>). Inclusion of key genes on the per-chromosome plot as given in a separate list or known CNV from the Database of Genomic Variants (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Iafrate et al., 2004</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Formatting features</head><p>Because each study will have varying numbers of individuals and events, the default layout may not be optimal. All positions and colors are available in an optional configuration file.Merger of exactly matching events into a larger block.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>The GREVE web front end is implemented in HTML/PHP as a wrapper around the Python (van<ref type="bibr">Rossum and Drake, 2001)</ref>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. script engine running on the web server. It requires ImageMagick software (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Still, 2005</ref>) for figure format conversion from the default Encapsulated PostScript format. The Poisson binomial test is implemented as a wrapper around the Poibin R-package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Hong et al., 2011</ref>). The web interface allows the upload of all necessary files and a convenient way to select filters and options. It then outputs ready-to-publish figures as well as overlapping details. Examples and frequently asked questions are available on the website. All the options in the engine software are available through the graphical interface. However, to allow batch processing and further analysis, the source code is available on the website. This should allow specific extensions to match any given project such as subgrouping of individuals (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Purdie et al., 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Purdie et al., , 2010</ref>). The large demo analysis with 709 events across 30 samples takes 7 s on an AMD64 3.0 GHz processor with 64 Gb of RAM to process with overlaps and scores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Input files</head><p>Only the list of events with corresponding sample labels and type is necessary to run GREVE. It can be generated from the output of various aberration callers from SNP or CGH array as well as sequencing data with eventual post-processing (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1a</ref>and b). Further optional flags, filters and files can be provided to add information or tailor the presentation:An optional configuration file allows further tailoring of the figures without the need to modify the program.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Output</head><p>The result of the analysis is composed of figures and tables (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1c</ref></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Size and color choice for each aberration type. Distance between successive events and chromosomes. Highlight aberration of certain type (default 'LOH').</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>The list of events with location, sample labels and type of aberration. An optional gene list with name and position.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>): Genome-wide and chromosome view of the events in all formats. Details of the overlap of events across each chromosome are available directly in the interface as a table or in a separate file. The counts and proportion of overlap reflect the comparison to a control set where no somatic event would be expected. The Poisson binomial P-value tests the probability of a type occurring at the same location depending on the individual proportion on a chromosome (C_P) or genome-wide (GW_P).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Usage of GREVE where (a) pre-processing from any source generates a list of events to be used as (b) input together with the optional DGV, Configuration and Gene file. This can generate several output (c): two types of genome-wide views (sorted by aberration type or individual), chromosome view with overlap, gene and labels, as well as the detailed list of overlapping events with corresponding counts and statistics</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel regions of acquired uniparental disomy discovered in acute myeloid leukemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Gupta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Chromosomes Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="729" to="739" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On computing the distribution function for the sum of independent and non-identical random indicators</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Hong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technical Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of large-scale variation in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Iafrate</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="949" to="951" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acquired mutations in TET2 are common in myelodysplastic syndromes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Langemeijer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="838" to="842" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GISTIC2.0 facilitates sensitive and confident localization of the targets of focal somatic copy-number alteration in human cancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Mermel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clonal evolution through loss of chromosomes and subsequent polyploidization in chondrosarcoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Olsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24977</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regions of acquired uniparental disomy at diagnosis of follicular lymphoma are associated with both overall survival and risk of transformation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Shea</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2298" to="2301" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microdeletions are a general feature of adult and adolescent acute lymphoblastic leukemia: unexpected similarities with pediatric disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Paulsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6708" to="6713" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic landscape of high hyperdiploid childhood acute lymphoblastic leukaemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Paulsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21719" to="21724" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single nucleotide polymorphism array analysis defines a specific genetic fingerprint for well-differentiated cutaneous SCCs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Purdie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Invest. Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1562" to="1568" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-resolution genomic profiling of human papillomavirus-associated vulval neoplasia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Purdie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br. J. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1044" to="1051" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Definitive Guide to ImageMagick</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Still</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Python Reference Manual</title>
		<editor>van Rossum,G. and Drake,F.L.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>