
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">GROMACS molecule &amp; liquid database</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<surname>Van Der Spoel</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cell and Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Uppsala University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Husargatan 3</addrLine>
									<postBox>Box 596</postBox>
									<postCode>SE-75124</postCode>
									<settlement>Uppsala</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Paul</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Van Maaren</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cell and Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Uppsala University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Husargatan 3</addrLine>
									<postBox>Box 596</postBox>
									<postCode>SE-75124</postCode>
									<settlement>Uppsala</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Carl</forename>
								<surname>Caleman</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>carl.caleman@cfel.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Coherent Imaging Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Free-Electron Laser Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron Notkestrasse 85</addrLine>
									<postCode>DE-22607</postCode>
									<settlement>Hamburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">GROMACS molecule &amp; liquid database</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="752" to="753"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts020</idno>
					<note type="submission">Databases and ontologies Advance Access publication January 11, 2012 Received on December 7, 2011; revised on January 2, 2012; accepted on January 5, 2010</note>
					<note>[13:15 25/2/2012 Bioinformatics-bts020.tex] Page: 752 752–753 Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The molecular dynamics simulation package GROMACS is a widely used tool used in a broad range of different applications within physics, chemistry and biology. It is freely available, user friendly and extremely efficient. The GROMACS software is force field agnostic, and compatible with many molecular dynamics force fields; coarse-grained, unified atom, all atom as well as polarizable models based on the charge on a spring concept. To validate simulations, it is necessary to compare results from the simulations to experimental data. To ease the process of setting up topologies and structures for simulations, as well as providing pre-calculated physical properties along with experimental values for the same we provide a web-based database, containing 145 organic molecules at present. Results: Liquid properties of 145 organic molecules have been simulated using two different force fields, OPLS all atom and Generalized Amber Force Field. So far, eight properties have been calculated (the density, enthalpy of vaporization, surface tension, heat capacity at constant volume and pressure, isothermal compressibility, volumetric expansion coefficient and the static dielectric constant). The results, together with experimental values are available through the database, along with liquid structures and topologies for the 145 molecules, in the two force fields. Availability: The database is freely available under http://cyclo
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Molecular dynamics simulations can be a very useful tool in understanding fundamental interactions in simple molecular liquids and crystals as well as complex biomolecular systems. The accuracy of predictions based on molecular dynamics simulations are limited by the applied force field. Force fields are normally developed to reproduce certain specific experimental properties, such as density or energies, or to reproduces known molecular structures. A model that captures the basic physics underlying the atomic interactions can in principle be used to predict outside the realm of parameterization, and this is in fact often done. In order to validate the predictions based on force fields, we have recently performed force field benchmarks of proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Lange et al., 2010</ref>) and liquids (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Caleman et al., 2012</ref>). * To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p><p>The latest incarnation of the GROMACS software was described by<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hess et al. (2008)</ref>while a recent overview paper (van der<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Spoel and Hess, 2011</ref>) describes future prospects for the software suite. Here we present a database holding simulation resources, namely liquid structures and topology files. The construction of molecular topologies—describing connectivity, atom types and partial charges—is unfortunately still cumbersome. There is a large user base for the GROMACS software—over 2000 people that subscribe to a mailing list—and therefore we envision that there will be a significant demand for the kind of service the molecule &amp; liquid database provides, since questions about topology building are among the most common ones on the mailing list.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>The database contains GROMACS topology files (.top/.itp) for all the included molecules, for both the Generalized Amber Force Field (GAFF) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Wang et al., 2004</ref>) and OPLS/AA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Jorgensen and Tirado-Rives, 2005</ref>) force fields. The molecular models were built using Molden (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Schaftenaar and Noordik, 2000</ref>) and PRODRG (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Schuettelkopf and van Aalten, 2004</ref>), and optimized using quantum calculations with Gaussian 03 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Frisch et al., 2004</ref>) at the Hartree-Fock level employing the 6-311G** basis set (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Blaudeau et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Krishnan et al., 1980</ref>), as provided by the Basis Set Exchange website (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Schuchardt et al., 2007</ref>). The GAFF topologies were generated using the Antechamber software (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Wang et al., 2004</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Wang et al., , 2005</ref>) using partial charges calculated with the restrained electrostatic potential method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bayly et al., 1993</ref>). The GAFF topologies were converted into GROMACS format using the amb2gmx.pl script (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Mobley et al., 2006</ref>) (http://ffamber.cnsm.csulb.edu/) — note that at present the ACPYPI tool (http://code.google.com/p/acpype/) is the recommended tool for converting from AMBER to GROMACS. OPLS/AA topologies were built using GROMACS tools and verfied manually. Gas-phase structures as well as liquid structures (after equilibration) are available for all molecules in pdb format. Finally, the database contains simulated and, where available, experimental physical properties (fully referenced) for up to eight different observables for all molecules: the density, enthalpy of vaporization, heat capacities at constant pressure and constant volume, the surface tension, isothermal compressibility, volumetric expansion coefficient and the static dielectric constant. For details about the underlying simulations and analysis, we refer to (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Caleman et al., 2012</ref>). All data are stored in a database, using the structured query langauge (SQL) to ensure portability, which is processed using a script to obtain the (at present) completely static website. The website is organized using a relatively simple directory structure with one subdirectory per compound, and within these one subdirectory per force field.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DISCUSSION</head><p>The molecular modeling community has a lot to gain from easy access to pre-equilibrated simulation structures and topologies thatare validated against experimental data. The GROMACS molecule &amp; liquid database freely provides this for a set of over a hundred molecules, an example molecule entry being shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>. Presently, two of the most widely used force fields for organic molecules, GAFF (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Wang et al., 2004</ref>) and OPLS/AA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Jorgensen and Tirado-Rives, 2005</ref>) are supported, and there are plans to include models based on the CHARMM generalized force field (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Vanommeslaeghe et al., 2010</ref>) as well. The expectation is that this test set will help users to establish how good these force fields are not only for the molecules included, but also for similar molecules. For this reason, the test set was picked such that it would include a large variety of chemical moieties. All topologies and structures available have been checked manually and calculated physical properties along with experimental data are provided for each of the the molecules, including corresponding experimental data which is fully referenced. A similar effort providing input files for molecules based on the GROMOS96 force field (van<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gunsteren et al., 1996</ref>) was announced recently (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Malde et al., 2011</ref>). Further molecules, simulation results and corresponding experimental data will be added to the database in the future. The ultimate goal with this work is to build up a large database, that can be used both for getting reliable topologies and liquid structures, and to provide a list of relevant physical properties for comparison to experiments. The reference values provided (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Caleman et al., 2012</ref>) can also serve as a benchmark for force field improvements, for instance using polarizable models (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Caleman and van der Spoel, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Caleman et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">van der Spoel and Hess, 2011</ref>; van Maaren and van der<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Spoel, 2001</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GROMACS Database</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>[13:15 25/2/2012 Bioinformatics-bts020.tex] Page: 753 752–753</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Example (partial) molecule entry for N-methylformamide.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We would also like to thank Minyan Hong and Marjolein van der Spoel for help with collecting experimental data. Funding: Swedish research council (to D.v.d.S.); Helmholtz Association through the Center for Free-Electron Laser Science (to C.C). We acknowledge a grant for computer time (SNIC022-09/10) through the national supercomputer center (NSC) in Linköping and the parallel computing center (PDC) in Stockholm, Sweden.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of Interest: none declared.</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A well-behaved electrostatic potential based method using charge restraints for deriving atomic charges – the RESP model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Bayly</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10269" to="10280" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extension of Gaussian-2 (G2) theory to molecules containing third-row atoms K and Ca</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Blaudeau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5016" to="5021" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaporation from water clusters containing singly charged ions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Caleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Van Der Spoel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5105" to="5111" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomistic simulation of ion solvation in water explains surface preference of halides</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Caleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6838" to="6842" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Force field benchmark of organic liquids: density, enthalpy of vaporization, heat capacities, surface tension, compressibility, expansion coefficient and dielectric constant</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Caleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Theor. Comp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Gaussian 03, Revision C.02</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Frisch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<publisher>Gaussian, Inc. Wallingford CT</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GROMACS 4: algorithms for highly efficient, load-balanced, and scalable molecular simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Hess</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Theory Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="447" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Potential energy functions for atomic-level simulations of water and organic and biomolecular systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Jorgensen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Tirado-Rives</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6665" to="6670" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-consistent molecular-orbital methods. 20. Basis set for correlated wave-functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Krishnan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="650" to="654" />
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scrutinizing molecular mechanics force fields on the submicrosecond timescale with NMR data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Lange</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="647" to="655" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An automated force field topology builder (ATB) and repository: version 1.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Malde</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Theory Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4026" to="4037" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the use of orientational restraints and symmetry corrections in alchemical free energy calculations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Mobley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">84902</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molden: a pre-and post-processing program for molecular and electronic structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Schaftenaar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Noordik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Aid. Mol. Des</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basis set exchange: a community database for computational sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Schuchardt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1045" to="1052" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PRODRG-a tool for highthroughput crystallography of protein-ligand complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Schuettelkopf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M F</forename>
				<surname>Van Aalten</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Act. Crystallogr. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1355" to="1363" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gromacs-the road ahead</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Van Der Spoel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Hess</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Mol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="710" to="715" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biomolecular Simulation: The GROMOS96 Manual and User Guide. Hochschuleverlag AG an der ETH Zürich Molecular dynamics simulations of water with a novel shell-model potential</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Van Gunsteren</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2618" to="2626" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Charmm general force field: a force field for druglike molecules compatible with the charmm all-atom additive biological force fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Vanommeslaeghe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="690" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development and testing of a general amber force field</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1157" to="1174" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antechamber, an accessory software package for molecular mechanical calculations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1157" to="1174" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>