
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">HiSpOD: probe design for functional DNA microarrays</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eric</forename>
								<surname>Dugat-Bony</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire Microorganismes: Génome et Environnement</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Clermont Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>BP 10448</addrLine>
									<postCode>F63000</postCode>
									<region>Clermont-Ferrand</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR CNRS 6023</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3 Clermont Université</addrLine>
									<postCode>63000</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">LIMOS</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>BP 10448</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-63000</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mohieddine</forename>
								<surname>Missaoui</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR CNRS 6158</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">LIMOS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-63173</postCode>
									<settlement>Aubière</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eric</forename>
								<surname>Peyretaillade</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR CNRS 6023</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3 Clermont Université</addrLine>
									<postCode>63000</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">LIMOS</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>BP 10448</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-63000</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire Microorganismes: Génome et Environnement</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Clermont Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université d&apos;Auvergne</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>BP 10448</addrLine>
									<postCode>F63000</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Corinne</forename>
								<surname>Biderre-Petit</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire Microorganismes: Génome et Environnement</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Clermont Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>BP 10448</addrLine>
									<postCode>F63000</postCode>
									<region>Clermont-Ferrand</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR CNRS 6023</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3 Clermont Université</addrLine>
									<postCode>63000</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">LIMOS</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>BP 10448</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-63000</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ourdia</forename>
								<surname>Bouzid</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire Microorganismes: Génome et Environnement</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Clermont Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>BP 10448</addrLine>
									<postCode>F63000</postCode>
									<region>Clermont-Ferrand</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR CNRS 6023</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3 Clermont Université</addrLine>
									<postCode>63000</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">LIMOS</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>BP 10448</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-63000</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christophe</forename>
								<surname>Gouinaud</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR CNRS 6158</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">LIMOS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-63173</postCode>
									<settlement>Aubière</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<surname>Hill</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR CNRS 6158</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">LIMOS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-63173</postCode>
									<settlement>Aubière</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pierre</forename>
								<surname>Peyret</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR CNRS 6023</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3 Clermont Université</addrLine>
									<postCode>63000</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Blaise Pascal</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">LIMOS</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>BP 10448</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-63000</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire Microorganismes: Génome et Environnement</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Clermont Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université d&apos;Auvergne</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>BP 10448</addrLine>
									<postCode>F63000</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">HiSpOD: probe design for functional DNA microarrays</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="641" to="648"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq712</idno>
					<note type="submission">Gene expression Advance Access publication January 6, 2011</note>
					<note>Page: 641 641–648 Associate Editor: Trey Ideker</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The use of DNA</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Microbes mediate almost every conceivable biological process on the planet. It is estimated that about 10 30 bacterial and archaeal cells are involved in these tremendous metabolic potentialities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Whitman et al., 1998</ref>). To access to this wide metabolic diversity, environmental functional gene arrays (FGAs) are high-throughput tools which allow analyzing the presence or the expression of thousands of genes encoding key enzymes involved in many metabolic process in only one experiment. However, designing * To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. DNA microarray probes to encompass the full diversity of gene family sequences encountered in nature and not yet identified is still one of the most difficult challenges. In addition, the difficulty to obtain sufficient nucleic acid materials for microarray studies from environmental samples requires the development of highly sensitive probes. Currently, the most complete FGA available to monitor bacterial metabolism in complex ecosystems is GeoChip (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">He et al., 2007</ref>) with a latest version covering ∼47 000 gene variants from more than 290 gene categories (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">He et al., 2008</ref>). GeoChip has already demonstrated its power in assessing in situ bacterial activity, reinforcing the idea that functional microarray are an efficient approach (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Berthrong et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kimes et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Leigh et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Liang et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Mason et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Rhee et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Van Nostrand et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Wang et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Yergeau et al., 2007</ref>). However, the main problem that must be faced for functional microarray applications is the complexity of the oligonucleotide design step which hinders their development. Many parameters such as probe length, melting temperature (T m ), %GC, complexity or still potential cross-hybridizations evaluation (percent similarity and identity stretch between probe and nontargeted sequences) must be taken into account to ensure the selection of the oligonucleotides offering the best compromise between specificity and sensitivity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Kane et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Pozhitkov et al., 2007</ref>). Fortunately, numerous bioinformatics tools, which estimate most of these parameters, have been developed to perform this crucial probe design step (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Lemoine et al., 2009</ref>). Currently, the most popular software for FGA probe design are OligoWiz (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Wernersson and Nielsen, 2005</ref>), CommOligo (also named OligoStar) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Li et al., 2005</ref>) or YODA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Nordberg, 2005</ref>). However, these softwares were developed for use on whole-genome data or on specific sets of genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gentry et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Lemoine et al., 2009</ref>). So, cross-hybridization research is performed only against a reduced set of sequences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Li et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wang and Seed, 2003</ref>;<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Wernersson and Nielsen, 2005</ref>). Thus, probe specificity must be checked against databases containing a very large set of sequences while staying within a reasonable time for the design. A second critical obstacle when dealing with environmental studies is the difficulty to design probes able to cover all the gene variants encoding proteins having a same function (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Habe and Omori, 2003</ref>). Although Hierarchical Probe Design (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Chung et al., 2005</ref>) and ProDesign (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Feng and Tillier, 2007</ref>) softwares propose clustering<ref type="bibr">[</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.Dugat-Bony et al.</head><p>methods to identify conserved regions allowing a probe design for gene families, they are unable to perform the specificity tests. The single promising approach to address this problem is implemented in the PhylArray program (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Militon et al., 2007</ref>) which consists in the design of degenerate probes targeting multiple sequence variants. This strategy allows the design of probes targeting sequences never described in international databases and therefore considered as explorative probes. Unfortunately, this tool is only dedicated to probe design for phylogenetic microarrays. Finally, despite the wide range of available programs, few provide access to oligonucleotide design through a web interface. This solution is the easiest one since it does not require any local software installation. Unfortunately, only six softwares offer this possibility and among them four (OligoFaktory, Osprey, PROBEmer and ROSO) allow the user to implement its own biological models for a tailor-made probe design. Therefore, many improvements in the probe design technology are still necessary and the HiSpOD (High Specific Oligo Design) program was developed to meet these challenges. In addition to take into account the crucial parameters for the design of effective probes, we combine: @BULLET the possibility to produce specific probes and also degenerate probes from consensus sequences, and thus with an explorative power, in order to detect a broad spectrum ofwere considered to avoid cross-hybridizations because they are components of mRNA sequences. To obtain a suitable and curated database, a filtering step is carried out to ensure that sequences with bad quality were rejected if:</p><p>(1) The percentage of N (unknown base) in the sequence is &gt;10%.</p><p>(2) At least one stretch of 10 consecutive N is detected.</p><p>The data extracted are then saved into a relational database implemented under Oracle and named EnvExBase. Finally, the whole database contains 9 129 323 sequences (about 10 GB). Proteins obtained from each original CDS were also saved in a separate table in order to allow rapid accession of their specific information like source organisms and biological functions of encoded proteins.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DESIGN ALGORITHM</head><p>HiSpOD software allows oligonucleotide probe design for FGAs in the context of microbial ecology but could also be adapted to various biological models. It needs an input file in FASTA format containing the target sequences. Two kinds of sequence are accepted by the program: specific nucleic acid sequence and degenerate nucleic acid sequence<ref type="bibr">[</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>):</p><p>(1) Oligonucleotide probe design. For each input sequence, the probe length is defined by the user. Along the sequence, the algorithm extracts all probes by incrementing the constant defined probe size in a window. First, in the case of degenerated sequences, all potential oligonucleotides generated with a maximal degeneracy higher than the threshold fixed by the user are removed. Then, all oligonucleotides or all combinations resulting from degenerate probes are filtered according to the melting temperature (minimum and maximum T m determined by the formula (A) in which<ref type="bibr">[Na + ]</ref>is fixed by default at 0.5 M) and the complexity stretch (maximum authorized number of identical consecutive bases). Tm = 79.8+18.5×log 10 (<ref type="bibr">[Na + ]</ref>)+58.4× yG+zC wA+xT +yG+zC +11.8×</p><formula>(yG+zC) 2 (wA+xT +yG+zC) 2 − 920 wA+xT +yG+zC (A)</formula><p>(2) Similarity search. Oligonucleotides which successfully pass the first step are tested for similarity search against all the sequences from EnvExBase database using BLASTN program (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Altschul et al., 1990</ref>). The BLAST program is tuned for this task as follows: the 'DUST' filter, used to mask low complexity regions from nucleic acid sequences, is inactive (−F F), the search strand is set to the positive one (−S 1), the expected-value (−e) is a parameter chosen by the user (1000 by default), the word size is set to the minimum length (−W 7) and the number of reported results is fixed to 500 (−b 500).(3) Cross-hybridization test. Kane's criteria (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Kane et al., 2000</ref>), e.g. percent similarity and identity stretch, defined by the user (default values: 85 and 15, respectively), are checked for all positive results from previous BLASTN analysis to identify potential cross-hybridization.</p><p>(4) Cross-hybridization result. All sequences identified to potentially cross-hybridize with designed probes are clustered using BLASTClust tool provided by the BLAST program. The options (−S) which gives the minimum percentage of similarity between sequences that should be grouped together and (−L) which gives the minimum percentage of length of the implicated sequences in the alignment that should be considered, are also fixed by the user (default values: 90 and 0, respectively).</p><p>(5) Selected probe result. The final result provided by our software is stored within two output files: the first file with the extension '.probes' included all filtered oligonucleotides sorted by the number of cross-hybridizations. The position on the input sequence, the length and the sequence of the oligonucleotide are also mentioned. The second file '.result' details the non-targeted sequences that may induce potential cross-hybridizations with their accession numbers, source organism and function of the encoded protein.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>HiSpOD is written in Perl 5 scripting language and uses a BioPerl module for better visibility and to simplify the source code. A parallel implementation allows probe finding to be done in parallel on computing cluster architecture. The parallelism is introduced in Step (3) (cross-hybridization test) which is the most time-consuming task of the process. For this step, HiSpOD integrates a distributed and parallel implementation of the BLAST program (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Darling et al., 2003</ref>) which uses the MPI library (Message Passing Interface) and runs on parallel architectures. HiSpOD software is installed on a symmetric multiprocessor (SMP) machine with 8 AMD Opteron Dual-Core processors at 1.8 GHz, 128 GB RAM and running Linux CentOS 64 bits. For large data storage, a SAN system disk with 2TB is used. The application is freely accessible from a web interface developed in PHP/MySql at http://fc.isima.fr/~g2im/hispod/. The design results are made available on the server. HiSpOD is started via the interface using the chosen data entered by the user. The computing is made on the symetric multiprocessor (SMP) machine after a remote connection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">EXPERIMENTAL VALIDATION</head><p>The efficiency of HiSpOD was then assessed by the design of probes targeting genes encoding enzymes involved in the chlorinated solvent biodegradation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Oligonucleotide probe set design</head><p>Probes were designed from 54 nucleic sequences corresponding to 21 genes coding for enzymes involved in chlorinated solvent biodegradation pathways (15 involved in anaerobic pathways and 6 in aerobic ones), which were downloaded from the NCBI database (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). Fourteen genes were treated, starting with individual nucleotide sequences (amoB, todC1, todC2, bmoC, mmoC, xamoA, bvcA, prdA, rdhA1, rdhA2, pceA from Dehalococcoides ethenogenes 195, pceA from Suflurospirillum multivorans, pceA from Dehalobacter restrictus PER-K23 and pceA from Shewanella sediminis HAW-EB3), 5 genes were treated at the gene family level (pceA from<ref type="bibr">Geobacter, rdhA1A, rdhA1B, rdhA2A</ref>Page: 644 641–648(−L) = 0 indicates that sequence length is not considered for the clustering.and rdhA2E) and 2 were treated at both the individual and the family levels (tceA and vcrA). In order to target gene families, multiple sequences were aligned by using ClustalW program (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Thompson et al., 1994</ref>) to determine degenerate consensus sequences before probe design with HiSpOD. For each job launched on HiSpOD program (23 entries), probes of 50mers in length were designed.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>summarizes the parameter values used for the probe design. T m range was determined to obtain a probe set with a GC content between 40 and 60%. Thus, ∼5 days (121 h) were necessary for the complete design with an average of 3.5 h for an individual sequence and of 9.5 h for a degenerate sequence. Based on the specificity (no or few cross-hybridizations) and the location of the probe along the target sequence, multiple probes were then selected per gene (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S1</ref>). In total, 295 oligonucleotide probes were designed. These were used to elaborate a functional DNA microarray.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.Dugat-Bony et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Experimental procedures</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1">Microarray building</head><p>Microarrays were produced with the NimbleGen high-density array synthesis technology (Roche NimbleGen, Madison, Wisconsin, USA). Each oligonucleotide was synthesized in situ in triplicate. Probes were randomly distributed across the array in order to minimize spatial effect. In addition, the microarray also reported 8863 random probes (20–56mers) used as a metric of technical background noise and 11 573 other control probes (positive and negative) which allowed quality control of oligonucleotide synthesis and hybridization conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.2">Synthetic antisense RNA target preparation and labelling</head><p>The complete mmoC (S81887), vcrA (AY322364) and tceA (AF228507) gene sequences associated to SP6 promoter sequence at their 3 end were synthesized by Biomatik Corporation (Cambridge, Ontario, Canada) and cloned into the pGH vector. Antisense RNAs (aRNAs) were produced by in vitro transcription using the MEGAscript SP6 Kit (Ambion, Austin, Texas, USA) and then labelled with Cy3-ULS as described in the Kreatech ULS labelling procedure (Kreatech Diagnostics, Amsterdam, The Netherlands). The aRNAs were quantified by spectrophotometry (at 260 nm) as well as dye incorporation (at 550 nm) with a Nanodrop ND-1000 (NanoDrop Technologies, Wilmington, North Carolina, USA) and RNA integrity was controlled with a Model 2100 Bioanalyzer using the RNA 6000 Nano kit (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, California, USA).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.3">Environmental target preparation and labelling Total</head><p>RNAs were extracted according a modified protocol (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Vetriani et al., 2003</ref>) from an industrial site contaminated with both tetrachloroethene (PCE) and TCE) and biostimulated during 31 months before sample collection by SITA Remediation Company (Lyon, France). In this protocol, freeze-thaw cycles were replaced by beat betting 1 min at 30 Hz with 1 g of glass beads of ≤106 µm in diameter (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, Missouri, USA). Coextracted DNA was removed by digestion with 4U of DNase I (DNA-free, Ambion, Austin, Texas, USA) at 37 @BULLET C for 35 min. Using the MicrobExpress kit (Ambion, Austin, Texas, USA), 8– 9 µg of total RNA mixture were subjected to mRNA enrichment protocol. In a second step, antisense amino-allyl dUTP marked RNA (aRNA) was obtained by amplification with the MessageAmp IIBacteria kit (Ambion, Austin, Texas, USA) and labelled with Cy3 fluorescent dye (GE Healthcare, Chalfont St Giles, UK) following the manufacturer's instructions. RNA integrity was controlled with a Model 2100 Bioanalyzer using the RNA 6000 Nano kit (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, California, USA).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.4">Microarray hybridization A microarray</head><p>was hybridized with 10 11 copies of each labelled Cy3-aRNA obtained from synthetic genes and another one with 6 µg of Cy3-aRNA obtained from the contaminated groundwater. Targets were dried in a SpeedVac (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Villebon sur Yvette, France) and resuspended in the NimbleGen Hybridization Buffer (Roche NimbleGen, Madison, Wisconsin, USA). Then, targets were hybridized on the microarray at 42 @BULLET C for 72 h using a 4-bay NimbleGen Hybridization system (Roche NimbleGen, Madison, Wisconsin, USA). Array washes were performed as Page: 645 641–648</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HiSpOD</head><p>recommended by NimbleGen and slides were scanned at 2 µm resolution using the InnoScan 900 and Mapix software (Innopsys, Carbonne, France). Finally, pixel intensities were extracted using NimbleScan™ v2.5 software (Roche NimbleGen, Madison, Wisconsin, USA) and pair reports containing signal intensity data for every spot on the array linked to its corresponding probe identifier were generated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.5">Data normalization and statistical analysis</head><p>The background noise was determined using random probes present on the microarrays with the method described in Supplementary Material 1 and was defined by two parameters: the background median intensity (B position ) and its dispersion (B dispersion ). Finally, a modified signal-to-noise ratio named SNR and based on the formula SNR = (probe signal intensity −B position )/B dispersion was calculated in order to normalize our data. As suggested in the study of He and Zhou (2008), positive hybridization was considered significant for probes having a SNR &gt; 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.6">Gene isolation from the contaminated groundwater</head><p>Genomic DNA (gDNA) was extracted from the industrial contaminated site using a modified protocol originally described by<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Vetriani et al. (2003)</ref>. In this protocol, freeze-thaw cycles were replaced by beat betting 1 min at 30 Hz with 1 g of glass beads of ≤106 µm in diameter (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, Missouri, USA). gDNA concentrations were measured using a NanoDrop ND-1000 spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Technologies, Wilmington, North Carolina, USA). PCR reactions were carried out to isolate gene fragments for vcrA, bvcA, pceA and todC1 (primer list and PCR conditions in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table S2</ref>). Amplicons of correct size were then cloned using the TOPO TA cloning kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, California, USA) and sequenced by MWG DNA sequencing services (Ebersberg, Germany).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.7">Quantitative RT-PCR</head><p>In order to validate the semiquantitative aspect of microarray results, qRT-PCR assays were performed. RT reactions were carried out in duplicate from 100 ng of total RNA extracted from the contaminated environment using vcrA, bvcA and pceA (0.625 µM of each primer) reverse primer mix (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table S2</ref>). Control for DNA contamination evaluation was the same reaction without reverse transcriptase. Then, quantitative reactions were performed for each gene independently. For each of the two RT replicates, the quantitative reaction was achieved twice, thus leading to four measurements for each gene. For the gDNA contamination control, the quantitative reaction was completed four times. Finally, three replicates for each point of the standard curve (serially diluted cDNA) were measured. The reaction was performed in a final volume of 20 µl containing 5 µl of cDNA, 10 µl of 2X MESA Green qPCR for SYBR assay mixture (Eurogentec, Liege, Belgium) and the corresponding primer sets described in Supplementary Material (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table S3</ref>) at 0.2 µM final concentration each. qPCR was realized in the Mastercycler Realplex (Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany) starting with 5 min of denaturation at 95 @BULLET C followed by 40 cycles consisting of denaturation at 95 @BULLET C for 15 s, annealing at 59 @BULLET C for 15 s and elongation at 68 @BULLET C for 30 s. Data analysis was achieved with realplex software version 1.5 (Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany). The quantification of transcripts in the RNA sample was determinedafter subtraction of the gene copy number obtained for the gDNA contamination control.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.8">Accession numbers</head><p>Nucleotide sequences without PCR primer sequences were deposited in the GenBank database under accession numbers HM140426 and HM140427 for vcrA, HM140428 and HM140429 for bvcA and HM140430 and HM140431 for pceA. The microarray data discussed in this publication are available at the GEO web site (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/) under accession number: GSE21492.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Probe efficiency analysis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.1">Probe sensitivity and specificity</head><p>A first experiment was performed to test the ability of probes to reliably identify genes involved in chlorinated solvent degradation. Thus, three synthetic genes [mmoC (S81887), vcrA (AY322364) and tceA</p><formula>(AF228507)]</formula><p>were used to produce aRNA by in vitro transcription. Then, 10 11 copies of each labelled aRNA were hybridized to the array. Whatever the gene tested, the results (GSE21492) showed that all corresponding probes gave a strong positive hybridization signal (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>), which is in agreement with a great sensitivity of probes designed with HiSpOD. These probes are also highly specific because no hybridization signals (SNR &gt; 5) were obtained with probes targeting the other genes (21 genes are targeted by the microarray).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.2">Industrial polluted site analysis</head><p>Microarray hybridization with labelled antisense mRNA extracted from a PCE/TCE contaminated groundwater, allowed a full identification of expressed genes on the environmental sample. Four genes were detected (average intensity of all specific probes with SNR &gt; 5): three encoded reductive dehalogenases involved in the anaerobic dehalorespiration pathway (vcrA and bvcA from Dehalococcoides and pceA from Sulfurospirillum) and one implicated in the aerobic TCE biodegradation pathway (todC1 from Pseudomonas). Positive hybridization signals were obtained for all regions of the three genes involved in the anaerobic dehalorespiration pathway. In contrast, only one out of the two targeted regions for todC1 was detected. This finding suggested that hybridization of the probes designed to target the 3 extremity of todC1 gene resulted from cross-hybridization and did not reflect the presence of transcripts on the contaminated site. In addition, PCR and sequencing experiments allowed the isolation of gene fragments for vcrA (HM140426 and HM140427), bvcA (HM140428 and HM140429) and pceA (HM140430 and HM140431) but not for todC1, confirming the results obtained with the DNA microarray.(A) microarray analysis and (B) qRT-PCR assays. For the three genes vcrA, bvcA and pceA, graphs indicate either the average ratio SNR obtained for all probes targeting the same gene (A) or the gene copy number per nanogram of total RNA (B).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Page: 646 641–648</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.Dugat-Bony et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.3">Gene expression quantification</head><p>SNR levels obtained for vcrA gene (average SNR = 205.6 for the individual gene design and average SNR = 220.6 for the gene family design) were much higher than those obtained for the last two genes bvcA and pceA (average SNR = 7.3 and 8.2, respectively), which could suggest a higher abundance of vcrA transcripts in the sample (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2A</ref>). To confirm these results, transcript quantification by qRT-PCR was performed on the same groundwater sample and the measurement of the expression level showed a higher number of transcripts for vcrA (7415 ± 949 copies/ng of RNA) than for both bvcA and pceA (1072±86 and 559±87 copies/ng of RNA, respectively) in the RNA sample (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2B</ref>). These data support the applicability of our FGA for gene identification and as a semi-quantitative tool for gene expression evaluation with the advantage to survey numerous genes at the same time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">DISCUSSION</head><p>HiSpOD takes into account a greater number of criteria to select more efficient probes (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>) compared with most popular softwares used for oligonucleotide probe design for FGAs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Li et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Nordberg, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Wernersson and Nielsen, 2005</ref>), The entire software suite is available through web services. To produce the DNA probes, users can enter their sequences of interest and set the required parameters. Furthermore, our software can be applied to both, individual nucleotide gene sequences and degenerated consensus sequences, produced by multiple alignments of gene sequences belonging to a same gene family. Therefore, the user has the possibility to identify specific probes either at the gene or at the gene family level. For this last case, design methods previously reported are based on sequence clustering (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Chung et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Feng and Tillier, 2007</ref>) or on the use of mismatch probes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Jaing et al., 2008</ref>), which constrain the selection of probes in the most conserved regions. In contrast, HiSpOD allows considering regions generating the least number of cross-hybridizations even if they are more variable within the gene family. Because all sequence combinations for each degenerate probe are re-created for the DNA microarray synthesis, some of them could detect new gene sequences not yet available in international databases. Furthermore, as the number of probes per array is no longer a constraint, given the development of very high density microarrays (several million probes proposed by NimbleGen), designing microarray to encompass the full diversity of sequence variants encountered in the environment or in specific metabolic process is now feasible. By this aspect, the HiSpOD method is then a pioneer explorative approach to the design of probes dedicated to FGAs. Today, the only probe design software described to allow an exploratory study of environmental samples using degenerate probes is PhylArray (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Militon et al., 2007</ref>), but it is dedicated to phylogenetic oligonucleotide microarrays (POAs). Cross-hybridizations with non-target sequences can be a significant contribution to the hybridization signal, potentially introducing substantial error. According to<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">He et al. (2007)</ref>, they represent one of the most critical limits of DNA microarray approach when dealing with complex environmental samples of unknown composition. However, over the past two decades, new sequencing technology developments and the trend of declining sequencing costs, allowed an exponential growth of public DNA sequence data. Data analysis has revealed an extraordinary gene diversity and a huge nucleic sequence polymorphism for all investigated environmental microbial habitats especially by metagenomics approach (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kottmann et al., 2010</ref>). This extraordinary resource can now be mined for DNA microarrays applications to assess the potential cross-hybridizations. Currently, HiSpOD is the most suitable tool to take into account this wide diversity to limit crosshybridations with a test of specificity conducted against EnvExBase, a large and representative database of all prokaryotic, fungal and environmental sequences. This database includes all known potential CDSs and their putative UTRs. However, as the HiSpOD algorithm extracts all probes by incrementing the constant defined probe size in a window along the sequence, the time required for evaluating their specificity can be quite long (several hours per gene) especially for highly degenerate oligonucleotide probes. So, HiSpOD is greatly dependent on the performance of MPIBLAST program used in the specificity test step. Currently, we are focusing our efforts to increase the program performance by deploying it on a larger cluster infrastructure and on a computing grid. Given the exponential increase in the number of sequences in databases, the DNA microarrays will be upgraded regularly with novel probes allowing the targeting of either new variants of the targeted genes or genes newly discovered. In addition, EnvExBase component of the HiSpOD software will be updated regularly. An Page: 647 641–648of the database structure, consisting in a split into multiple sub-databases according to particular ecosystems (soil, marine, freshwater, atmosphere, etc.), is also under development. It will provide an enhanced usability of the program, with a faster speed and an elimination of unneeded cross-hybridization information. Currently, no known software offers the opportunity to test for specificity on such a large database. Furthermore, no tested software (i.e. OligoWiz, CommOligo and Yoda) is able to integrate this database to perform the specificity test with it. This is probably due to an inadequate performance optimization of these algorithms which systematically crashed when using a large database. In addition, the clustering of cross-hybridization sequences using BLASTClust tool is another original approach proposed by our software to define gene sequence families that may induce potential cross-hybridizations and so to facilitate selection of the most appropriate probes. Probe sensitivity is another crucial parameter, particularly for environmental studies, where biomass can be low. So, design process allowing the selection of oligonucleotide probes need to be optimized. Generally, microarray-based hybridization presents a low detection limit. For example, 50mer probe FGA detection limit was estimated to be in the range of 5–10 ng of gDNA in the absence of background DNA and was about 10-fold lower in its presence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Rhee et al., 2004</ref>). In this last case, target sequences were extrapolated to represent genomic material from &lt;5% of the total community of an environment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gentry et al., 2006</ref>). For mRNA, no detection limit is currently assessed in environmental sample. It remains hard to solve the sensitivity issue despite the existence of some protocols bringing those limits down (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Gao et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Wu et al., 2006</ref>). In this study, we demonstrated the ability of probes designed with HiSpOD to detect mRNA retrieved from environmental samples with a high sensitivity (e.g. 559±87 copies/ng of RNA for pceA) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>). Furthermore, expression profiles obtained were comparable with those of qRT-PCR assays suggesting the semi-quantitative aspect of the microarray elaborated using this software. We demonstrate that the microarray developed in this study provides a powerful tool to monitor chlorinated ethene biodegradation capabilities in complex environments. This tool will be now used for a wider study incorporating several industrial polluted sites where a more or less complete degradation of chlorinated solvents was observed. However, certain limitations still remain. Indeed, numerous authors have highlighted the problem of signal variability obtained with probes targeting different regions of the same gene (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Bruun et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Held et al., 2006</ref>), certainly when linked with probe thermodynamic properties and/or target secondary structure. The function of these parameters is still difficult to evaluate and to visualize in the microarray results. Although their calculation is time consuming, they will be taken into account in the next version of HiSpOD. In this study, the new software was shown to be particularly accurate to design probes dedicated to microbial ecology. The experimental validation of the oligonucleotide probe set designated using HiSpOD was performed with mRNA extracted from a PCE/TCE contaminated aquifer where pollutant biodegradation was observed (Site description and chemical analysis in Supplementary Material 2 and<ref type="figure" target="#tab_4">Table S4</ref>). These pollutants undergo biodegradation through two different pathways: (i) use as an electron acceptor (reductive dechlorination) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Futagami et al., 2008</ref>) and (ii) cometabolism where degradation of the chlorinated solvent is simply fortuitous and provides no benefit to the microorganism (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Arp et al., 2001</ref>), the first being the major process for the natural biodegradation of chlorinated solvents. In this study, the most recognized gene sequences involved in these two metabolic processes where extracted from international databases and were used for probe design. The microarray presented here is, to our knowledge the most complete high-throughput molecular tool describing these pathways with 295 probes covering 54 sequence variants of 21 genes and in addition with an explorative side. By comparison, GeoChip mentioned 35 probes targeting genes characteristics of PCE/TCE biodegradation pathways (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">He et al., 2007</ref>). In the context of industrial site rehabilitation, it could be also applied as a diagnostic tool to detect microbial activities before, during and after bioremediation treatment. Moreover, this explorative highthroughput tool could be used to monitor the distribution of these catabolic pathways along non-contaminated ecosystems in order to better understand the origin of these fascinating microbial functions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HiSpOD</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">CONCLUSION</head><p>In summary, we present a novel probe design software called HiSpOD dedicated to FGA developments. HiSpOD allows probe design at both specific gene and gene family levels through an original approach based on degenerated probe determination. Moreover, specificity test was conducted against a large formatted database composed of all known CDS retrieved from the taxonomic divisions PRO, FUN and ENV of the EMBL databank in order to avoid cross-hybridization events. Finally, the user-friendly web interface developed simplifies greatly the user access to the program.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. HiSpOD design workflow. HiSpOD program is composed of five steps and each parameter chosen by the user are indicated on the left.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Gene expression profile identified in a contaminated groundwater obtained with (A) microarray analysis and (B) qRT-PCR assays. For the three genes vcrA, bvcA and pceA, graphs indicate either the average ratio SNR obtained for all probes targeting the same gene (A) or the gene copy number per nanogram of total RNA (B).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Input parameters for HiSpOD probe design</figDesc><table>Probe characteristics 
Probe specificity 

Probe 
length 
(mers) 

T m range ( @BULLET C) 
Single nucleotide 
stretch length 
(complexity) 

Maximal 
degeneracy 

Maximal 
consecutive match 
with non-target 

Maximal identity 
with non-target 
(%) 

BLASTClust 
option (−S) (%) 

BLASTClust 
option (−L) (%) 

50 
64–79 
10 
1 or 32 
15 
75 
90 
0 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2.</figDesc><table>Total number of selected probes and time consuming for the design 
for individual gene sequences and degenerate consensus sequences (gene 
family) 

Data observed 
Individual 
gene 
sequences 

Degenerate 
consensus 
sequences 

Design time (min) 
3256 
4014 
Average design time per sequence (min) 
203.5 
573 
No. of probes selected 
140 
54 (155 a ) 
Average No. of probes per sequence 
9 
8 (22 a ) 

a Number of probes after non-degenerate probe creation from each degenerate ones. 

No, number. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 3. Probe sensitivity and specificity assessment after microarray hybridization with three aRNA targets (mmoC, vcrA and tceA) Targeted</figDesc><table>gene 
No. of positive probes/No. 
of total probes 

Average SNR' 

mmoC 
5/5 
1522.5 
vcrA 
38/38 
1624.5 
tceA 
9/9 
1709.4 
Others 
0/243 
&lt; 5 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 4. Comparison of parameters used by HiSpOD and by three popular softwares</figDesc><table>Software 
Probe length 
T m 
GC% 
Complexity 
% Similarity 
Identity stretch 
Degeneracy 
Cross-hybridization 
clustering 

Web interface 

OligoWiz 
Yes 
Yes 
No 
No 
Yes 
Yes 
No 
No 
No 
CommOligo 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
No 
Yes 
Yes 
No 
Yes 
No 
YODA 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
No 
No 
No 
HiSpOD 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 

improvement </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We are grateful to our undergraduate bioinformatics students Nicolas Parisot (IUT Génie Biologique option bio-infomatique, Aurillac) and Mathieu Roudel (Master Bioinformatique, Université Blaise Pascal, Clermont-Ferrand) for the development of statistical and annotation</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>btq712. .tex]</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="641" to="648" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">scripts used in HiSpOD, Pascale Gouinaud for her assistance and Dr Biron David for reviewing the English version of the manuscript. We thank SITA Remediation society for sample collection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Dugat-Bony</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Agence De l&apos;Environnement et de la Maîtrise de l&apos;Energie&apos; (ADEME, France)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>grant. ID 2598</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">LifeGrid programs financed by the regional council of Auvergne (France), the FEDER European commission and the &apos;Centre national de la Recherche Scientifique&apos; (CNRS, France); the grant ANR-07-ECOT-005-05 for the program PRECODD Evasol from</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Instruire</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Prevoir</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Agence Nationale de la Recherche&apos; (ANR, France</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Conflict of Interest: none declared</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">REFERENCES</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basic local alignment search tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">215</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="410" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular and cellular fundamentals of aerobic cometabolism of trichloroethylene</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Arp</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biodegradation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Afforestation alters the soil functional gene composition and biogeochemical processes in South American grasslands</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Berthrong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6240" to="6248" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving comparability between microarray probe signals by thermodynamic intensity correction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Bruun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">48</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design of long oligonucleotide probes for functional gene detection in a microbial community</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W.-H</forename>
				<surname>Chung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4092" to="4100" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The design, implementation, and evaluation of mpiBLAST</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Darling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">4th International Conference on Linux Clusters</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Jose, California</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fast and flexible approach to oligonucleotide probe design for genomes and gene families</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Feng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R M</forename>
				<surname>Tillier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1195" to="1202" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biochemical and genetic bases of dehalorespiration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Futagami</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Rec</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microarray-Based analysis of microbial community RNAs by whole-community RNA amplification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Gao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="563" to="571" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microarray applications in microbial ecology research</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Gentry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microb. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetics of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon metabolism in diverse aerobic bacteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Habe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Omori</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="243" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeoChip: a comprehensive microarray for investigating biogeochemical, ecological and environmental processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ISME J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empirical evaluation of a new method for calculating signal-to-noise ratio for microarray data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Zhou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2957" to="2966" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development and application of functional gene arrays for microbial community analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans. Nonferrous Met. Soc. China</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1319" to="1327" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between gene expression and observed intensities in DNA microarrays–a modeling study</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Held</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">70</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A functional gene array for detection of bacterial virulence elements</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Jaing</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2163</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessment of the sensitivity and specificity of oligonucleotide (50mer) microarrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Kane</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4552" to="4557" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microbial functional structure of &quot; Montastraea faveolata &quot; , an important Caribbean reef-building coral, differs between healthy and yellow-band diseased colonies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Kimes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="541" to="556" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Megx.net: integrated database resource for marine ecological genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Kottmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="391" to="395" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biphenyl-utilizing bacteria and their functional genes in a pine root zone contaminated with polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Leigh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ISME J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An evaluation of custom microarray applications: the oligonucleotide design challenge</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Lemoine</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1726" to="1739" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selection of optimal oligonucleotide probes for microarrays using multiple criteria, global alignment and parameter estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6114" to="6123" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microarray-based analysis of microbial functional diversity along an oil contamination gradient in oil field</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Liang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEMS Microbiol. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="324" to="333" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prokaryotic diversity, distribution, and insights into their role in biogeochemical cycling in marine basalts</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">U</forename>
				<surname>Mason</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ISME J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PhylArray: phylogenetic probe design algorithm for microarray</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Militon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2550" to="2557" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">YODA: selecting signature oligonucleotides</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Nordberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1365" to="1370" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oligonucleotide microarrays: widely applied poorly understood</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Pozhitkov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Funct. Genomic Proteomic</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of genes involved in biodegradation and biotransformation in microbial communities by using 50-mer oligonucleotide microarrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S.-K</forename>
				<surname>Rhee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4303" to="4317" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Thompson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4673" to="4680" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeoChip-based analysis of functional microbial communities during the reoxidation of a bioreduced uranium-contaminated aquifer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Van Nostrand</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2611" to="2626" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fingerprinting microbial assemblages from the oxic/anoxic chemocline of the black sea</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Vetriani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6481" to="6488" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeoChip-based analysis of metabolic diversity of microbial communities at the Juan de Fuca Ridge hydrothermal vent</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4840" to="4845" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selection of oligonucleotide probes for protein coding sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Seed</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="796" to="802" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OligoWiz 2.0–integrating sequence feature annotation into the design of microarray probes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Wernersson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Nielsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="611" to="615" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prokaryotes: the unseen majority</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Whitman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6578" to="6583" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microarray-based analysis of subnanogram quantities of microbial community DNAs by using whole-community genome amplification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4931" to="4941" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional microarray analysis of nitrogen and carbon cycling genes across an Antarctic latitudinal transect</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Yergeau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ISME J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="179" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>