
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Identification of transcription factor binding sites from ChIP-seq data at high resolution</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anaı¨sanaı¨s</forename>
								<forename type="middle">F</forename>
								<surname>Bardet</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Research Institute of Molecular Pathology (IMP)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jonas</forename>
								<surname>Steinmann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Molecular Biotechnology (IMBA)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sangeeta</forename>
								<surname>Bafna</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Friedrich Miescher Institute for Biomedical Research (FMI)</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Stowers Institute for Medical Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Kansas City</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country>USA, Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Vanderbilt University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Juergen</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Knoblich</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Molecular Biotechnology (IMBA)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Julia</forename>
								<surname>Zeitlinger</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Friedrich Miescher Institute for Biomedical Research (FMI)</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Stowers Institute for Medical Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Kansas City</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country>USA, Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Vanderbilt University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alexander</forename>
								<surname>Stark</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Research Institute of Molecular Pathology (IMP)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Identification of transcription factor binding sites from ChIP-seq data at high resolution</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2705" to="2713"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt470</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 21, 2013; revised on July 28, 2013; accepted on August 7, 2013</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER y Present address: Associate Editor: Inanc Birol signature to discriminate functional from abundant non-functional or neutral TF binding. Peakzilla is easy to use, as it estimates all the necessary parameters from the data and is freely available. Availability and implementation: The peakzilla program is available from https://github.com/steinmann/peakzilla or http://www.starklab. org/data/peakzilla/. Contact: stark@starklab.org Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Chromatin immunoprecipitation coupled to next-generation sequencing (ChIP-seq) is widely used to study the in vivo binding sites of transcription factors (TFs) and their regulatory targets. Recent improvements to ChIP-seq, such as increased resolution, promise deeper insights into transcriptional regulation, yet require novel computational tools to fully leverage their advantages. Results: To this aim, we have developed peakzilla, which can identify closely spaced TF binding sites at high resolution (i.e. resolves individual binding sites even if spaced closely), as we demonstrate using semisynthetic datasets, performing ChIP-seq for the TF Twist in Drosophila embryos with different experimental fragment sizes, and analyzing ChIP-exo datasets. We show that the increased resolution reached by peakzilla is highly relevant, as closely spaced Twist binding sites are strongly enriched in transcriptional enhancers, suggesting a</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Gene expression is mainly regulated at the transcriptional level and achieved through the binding of transcription factors (TFs) to genomic regulatory regions called promoters and enhancers. Chromatin immunoprecipitation followed by sequencing (ChIPseq) is extensively used to determine transcription factor binding sites (TFBSs) genome-wide (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Johnson et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Robertson et al., 2007</ref>). Compared with ChIP-chip (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Iyer et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Ren et al., 2000</ref>), ChIP-seq has dramatically improved the resolution of the identified TFBSs (from hundreds to only tens of nucleotides). A recent refinement of ChIP-seq, the ChIP-exo method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Rhee and Pugh, 2011</ref>), further increases the resolution of ChIP-seq experiments, theoretically to single nucleotides. The specific features and strategies of TF ChIP-seq data analysis have been well described by several reviews (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Pepke et al., 2009</ref>) and protocols (e.g.<ref type="bibr">Bardet et al., 2012</ref>). Briefly, as typically only one of both ends of the immunoprecipitated DNA fragments is sequenced, the sequencing reads (or tags) result in a bimodal distribution that is characteristic for true TFBSs (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1a</ref>). This distribution is typically used to estimate the average size of the fragments, which subsequently allows the prediction of TFBSs across the genome. Many computational tools have been developed and are successfully used to predict such binding events (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Wilbanks and Facciotti, 2010</ref>). However, in our experience, these tools are not optimized to take advantage of recent methodological improvements, which comprise paired-end sequencing, high sequencing depth (e.g. on Illumina HiSeq systems) and—most importantly—an increase in experimental resolution, both of conventional ChIP-seq and of ChIP-exo. Available tools typically merge closely spaced read-density peaks into large regions, which is preferable when analyzing certain chromatin features that mark extended regions (e.g. histone modifications), but means that the ability to distinguish (i.e. resolve) individual closely spaced TFBSs is lost. High resolution and precision [i.e. the correct prediction of the TFBSs' exact locations as measured for example as the distance from the inferred TFBS (the reported peak summit) to the TF's sequence motif] are crucial when determining individual TFBSs (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Guo et al., 2012</ref>), as promoter and enhancer regions often consist of multiple TFBSs for the same TF (homotypic TFBSs clusters) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Gotea et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">He et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Lifanov et al., 2003</ref>) or different TFs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Berman et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Schroeder et al., 2004</ref>). Thus, to fully leverage current ChIP methodologies toward understanding the structure and function of enhancers, the ability to determine multiple closely spaced TFBSs is critical. To meet this need, we developed a new computational tool, peakzilla, which fully exploits the bimodal distribution of sequence reads characteristic of true TF binding events, to identify closely adjacent TFBSs with high resolution and precision. Peakzilla is not meant for the identification of broad enriched regions (e.g. histone marks) for which we recommend using MACS or similar programs. *To whom correspondence should be addressed. § The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors.</p><p>We evaluate peakzilla by comparing it with three widely used peak-finders of the first generation such as MACS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Zhang et al., 2008</ref>), QuEST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Valouev et al., 2008</ref>) and cisGenome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Ji et al., 2008</ref>), as well as four methods developed more recently for the detection of high-resolution peaks such as spp (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Kharchenko et al., 2008</ref>), SISSRs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Jothi et al., 2008</ref>), GPS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Guo et al., 2010</ref>) and PeakRanger (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Feng et al., 2011</ref>). Peakzilla shows superior resolution and precision on conventional ChIP-seq datasets from Saccharomyces cerevisiae (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Zheng et al., 2010</ref>), Caenorhabditis elegans (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Zhong et al., 2010</ref>), Drosophila melanogaster (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">He et al., 2011</ref>), mouse (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Schmidt et al., 2010</ref>) and human (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kasowski et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cuddapah et al., 2009</ref>) and on recent ChIP-exo datasets (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Rhee and Pugh, 2011</ref>). We also specifically test the resolution limits of each method using semisynthetic ChIP-seq datasets and show experimentally that peakzilla fully reflects increased experimental resolution by performing ChIPseq experiments for Twist in D.melanogaster at normal, medium and high resolution. These results suggest that peakzilla is best suited for the identification of TFBSs with recent ChIP methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">PEAKZILLA ALGORITHM</head><p>Peakzilla uses the bimodal distribution of the reads (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1a</ref>) not only to estimate the fragment length but also to weight the read counts during peak calling and to score the candidate TFBSs. This has two important advantages: first, it enables peakzilla to more clearly discriminate between reads from adjacent TFBSs, leading to a substantial increase in resolution compared with treating reads irrespective of their directionality. Second, it avoids false positives that originate from artifacts during library<ref type="bibr">Peakzilla algorithm. (a)</ref>Overview of the ChIP-seq pipeline. TFBSs display a characteristic bimodal distribution of the positive and negative strand reads. (b) Example of a true-positive (Peak A) and false-positive (Peak B) peak in the Twist dataset in D.melanogaster (genomic coordinates chr2L:12420984-12423043 and chrX: 9899747-9905926, respectively). Peak B, unlike peak A, does not exhibit the characteristic double distribution of reads on the positive and negative strands. (c) Read distribution model using two Gaussian distributions. (d) Peak score. While both peaks A and B from</p><p>(b) show the same enrichment of read count over control, the score for peak B is penalized by the distribution score, a multiplicative factor<ref type="bibr">[0. .. 1]</ref>, as it does not fit to the specific double distribution of the model in (c). (e) Fragment diversity or data non-redundancy. Y-axis denotes the number of genomic positions that contain 90% of the reads that contribute to a peak. Peaks with a distribution score of 0 are more redundant, whereas peaks with a distribution score of 1 are more diverse. The same plot for all peaks in shown in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S2</ref>(f) Fraction of peaks with a distribution score of 0 or 1 that contain the corresponding TF motif preparation or sequencing, without the need to collapse or downweight reads that map to identical genomic positions (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). This is especially important when working with high sequence coverage, as obtained for small genomes (e.g. yeast, flies or nematodes) and with modern next generation sequencers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chen et al., 2012</ref>). Finally, when using peakzilla on paired-end ChIP-seq data, the estimated fragment size is directly averaged from the mapped reads. Peakzilla first scans the genome for candidate TFBSs that show high coverage in sequencing reads of the immunoprecipitated (IP) sample compared with the control sample (note that the control sample is optional, allowing peakzilla to be used with ChIP-exo). It then scores the candidates by the normalized read count of IP sample minus the control sample if available. To discriminate between artifacts and true binding events in enriched regions, each candidate TFBS score is further weighted by a distribution score that estimates how well the observed distribution of the reads in the peak region fits to a model for the bimodal read distribution (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1c</ref>and d). Indeed, further analyses suggest that candidates who are penalized using this distribution score are likely false because they contain substantially less diverse sequence reads (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1e</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S2</ref>). Their high read densities stem from only a few highly duplicated sequences, which are likely amplification artifacts, and are significantly less enriched in the corresponding TF motif (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1f</ref>). The method is illustrated in the method section and in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure S3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Overall performance</head><p>To evaluate peakzilla, we compared it with other methods using diverse ChIP-seq datasets from S.cerevisiae, C.elegans, D.melanogaster, mouse and human. Although the number of peaks called by the different methods is highly dependent on the thresholds and parameters used, the respective genomic regions overlap well (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S4</ref>), demonstrating the maturity of available tools for 'peak calling'. For example, all known Twist enhancers are identified by all methods, except for four and three enhancers that are not found by QuEST and GPS, respectively (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. S5</ref>). For most TFs tested, of all peaks identified by only one of the methods, those found exclusively by peakzilla are significantly more highly enriched in TF motif occurrences (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2a</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6</ref>). They also have higher fold enrichments of ChIP over input than peaks found exclusively by any of the other methods (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2b</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">High precision of peakzilla peaks</head><p>When identifying TFBSs at high resolution, the correct prediction of the precise TFBSs' location is important and critical for subsequent analyses of sequence features of TF binding. We found that most methods, including peakzilla, place the summits of the peak regions closely to the nearest motif occurrence (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S7</ref>, which also shows that the fraction of peaks that contain a motif is comparable across methods), arguing that the high resolution of peakzilla's peak (see below) does not come at the expense of precision.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Multiple peak regions function as transcriptional enhancers</head><p>The main strength of peakzilla is its ability to find peaks at high resolution. As the locations of sequencing reads that originate from a single TFBS are limited by the fragment size used for library preparation, we adjust our search window for counting and scoring sequence reads accordingly, and report peak regions as the average fragment size centered on the summit position. This is different from the large peak regions reported by MACS and to a lesser extent QuEST, CisGenome and PeakRanger (and from reporting only the summit positions as do SISSRs and spp;<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3a</ref>), and is one of the key features that allow peakzilla to resolve closely spaced peaks up to distances that correspond to half the fragment size. This is the highest resolution that can easily be obtained without losing the ability to uniquely assign reads to individual TFBSs. A further gain in resolution would require the deconvolution of overlapping read distributions by model fitting, a computationally intensive approach used, for example, by GPS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Guo et al., 2010</ref>). Peakzilla splits a substantial number of MACS peaks (e.g. 22% for Twist) into several peaks, each constituting a putative TFBS (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S8</ref>). Indeed, as expected for independent TFBSs, both the split peaks that correspond to the MACS summits (major peaks) and the minor peaks weresignificantly enriched for the Twist motif (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3b</ref>). Thus, many split MACS peaks may represent homotypic clusters of Twist binding sites. In addition, minor peaks frequently contained motifs for the TFs Snail and Dorsal, which are known to cooperate with Twist and might have been co-precipitated after cross-linking (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3b</ref>). Most importantly, MACS peaks split by peakzilla appear to be more often functional than MACS peaks that are not split (one-to-one peaks) and control regions (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3c</ref>): TF binding to split peaks is more highly conserved in other Drosophila species (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">He et al., 2011</ref>) and they are significantly more enriched for known Twist or mesodermal enhancers than one-to-one peaks one or controls (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig.3d and e</ref>). This is highly relevant as the large fraction of TFBS that are identified by ChIP approaches yet do not appear to be functioning as transcriptional enhancers ('neutral binding' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Li et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Kvon et al., 2012</ref>)) have been a major obstacle to studying the direct regulatory targets of TFs and to understanding the true number and density of enhancers in animal genomes. All together, these results suggest that peakzilla is ideal for identifying regions with multiple binding sites and that such information is important for detecting functional enhancers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">High resolution of peakzilla</head><p>The evaluation of TFBS predicted from ChIP-seq data (i.e. peaks) is complicated by the fact that a ground truth typically does not exist for experimental ChIP-seq datasets. This is especially true for the evaluation of peak calls at different resolutions that predict a single TFBS versus several closely spaced TFBS. Although the occurrence of TF motifs is a good proxy for independent binding events, we sought to demonstrate the validity of peak splitting more directly by generating semisynthetic datasets with defined peak-to-peak distances. We found that peakzilla is still able to separate all peak pairs at 150 bp without calling any false positives, which is the best resolution compared with all others methods (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 4</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Peakzilla leverages increased resolution of ChIP experiments</head><p>To directly demonstrate peakzilla's ability to make use of increased experimental ChIP resolution, we performed conventional ChIP-seq for Twist from Drosophila embryos with increasingly smaller fragment sizes. For this, the chromatin was sonicated into relatively small DNA fragments and then further). This yielded three ChIP datasets with estimated fragment sizes of 102, 72 and 49 bp, from which we called peaks with the different peak finders (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5a</ref>). We expected that with decreasing fragment sizes, the width of the identified peaks should decrease and the resolution, i.e. the ability to resolve closely spaced binding sites, should increase. Indeed, the peak regions reported by peakzilla, but not those reported by most other methods, showed decreased width with decreasing fragment sizes (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5a</ref>). More importantly, the resolution, as measured by the minimal peakto-peak distance (after removing 1% outliers), increased with decreasing fragment sizes for peakzilla, but not for other methods (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5b</ref>). SISSRs, GPS and peakzilla performed well on the small-fragment sample, with peakzilla reaching the highest resolution of all methods. These results demonstrate that the maximum benefit of experimental methods with higher resolution can only be obtained when used together with high-resolution computational methods such as peakzilla.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">Peakzilla as a peak caller for ChIP-exo data</head><p>The recently developed ChIP-exo method adds a lamda exonuclease digestion step after ChIP, which trims the 5 0 DNA strand until the cross-linked TFBS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Rhee and Pugh, 2011</ref>). This digestion end point can be mapped to the genome using the remaining single-stranded overhang. Because each TFBS can be mapped from both sides, the resulting distribution of mapped breakpoints is also bimodal and resembles that of conventional ChIP-seq, with the 'fragment sizes' corresponding directly to the actual sizes of the TF footprints. To our knowledge, no computational method has been specifically developed for the analysis of ChIP-exo data. We therefore assessed how well peakzilla and other methods perform on ChIP-exo datasets. We called human CTCF binding sites from published ChIP-seq data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cuddapah et al., 2009</ref>) and ChIP-exo data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Rhee and Pugh, 2011</ref>). Peakzilla reported estimated fragment sizes of 98 bp for ChIP-seq and 36 bp for ChIP-exo (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5c</ref>) and had the highest resolution (smallest peak-to-peak distance) among all methods tested (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5d</ref>). This suggests that peakzilla is well suited for high-resolution ChIP-seq data, including ChIP-exo.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>Understanding how combinations of TFs bind to DNA to regulate gene expression is one of the most pressing questions of today's biology. Its importance is witnessed by recent community efforts that aim to determine all functional elements in the genomes of model organisms and the human [e.g. ENCODE (ENCODE Project<ref type="bibr">Consortium, 2004</ref>), modENCODE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Celniker et al., 2009</ref>), Mouse ENCODE (Mouse ENCODE<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Consortium et al., 2012)]</ref>. The availability of high-throughput sequencing at low cost widely promoted the use of the ChIPseq methodology and an enormous number of datasets for different TFs from various species, developmental stages or tissues are becoming available. This enables the identification of in vivo binding sites and thus enhancers that contain multiple binding sites for a single TF or multiple different TFs. While it is widely accepted that enhancers are characterized by clusters of TF binding motifs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Berman et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Schroeder et al., 2004</ref>), it has remained less clear to what extent each of several clustered TF binding motifs is bound in vivo (Ya´n˜ezYa´n˜Ya´n˜ez<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Cuna et al., 2012</ref>). Similarly, potential constraints on the relative distance or orientation of co-bound TFs have remained unclear, yet might be crucial to understand the molecular mechanisms and to decipher the sequence basis of gene regulation (Ya´n˜ezYa´n˜Ya´n˜ez<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Cuna et al., 2013</ref>). To experimentally address this question, it is important to resolve closely spaced binding sites and precisely predict their location from ChIP-seq data, challenges that current improvements to the ChIP methodology have started to address [e.g. ChIP-exo (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Rhee and Pugh, 2011)]</ref>. However, while many computational tools exist to identify enriched regions (peaks) from ChIP data ('peak calling'), many of them are not designed to fully leverage these improvements, e.g. the increased resolution or the vastly increased number of deep sequencing reads of modern deep sequencing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chen et al., 2012</ref>). To meet these challenges, especially the need for discovering TFBSs at highresolution, we have developed a new computational method, peakzilla. The importance of high resolution and precision is also supported by alternative efforts to correctly position predicted TFBSs, for example, by taking the location of enriched sequence motifs into account (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Boeva et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Guo et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Wu et al., 2010</ref>). Although TFBSs predicted by peakzilla coincide well with the known sequence motifs of the respective TFs, it is important to note that we chose to predict the TFBS locations from the ChIP-seq data alone, without taking sequence motifs into account: it is well established that within TFBSs, motifs for different TFs can be more highly enriched in TFBSs than motifs for the precipitated TF itself. For example, the binding sites of most TFs in the early Drosophila embryo are highly enriched in motifs for the TF Zelda (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bradley et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Li et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Kvon et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">modENCODE Consortium et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Satija and Bradley, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Ya´n˜ezYa´n˜Ya´n˜ez-Cuna et al., 2012</ref>), such that the Zelda motif–which is sometimes more highly enriched than the motif of the TF of interest–might bias the correct prediction of the TFBSs and possibly hinder the study of relative positioning and orientation of TFBSs. The combination of maximum experimental resolution and a peak caller like peakzilla thus makes full use of recent ChIP-seq approaches and will be invaluable for testing hypotheses on how combinatorial TF binding realizes the developmental blueprint encoded in the regulatory regions of our genomes. Indeed, closely spaced Twist binding sites resolved by peakzilla coincided and were strongly enriched in known enhancers, corroborating the prevalent model that functional enhancers are characterized by clusters of TFBSs. The increasing number of ChIP studies that determine the in vivo binding sites of TFs at high resolution will prove invaluable for our understanding of enhancer function and transcriptional regulation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Peakzilla algorithm</head><p>Initially, peakzilla reads the coordinate files of the mapped reads of the IP and–optionally–control sample. These can stem from either single-end (BED format) or paired-end (BEDPE format) deep sequencing data. Peakzilla then first determines the average fragment size of the sequencing library to determine the peak size that should result from a true TFBS. For paired-end data, this corresponds directly to the average fragment size (i.e. the average distance of the two mapped ends of each fragment). For single-end data, the average fragment size is estimated from the shift size of positive and negative reads in the top 200 enriched regions in the ChIP sample as described before. Peakzilla then defines peak size as two times the fragment size, as all reads from the ends offragments immunoprecipitated due to a single TFBS will on average lie in this region. In a second step, the distribution of positive and negative strand reads that are to be expected is modeled. By default, two normal distributions are used with standard deviations stdev ¼ peak size/5 and locations of their means at one-fourth and three-fourth of the peak size, respectively. Alternatively, the user can choose to estimate the model empirically from the average distribution of reads within the top 200 candidate peaks in the ChIP. To call TFBSs, peakzilla first scans the genome counting reads within a 'double-window': each putative (candidate) TFBS receives the counts of positive strand reads within a window of the fragment size downstream of the candidate TFBS and the negative strand reads within an equivalent window upstream of the candidate TFBS. This scores all candidates with a raw score defined as the normalized read count in the IP sample (normalized to a library size of 1 million reads) minus the normalized read count in the control (i.e. input) sample (note that the correction with a control sample is optional). Final peaks are the candidates with summits that are local maxima at least one fragment length (half peak size) apart from each other. This scanning mode allows for both fast and comprehensive investigation of large genomes at single base resolution. To obtain a final peak score, each raw score is corrected with a multiplicative distribution score [0. .. 1] that assesses the fit of the observed read count distribution to the distribution expected from the model (see above). This fit is assessed by a chi-square test and the chi-square P-value becomes the distribution score, which provides a measure of how likely the candidate peak is a true TFBS (distribution score: 1) or the result of a sequencing artifact (distribution score: 0). Note that to robustly estimate the average fragment size we only count distinct reads, i.e. remove duplicates (before model building). For peak calling, however, we did not remove duplicates but use the model to penalize polymerase chain reaction duplicates. This strategy is more sensitive for datasets on small genomes or with high coverage (see main text). If a control sample is provided, an empirical false discovery rate (FDR) is calculated for each peak by repeating the peak-calling step (after fragment size estimation) with swapped IP and control sample and scoring the resulting control peaks by the raw and distribution score. This provides for each final peak score the number of true and control peaks that achieve this score or better and thus an FDR estimate. Peakzilla reports the TFBSs in a BED-like format including the genomic positions, raw, distribution and final score, FDR and a peak number according to each peak's rank. In addition, the control peaks and a log are reported. The method is illustrated in a flowchart in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure S3</ref>. Peakzilla can be downloaded from http://github.com/steinmann/peakzilla or http://www.starklab.org/data/peakzilla/</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Program implementation</head><p>Peakzilla is implemented in Python 2 and runs on both the standard CPython and the fast PyPy interpreter. The program is freely available under the terms of the General Public License at http://github.com/steinmann/peakzilla. It runs from the command line under any Linux distribution or OSX. The only required argument is the name of the file with the aligned reads from the ChIP sample and–optionally–from the control sample (both BED format). In addition, the following parameters can be used: Àm to specify the number of candidate binding sites to use to estimate fragment size (default: 200); Àl to limit the candidate regions to lengths above a certain minimum length (which may be necessary if the dataset contains a large number of strong polymerase chain reaction artifacts; default: off<ref type="bibr">[1]</ref>); Àf to set a FDR cutoff (default: off<ref type="bibr">[100]</ref>); Àc to set an enrichment cutoff (default: 2); Às to set a score cutoff (default: 1); Àl to specify logfile (default: log.txt); Àe to use an empirical estimate derived from the data for the model instead of a normal distribution (default: off); Àp to specify that the data corresponds to fragments sequenced at both ends (paired-end sequencing; default: off). For a human ChIP-seq dataset with 19.7 million reads and 7.8 in the control peakzilla runs in 4 min and consumes 5800 MB of memory under CPython. Using the faster PyPy interpreter reduces time needed for analysis and memory requirements by half. Peakzilla can therefore be run efficiently on any modern desktop computer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">ChIP-seq datasets</head><p>Raw sequencing reads for Twist in D.melanogaster (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">He et al., 2011</ref>) (ArrayExpress accession code E-MTAB-376), CEBPA in Mus musculus (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Schmidt et al., 2010</ref>) (GEO accession code GSE22078) and PHA-4 in C.elegans (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Zhong et al., 2010</ref>) (GEO accession code GSE14545) were aligned uniquely using bowtie allowing for three mismatches to the corresponding genomes (assemblies dm3, mm9 and ce6, respectively). For NFkB in Homo sapiens (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kasowski et al., 2010</ref>) (GEO accession code GSE19486), Ste12 in S.cerevisiae (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Zheng et al., 2010</ref>) (GEO accession code GSE19636) and CTCF ChIP-seq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cuddapah et al., 2009</ref>) (GEO accession code GSE12889) and ChIP-exo (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Rhee and Pugh, 2011</ref>) (which the authors kindly shared) in H.sapiens, already mapped reads were used (assemblies hg18, sarCer2 and hg18, respectively).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Semisynthetic datasets</head><p>We generated semisynthetic control (input) and ChIP samples by subsampling input samples and ChIP peaks: we generated two 30 million bp artificial chromosomes by repeatedly randomly subsampling an arbitrarily selected region from the Twist input sample that showed no strong enrichment, one as a semisynthetic input control and the second as a ChIP background. We next selected several highly ranking peaks from the Twist ChIP sample that were found by all methods, had no other peak nearby and showed a regular fragment density distribution. We subsampled them to yield peaks with an enrichment of 5-fold or higher over background and placed such peaks as pairs with defined peak-topeak distances into the background every 30 000 bp for 1000 peak-pairs. For each distance between the semisynthetic peak-pairs, we combined the semisynthetic chromosome with the experimental ChIP data for peak calling of the combined set (i.e. parameters are estimated primarily on the experimental dataset as it contains higher peaks).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5">High-resolution ChIP-seq</head><p>Embryos aged 2–4 h after egg laying were processed and immunoprecipitated with Twist antibodies based on the protocol by<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">He et al. (2011)</ref>with slight modifications. Sonication occurs in three microfuges, each with $80 mg chromatin extracts resuspended in 250 ml A2 buffer, in a Biorupter sonicator for 15 min on high (30 s on and off) at 4 C. After 15 min cooling, the sonication step is repeated, followed by high-speed centrifugation at 4 C for 10 min and pooling of the supernatant (the DNA fragments should be mostly between 200–500 bp). Six hundred microliters of supernatant are then incubated with 120 ml of DNAse I (RNAse-free from NEB, to 0.3 U/ml final concentration) and 80 ml of DNAse I buffer for 30 min at 37 C. To stop DNAse I activity, A2 buffer with 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate is added to a give a final concentration of 1% sodium dodecyl sulfate. The extract is then directly used for ChIP (the DNA fragments should now be mostly between 50 and 200 bp). During Illumina library preparation, the samples are run on a 2% gel at 90 V for $2 h, and fragments corresponding to $50, $75 and $100 bp inserts are cut out of the gel (slices are $25 bp thick). The final libraries are run a BioAnalyzer to measure the actual average insert size. The high-resolution ChIP-seq data for Twist is deposited on GEO under the accession code GSE40664.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.6">Peak calling</head><p>The format of the mapped reads was adapted to each method. Peakzilla, SISSRs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Jothi et al., 2008</ref>) version 1.4, cisGenome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Ji et al., 2008</ref>) version 2.0, Spp (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kharchenko et al., 2011</ref>) version 1.8 and GPS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Guo et al., 2010</ref>) version 0.10.1 were run with default parameters. MACS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Zhang et al., 2008</ref>) version 1.4.1 was run with an mfold parameter 3,30 and the gsize parameter was adapted for each genome. QuEST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Valouev et al., 2008</ref>) version 2.4 was run with the following interactive choices: TFBSs with recommended (or relaxed) peak calling parameters. PeakRanger (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Feng et al., 2011</ref>) read extension length parameter was run using peakzilla's estimated fragment length. Both QuEST and PeakRanger could not be used for the CTCF samples without a control dataset.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.7">Functional analyses</head><p>We used the known motif CACATGT for Twist and the motifs from JASPAR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Sandelin et al., 2004</ref>): snail (sna MA0086.1), dorsal (dl_1 MA0022.1), NFkB (NFKB1 MA0105.1), CEBPA (CEBPA MA0102.2), pha-4 (Foxa2 MA0047.1), Ste12 (STE12 MA0393.1). We searched for motif de novo using MEME (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bailey and Gribskov, 1998</ref>) within 31 bp around peak summits and for occurrences of the known motifs using MAST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bailey and Gribskov, 1998</ref>) (from the MEME suite programs version 4.1.1) with a P-value of 10 À3 (10 À2 for Twist, which corresponds to allowing for one mismatch) in an area of 151 bp (average genomic frag</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Peakzilla algorithm. (a) Overview of the ChIP-seq pipeline. TFBSs display a characteristic bimodal distribution of the positive and negative strand reads. (b) Example of a true-positive (Peak A) and false-positive (Peak B) peak in the Twist dataset in D.melanogaster (genomic coordinates chr2L:12420984-12423043 and chrX: 9899747-9905926, respectively). Peak B, unlike peak A, does not exhibit the characteristic double distribution of reads on the positive and negative strands. (c) Read distribution model using two Gaussian distributions. (d) Peak score. While both peaks A and B from (b) show the same enrichment of read count over control, the score for peak B is penalized by the distribution score, a multiplicative factor [0. .. 1], as it does not fit to the specific double distribution of the model in (c). (e) Fragment diversity or data non-redundancy. Y-axis denotes the number of genomic positions that contain 90% of the reads that contribute to a peak. Peaks with a distribution score of 0 are more redundant, whereas peaks with a distribution score of 1 are more diverse. The same plot for all peaks in shown in Supplementary Figure S2 (f) Fraction of peaks with a distribution score of 0 or 1 that contain the corresponding TF motif</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. High precision of peakzilla peaks. Analyses performed on the Twist dataset in D.melanogaster. (a) Enrichment of motifs in differential peaks between peakzilla and other methods. Bionomial P-values of enrichment over control and number of differential peaks with a motif are shown on top of the bars. See Supplementary Figure S6 for other datasets and species. (b) Fold enrichment values of differential peaks and associated Wilcoxon P-values (NA: no peak available)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Functionality of multiple peak regions. Analyses performed on the Twist dataset in D.melanogaster. (a) Example of peak split. Peakzilla detects three adjacent peaks, while MACS, QuEST, CisGenome and PeakRanger report a single large peak region, and SISSRs and spp report two peak regions (GPS did not call any peak in that region; we considered all peaks called with standard parameters for each method). (b) Split peaks match motif occurrences. All peakzilla peaks corresponding to a single MACS peak (major: same summit; minor: additional summit) are more highly enriched in Twist motifs than control regions, suggesting that they constitute true independent TFBSs. The same is true for motifs of Snail and Dorsal, which are TFs known to cooperate with Twist. (c) Split peaks are highly conserved. (d) Split peaks are enriched for known enhancers. (e) Split peaks are enriched for mesodermal enhancers</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. High resolution of peakzilla. We evaluated the different methods on semisynthetic datasets that contained peak pairs at decreasing peak-to-peak distances (i.e. resolution). For each method, we determined a true-positive rate (TPR; number of correct peak calls divided by the total number of true peaks) and FDR (number of false peak calls divided by the number of total peak calls) and indicate the best resolution reached (in base pairs below each method's name)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. Application to high-resolution data. (a) Average fragment densities and peak regions from low-(red), medium-(purple) and high-resolution (blue) peaks for Twist (best 1000 peaks of each method). SISSRs, spp and GPS are not shown, as they do not report peak regions but only summit positions. (b) Resolution achieved by the different methods at low-(red), medium-(purple) and high-resolution (blue) as calculated as the minimal peakto-peak distance (after removing 1% outliers for each method). (c) Average fragment densities and peak regions from ChIP-seq (red) and ChIP-exo (blue) peaks for CTCF (best 1000 peaks of each method; QuEST and PeakRanger cannot be used without a control sample). (d) Resolution of the methods calculated as in (b)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><figDesc>ment length) around each peak summit. We called a peak conserved when it overlapped with a peak region in all other Drosophila species from He et al. (2011) (Drosophila simulans, Drosophila yakuba, Drosophila erecta, Drosophila ananassae and Drosophila pseudoobscura). We overlap peaks with known Twist enhancers from He et al. (2011) and the known mesodermal enhancers from Bonn et al. (2012) (only M for mesoderm at stage 5,</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">A.F.Bardet et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Peak calling at high resolution at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="6"> and 7). To create a set of control peaks, we shuffled peaks randomly within the same chromosomes.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors are grateful to Ho Sung Rhee and Franklin Pugh for kindly sharing the mapped read coordinates for ChIP-exo of human CTCF (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Rhee and Pugh, 2011</ref>). They would like to thank J. Omar Ya´n˜ezYa´n˜Ya´n˜ez-Cuna and Gerald Stampfel (IMP) for discussions, help and advice. A.F.B., J.S., J.A.K., J.Z. and A.S. conceived the project. J.S. wrote peakzilla. A.F.B. benchmarked peakzilla and performed all computational analyses. A.F.B. and A.S. analyzed the data. S.B. and J.Z. designed and performed the high-resolution ChIP-seq experiments. A.F.B., J.Z. and A.S. wrote the manuscript.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combining evidence using p-values: application to sequence homology searches</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Bailey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Gribskov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2012) A computational pipeline for comparative ChIP-seq analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Bardet</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="61" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploiting transcription factor binding site clustering to identify cis-regulatory modules involved in pattern formation in the Drosophila genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Berman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="757" to="762" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">De novo motif identification improves the accuracy of predicting transcription factor binding sites in ChIP-Seq data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Boeva</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">126</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tissue-specific analysis of chromatin state identifies temporal signatures of enhancer activity during embryonic development</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Bonn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="148" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Binding site turnover produces pervasive quantitative changes in transcription factor binding between closely related Drosophila species</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Bradley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000343</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unlocking the secrets of the genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Celniker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">459</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="927" to="930" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic evaluation of factors influencing ChIP-seq fidelity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="609" to="614" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Global analysis of the insulator binding protein CTCF in chromatin barrier regions reveals demarcation of active and repressive domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Cuddapah</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="32" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ENCODE (ENCyclopedia Of DNA Elements) Project</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ENCODE Project Consortium. Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">306</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="636" to="640" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PeakRanger: a cloud-enabled peak caller for ChIP-seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Feng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">139</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homotypic clusters of transcription factor binding sites are a key component of human promoters and enhancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Gotea</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="565" to="577" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovering homotypic binding events at high spatial resolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Guo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3028" to="3034" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High resolution genome wide binding event finding and motif discovery reveals transcription factor spatial binding constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Guo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002638</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High conservation of transcription factor binding and evidence for combinatorial regulation across six Drosophila species</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="414" to="420" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic binding sites of the yeast cell-cycle transcription factors SBF and MBF</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Iyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">409</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="533" to="538" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated software system for analyzing ChIP-chip and ChIPseq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Ji</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1293" to="1300" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide mapping of in vivo protein-DNA interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Johnson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">316</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1497" to="1502" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide identification of in vivo protein-DNA binding sites from ChIP-Seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Jothi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5221" to="5231" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variation in transcription factor binding among humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kasowski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">328</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive analysis of the chromatin landscape in Drosophila melanogaster</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Kharchenko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">471</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="480" to="485" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design and analysis of ChIP-seq experiments for DNA-binding proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Kharchenko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1351" to="1359" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HOT regions function as patterned developmental enhancers and have a distinct cis-regulatory signature</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Z</forename>
				<surname>Kvon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="908" to="913" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcription factors bind thousands of active and inactive regions in the Drosophila blastoderm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X.-Y</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homotypic regulatory clusters in Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Lifanov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="579" to="588" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of functional elements and regulatory circuits by Drosophila modENCODE</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Modencode Consortium</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">330</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1787" to="1797" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An encyclopedia of mouse DNA elements (Mouse ENCODE)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Encode</forename>
				<surname>Mouse</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Consortium</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">418</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computation for ChIP-seq and RNA-seq studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Pepke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide location and function of DNA binding proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Ren</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">290</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2306" to="2309" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive genome-wide protein-DNA interactions detected at single-nucleotide resolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Rhee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Pugh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1408" to="1419" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide profiles of STAT1 DNA association using chromatin immunoprecipitation and massively parallel sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Robertson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="651" to="657" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">JASPAR: an open-access database for eukaryotic transcription factor binding profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Sandelin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The TAGteam motif facilitates binding of 21 sequence-specific transcription factors in the Drosophila embryo</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Satija</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Bradley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="656" to="665" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Five-vertebrate ChIP-seq reveals the evolutionary dynamics of transcription factor binding</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Schmidt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">328</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1036" to="1040" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptional control in the segmentation gene network of Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Schroeder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">271</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide analysis of transcription factor binding sites based on ChIP-Seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Valouev</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="829" to="834" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of algorithm performance in ChIP-seq peak detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Wilbanks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Facciotti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11471</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ChIP-PaM: an algorithm to identify protein-DNA interaction using ChIP-Seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theor. Biol. Med. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uncovering cis-regulatory sequence requirements for context-specific transcription factor binding</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Ya´n˜ezya´n˜ya´n˜ez-Cuna</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2018" to="2030" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deciphering the transcriptional cis-regulatory code</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Ya´n˜ezya´n˜ya´n˜ez-Cuna</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Model-based analysis of ChIP-Seq (MACS)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">137</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic analysis of variation in transcription factor binding in yeast</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Zheng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">464</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1187" to="1191" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide identification of binding sites defines distinct functions for Caenorhabditis elegans PHA-4/FOXA in development and environmental response</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Zhong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000848</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>