
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology Identification of feedback loops in neural networks based on multi-step Granger causality</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chao-Yi</forename>
								<surname>Dong</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Automatic Control</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Inner Mongolia University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>010080</postCode>
									<settlement>Huhhot</settlement>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dongkwan</forename>
								<surname>Shin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Automatic Control</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Inner Mongolia University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>010080</postCode>
									<settlement>Huhhot</settlement>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sunghoon</forename>
								<surname>Joo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Automatic Control</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Inner Mongolia University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>010080</postCode>
									<settlement>Huhhot</settlement>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yoonkey</forename>
								<surname>Nam</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Automatic Control</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Inner Mongolia University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>010080</postCode>
									<settlement>Huhhot</settlement>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kwang-Hyun</forename>
								<surname>Cho</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Automatic Control</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Inner Mongolia University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>010080</postCode>
									<settlement>Huhhot</settlement>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Olga</forename>
								<surname>Troyanskaya</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Bio and Brain Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Advanced Institute of Science and Technology (KAIST)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>305-701</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
									<country>Korea, Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology Identification of feedback loops in neural networks based on multi-step Granger causality</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2146" to="2153"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts354</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 28, 2011; revised on April 23, 2012; accepted on June 4, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [18:52 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts354.tex] Page: 2146 2146–2153 Associate Editor: Contact: ckh@kaist.ac.kr Availability: The software implementing MSGCM is available at Supplementary Information. Supplementary Information: Supplementary material are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Feedback circuits are crucial network motifs, ubiquitously found in many intra-and inter-cellular regulatory networks, and also act as basic building blocks for inducing synchronized bursting behaviors in neural network dynamics. Therefore, the system-level identification of feedback circuits using time-series measurements is critical to understand the underlying regulatory mechanism of synchronized bursting behaviors. Results: Multi-Step Granger Causality Method (MSGCM) was developed to identify feedback loops embedded in biological networks using time-series experimental measurements. Based on multivariate time-series analysis, MSGCM used a modified Wald test to infer the existence of multi-step Granger causality between a pair of network nodes. A significant bi-directional multi-step Granger causality between two nodes indicated the existence of a feedback loop. This new identification method resolved the drawback of the previous non-causal impulse response component method which was only applicable to networks containing no co-regulatory forward path. MSGCM also significantly improved the ratio of correct identification of feedback loops. In this study, the MSGCM was testified using synthetic pulsed neural network models and also in vitro cultured rat neural networks using multi-electrode array. As a result, we found a large number of feedback loops in the in vitro cultured neural networks with apparent synchronized oscillation, indicating a close relationship between synchronized oscillatory bursting behavior and underlying feedback loops. The MSGCM is an efficient method to investigate feedback loops embedded in in vitro cultured neural networks. The identified feedback loop motifs are considered as an important design principle responsible for the synchronized bursting behavior in neural networks.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Feedback circuits are key regulatory motifs in many biological systems. Previous studies show that positive feedback loops * To whom correspondence should be addressed. determine a variety of cellular processes such as development, cell proliferation, apoptosis and responses to stress (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Eisen et al., 1967;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Wolpert and Lewis, 1975</ref>), and negative feedback loops contribute to maintaining the homeostasis of biological systems under internal and external interferences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kim et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Maeda et al., 2004</ref>). Moreover, many functional modules in biological systems are composed of multiple feedback loops. Various nonlinear dynamic behaviors of biological systems are generated by combination of positive and negative feedback loops (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Glendinning, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Strogatz, 2000</ref>). Interlinked fast and slow positive feedback loops (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Brandman et al., 2005</ref>) can form a 'dual-time' switch which is rapidly inducible and also resistant to noises propagated from the upstream signaling system. Coupled direct and indirect positive feedback loops induce robust synchronized bursting behaviors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Dong et al., 2009a</ref>). Identifying the existence of an intra-or inter-cellular feedback circuit in biological networks is an important systems biological issue. A variety of network motif search tools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alon, 2007</ref>) such as mfinder (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kashtan et al., 2002</ref>), FANMOD (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Wernicke and Rasche, 2006</ref>) and MAVisto (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Schreiber and Schwobbermeyer, 2005</ref>) were proposed to find small vertex-induced subgraphs (occurring more frequently than those in random networks) from a network with known topology, but such methods cannot be used to identify hidden feedback loops in a network with unknown topology from timeseries measurements On the other hand, time-series measurements of dynamical responses are now increasingly available [e.g. real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Heid et al., 1996</ref>), microarray (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Schena et al., 1995</ref>), immunofluorescence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Henle and Henle, 1966</ref>) and multi-electrode array (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chong et al., 2011)]</ref>and various types of biological networks can be investigated using such data. So, there is a pressing need to develop an efficient method to identify feedback loops from multi-channel dynamical response data. Based on timeseries analysis and system identification theory, several methods have been proposed to tackle this problem. For instance,<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Caines and Chan (1975)</ref>proposed the likelihood ratio test method (LRTM) based on the minimum phase spectral factor (MPSF) which is a canonical representation of the power spectral density matrix of the joint stochastic process of input and output data. In LRTM, the feedback effect between two-partitioned node sets was investigated with a priori knowledge on the system order and structure. Although LRTM can identify a feedback loop between two-partitioned node sets, it cannot identify a feedback loop between two individual nodes in the network.<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Schnider et al. (1989)</ref>developed a direct coherence method in the frequency domain to detect feedbacks in the central</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Identification of feedback loops based on multi-step Granger causality</head><p>nervous system. Subsequent studies have further developed and extended this method for other physiological applications such as detecting bi-directional hippocampal interactions between the CA3 and CA1 regions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baccala and Sameshima, 1999</ref>) and quantifying the linear causal strength in closely interacting cardiovascular variability signals (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Porta et al., 2002</ref>). The direct coherence approach can unravel the existence of a strong or weak feedback interaction between two variates, but a statistical test of this approach has not yet been provided. In our previous study, we have developed the noncausal impulse response component method (NIRCM) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Dong et al., 2009a</ref>, b) on the basis of correlation identification and spectral factor analysis. NIRCM does not require any explicit knowledge about the system order or structure and has also relatively low computational complexity, but it was only applicable to networks that do not include co-regulatory forward paths. Although several different methods for identification of biological feedback loops have been developed, all the methods still have fundamental limitations in finding feedback interactions between individual nodes in complex biological networks without a priori knowledge on the system. Hence, it is indispensable to develop a more efficient identification method which can overcome such difficulties of the previous methods. In this study, we proposed a multi-step Granger causality method (MSGCM) to identify the feedback loops embedded in biological networks where a pair of nodes might share some common predecessors. Note that NIRCM cannot be applied to networks in case input and output noises from a pair of nodes are correlated through a co-regulating predecessor (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Caines and Chan, 1975</ref>). Basically, MSGCM is a multiple timeseries analysis method based on the vector autoregressive (VAR) model. So, it is suitable to identify feedback loops between any pair of network nodes by simultaneously analyzing all dynamical couplings inside the network. The parameter values of the VAR model are estimated using the multivariate least-squares method (MLSM) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Ruppert and Wand, 1994</ref>). Then, a multi-step causality test is applied to the VAR model with the estimated parameter values to infer the h-step causality between all pairs of nodes. In particular, modified Wald statistics were used to avoid the problem of matrix rank reduction (<ref type="bibr">Lütkepohl, 2005</ref>). Finally, an asymptotic distribution of the Wald statistics was formed to examine the existence of h-step causality. Bi-directional h-step causality between a pair of nodes indicates the existence of a feedback loop between the two nodes. This method can be considered as a natural extension of the NIRCM to multivariate systems by introducing multivariate time-series analysis. Since the dynamical couplings between nodes can be decoupled by MSGCM, it will be more useful for the identification of feedback loops in a densely connected biological network. We applied the proposed MSGCM to synthetic neural network simulation data based on Spike Response Model (SRM) and also to the time-series data obtained from in vitro cultured neural networks. As a result, a significant number of feedback loops were identified from the synchronized oscillatory behaviors, indicating a close correlation between such behaviors and the underlying feedback loops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">VAR model</head><p>Dynamical characteristics of complex systems such as biological networks can be inferred from the analysis of a multivariate stochastic model fitted to the observation of time-series data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Tiao and Box, 1981</ref>). In practice, many spontaneous time-series data are considered as the measured output of stationary stochastic processes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Ross, 1996</ref>). Assume X k = (x 1 (k), x 2 (k), … , x N (k)) (k= 0, ±1, ±2, … , which indicates the time index) to be a stationary multivariate stochastic process. X k denotes the N-dimensional measurements vector of the biological network composed of N-nodes. The purpose of feedback loop identification is to infer the bi-directional dynamical coupling between any pair of nodes x i (k) and x j (k), where i,j = 1,2,...,N with i = j. In this study, the dynamical coupling is conceptually identical to the directional multi-step (say h-step, where h can be any positive integer up to infinity) Granger causality that is described in detail in the following section. If bidirectional multi-step Granger causalities are identified between two nodes, it means that a feedback loop exists between them. Among various models representing stationary multivariate time-series data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Brillinger, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Cadotte et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Lütkepohl, 2005</ref>), the VAR model is selected here to model biological multivariate data because of its feasibility and ease of computations. The pth-order VAR model (VAR(p)) is constructed by expressing X k , the value of a (multivariate) process X at current time k, with its past values weighted with certain coefficients A l and a (multivariate) white noise value E k :</p><formula>X k = V + p l=1 A l X k−l +E k , k = 0</formula><p>,±1,±2,...,</p><formula>(1)</formula><formula>where X k = x 1 (k), x 2 (k), ..., x N k , E k = e 1 (k),e 2 (k),...,e N k and V = v 1 ,v 2</formula><p>,...,v N which is a constant vector of intercept terms representing the mean of X k. For a given vector of multivariate time series, its VAR(p) model can be readily estimated by MLSM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Ruppert and Wand, 1994</ref>). Suppose that we have a sample of size L for each of N variates with the same sample period. The estimation of A := A 1 , A 2 , .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>.. ,A p</head><p>N×Np is calculated as follows:</p><formula>ˆ A = Y 0 X XX −1 ,</formula><formula>(2)</formula><p>where Y 0 := [X 1 −μ, X 2 −μ,...,</p><formula>X L −μ] N×L ,Y 0 k := ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ X k −μ . . . X k−p+1 −μ ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ Np×1 , X := Y 0 0 , Y 0 1 ,...,Y 0 L−1 Np×L and μ := E(X k ) ≈ 1 L L k=1 X k .</formula><p>In addition, an unbiased estimate of the covariance matrix E of E k is obtained as (<ref type="bibr">Lütkepohl, 2005</ref>)</p><formula>ˆ E = 1 L −Np−1 L k=1ˆE k=1ˆ k=1ˆE k ˆ E k = 1 L −Np−1 (Y 0 − ˆ AX)(Y 0 − ˆ AX) .</formula><formula>(3)</formula><p>If the preceding estimation procedures are repeated for different p-values, the order of the VAR(p) model can be selected by HQ criterion (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Hannan and Quinn, 1979</ref>) which provides an optimal solution of p using the knowledge of data size L, network dimension N and estimated covariance matrixˆEmatrixˆ matrixˆE. According to the HQ criterion, model order p is estimated by optimizing HQ(p) = lnˆE lnˆ lnˆE (p)</p><formula>+ 2lnlnL L pN 2 .</formula><formula>(4)</formula><p>Therefore, the optimal order can be determined as p opt = arg</p><formula>p min(HQ(p)).</formula><p>The advantage of the HQ criterion is that p opt is a consistent estimatorˆp estimatorˆ estimatorˆp converging in probability to p, which is superior to other estimators using different criteria such as Akaike Information Criterion (AIC), Final Prediction Error (FPE) and Schwarz (SC) (<ref type="bibr">Lütkepohl, 2005</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">h-Step optimal prediction and multi-step causality</head><p>The concept of multi-step Granger causality is defined in light of an optimal prediction of the future value of one variate by using the current and past values of all network variates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Granger, 1969</ref>). If a contribution to the prediction comes from the variate itself, it is considered as a self-coupling;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.-Y.Dong et al.</head><p>otherwise, if a contribution comes from the other variates, it is called an alien coupling. Such predicted effects include not only most recent contributions but also very earlier contributions of all variates, depending on how much delayed couplings reach from the variates. We use h-step (h can be 1,2,...,∞, and it denotes the number of sampling periods) to quantify such 'multi-step' delayed coupling effects. In the following, some crucial inferences, such as hstep optimal prediction of a process and multi-step Granger causality between network variates, are immediately derived from the identified VAR(p). For an N-dimensional stable VAR(p) process denoted by</p><formula>X k = (x 1 (k), x 2 (k), … , x N (k)</formula><p>) , it was shown that the minimum mean square error (MSE) predictor for prediction horizon h at prediction origin k is the conditional expected value</p><formula>E k (X k+h ) := E(X k+h |{X l |l k } ), (5)</formula><p>which minimizes the MSE of X k+h (<ref type="bibr">Lütkepohl, 2005</ref>). Herein, the notation {X l |l k } stands for all available information of X until time k. For a zero mean representation of the VAR(p) model, the optimal h-step predictor (in the sense of minimum MSE) of X k at origin time k can be represented as</p><formula>X k (h) = J(I Np + A+ A 2 +···+ A h−1 ) V +J A h X k , h ∈{1,2,...,∞}, (6)</formula><formula>where A := ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ A 1 A 2 ··· A p−1 A p I N 0 ··· 0 0 0 I N ··· 0 0 . . . . . . .. . . . . . . . 0 0 ··· I N 0 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ Np×Np, X k := ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ X k X k−1 . . . X k−p+1 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ Np×1, E k := ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ E k 0 . . . 0 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ Np×1, V := ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ V 0 . . . 0 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ Np×1 and J := [I N : 0 : ··· : 0] N×Np .</formula><p>The h-step prediction error is E k (h) = X k+h −X k (h) = h−1 m=0 m e k+h−m and the corresponding prediction error covariance matrix is X (h) = h−1 m=0 m E m , where m := J A m J and E is the covariance matrix of white noises E k. The proof of the above derivation is provided in the Supplementary Material (Section 1).<ref type="bibr">Equation (6)</ref>shows how all the network variates contribute to predicting each single variate. For instance, x k j (h), which corresponds to the jth row in Equation (6) (j= 1, 2, … , N), is the optimal (minimum MSE) h-step predictor of the jth variate x(k) at origin k obtained by using the current and past information of all variates. The corresponding prediction MSE is denoted by</p><formula>x i (h|{X l |l k }) (i= 1, 2, … , N).</formula><p>The prediction MSE will increase if the information of some preceding variables is not considered. So, multi-step Granger causality from a stochastic variate x 1 (k) to another variate x 2 (k) was formally defined as follows (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Granger, 1969</ref>): the process x 1 (k) is said to cause x 2 (k) in multi-step Granger's sense if</p><formula>x 2 (h|{X l |l k } ) &lt;&lt; x 2 (h|{X l |l k } \{x 1 (s)|s k }) (7)</formula><p>for at least one h ∈{1,2,...,∞} (in practice, we only need to check for a finite step—see later of this section for details), i.e. the prediction of x 2 (k) can be improved if the past and current information in x 1 (k) is taken into account in addition to all the relevant information under consideration [the backslash in Equation (7) denotes the exclusion of the information of {x 1 (s)|s k }<ref type="bibr">]</ref>. Note that the case of h = 0 is considered as instantaneous Granger causality which is physically unfeasible in biological networks because there is usually a significant time delay accompanied with the coupling process. So, we have excluded in this article such instantaneous Granger causality as well as self-coupling for nontrivial discussion. That is, only delayed alien (between different variates) couplings are considered in this article. Feedback loops are found when significant bi-directional multi-step Granger causalities are identified between two different network variates. Multi-step Granger causality is fairly easy to evaluate in the context of a VAR model. Let us consider the multi-step Granger causality between two variates x i (k) and x j (k) (i,j = 1,2,...,N and i = j) in an N-dimensional network. Consistent with the definition of multi-step Granger causality, x i (k) is called h-step non-causal for x j (k) if the m-step ahead predictions of x j (k) cannot be improved for all m h by taking into account the past and present x i (l)(l k). Therefore, x i (k) is h-step non-causal for x j (k) if and only if all elements in the jth row and ith column in matrix J A h l</p><p>, which is the lth column block matrix of J A m (for m = 1,2,...,h and l = 1,2,...,p), are zeros. This means that there is no contribution from the regulating variate x i (k) to the prediction of the regulated variate x j (k) until h-step delays. We can derive this from h-step optimal predictor X k (h) [see Equation (6) and its expansion in Equation (8)]:</p><formula>X k (h) = J(I Np + A+ A 2 +···+ A h−1 ) V + J A h 1 X k + J A h 2 X k−1 +··· J A h p X k−p+1 .</formula><formula>(8)</formula><p>For a two-partitioned process, one-step Granger causality is equivalent to multi-step Granger causality (details can be found from<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Baccala et al., 1998</ref>). The problem of feedback identification is now transformed into a problem of investigating whether non-diagonal blocks in A l (l = 1,2,...,p) are zero simultaneously or not. However, in most biological networks, researchers are often interested in the causal couplings between a pair of variates rather than those between two-partitioned variate sets. Therefore, it is necessary to develop an approach to identify the multi-step Granger causality between any two variates in a higher dimensional network (N 3). In the previous analysis, we need to prove h-step non-causality up to infinity to show that x i (k) does not contribute to the predictions of x j (k) (in the sense of multi-step Granger causality) in a multi-dimensional network. This task seems daunting and time-consuming. However,<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dufour and Renault (1998)</ref>showed that we only need to examine a limited step of p(N −2)+1 instead of examining until infinite steps. This makes a statistical test of the MSGCM feasible for computation. See Supplementary Material (Section 2) for details on the modified Wald test to examine the multi-step Granger causality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">The algorithm for identification of feedback loops based on MSGCM</head><p>In this section, we propose an algorithm to identify feedback loops in multivariate biological networks. As this algorithm is based on the foregoing multi-step Granger causality test, it is called the MSGCM. The MSGCM algorithm can be implemented in Matlab 2007 (Mathworks, Inc.) [codes are provided in the Supplementary Material (<ref type="bibr">Section 8)]</ref>and the identification steps are summarized in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 1</ref>. The aforementioned algorithm can identify direct couplings as well as indirect couplings, i.e. when the signal from one node is or is not relayed through another node(s) before reaching the target node since the predictions for one variate would naturally include these two parts of contributions that usually appear in different prediction step h. In the following section, MSGCM is applied to simulated datasets obtained from computational neural network models [i.e. synthetic pulsed neural networks, see the Supplementary Material (Section 3) for a brief introduction of the models]. It turns out that MSGCM can successfully identify the direct as well as indirect feedback loops in two-, three-and (a more complicated) six-node networks. See the Supplementary Material (Section 4) for details on the sampling method of spike data. In our analysis, we used a limited bin size to low-pass filter the spike train data. In particular, a bin size of 10 ms was chosen to minimize false-positive identification (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Golub and Van Loan, 1996</ref>). The sampling with a 10 ms interval corresponds to the low-pass filtering with the cutoff frequency of 100 Hz, which can filter out high frequency noises that contribute to false-positive identifications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Multichannel recordings of in vitro neural networks</head><p>Hippocampal or cortical neurons used for developing in vitro neural networks were isolated from the brain of the Sprague-Dawley rat at embryonic day 18 (E18). Mechanically dissociated neurons were seeded on a planar-type microelectrode array (MEA) which has 60 surface-embeddedshows the detailed sub-steps for identifying the significance of multi-step Granger causality for a sequential pair (x i (k),x j (k)) by the modified Wald test microelectrodes for neural signal recordings. The MEA was cultivated in a humidified incubator with 37˚C, 5% CO 2. After 2 weeks of maturation period inside the incubator, the cultured MEA chip was connected with a MEA1060BC preamplifier (Gain 50, BW 0.1—8500 Hz; Multi Channel Systems, Reutlingen, Germany) and FA60S amplifier (Gain 20, BW 10—5000 Hz; Multi Channel Systems). Multichannel signals were digitized and processed by MC Rack (Multi Channel Systems) and Offline Sorter (Plexon Inc., TX, USA). Extracellular action potentials (spikes) were detected by setting the threshold level at 5× standard deviation (SD of background noise level) and spike waveforms were classified (sorted) by principal component analysis (PCA) using dedicated spike sorting program (Offline Sorter). There can be multiple neurons (or units) generating spikes near a sensor. So, detected spikes are classified and clustered according to the shape of spikes. PCA has been used as one of the classification techniques to find a well-clustered spike signals (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Hill et al., 2011</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Identification of feedback loops based on multi-step Granger causality</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Synthetic neural network simulations</head><p>To examine the efficacy of MSGCM for identification of feedback loops, we first applied it to two-and three-node pulsed neural networks of 12 different topologies as shown in Supplementary (Section 5)<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure S3a</ref>. The spike trains of each network were displayed for a period of 1 s, extracted from 20 s simulations [Supplementary (Section 5) Fig.<ref type="bibr">S3b]</ref>. Finally, the sampled timeseries data of the neurons in each network were obtained as shown in Supplementary (Section 5)<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure S3c</ref>. Based on these time-series data, MSGCM was applied to the six networks. As a result, we successfully identified the existence of feedback loops</p><formula>(b)</formula><formula>(c)</formula><p>(a)<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>. The MSGCM was also applied to a more complicated sixnode network model containing two direct feedback loops and one indirect feedback loop. We constructed this model based on the same dynamical mechanism as those of the previous two-and three-node pulsed neural network models (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 2a</ref>). Based on the obtained time-series data (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 2c</ref>), MSGCM was then used to identify the existence of feedback loops with three multiples of the SD credence level (α = 0.00135). Using HQ criterion, we determined an optimal order p opt = 6 which corresponds to an HQ value of −7.5071. With the estimated parameters of the VAR(6) model, the Wald statistics showed significant Granger causalities in the network (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). Since the bi-directional Granger causalities exist, we conclude that there is a feedback loop between neuron 1 and neuron 5. In the same way, we identified the other bi-directional couplings between neurons (2,3), (3,4) and (2,4). At this stage, we do not know whether the identified feedback loops are direct or indirect. However, MSGCM can correctly discern the existence of feedback loops between any pair of nodes. So, we can eventually identify all direct or indirect feedback loops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Comparison of MSGCM and NIRCM</head><p>For quantitative comparison of the efficacies of MSGCM and NIRCM, we applied both methods to the same synthetic pulsed neural networks and compared their identification results. We simulated<ref type="bibr">[</ref>The '1's in the table represent the existence of significant Granger causalities from a column index to a row index, while '0's denote the non-existence of any significant Granger causality. The comparison between λ mod W and χ 2 1−α (hp) is listed to the right of the identified results, where if λ mod W ≤ χ 2 1−α (hp), then '0' is inferred and if λ mod W ≤ χ 2 1−α (hp), then '1' is inferred. The four red-colored '1's in a symmetrical position by the right diagonal show the three identified feedback loops, which corresponds two pairs of bi-directional Granger causalities across nodes (1,5), nodes (3,4), nodes (2,3) and nodes (2,4).For each network scale, 100 randomly connected networks were tested using MSGCM and NIRCM. networks where the synaptic efficacies w ij were randomly chosen from a uniform distribution<ref type="bibr">[−1, 1]</ref>[see Supplementary Material (Section 3) for further details on<ref type="bibr">SRM]</ref>. For in vitro cultured neural networks, it has already been shown that each neuron is mono-synaptically connected to 10–30% of all other neurons at their matured phase and a matured inhibitory synaptic ratio of all the synapses is about 10–20% (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Jimbo et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Marom and Shahaf, 2002</ref>). To mimic such in vitro cultured neural networks, the structure of the simulated network was randomly formed by keeping CR of 20% and ER of 90% [see detailed definitions of CR and ER in the Supplementary Material (<ref type="bibr">Section 7)]</ref>. For each network size, 100 randomly connected networks were tested for identification of their feedback loops using the two methods. For each n-node network, we judged whether the feedback loop identification is correct or not with respect to all pairs of nodes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.-Y.Dong et al.</head><p>Then, for all the pairs of nodes (n(n−1)/2 in total), we counted the following four categorized cases: (1) the number of cases for correct identification of a feedback loop, n cf ; (2) the number of cases for correct identification of no feedback loop, n cnf ; (3) the number of cases for false-positive identification of a feedback loop, n fp and (4) the number of cases for false-negative identification of no feedback loop, n fn. Then, the ratio of correct identifications is defined as 2(n cf +n cnf )/(n(n−1)); the false-positive ratio as 2n fp /(n(n−1)) and the false-negative ratio as 2n fn /(n(n−1)). The means and SDs of the defined three ratios using two different methods were shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>.</p><p>The simulation results showed that the correct identification ratios of MSGCM are always significantly higher than those of NIRCM. Both methods had a low level of means for false-positive and false-negative ratios. The false-positive ratios of MSGCM were significantly less than those of NIRCM and the false-negative ratios of MSGCM were slightly higher than those of NIRCM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Investigation of feedback loops in cultured neural networks</head><p>In previous sections, we showed the efficacy of MSGCM in identifying feedback loops in the artificial neuronal networks. Then, we also investigated the presence of feedback loops in real biological neural networks that spontaneously generate dynamical behaviors. The experimental data were obtained from a MEA (diameter 30 µm and spacing 200 µm) which can measure electrical signals (extracellular spikes) present in in vitro hippocampal neural networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Eytan et al., 2003</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Eytan et al., , 2004</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Marom and Shahaf, 2002</ref>;<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Shahaf and Marom, 2001</ref>). A detailed experimental protocol is described in the Supplementary Material (The age of each sample network is defined by DIV (days in vivo). Average SIs were calculated by averaging the SIs for all possible channel pairs in each culture with a time bin of 0.2 s; average burst rates (BR) are the counted number of bursts happening in per minutes for all nine channel data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Identification of feedback loops based on multi-step Granger causality</head><p>Culture 4 was a micro-island neuronal culture in an agarose microwell array (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kang et al., 2009</ref>) in which all physical connections between neurons were 'cut off' by the deliberate design. Then, electrodes under Culture 4 recorded spike trains from completely isolated neuronal circuits. Each electrode presented bursting activity generated by a few neurons, but the activity was not able to propagate through other electrodes due to the absence of biological connections between the electrodes. Therefore, the resultant spike trains of each electrode were affected by neurons from other electrodes. This was confirmed by applying MSGCM, as no feedback loop from Culture 4 was identified among 10 electrodes, as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>. Therefore, the identification validated the feedback free cases in this nonconnective culture. We also tried to identify feedback loops in the four cultures using NIRCM. The resulting identified feedback loops are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>. Although the number of channels was similar in all experiments, the identified feedback loops were different depending on the temporal patterns of spike trains. In particular, the enrichment of identified feedback loops was related to synchronized bursting behaviors. To quantify the temporal relationship of a pair of channels, the cross-correlation coefficient of the two binned data was defined as a synchrony index (SI) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Sasaki et al., 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Wylie et al., 1995</ref>). In this study, a sample correlation coefficient was calculated to approximate the cross-correlation coefficient. Given two binned data, x(k) and y(k) (k = 1,2,...,L), then the sample correlation coefficient is as follows:</p><formula>r xy = L k=1 (x(k)−¯ x)(y(k)−¯ y) L k=1 (x(k)−¯ x) 2 L k=1 (y(k)−¯ y) 2 where ¯ x = 1 L L k=1 x(k) and ¯ y = 1 L L k=1 y(k)</formula><p>. Average SIs were then calculated by averaging the SIs for all possible pairs of channels in each culture to evaluate the degree of synchronized behaviors. In the raster plots of Cultures 1 and 2, we can find apparent synchronized oscillations among most of the electrodes (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 3</ref>). This was also indicated by high SI index in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>. For Culture 3, SI index was significantly smaller than Cultures 1 and 2 despite high burst rates. These distinct behaviors were closely linked to the existence of a feedback loop. A larger number of feedback loops were found from Cultures 1 and 2 than Culture 3 (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>). As expected, Culture 4 did not show any synchrony due to the isolation of each electrode indicating no identified feedback loop from the spike trains in Culture 4.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 4</ref>shows two sets of feedback loops identified from Cultures 1 and 3, respectively. We can see a distinct distribution of feedback loops between these two cultures. Culture 1, presenting<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>apparent synchronized oscillatory behavior, had 11 feedback loops among 9 electrodes, whereas Culture 3, showing less synchronized oscillations, had just 4 feedback loops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>In this study, we investigated the problem of identifying feedback loops embedded in intra-or inter-cellular biological networks using time-series measurements. Based on multivariate time-series analysis, our proposed MSGCM can simultaneously analyze all network variates in the process of identifying the feedback loops from complicated biological networks. MSGCM can completely decouple the correlations between a pair of examined variates and the remaining variates in the network. This makes MSGCM overcome the shortcoming of NIRCM since co-regulatory forward paths always cause an input–output noise correlation. In this regard, MSGCM is more advanced than NIRCM and suitable for complex multivariate systems like biological networks. The application of MSGCM and NIRCM to the same synthetic pulsed neural networks showed that the correct identification ratios of MSGCM are always significantly higher than those of NIRCM. Although MSGCM can identify feedback loops of multivariate networks more accurately, its computational complexity is higher than NIRCM. However,The nodes and their corresponding micro-electrodes were numbered according to their locations on the MEA. The feedback loops were denoted by bi-directional arrows. For Culture 1, 11 feedback loops were found, corresponding to a synchronized oscillatory behavior, while for Culture 3, only 4 feedback loops were found, related to a nearly random behavior such complexity issues can be alleviated as high-performance computation devices become more available. In this study, we showed that MSGCM can successfully identify feedback loops in synthetic neural network models and in vitro cultured neural networks. We also found that synchronized oscillatory bursting behaviors were closely related to the existence of feedback loops. From this finding, we infer that a feedback loop might be an important network motif for the synchronized oscillatory behavior in pulsed neural networks. In fact, the experiments using in vitro cultured neural networks showed that the adjustment of synaptic connections was highly correlated with the development of neuronal network behaviors characterized by the evolvement of spontaneous electrical activities of the network (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Muramoto et al., 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Van Huizen et al., 1985</ref>). An interesting phenomenon was that the visibility of synchronized bursting behaviors was dependent on the developing phase of the tested in vitro neuron cultures. In vitro cultured neural networks showed spontaneous and uncorrelated bursting activities in the beginning, but, after about six DIVs, they exhibited abruptly a synchronized bursting activity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Habets et al., 1987</ref>). Then a question arises as to what triggered such an emergent property in the cultured neural networks? The feedback identification method proposed in this study provides a very useful tool to infer a network motif responsible for this emergent property. Previous studies indicated that developing neurons showed their maximum synchronized activities at the 2nd or 3rd week of the brain development (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Habets et al., 1987</ref>) and after that neuronal circuits reached an optimal connectivity by pruning their connections (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Van Huizen et al., 1985</ref>), i.e. undergoing an overall decline in the number of synapses. We can also find such a development trend by tracing the variation of feedback loop abundance in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>(the number of feedback loops: 11 → 22 → 4 for DIV: 14 → 18 → 21). As the networks are considered to be randomly connected, it would be reasonable to presume that the abundance of feedback loops is positively correlated with the whole network connectivity. Thus, identifying feedback loops using MSGCM can also be validated from this comparison. Although we showed in this article the identification of feedback loops in cultured neural networks and investigations into the relationship between the structure of a network and its dynamical behavior, the presented approach can also be applied to studying other biological networks based on time-series measurements using, for example, real-time PCR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Heid et al., 1996</ref>), immunofluorescence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Henle and Henle, 1966</ref>) and microarray (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Schena et al., 1995</ref>). If the dynamical response of a biological network can be measured and obtained in the form of multivariate time-series data, MSGCM can be used to investigate the underlying causal feedback connections in the network. For instance, recent advances in neural imaging devices have provided enormous time-course data from the brain. Examples include macroscopic electroencephalography and magnetoencephalography signals recorded from the scalp, invasive electrocorticography from the cortical surface and mesoscopic local field potential with electrodes inserted deep inside the brain. These data have opened a new era for experimental studies on the detailed wiring structure of a functional neural network (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">He et al., 2011</ref>). Most of the studies to date, however, have dealt with the functional connectivity of a brain using simple correlation or effective connectivity of a local brain region. MSGCM enables us to construct a functional feedback network covering the whole brain regions and to further project a brain network to a more precise interaction map compared with previous studies. Our method can also be used as a useful tool for examining the functional connectivity anomalies occurring in patients with psychiatric disorders.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [18:52 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts354.tex] Page: 2147 2146–2153</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [18:52 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts354.tex] Page: 2149 2146–2153</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The flow chart of the algorithm of MSGCM. The right inset shows the detailed sub-steps for identifying the significance of multi-step Granger causality for a sequential pair (x i (k),x j (k)) by the modified Wald test</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. A six-node pulsed neural network simulations. (a) The scheme of the six-node pulsed neural network. The red arrows highlight the locations of two direct feedback loops (1,5) and (3,4) and one indirect feedback loop (2,3,4). The weights of the synapses are denoted by the numbers around the arrows. (b) The raster plots of six neuron recordings (only the first 1 s segment of 20 s is shown). (c) The sampled time series from the six spike trains after binning them at 10 ms interval (only the first 1 s second segment of 20 s is shown)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><figDesc>with the same simulation protocol as detailed in the Supplementary Material (Section 5)] a number of neural networks of different sizes ranging from 6 to 20 nodes. Simulations were performed using SRMs for realization of randomly connected Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [18:52 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts354.tex] Page: 2150 2146–2153</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>2.</head><figDesc>The means and standard deviations of the ratios of correct identifications, the false-positive ratios, and the false-negative ratios for different network scales with Connective Ratio (CR) of 20% and Excitatory Ratio (ER) of 90% Network scale (the number of nodes) Correct identification ratio False-positive ratio False-negative ratio</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. The four 40 s segments of spike trains obtained from Cultures 1– 4. Spike trains in Cultures 1–3 were from massively inter-connected neural networks, while spike trains in Culture 4 were from isolated micro-neural clusters by cell repulsive layer (agarose solution 2% wt/vol (mg/ml)). The numbers of identified feedback loops are summarized in Table 3</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. The maps of identified feedback loops in Cultures 1 and 3. The nodes and their corresponding micro-electrodes were numbered according to their locations on the MEA. The feedback loops were denoted by bi-directional arrows. For Culture 1, 11 feedback loops were found, corresponding to a synchronized oscillatory behavior, while for Culture 3, only 4 feedback loops were found, related to a nearly random behavior</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) grants funded by the Korea Government, the Ministry of Education, Science &amp; Technology (MEST) (2009-0086964 and 2010-0017662); The WCU (World Class University) program (R32-2008-00010218-0) and the Brain Research Center of the 21st Century Frontier Research Program. Conflict of interest: None declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>. 2. A six-node pulsed neural network simulations. (a) The scheme of the six-node pulsed neural network. The red arrows highlight the locations of two direct feedback loops (1,5) and (3,4) and one indirect feedback loop (2,3,4). The weights of the synapses are denoted by the numbers around the arrows. (b) The raster plots of six neuron recordings (only the first 1 s segment of 20 s is shown). (c) The sampled time series from the six spike trains after binning them at 10 ms interval (only the first 1 s second segment of 20 s is shown) in all two-and three-node network topologies. The key parameters and results for identifications are summarized in Supplementary (Section 5)</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. The identified multi-step Granger causalities in the six-node synthetic neural network</figDesc><table>Node 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 

1 
0 
0 (256.1 &lt; 263.6) 
0 (190.8 &lt; 263.6) 
0 (250.3 &lt; 263.6) 
1 (611.6 &gt; 263.6) 
0 (205.9 &lt; 263.6) 
2 
1 (339.1 &gt; 263.6) 
0 
1(331.9 &gt; 263.6) 
1 (424.2 &gt; 263.6) 
1 (578.1 &gt; 263.6) 
1 (308.5 &gt; 263.6) 
3 
1 (402.2 &gt; 263.6) 
1 (286.0 &gt; 263.6) 
0 
1 (523.3 &gt; 263.6) 
1 (472.0 &gt; 263.6) 
0 (222.7 &lt; 263.6) 
4 
1 (314.4 &gt; 263.6) 
1 (301.6 &gt; 263.6) 
1 (451.6 &gt; 263.6) 
0 
1 (325.2 &gt; 263.6) 
1 (335.3 &gt; 263.6) 
5 
1 (474.9 &gt; 263.6) 
0 (225.3 &lt; 263.6) 
0 (212.7 &lt; 263.6) 
0 (189.2 &lt; 263.6) 
0 
0 (231.3 &lt; 263.6) 
6 
0 (183.2 &lt; 263.6) 
0 (183.3 &lt; 263.6) 
0 (215.9 &lt; 263.6) 
0 (219.3 &lt; 263.6) 
0 (185.0 &lt; 263.6) 
0 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><figDesc>Table</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 3. The identification results of feedback loops in four cultured neural networks obtained by applying MSGCM and NIRCM</figDesc><table>Network 
index 

Age of network 
(DIV) 

No. of 
nodes 

Average BR 
(bursts/min) 

Average SI 
(bin = 0.2 s) 

No. of identified feedback 
loops by MSGCM 

No. of identified feedback 
loops by NIRCM 

1 
14 
9 
9.2 
0.6918 
11 
20 
2 
18 
9 
31.7 
0.8707 
22 
20 
3 
21 
9 
7.3 
0.3943 
4 
6 
4 
7 
10 
1.8 
0.0033 
0 
1 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network motifs: theory and experimental approaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<surname>Alon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="450" to="461" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Direct Coherence: A Tool for Exploring Functional Interactions among Brain Structures, Methods for Neural Ensemble Recordings</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Baccala</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Sameshima</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>CRC press LLC</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boca Raton</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Studying the interaction between brain structures via directed coherence and Granger causality</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Baccala</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">40</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interlinked fast and slow positive feedback loops drive reliable cell decisions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Brandman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">310</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="496" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Time Series: Data Analysis and Theory. SIAM, Society for Industrial Mathematics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Brillinger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<pubPlace>Holt, Rinehart. &amp; Winston, New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal measures of structure and plasticity in simulated and living neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Cadotte</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3355</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Feedback between stationary stochastic processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Caines</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Chan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="498" to="508" />
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synaptic dysfunction in hippocampus of transgenic mouse models of Alzheimer&apos;s disease: a multi-electrode array study</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Chong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurobiol. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="284" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic analysis of synchronized oscillatory neuronal networks reveals an enrichment for coupled direct and indirect feedback motifs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C.-Y</forename>
				<surname>Dong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1680" to="1685" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Short run and long run causality in time series: theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Dufour</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Renault</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1099" to="1125" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulation of repressor inhibition in lambda</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Eisen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1967" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="855" to="862" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selective adaptation in networks of cortical neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Eytan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9349" to="9356" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dopamine-induced dispersion of correlations between action potentials in networks of cortical neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Eytan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1817" to="1824" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Stability, Instability and Chaos: An Introduction to the Theory of Nonlinear Differential Equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Glendinning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Matrix Computations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Golub</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Van Loan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bioinformatics-bts354.tex] Page</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="71" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Identification of feedback loops based on multi-step Granger causality</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating causal relations by econometric models and crossspectral methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W J</forename>
				<surname>Granger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="424" to="438" />
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spontaneous neuronal firing patterns in fetal rat cortical networks during development in vitro: a quantitative analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Habets</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp. Brain Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The determination of the order of an autoregression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Hannan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Quinn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Roy. Stat. Soc. Ser. B Methodol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electrophysiological imaging of brain activity and connectivity— challenges and opportunities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Biomed. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1918" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real time quantitative PCR</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Heid</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="986" to="994" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunofluorescence in cells derived from Burkitt&apos;s lymphoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Henle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Henle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bacteriol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1248" to="1256" />
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quality metrics to accompany spike sorting of extracellular signals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Hill</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8699" to="8705" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneous induction of pathway-specific potentiation and depression in networks of cortical neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Jimbo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="670" to="678" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Agarose microwell based neuronal micro-circuit arrays on microelectrode arrays for high throughput drug testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Kang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lab Chip</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3236" to="3242" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mfinder Tool Guide</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Kashtan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Weizmann Institute of Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Rehovot. Israel</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coupled feedback loops form dynamic motifs of cellular networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">359</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">New Introduction to Multiple Time Series Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Lütkepohl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Periodic signaling controlled by an oscillatory circuit that includes protein kinases ERK2 and PKA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Maeda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">304</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="875" to="878" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development, learning and memory in large random networks of cortical neurons: lessons beyond anatomy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Marom</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Shahaf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Q. Rev. Biophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Frequency of synchronous oscillations of neuronal activity increases during development and is correlated to the number of synapses in cultured cortical neuron networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Muramoto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurosci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">163</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="165" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantifying the strength of the linear causal coupling in closed loop interacting cardiovascular variability signals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Porta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Stochastic Processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Ross</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multivariate locally weighted least squares regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Ruppert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Wand</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1346" to="1370" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple Purkinje cell recording in rodent cerebellar cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Sasaki</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="572" to="586" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative monitoring of gene expression patterns with a complementary DNA microarray</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Schena</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">270</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="467" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of feedback in the central nervous system using system identification techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Schnider</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MAVisto: a tool for the exploration of network motifs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Schreiber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Schwobbermeyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3572" to="3574" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning in networks of cortical neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Shahaf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Marom</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8782</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear Dynamics and Chaos: With Applications to Physics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Strogatz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biology, Chemistry, and Engineering. Perseus Books Group</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling multiple time series with applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Tiao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E P</forename>
				<surname>Box</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="802" to="816" />
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synaptogenesis in rat cerebral cortex cultures is affected during chronic blockade of spontaneous bioelectric activity by tetradotoxin</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Van Huizen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FANMOD: a tool for fast network motif detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Wernicke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Rasche</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1152" to="1153" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a theory of development</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Wolpert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Lewis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fed. Proc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal relations of the complex spike activity of Purkinje cell pairs in the vestibulocerebellum of rabbits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Wylie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2875</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>