
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:31+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology IDEOM: an Excel interface for analysis of LC–MS-based metabolomics data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">7 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Darren</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Creek</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Infection, Immunity and Inflammation</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Medical, Veterinary and Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wellcome Trust Centre for Molecular Parasitology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Glasgow</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>G12 8TA</postCode>
									<settlement>Glasgow</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Melbourne</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3010</postCode>
									<settlement>Parkville</settlement>
									<region>Victoria</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andris</forename>
								<surname>Jankevics</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Molecular, Cell and Systems Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Medical, Veterinary and Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Glasgow</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>G12 8QQ</postCode>
									<settlement>Glasgow</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Groningen Bioinformatics Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Groningen Biomolecular Sciences and Biotechnology Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Groningen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>9700 CC</postCode>
									<settlement>Groningen</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Karl</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E V</forename>
								<surname>Burgess</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Infection, Immunity and Inflammation</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Medical, Veterinary and Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wellcome Trust Centre for Molecular Parasitology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Glasgow</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>G12 8TA</postCode>
									<settlement>Glasgow</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rainer</forename>
								<surname>Breitling</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Molecular, Cell and Systems Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Medical, Veterinary and Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Glasgow</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>G12 8QQ</postCode>
									<settlement>Glasgow</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Groningen Bioinformatics Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Groningen Biomolecular Sciences and Biotechnology Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Groningen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>9700 CC</postCode>
									<settlement>Groningen</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Barrett</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Infection, Immunity and Inflammation</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Medical, Veterinary and Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wellcome Trust Centre for Molecular Parasitology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Glasgow</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>G12 8TA</postCode>
									<settlement>Glasgow</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology IDEOM: an Excel interface for analysis of LC–MS-based metabolomics data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1048" to="1049"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">7 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received on December 1, 2011; revised on January 9, 2012; accepted on January 31, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [12:40 12/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts069.tex] Page: 1048 1048–1049 Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren (.xlsb). Implementation requires Microsoft Excel (2007 or later). R is also required for full functionality. Contact: michael.barrett@glasgow.ac.uk Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The application of emerging metabolomics technologies to the comprehensive investigation of cellular biochemistry has been limited by bottlenecks in data processing, particularly noise filtering and metabolite identification. IDEOM provides a user-friendly data processing application that automates filtering and identification of metabolite peaks, paying particular attention to common sources of noise and false identifications generated by liquid chromatography– mass spectrometry (LC–MS) platforms. Building on advanced processing tools such as mzMatch and XCMS, it allows users to run a comprehensive pipeline for data analysis and visualization from a graphical user interface within Microsoft Excel, a familiar program for most biological scientists. Availability and implementation: IDEOM is provided free of charge at http://mzmatch.sourceforge.net/ideom.html, as a macro-enabled spreadsheet</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Metabolomics aims to measure all small molecules (metabolites) in a biological system. However, challenges associated with data analysis, in particular the accurate identification of metabolites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Moco et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Neumann and Böcker, 2010</ref>) have restricted progress. Recent advances in high resolution mass spectrometry (MS) provide accurate mass detection that significantly improves metabolite identification from liquid chromatography–MS (LC–MS) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Breitling et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Moco et al., 2007</ref>) although limitations still abound (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kind and Fiehn, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Neumann and Böcker, 2010</ref>), and noise or artifact peaks are often incorrectly identified as metabolites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Scheltema et al., 2009</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IDEOM</head><p>to average peak height and internal standards (optional), is automatically checked and normalization can be applied. Noise filtering within IDEOM removes common sources of noise in high resolution LC–MS data: chromatographic peak shoulders, irreproducible peaks, background or contaminant signals, and fourier transform (FT) and electrospray ionisation (ESI) artifacts including isotopes, adducts and fragments (based on<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Brown et al., 2011 and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Scheltema et al., 2011</ref>), as described in the documentation (Supplementary Material). Metabolite identification is achieved by matching the accurate mass and retention time of observed peaks to metabolites in the included database, which incorporates all likely metabolites from a wide range of biological databases, and can be updated by users for specific applications. Retention times for authentic standards, and a retention time prediction model, are included for ZIC-HILIC chromatography data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Creek et al., 2011</ref>); however, as retention times are instrument specific, users are encouraged to upload standard retention times from their own platform with the macro provided. Subsequent to initial metabolite identification, a data-dependent polynomial mass recalibration step can be applied to correct for massdependent calibration errors. The final lists of identified, and rejected, peaks are annotated with confidence scores regarding the identification of each metabolite, based on retention times, organism-specific (or user-defined) databases and annotation as possible 'related peaks' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Scheltema et al., 2009</ref>). Univariate statistics (mean, relative intensity, SD, t-test and Fisher ratio) are calculated in Excel. Multivariate statistics are obtained by calls to the R environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>The automated pre-processing steps in IDEOM drastically reduce the need for manual curation of LC–MS data by applying filters to remove hundreds of false-identifications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Creek et al., 2011</ref>). The example tutorial dataset (Supplementary Material) demonstrates putative identification of 1314 metabolites and rejection of 1942 false-identifications from serum samples. The putatively identified metabolites are displayed in an interactive table that includes metabolite information, sample intensities, comparative statistics, LC–MS data, and links to websites and graphs (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). Putative identifications can be rapidly scrutinized by double-click access to LC–MS metadata, or adjusted by selecting alternative isomers from dropdown lists. Data visualization is enhanced by Excel's conditional formatting, filtering and sorting, allowing users to view</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [12:40 12/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts069.tex] Page: 1049 1048–1049</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Screenshot of results visualization showing the dropdown list selection of isomers and some of the automatically generated hyperlinked charts.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Applications are freely available for detection, quantification and alignment of signals in LC–MS data (Blekherman et al., 2011), and numerous multivariate statistical methods have been proposed to extract significant features from these high-dimensional datasets (Madsen et al., 2010). However, many of the most powerful tools are implemented in statistical software, and while the graphical user interface (GUI) in MZmine (Pluskal et al., 2010) simplifies data pre-processing, recent advances in noise filtering and identification algorithms (Brown et al., 2011; Scheltema et al., 2011) are difficult to use without special training. IDEOM is a Microsoft Excel template with a collection of VBA macros that enable automated data processing of high resolution LC– MS data from untargeted metabolomics studies, with a particular focus on removal of noise [which accounts for ∼80% of peaks in typical LC–MS metabolomics datasets (Jankevics et al., 2012)], metabolite identification and data visualization. Its GUI allows users to exploit the power of data-processing methods such as mzMatch (Scheltema et al., 2011) and XCMS (Smith et al., 2006) from within Excel, and enables rapid and simple conversion of raw or pre-processed LC–MS data into a filtered, interpretable list of putative metabolites, with associated confidence levels and sample intensities. 2 METHODS Opening the IDEOM template in Excel provides a spreadsheet on which to specify the parameters for data processing (default values are provided). All IDEOM macros for data processing are then activated by buttons or in-cell hyperlinks, and pop-up dialog boxes are used to specify important parameters for individual processing steps. Raw LC–MS data files (.mzXML) are processed by IDEOM using the freely available XCMS (Smith et al., 2006) and mzmatch.R tools (http://mzmatch.sourceforge.net/index.php) (Scheltema et al., 2011), by automatic generation and execution of scripts in the R environment (www.r-project.org) (R, 2008) using readily adjustable parameters. Raw peaks are extracted by XCMS, and mzMatch applies peak matching, noise filtering, gap-filling and annotation of related peaks. Pre-processed peak lists from mzMatch or MZmine can be directly imported into IDEOM as text or csv files. During data import, any number of samples can be assigned to (up to 30) study groups (e.g. blanks, controls and QCs) to improve data filtering, analysis and visualization. Sample consistency, according</note>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">results according to sample intensities, significance, pathways or other properties. Additional IDEOM tools include: merging dual-polarity data, chemical formula determination for unidentified masses, stable isotope tracking and targeted analysis. Full documentation, tutorials, source code and the IDEOM template are freely available at http://mzmatch.sourceforge.net/ideom.html. IDEOM provides a user-friendly interface for analysis of complex metabolomics datasets without the need for specialist bioinformatics skills, allowing for the rapid production of meaningful, interactive results for biological interpretation of untargeted metabolomics data sets.</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank Gavin Blackburn, Isabel Vincent and Anubhav Srivastava for testing and feedback. Example datasets were provided by the Scottish Metabolomics Facility, funded by the Scottish Universities Life Sciences Alliance (SULSA).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bioinformatics tools for cancer metabolomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Blekherman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metabolomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="343" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Precision mapping of the metabolome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Breitling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Biotech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="543" to="548" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automated workflows for accurate mass-based putative metabolite identification in LC/MS-derived metabolomic datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Brown</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1108" to="1112" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards global metabolomics analysis with Liquid Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry: improved metabolite identification by retention time prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Creek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8703" to="8710" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Separating the wheat from the chaff: a prioritisation pipeline for the analysis of metabolomics datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Jankevics</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metabolomics [Epub ahead of print</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advances in structure elucidation of small molecules using mass spectrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Kind</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Fiehn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioanal. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemometrics in metabolomics—a review in human disease diagnosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Madsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">659</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolomics technologies and metabolite identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Moco</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Analyt. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="855" to="866" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational mass spectrometry for metabolomics: identification of metabolites and small molecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Neumann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Böcker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Bioanal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">398</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2779" to="2788" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MZmine 2: modular framework for processing, visualizing, and analyzing mass spectrometry-based molecular profile data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Pluskal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">395</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">R: a language and environment for statistical computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Development</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Core</forename>
				<surname>Team</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">R Foundation for Statistical Computing. R Development Core Team</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Vienna, Austria</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simple data-reduction method for high-resolution LCMS data in metabolomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Scheltema</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioanalysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1551" to="1557" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PeakML/mzMatch: a File Format, Java Library, R Library, and Tool-Chain for mass spectrometry data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Scheltema</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2786" to="2793" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">XCMS: processing mass spectrometry data for metabolite profiling using nonlinear peak alignment, matching, and identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="779" to="787" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>