
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics iFoldRNA v2: folding RNA with constraints</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andrey</forename>
								<surname>Krokhotin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry &amp; Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<settlement>Chapel Hill</settlement>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kevin</forename>
								<surname>Houlihan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry &amp; Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<settlement>Chapel Hill</settlement>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nikolay</forename>
								<forename type="middle">V</forename>
								<surname>Dokholyan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry &amp; Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<settlement>Chapel Hill</settlement>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics iFoldRNA v2: folding RNA with constraints</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv221</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on January 2, 2015; revised on March 26, 2015; accepted on April 19, 2015</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>A key to understanding RNA function is to uncover its complex 3D structure. Experimental methods used for determining RNA 3D structures are technologically challenging and laborious, which makes the development of computational prediction methods of substantial interest. Previously, we developed the iFoldRNA server that allows accurate prediction of short (&lt;50 nt) tertiary RNA structures starting from primary sequences. Here, we present a new version of the iFoldRNA server that permits the prediction of tertiary structure of RNAs as long as a few hundred nucleotides. This substantial increase in the server capacity is achieved by utilization of experimental information such as base-pairing and hydroxyl-radical probing. We demonstrate a significant benefit provided by integration of experimental data and computational methods. Availability and implementation: http://ifoldrna.dokhlab.org Contact: dokh@unc.eu</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The iFoldRNA is a physical simulation-based automated RNA structure prediction webserver designed to predict 3D RNA structure based on available sequence data. The previous version of iFoldRNA allowed prediction of the structure of short RNA molecules (&lt;50 nt) within 4 A ˚ Root-Mean-Square deviation (RMSD) from corresponding experimental structures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Sharma et al., 2008</ref>). The limitation on RNA size is due to inaccuracies in the force-field and insufficient sampling. Increasing sequence size quickly becomes computationally prohibitive, since the RNA conformational space grows exponentially. We have previously shown that sampling conformational space can be drastically reduced by use of experimental constraints allowing us to correctly predict the tertiary structure of RNA up to a few hundred nucleotides long (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ding et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Gherghe et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Lavender et al., 2010</ref>). Here, we present a second version of iFoldRNA, which allows automated inclusion of two categories of constraints: base-pairing and nucleotide solvent accessibility. The source of base-pairing information can be generated either by sequence covariation analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gutell et al., 1992</ref>) or by using a number of chemical probing techniques. The SHAPE technique, in particular, has proven to be a quick and effective method for determining RNA secondary structure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Low et al., 2010</ref>). To infer solvent accessibility iFoldRNA v2 uses data from hydroxyl radical probing (HRP) experiments. In HRP, RNA in solution is treated with reagents that generate hydroxyl radicals, which cleave RNA strands. By identifying cleavage frequency for specific nucleotide bonds, solvent exposure can be determined. Incorporating these data as a burial force in simulations imposes long-range constraints on folded structures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ding et al., 2012</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>The prediction of RNA structure in iFoldRNA v2 is accomplished using a coarse-grained 3-bead RNA model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ding et al., 2008</ref>). Each bead in this model represents a phosphate, sugar or nucleobase. Simulations are performed using the Discrete Molecular Dynamics (DMD) simulation engine (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Dokholyan et al., 1998</ref>). Base-pairing information is implemented as an additional potential promoting tertiary contacts between corresponding nucleotides. An ensemble of RNA molecules at different temperatures that undergo replica exchange is used to enhance conformation sampling (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Sugita and Okamoto, 1999</ref>). Following DMD simulation, one hundred of the lowest energy structures are selected and clustered according to RMSD between pairs of selected structures. The centroids of the resulting clusters are retained for all-atom reconstruction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">HRP constraints</head><p>If HRP data are available, an additional force field, effectively biasing RNA towards the correct structure, is applied. The structures selected for clustering are also required to have high structurereactivity correlations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ding et al., 2012</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">All-atom reconstruction</head><p>Conversion to an all-atom representation is performed by replacing each 3-bead nucleotide by randomly selected rotamers of corresponding nucleotides in an all-atom representation. The initial allatom structure is run through a short DMD simulation to connect bonds and remove clashes. This simulation is performed with a high heat exchange coefficient, which allows for rapid dissipation of excess heat generated. A user is allowed to change the values of temperatures used to run replica exchange simulations and the number of DMD time steps. Simulations are performed on the Kure computational cluster at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, which consist of 122 blade servers, each with 8-cores 2.80 GHz processors running RHEL 5.6 operating system. The users are able to check the status of submissions through the server interface and are notified by email of job completion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>The iFoldRNA v2 webserver generates accurate predictions of RNA tertiary structure using DMD. Predicted structures are typically within 10–20 A ˚ RMSD from crystal structures for 200 nt RNA. The average processing time for an RNA of this size is $1 day. We demonstrate how the inclusion of constraints increases the performance of the server on the example of M-box riboswitch (161 nt). The structure of RNA of this size is challenging to predict de novo. Without constraints the quality of the predicted structure is poor. RMSD between the predicted and the crystal structures calculated through phosphate atoms is 32 A ˚. The interaction network fidelity (INF) is 0.363 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Parisien et al., 2009</ref>). The inclusion of the basepairing constraints improves the prediction (RMSD ¼ 25 A ˚ , INF ¼ 0.692). The resulting structure has correct base pairing while most of the higher order tertiary contacts are missing. The addition of HRP data significantly increases the quality of the prediction (RMSD ¼ 7.7 A ˚ , INF ¼ 0.725) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). We observe formation of the correct secondary and tertiary structures. Closer examination of the predicted structure using MC Annotate (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Gendron et al., 2001</ref>) reveals that it has 39 out of 46 canonical base pairs (AU or CG; Aadenine, U-uracil, C-cytosine, G-guanine) and 5 out of 6 noncanonical UG base pairs as compared with the crystal structure. As a benchmark we used two other servers RNAComposer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Popenda et al., 2012</ref>) and 3dRNA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Zhao et al., 2012</ref>). The structure predicted by RNAComposer (RMSD ¼ 25.8 A ˚ , INF ¼ 0.792) has correct base pairing; however, most of the higher order tertiary contacts are missing. The structure predicted by 3dRNA (RMSD ¼ 22.4 A ˚ , INF ¼ 0.621) only partially reproduces correct base pairing and does not recapitulate most of the higher order tertiary contacts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusions</head><p>The iFoldRNA v2 webserver offers a platform that combines experimental data and molecular dynamics simulations to predict tertiary structures of RNA as long as a few hundred nucleotides with atomic level detail. The comparison with other servers demonstrates the superior performance of iFoldRNA v2 for predicting the structure of long RNA molecules, provided HRP data is available. Currently, the server operates on two types of experimental constraints that include base-pairing information and reactivities derived from HRP experiments. However, there is growing number of approaches used to translate data from chemical probing experiments to constraints on RNA structure. For example, the recently proposed RING-MaP technique (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Homan et al., 2014</ref>) uses chemical probing, massive parallel sequencing and correlation analysis to find nucleotides located close in space. To keep pace with experimental innovations we plan to introduce a new interface that allows users to set up constraints between any two nucleotides of their choice. The iFoldRNA v2 webserver is freely accessible at http://iFoldRNA.dokhlab.org for academic and non-profit users.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The structure of M-box riboswitch predicted by iFoldRNA v2 (sand color) is superimposed on the top of the crystal structure (PDB ID: 3pdr) (blue). RMSD between the predicted and the crystal structures is 7.7 A ˚. Pvalue, showing statistical significance of the prediction (Hajdin et al., 2010), is less than 10 À6. RMSD was calculated using phosphate atoms only. INF ¼ 0.725 (Parisien et al., 2009). Experimental HRP data and base-pairing information were used (Ding et al., 2012) (Color version of this figure is available at Bioinformatics online.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 2891 Bioinformatics, 31(17), 2015, 2891–2893 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv221 Advance Access Publication Date: 24 April 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">A.Krokhotin et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank the University of North Carolina IT Services for providing hardware support.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health Grant GM064803 (PI: Kevin M. Weeks).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ab initio RNA folding by discrete molecular dynamics: from structure prediction to folding mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Ding</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RNA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1164" to="1173" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-dimensional RNA structure refinement by hydroxyl radical probing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Ding</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="603" to="608" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discrete molecular dynamics studies of the folding of a protein-like model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Dokholyan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fold. Des</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="577" to="587" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the significance of an RNA tertiary structure prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Hajdin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RNA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1340" to="1349" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single-molecule correlated chemical probing of RNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Homan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U.S.A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13858" to="13863" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative analysis of nucleic acid threedimensional structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Gendron</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">308</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="919" to="936" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Native-like RNA tertiary structures using a sequence-encoded cleavage agent and refinement by discrete molecular dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Gherghe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2541" to="2546" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying constraints on the higher-order structure of RNA: continued development and application of comparative sequence analysis methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Gutell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5785" to="5795" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust and generic RNA modeling using inferred constraints: a structure for the hepatitis C virus IRES pseudoknot domain</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Lavender</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4931" to="4933" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SHAPE-directed RNA secondary structure prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Low</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New metrics for comparing and assessing discrepancies between RNA 3D structures and models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Parisien</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RNA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1875" to="1885" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automated 3D structure composition for large RNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Popenda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">iFoldRNA: three-dimensional RNA structure prediction and folding</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Sharma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1951" to="1952" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Replica-exchange molecular dynamics method for protein folding</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Sugita</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Okamoto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">314</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automated and fast building of three-dimensional RNA structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Zhao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>