
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:38+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics In silico analysis of phytoene synthase and its promoter reveals hints for regulation mechanisms of carotenogenesis in Duanliella bardawil</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yong-Min</forename>
								<surname>Lao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Food and Bioengineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">South China University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510640</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lan</forename>
								<surname>Xiao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Food and Bioengineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">South China University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510640</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zhi-Wei</forename>
								<surname>Ye</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Food and Bioengineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">South China University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510640</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jian-Guo</forename>
								<surname>Jiang</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>jgjiang@scut.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Food and Bioengineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">South China University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510640</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Shi-Shui</forename>
								<surname>Zhou</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Biological Science &amp; Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">South China University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510006</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics In silico analysis of phytoene synthase and its promoter reveals hints for regulation mechanisms of carotenogenesis in Duanliella bardawil</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2201" to="2208"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr371</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 12, 2011; revised on June 2, 2011; accepted on</note>
					<note>[12:24 22/7/2011 Bioinformatics-btr371.tex] Page: 2201 2201–2208 Advance access publication: June 27, 2011 Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Contact: * To whom correspondence should be addressed.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Previous researches showed that phytoene synthase (Psy) from Dunaliella bardawil is the first regulatory point in carotenogenesis. We hypothesize certain interactions between the environmental stress factors and the regulatory sequences of Psy in D.bardawil (DbPsy). Consequently, LA PCR-based genomic walking approach was performed for isolation of psy promoter and terminator, respectively. The obtained nucleic acid sequences and the corresponding protein structure of DbPsy were analyzed and predicted using various bioinformatics tools. Finally, we presented some hints for the regulation mechanisms of DbPsy at the molecular level according to the computed results. Results: LA PCR-based genomic walking results showed that the isolated sequences are the promoter and terminator of psy, correspondingly. Computational analysis demonstrated several candidate motifs of the promoter exhibiting hypothetic UV-B-, norglurzon-and salt-induced characteristics, as well as some typical domains universally discovered in promoter sequences, such as TATA-box, CCAAT-box and GATA-box, etc. Furthermore, the structure of Psy was also predicted and aligned along with many counterparts at the protein level. Low homology of N-terminus was found in D.bardawil, while a relatively conserved C-terminus was predicted to be involved in the catalytic activity and substrate recognization/binding. Phylogenic analysis classified the DbPsy into a cluster with other algae. These results implied that Psy may share similar regulation mechanisms among algae with respect to their C-termini; while the diversity in N-terminus among Psys, along with the predicted inducible motifs in psy promoter from D.bardawil, may confer the fine tuning differences between D.bardawil and other algae. Conclusion: By means of computer techniques, we found in D.barawali that two interesting conserved motifs of psy promoter may involve in UV-B, norglurzon and salt regulation correspondingly; and that the diversity of Psy protein mainly lies in the N-termini among algae. These results indicate some hints for regulation mechanisms of carotenogenesis in D.bradawil.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Carotenoids are a wide family of polyene pigments synthesized by all plants, various algae and certain species of bacteria, fungi and archaea (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Goodwin, 1980</ref>). In photosynthetic organisms, carotenoids carry out several essential functions, i.e. participating in photosynthesis to protect the photosynthetic apparatus from potential oxidative damage besides light harvesting (Demmig<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Adams and Adams, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Siefermann-Harms, 1987</ref>). Animals cannot synthesize carotenoids but may obtain them through derivative pigmentation from diet (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Olson, 1994</ref>). Some carotenoids have vitamin A activity in humans; therefore, they are classified as essential nutrients (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Farré et al., 2010</ref>). Many researches show the prevention and treatment properties of carotenoids against several kinds of diseases, such as certain chronic disease (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Landrum and Bone, 2001</ref>), cardiovascular disease (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Shaish et al., 2006</ref>) as well as certain cancers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Michaud et al., 2000</ref>). These promoting properties of carotenoid have attracted intensive interesting in carotenoid biosynthesis and its commercial exploitation. So far, at least 700 carotenoids have been characterized from nature carotenoid biosynthetic pathways involving in C30 and C40 isoprenoids (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Feltl et al., 2005</ref>). In recent years, Dunaliella bardawil has received intensive attention as a natural rich source of β-carotene, owing to its capability to accumulate massive amount of β-carotene under stress conditions such as high light density, high salt concentration and nutrient starvation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Ben-Amotz et al., 1982</ref>). Many studies on accumulation of β-carotene and phytoene have been conducted to date (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ben-Amotz et al., 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">León et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mogedas et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Muthukannan et al., 2010</ref>). For large production of β-carotene, the optimal conditions should be high UV-A intensity, slightly alkaline pH, low NaCl concentration and moderate NaNO 3 concentration (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mogedas et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Muthukannan et al., 2010</ref>); while UV-B and other photobleaching compounds could elevate phytoene production, instead of β-carotene (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ben-Amotz et al., 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">León et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">White and Jahnke, 2002</ref>). Nevertheless, these investigations were primarily focused on culture condition optimization at physiologic and biochemical level, none of them probed into the molecular mechanisms for carotenogenic regulation in D.bardawil. The hypothetic biosynthetic pathway of carotenoid in Dunaliella is disproportional to synthesize various carotenoids such as β-carotene, neoxanthin, lutein and so on (<ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Ye et al., 2008</ref>). The most universal carotenoid biosynthetic pathway is the successional</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Y.-M.Lao et al.</head><p>reactions leading to the formation of β-carotene. The first committed step is a head-to-head condensation of two geranylgeranyl diphosphate (GGPP) molecules to produce phytoene by phytoene synthase (Psy) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Salvini et al., 2005</ref>). Subsequently, phytoene is converted to lycopene through four desaturation reactions, and β-carotene is finally formed by two cyclization steps. Enzymes involved are membrane-associated or integrated into membranes, and Psy is considered to be the first rate-determining point to control the carbon resource flux toward carotenoid synthesis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Shewmarker et al., 1999</ref>). At present, many Psy cDNAs have been isolated to investigate the regulation mechanisms controlling carotenoid biosynthesis in plants and microalgae (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Salvini et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Yan et al., 2005</ref>); however, most of them remain confined to molecular cloning and expression analysis. In D.bardawil, Psy is even merely cloned and sequenced (GenBank: EU328287.1). We hypothesize certain interactions between the environmental stress factors and the regulatory sequences of Psy in D.bardawil (DbPsy), more specifically, the conserved motifs encompassing the psy gene and the resulting diversity of protein structure caused by the variation of amino acid sequence in comparison to other species. Therefore, we isolated and cloned the promoter and terminator of psy, and then analyzed the obtained nucleic acid sequences and predicted the corresponding protein structure of DbPsy using various bioinformatics tools. Finally, we presented some hints for the regulation mechanisms of DbPsy at the molecular level according to the computed results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Strains and culture conditions</head><p>Dunaliella bardawil cells, obtained from the Institute of Hydrobiology, Chinese Academy of Science, were grown in defined medium (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Sheffer and Avron, 1986</ref>) containing 2 mol/l NaCl at 26 @BULLET C under a 14/10 h dark/light cycle, and were collected at the log phase or late log phase. Escherichia coli TOP10 was used as the host for the multiplication of plasmids.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Known sequence verification</head><p>For validation of the psy sequence deposited at NCBI (GenBank: EU328288.1), two pairs of overlapping primers (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>) were designed according to the Psy mRNA sequence (GenBank: EU328287.1). Total RNA was extracted from 6 ml of D.bardawil cells grown at the late log phase using E.Z.N.A. Total RNA Kit II (OMEGA) following conditions recommended by the manufacturer. First strand cDNA was synthesized with Oligo dT-Adaptor Primer in a total volume of 10 µl, and subsequent PCR amplification of two cDNA fragments, with two pairs of specific primes (Dbpsy-F and Dbpsy-inR; Dbpsy-inF and Dbpsy-R), respectively, was fulfilled using an RNA PCR Kit (AMV) ver. 3.0 (TaKaRa) according to the manufacturer's protocol. The PCR procedure to amplify the Psy cDNA fragments is as follows: 95 @BULLET C, 5 min; 35 cycles of 94 @BULLET C, 45 s; 60 @BULLET C, 45 s; and 72 @BULLET C, 1 min. The amplified fragments were cloned to pMD 19-T vector (TaKaRa) and sequenced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Genomic walking for isolation of psy promoter and terminator</head><p>Based on the sequences of the psy gene of D.bardawil (GenBank: EU EU328288.1), three gene-specific primers for cloning of psy promoter, pSP1, pSP2 and pSP3, were designed (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). Likewise, the primers for isolation of psy terminator, tSP1, tSP2 and tSP3, are also shown in(TaKaRa), LA PCR-based genomic walking was performed to obtain the psy promoter and terminator, respectively. The primary nested PCR products were diluted to 1:100 with distilled water for subsequent nested PCR reactions; all manipulations were corresponding with the manufacturer's protocol. Validation of putative psy promoter and terminator were performed using primers Ptest For (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>) and pSP3 or primers tSP3 and Ttest Rev (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>), respectively. Sequence analysis was performed using Blast Software (http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/), promoter predictions software PlantPAN (http://plantpan.mbc.nctu.edu.tw/), CorePromoter program (http://rulai.cshl.org/tools/genefinder/CPROMOTER/) for transcriptional start site (TSS) search and terminator scan program Poly (A) Signal Miner (http://dnafsminer.bic.nus.edu.sg/) and RibEx (http://132.248.32.45/cgi-bin/ribex.cgi).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Bioinformatics analysis and phylogenetic construction</head><p>Psy splicing pattern was predicted through NCBI Splign (http://www .ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sutils/splign/splign.cgi?textpage=online&amp;level=form) and GENSCAN (http://mobyle.pasteur.fr/cgi-bin/portal.py?form=genscan). Component analysis of psy was calculated using DNAStar software 7.1.0. Physical and chemical characteristics of DbPsy were analyzed by ProtParam tool (http://expasy.org/tools/protparam.html). Subcellular localization presumption was performed using WoLF PSORT (http://wolfpsort.org/). Conserved domains in DbPsy were detected using the Conserved Domains Search tool (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/cdd/wrpsb.cgi). Secondary structure was predicted via the PSIPRED server (http://bioinf .cs.ucl.ac.uk/psipred/); 3D structure was constructed using 3D-JIGSAW (http://bmm.cancerresearchuk.org/∼3djigsaw/). Multiple alignments among similar enzymes were conducted using Clustal X 1.83. Phylogenetic and molecular evolutionary analysis of the amino acid sequences of different Psys were conducted using the Neighbor Joining method and the molecular evolution genetics analysis (MEGA) software, version 4.0.2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Isolation and sequence analysis of the full-length DbPsy cDNA</head><p>The Psy template deposited at NCBI comes from direct submission without any support of report hitherto, which necessitates the validation work before genomic walking. To this end, RT–PCR Page: 2203 2201–2208Promoter isolation by LA PCRbased genome walking. Three fragments were obtained and sequenced; the shortest one with 689 bp nucleotides did not have any homology with the upstream of psy, while the 3763 bp fragement was supposed probably to be the 5-UTR of psy. M, DL5000 DNA marker; land 1–3, products of 1st nested PCR, 2nd nested PCR and 3rd nested PCR, correspondingly. (c) Isolated fragment assumed to be the terminator of psy. The brightest fragment of 1100 bp recovered, with an 184 bp region identical to the downstream of psy, was inferred to be the psy terminator. M, DL2000 DNA marker; lane 1–3, products of 1st nested PCR, 2nd nested PCR and 3rd nested PCR, respectively; M, 500 bp DNA marker. (d) Validation of hypothetic psy promoter and terminator using testing primers Ptest For and Test Rev with pSP3 and tSP3, respectively. Two segments, length in 3458 bp and 1099 bp, respectively, corresponding to psy promoter and terminator, were obtained. was performed and two cDNA fragments, 555 bp and 741 bp in length respectively, were obtained with overlapping primers DbpsyF/inR and Dbpsy-inF/R, correspondingly (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1a</ref>). Sequencing and sequence assembly results fed back a complete full-length cDNA of DbPsy (GenBank: EU328287.1, 1275 bp in length), which validates the psy gene deposited at NCBI (GenBank: EU328288.1) indirectly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Regulation mechanisms of carotenogenesis in Duanliella bardawil</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Isolation of the promoter and terminator of DbPsy</head><p>Three candidate promoter fragments of the third nested PCR were purified and sequenced (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1b</ref>). Sequence analysis by BlastN found that both the 3763 bp and 2975 bp fragments possess identical regions (130 bp in length) as expected with the 5-end of psy. Comparison of the sequences showed that the 3763 bp fragment is the extension of the shorter one. Likewise, a putative terminator fragment shares 184 bp identical nucleotides with the 3-end of psy as intended (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1c</ref>). The AGE and sequencing results further validate the hypothetic promoter and terminator (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1d</ref>). These results suggested that the obtained sequences are the upstream and downstream UTR of psy, correspondingly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Computational analysis of promoter and terminator of DbPsy</head><p>BlastN search found that the obtained sequences have great homology with the 5-and 3-end of psy gene, respectively. CorePromoter detection suggested that the TSS, 'A' marked in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2a</ref>, locates at 370 nt upstream of the initiator codon ATG. Five species (Arabidopsis, Maize, Rice, Tomato and other) were selected when conducting transcriptional factor binding sites search at PlantPAN server (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Chang et al., 2008</ref>). The retrieval results showed that the isolated promoter possesses many conserved motifs of plant (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2a</ref>), e.g. GATA box at position +149, CCAAT boxes widely found in eukaryotic genes, CGCG boxes with conserved<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Zhu et al., 2002)</ref>; (2) C8GARGAT, a A/T-rich binding site for plant MADS-domain protein AGL15 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Tang and Perry, 2003</ref>); (3) BOXLCOREDCPAL, box-L-like sequences with consensus ACCTTCC core sequences for a transcriptional activator DCMYB1 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Maeda et al., 2005</ref>); (4) GT-1GMSCAM4, GT-1 motif found in the promoter of soybean SCaM-4, whose expression is induced by pathogen and salt through GT-1 like factor (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Park et al., 2004</ref>); (5) BOXIIPCCHS, Box II/G box found in the parsley chs genes, essential for light regulation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Block et al., 1990</ref>); (6) ASF1MOTIFCAMV, TGACG motif for the basic domain/leucine zipper transcription factor TGA1, may be relevant to light regulation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Després et al., 2003</ref>). (b) Psy gene consists of six exons separated by five introns franked by canonical GT donor site and AG acceptor site. (c) Though no poly (A) signal was detected, we predicted a reverse translation attenuator inside the last intron. sequences GCGCGC and ACGCGC at position −344 and +121 correspondingly. In addition, some regulatory elements were also found, such as AFRAT involving in IAA regulation with consensus sequence TGTCTC at position +341 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Goda et al., 2004</ref>), the light-regulated elements G box (position −28) and ASF-1 binding site (position +102), etc. Interestingly, two remarkable motifs were also found in the promoter: box-L-like core sequences (position −491, also named BOXLCOREDCPAL in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2a</ref>) and GT-1 motifs (position −85 and −2606). Previous researches has implied a valuable application of UV irradiation for accumulating carotenoids (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mogedas et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Salguero et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">White and Jahnke, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Xue et al., 2005</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">). Maeda et al. (2005</ref>showed that BOXLCOREDCPAL involved in UV-B irradiation regulation in Daucus carota, therefore, such motif in D.bardawil might function in a similar way. The GT-1 box (also called GT1GMSCAM4,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2a</ref>) might contribute to pathogen-and NaCl-induced expression of the promoter (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Park et al., 2004</ref>). Both the Signal Miner and RibEx programs (Abreu-Goodger and<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Merino, 2005</ref>) failed to detect any canonical poly (A) signal in the hypothetic terminator. While a reverse translation attenuator inside the last intron of psy was identified by RibEx at 322 bp upstream of the TAA terminator codon, as is shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2c</ref>. Such disappointing results prompted us to clone and analyze psy terminator sequence again, resulting in the same outcome (data not shown). These results suggest that we may fail to isolate the genuine terminator of psy in D.bardawil, or the psy terminator may possess no canonical poly (A) signal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Analysis of the genomic structure of psy</head><p>To further validate and elucidate the genomic structure of psy, NCBI Splign (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Kapustin et al., 2008</ref>) and GENSCAN (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Burge and Karlin, 1997</ref>) were performed. Both servers returned a consistent result that Page: 2204 2201–2208psy contains six exons separated by five introns (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2b</ref>). As shown in</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Y.-M.Lao et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Physical and chemical characteristics of DbPsy</head><p>The 424 amino acid peptide possesses a computed molecular weight of 48.30 kDa, a theoretical isoelectric point (pI) of 9.16, and exhibits an aliphatic index of 76.65. It contains 46 negatively charged residues (Asp + Glu) and 57 positively charged residues (Arg + Lys) with several hydrophilic and hydrophobic regions, as determined by ExPASy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Gasteiger et al., 2003</ref>). In addition, it is classified as an unstable protein with a considered methionine N-terminus. WoLF PSORT showed that DbPsy may be situated in the chloroplast (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Horton et al., 2007</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">Conserved domain and motifs in DbPsy</head><p>Through the NCBI Conserved Domain Search (Marchler<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Bauer et al., 2009</ref>), the deduced amino acid sequence was specifically hit by the trans-Isoprenyl Diphosphate Synthases (Trans_IPPS) which included squalene and phytoene synthases. The prediction showed that DbPsy can be classified into the superfamily of IPPS and Class I terpene cyclases. Six regions together forming Trans_IPPS were also predicted in DbPsy (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>): substrate binding pocket, Mg 2+ binding site, active site lid residues, catalytic residues and two aspartate-rich sites (171-DELVD-175, 297-DVGED-301). In rat, the catalytic site consists of a large central cavity formed by mostly antiparallel alpha helices with two aspartate-rich regions (DXXXD) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Gu et al., 1998</ref>). The catalytic residues involved in the reactions of forming squalene. However, unlike squalene synthase, Psy does not require NADPH for its activity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Gu et al., 1998</ref>). The two aspartate-rich motifs, along with Tyr and Phe rich in the rest conserved regions, may involve in condensation reactions in DbPsy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Tansey and Shechter, 2000</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.7">The advanced structures of DbPsy</head><p>The secondary structure prediction run at the PSIpred server (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">McGuffin et al., 2000</ref>) showed that the DbPsy consists of 72.64%<ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>). MEMSAT3 and MEMSAT-SVM program detected a transmembrane region between amino acids 250 and 265. The carboxy-terminus is possible in the cytoplasm; while the aminoterminus, followed by a 37 amino acid signal peptide, locates in the extracellular fluid (<ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>). Moreover, the tertiary structure of DbPsy was also constructed by 3D-JIGSAW (Contreras<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Moreira and Bates, 2002</ref>). The calculated result shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref>revealed that the single polypeptide chain model covers 322 residues from 103 to 424 amino acids, which is composed of 209 H-bonds, 20 helix elements and 32 turns. However, unlike the secondary structure retrieved from PSIPRE server, there is no strand element predicted using the 3D-JIGSAW server.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.8">Homologous alignment and phylogenetic analysis of DbPsy</head><p>The gene family alignment of amino acidic sequences obtained by ClustalX analysis revealed that the overall structure of theTrans_IPPS_HH domains has been conserved from bacteria to higher plant (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figs 3 and 6</ref>), though all of the homologs aligned varied considerably in their N-termini (data not shown). The functional conserved domain may cover from 132 to 424 amino acids. The BlastP search demonstrated that DbPsy shares the highest homology with D.salina at the protein level (79% identity and 87% similarity), 68% identity and 80% similarity with the Haematococcus pluvialis counterpart, 69% and 81% with the Chlammydomonas reinhardtii counterpart, 55% and 69% with the Arabidopsis thaliana counterpart. A lower homology of DbPsy was found with the prokaryote counterparts, with the exception of cyanobacterial Psys (40–42% identity). The phylogenetic tree was constructed using Neighbor Joining method by MEGA 4.0.2 software (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Tamura et al., 2007</ref>) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 7</ref>). Three defined clusters can be found: Clusters I, II and III. Cluster I contains Psys from higher plants, cluster II consists of the algae Psys and cluster III comprises the bacterial homologs. Such phylogenetic dendrogram showed similar patterns with BlastP search and DNA sequence alignment results (data not shown); which indicated that Psys isolated from green algae can be classified into one group (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 7</ref>). Accordingly, these results indicated an evolutionary relationship among green algae.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Regulation mechanisms of carotenogenesis in Duanliella bardawil</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Duanliella bardawil and D.salina</head><p>are recognized as the most promising natural sources to produce β-carotene in biotechnology commercial-production applications, due to their ability of massive accumulation of β-carotene under stress conditions, such as high</p><formula>1, XP_002271575.1, AAM45379.1, NP_001108117.1, ABU40771.1, ABA99494.1, NP_197225.1, ABB52068.1, CAC19567, NP_441168, NP_485873, NP_217974, YP_006040, P17056, NP_786525, AAL42564, NP_280449, NP_737251, CAA45350.</formula><p>light intensity and salinity, stress temperature, privative nutrients, etc. Plenty of studies have been performed to investigate the carotenoid biosynthesis pathway for the ultimate goal to produce as much β-carotene as possible (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mogedas et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Salguero et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Xue et al., 2005</ref>). Nevertheless, most of these researches mainly focused on culture conditions and extraction approaches, or other aspects except carotenogenic enzyme genes. So far, a small number of enzymes directly involving in carotenoid biosynthetic pathway have been studied in Dunaliella, especially in D.bardawil (<ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Yan et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Zhu et al., 2005</ref>). Psy is one of the few which were cloned in D.salina and D.bardawil. However, it has not yet been experienced deeply functional validation up to now in D.bardawil. The attempts to obtain psy regulatory elements from D.bardawil would facilitate interpretation of the regulation mechanisms for Psy expression and accumulation of β-carotene. Additionally, works on elaborating the Psy structure at the protein level would help further presentation of the differentiations of Psy regulation even the Page: 2206 2201–2208whole carotenoid metabolic pathway between species. We strongly speculate, based on previous intensive efforts (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ben-Amotz et al., 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">León et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">White and Jahnke, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Xue et al., 2005</ref>), that regulation of Psy and carotenogenesis is fulfilled at multiple levels from DNA structure to post-translational control. More specifically, the regulatory elements of psy gene and its protein structure may confer different regulation mechanisms in D.bardawil from other aglae. As shown previously, massive accumulation of β-carotene is triggered by environmental stress (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mogedas et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">White and Jahnke, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Ye et al., 2008</ref>), implying a regulatory expression pattern of many carotenogenic genes. Among these environmental stresses, UV interference executes different effects on β-carotene accumulation through photosynthetic responses (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mogedas et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">White and Jahnke, 2002</ref>). One of the protective mechanisms against UV-induced photosynthetic damage involves in massive accumulation of β-carotene in D.bardawil exposed to UV-A rather than UV-B, while D.salina lacks such ability (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">White and Jahnke, 2002</ref>). UV-B even executes contrasting effects on β-carotene biosynthesis: decreases β-carotene but enriches other carotenoids including phytoene. However, this UV-A-induced protection is lost in cells treated with the bleaching herbicide norflurazon (<ref type="bibr">BenAmotz et al., 1987</ref>). In such cells phytoene synthesis is enhanced significantly, with a decreased level of β-carotene, so that<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">León et al. (2005)</ref>applied this bleaching herbicide to product phytoene in D.bardawil. Our study found that the promoter of DbPsy possesses a conserved motif BOXLCOREDCPAL (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>) homologous with DcPAL1 counterpart in D. carota. Such motif participates in upregulation responses of DcPAL1 to UV-B irradiation in D. carota mediated by DcMYB1 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Maeda et al., 2005</ref>). These proofs suggest that, in accordance with the investigations discussed above (<ref type="bibr">BenAmotz et al., 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mogedas et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">White and Jahnke, 2002</ref>), DbPsy may be regulated by UV-B and norflurazon with respect to similar photobleaching effects to accumulate phytoene, rather than β-carotene, through its promoter region. We conclude that UV-B and norglurzon may induce photobleaching through the BOXLCOREDCPAL situated within the promoter of DbPsy. Moreover, a salt-and light-induced pattern of β-carotene should be concerned with certain regulatory domains in carotenogenic genes. Here, we found two GT-1-like boxes deposited inside the isolated promoter, which were widely discovered in many light-regulated genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Terzaghi and Cashmore, 1995</ref>). With respect to GT1CONSENSUS (GAAAAA, position −354), we speculate an intermediary role on interaction between TFIIA and GT-1-like factors in D.bardawil (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Terzaghi and Cashmore, 1995</ref>): TFIIA indirectly interacts with GT-1-like factors through GT1CONSENSUS to accumulate β-carotene induced by light. Another GT-1-like box (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3, GT1GMSCAM4</ref>) involves in NaClinduced up-regulated expression of SCaM-4 in Glycine max (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Park et al., 2004</ref>), consequently, GT1GMSCAM4 found in DbPsy promoter may fulfill similar function as its counterpart in Glycine max: up-regulates its host gene psy in order to enhance βcarotene synthesis by NaCl. Since both motifs up-regulate their corresponding genes in their own species, we suppose parallel effect in D.bardawil. Furthermore, as described above, the contrasting effects of UV-A and UV-B exclusively in D.bardawil (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">White and Jahnke, 2002</ref>) suggest UV-B may also up-regulate the expression of Psy through these motifs. Such unique characteristics imply fine tuning of Psy (even the whole carotenogenesis) related to diversity of DNA-protein interactions between D.bardawil and other algae. Psy has been regarded as the first key enzyme to catalyze a head to head combination reaction, generating colorless phytoene in carotenoid biosynthesis. It is supposed to be the regulatory point controlling the flux of carbon source towards carotenoids (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Shewmarker et al., 1999</ref>). To further illuminate the regulation mechanisms of DbPsy, we performed a series of in silico analysis at the protein level. Advanced protein structure analysis manifests a relatively conserved C-terminus containing putative substrate binding and catalytic domains from around 100 to 400 amino acids. Phylogenetic analysis indicated that Psys isolated from algae occupy one cluster (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 7</ref>). These clues imply that they may share some similar regulation mechanisms distinctively with regard to the C-terminus of Psy in algae. Furthermore, alignments of the deduced amino acid sequence showed the sequence diversity Page: 2207 2201–2208</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Y.-M.Lao et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Regulation mechanisms of carotenogenesis in Duanliella bardawil</head><p>between species primarily in the N-terminus.<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Tran et al. (2009)</ref>suggested the N-terminal regions, unessential to the enzymatic function, uniquely account for the major differences of the two Psy classes found in some algae. Moreover, the N-terminal region of plant Psy is generally longer than bacterial enzymes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kim et al., 2003</ref>). This region is crucial for protein targeting and dimerization that are critical for enzyme stability and activity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Cunningham and Gantt, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Sun et al., 1996</ref>). The N-terminus diversity between D.bardawil and other algae may affect Psy turnover and catalytic activity in certain similar patterns. In addition, increased level of Psy does not directly correlate with increased carotenoids content (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kim et al., 2003</ref>); the N-terminal variety may render different capabilities between different Psy members of inter and intra species with regard to protein targeting, processing or assembly into a fully functional complex. As discussed above, we speculate the sequence differences of Psy at the protein and DNA levels may be responsible for the fine tuning differences between D.bardawil and D.salina, we also conducted alignments between these two algae, which returned similar diversity of N-terminus (or the 5-end of the Psy mRNA CDS) and conserved C-terminus (or the 3-end of the Psy mRNA CDS) (data not shown). Accordingly, we speculate that the fine tuning mechanisms of Psys between algae may lie in the variation of their N-terminus. Studies on the N-terminal diversity as well as other differential regions between species would be helpful to clarify the distinct regulation mechanisms for Psy in D.bardawil. An in-depth understanding of the regulation mechanisms of DbPsy still requires further intensive investigations on the promoter function involving in the putative motifs discussed above and other related conserved sequences. Moreover, the identification of psy promoter in D.salina and subsequent comparison with the one in D.bardawil will shed light on the fine tuning differences between the two algae at the DNA level. Besides, the protein structure is also a key point to aid the presentation of these mechanisms, especially its N-terminus. Such understanding would also contribute to bioengineering using DbPsy promoter to product foreign proteins.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>[12:24 22/7/2011 Bioinformatics-btr371.tex] Page: 2202 2201–2208</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Isolation of promoter and terminator of psy gene in D.bardawil. (a) Validation of psy template. M, 100 bp DNA marker; land 1 and 2, Psy cDNA fragments with 21 bp overlapped. (b) Promoter isolation by LA PCRbased genome walking. Three fragments were obtained and sequenced; the shortest one with 689 bp nucleotides did not have any homology with the upstream of psy, while the 3763 bp fragement was supposed probably to be the 5-UTR of psy. M, DL5000 DNA marker; land 1–3, products of 1st nested PCR, 2nd nested PCR and 3rd nested PCR, correspondingly. (c) Isolated fragment assumed to be the terminator of psy. The brightest fragment of 1100 bp recovered, with an 184 bp region identical to the downstream of psy, was inferred to be the psy terminator. M, DL2000 DNA marker; lane 1–3, products of 1st nested PCR, 2nd nested PCR and 3rd nested PCR, respectively; M, 500 bp DNA marker. (d) Validation of hypothetic psy promoter and terminator using testing primers Ptest For and Test Rev with pSP3 and tSP3, respectively. Two segments, length in 3458 bp and 1099 bp, respectively, corresponding to psy promoter and terminator, were obtained.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Structure of full-length genomic DNA of psy including promoter and terminator. (a) A 3633 bp length promoter was obtained and analyzed. Several conserved motifs in addition to a CpNpG Island were identified in the promoter: (1) TATABOXOSPAL, a typical box found in various species (Zhu et al., 2002); (2) C8GARGAT, a A/T-rich binding site for plant MADS-domain protein AGL15 (Tang and Perry, 2003); (3) BOXLCOREDCPAL, box-L-like sequences with consensus ACCTTCC core sequences for a transcriptional activator DCMYB1 (Maeda et al., 2005); (4) GT-1GMSCAM4, GT-1 motif found in the promoter of soybean SCaM-4, whose expression is induced by pathogen and salt through GT-1 like factor (Park et al., 2004); (5) BOXIIPCCHS, Box II/G box found in the parsley chs genes, essential for light regulation (Block et al., 1990); (6) ASF1MOTIFCAMV, TGACG motif for the basic domain/leucine zipper transcription factor TGA1, may be relevant to light regulation (Després et al., 2003). (b) Psy gene consists of six exons separated by five introns franked by canonical GT donor site and AG acceptor site. (c) Though no poly (A) signal was detected, we predicted a reverse translation attenuator inside the last intron.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Conserved domains in DbPsy detected by NCBI Conserved Domains Search. There is a conserved domain homologous with the trans-Isoprenyl Diphosphate Synthases in DbPsy from 132 to 407 amino acids, which consists of six motifs: substrate binding pocket, Mg 2+ binding site, active site lid residues, catalytic residues and two aspartate-rich sites.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Predicted secondary structure of DbPsy using the PSIPRED server. A transmembrane motif is revealed, along with a 37 amino acid signal peptide at the N-terminus extracellular (lower right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>[12:</head><figDesc>24 22/7/2011 Bioinformatics-btr371.tex] Page: 2205 2201–2208</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. The tertiary structure of DbPsy. Comparative modeling was performed using 3D-JIGSAW. The structure was presented as ribbons (the secondary structure elements) and wireframe using RasMol version 2.7.2.1 .1. The α-helix and β-turn regions of the putative protein were indicated with cylinders (red) and bands (blue), respectively. The two aspartate-rich motifs were colored by yellow, and the distinctive Asp residues (171, 175, 297 and 301) were labeled and highlighted as spacefill. The N-terminus and C-terminus were also shown.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig.6.</head><figDesc>Fig. 6. The hypothetic Trans_IPPS_HH domain found in DbPsy. Comparison of deduced amino acid sequence of DbPsy with its homologs indicated a functional conserved domain Trans_IPPS_HH, which lays in the C-terminus from 132 to 424 amino acids. The active site lid residues (141 aa to 145 aa) are marked with red line above; the highly conserved catalytic residue Try164 is marked with red asterisk; two aspartate-rich regions are boxed in blue. Gaps introduced to maximize sequence homology are indicated by dashes. Amino acid residues identical in all sequences are highlighted in white type on a black background; less conserved residues appear on a light gray background. Psys are shown as GenBank accession number: AAT46069.1, AAW28851.1, XP_002956783.1, XP_001701192.1, CAL54118.1, XP_002508518.1, XP_001775752.1, ABB29857.1, XP_002302132.1, XP_002442578.1, ABR16198.1, AAR86104.1, ADC34069.1, ACU17983.1, AAX19898.1, XP_002271575.1, AAM45379.1, NP_001108117.1, ABU40771.1, ABA99494.1, NP_197225.1, ABB52068.1, CAC19567, NP_441168, NP_485873, NP_217974, YP_006040, P17056, NP_786525, AAL42564, NP_280449, NP_737251, CAA45350.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig.7.</head><figDesc>Fig. 7. Phylogenetic relationship of the DbPsy to other Psys of various species. The Psys used for phylogenetic tree construction are as the amino acid sequences used for homology alignment above. Numbers below the branches are the Neighbor Joining bootstrap values. The evolutionary distance is reflected by the numbers above the branches and the branch lengths proportional to the degree of amino acid substitutions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: National Natural Foundation of China (grant 30870025). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1. Genomic DNA of D.bardawil was extracted following the method described by Yang et al. (2000). Using Genomic Walking Kit</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1.</figDesc><table>Primers used in this study (5 → 3 ) 

Procedure 
Primer 
Primer sequence 

PCR 
Dbpsy-F 
ATGGCACAGCGAACAGCAACTT 
CCTCCTCCTCCTCTCCTAGCATCA 
Dbpsy-inR 
GCCTGAGGCGTGATCTTTGA 
Dbpsy-inF 
GCATCAAAGATCACGCCTCAG 
Dbpsy-R 
TTATTTGTTCTTGGGCACCAAG 

Genomic 
walking 

pSP1 
CGAGGTAGAAGGTCTTGGCGTA 

pSP2 
GGCACTGACTGAGCGGTCTTTA 
pSP3 
CTGCTCTGCGACTACCATTCCT 
tSP1 
AATGCCCAAAGCAGAAGACAGG 
tSP2 
CACACTACCCTTGGTGATGTCTTG 
tSP3 
AGACTGGCTGCCGTTTCCTGAT 

Sequence 
validation 

Ptest For 
AACAATGCCACCAATACC 

Ttest Rev 
CGACGGATGACTGATTACGC 

Dbpsy-inR and Dbpsy-inF are overlapping primers. Complement sequences of the 
DbPsy cDNA are in bold and italic. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2. Components of psy gene in D.bardawil Start</figDesc><table>End 
Length (bp) 
GC content (%) 

Exon 
1 
1 
555 
555 
60.54 
2 
810 
1070 
261 
55.17 
3 
2090 
2245 
156 
56.41 
4 
2614 
2765 
152 
55.92 
5 
3150 
3300 
151 
49.67 
Total 
1275 
52.85 

Intron 
1 
556 
809 
254 
49.61 
2 
1071 
2089 
1019 
47.2 
3 
2246 
2613 
368 
53.8 
4 
2766 
3149 
384 
54.95 
Total 
2025 
50.33 
mRNA 
1 
1275 
1275 
47.15 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2,</figDesc><table>the GC content (%) of all six exons varies from 49.67% 
to 60.54%, whereas the GC content (%) of the five introns ranges 
from 47.2% to 54.95%. Although the introns of psy are flanked 
by conventional 5 splice donor GT and 3 splice acceptor AG, 
they appear to be lack of A + T-rich region, which characterizes a 
canonical intron. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RibEx: a web server for locating riboswitches and other conserved bacterial regulatory elements</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Abreu-Goodger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Merino</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acid Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="690" to="692" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Massive accumulation of phytoene induced by norflurazon in Dunaliella bardawil (Chlorophyceae) prevents recovery from photoinhibition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ben-Amotz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phycol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="176" to="181" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accumulation of b-carotene in halotolerant algae: purification and characterization of b-carotene-rich globules from Dunaliella bardawil (Chlorophyceae)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ben-Amotz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phycol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="537" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional borders, genetic fine structure, and distance requirements of cis elements mediating light responsiveness of the parsley chalcone synthase promoter</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Block</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5387" to="5391" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of complete gene structures in human genomic DNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Burge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Karlin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">268</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PlantPAN: Plant Promoter Analysis Navigator, for identifying combinatorial cis-regulatory elements with distance constraint in plant gene group</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Chang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="561" to="574" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Domain Fishing: a first step in protein comparative modelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Contreras-Moreira</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Bates</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1141" to="1142" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genes and enzymes of carotenoid biosynthesis in plants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">X</forename>
				<surname>Cunningham</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Jr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Gantt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Plant Physiol. Plant Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="557" to="583" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of xanthophyll cycle carotenoids in the protection of photosynthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Demmig-Adams</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Adams</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Plant Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Arabidopsis NPR1 disease resistance protein is a novel cofactor that confers redox regulation of DNA binding activity to the basic domain/leucine zipper transcription factor TGA1</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Després</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2181" to="2191" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Travel advice on the road to carotenoids in plants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Farré</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">179</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reliability of carotenoid analyses: a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Feltl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ExPASy: the proteomics server for in-depth protein knowledge and analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Gasteiger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acid Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3784" to="3788" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive comparison of auxin-regulated and brassinosteroid-regulated genes in Arabidopsis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Goda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Biochemistry of Carotenoids, vol. I, Plants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Goodwin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
			<publisher>Chapman &amp; Hall</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">98</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Function-structure studies and identification of three enzyme domains involved in the catalytic activity in rat hepatic squalene synthase</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Gu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">273</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12515" to="12525" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WoLF PSORT: protein localization predictor</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Horton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acid Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="585" to="587" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Splign: algorithms for computing spliced alignments with identification of paralogs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Kapustin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Direct</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expression and activity of citrus phytoene synthase and β-carotene hydroxylase in Escherichia coli</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="212" to="218" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lutein, zeaxanthin, and the macular pigment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Landrum</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Bone</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch. Biochem. Biophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">385</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Production of phytoene by herbicide-treated microalgae Dunaliella bardawil in two-phase systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>León</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnol. Bioeng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="695" to="701" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DcMYB1 acts as a transcriptional activator of the carrot phenylalanine ammonia-lyase gene (DcPAL1) in response to elicitor treatment, UV-B irradiation and the dilution effect</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Maeda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="739" to="752" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CDD: specific functional annotation with the Conserved Domain Database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Marchler-Bauer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acid Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The PSIPRED protein structure prediction server</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Mcguffin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="404" to="405" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intake of specific carotenoids and risk of lung cancer in 2 prospective US cohorts</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Michaud</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Clin. Nut</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="990" to="997" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beta-carotene production enhancement by UV-A radiation in Dunaliella bardawil cultivated in laboratory reactors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Mogedas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biosci. Bioeng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vitro evaluation of β-carotene production in two different strains of Dunaliella salina Teodoresco (Chlorophyta)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Muthukannan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biosci. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Needs and sources of carotenoids and vitamin</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Olson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nutr. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathogen-and NaCl-induced expression of the SCaM-4 promoter is mediated in part by a GT-1 box that interacts with a GT-1-like transcription factor</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Park</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2150" to="2161" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UV-A mediated induction of carotenoid accumulation in Dunaliella bardawil with retention of cell viability</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Salguero</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="506" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">cDNA cloning and expression of the phytoene synthase gene in sunflower</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Salvini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Plant Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">162</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="479" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">9-cis β-carotene-rich powder of the alga Dunaliella bardawil increases plasma HDL-cholesterol in fibrate-treated patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Shaish</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Atherosclerosis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">189</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="221" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isolation of the plasma-membrane of the halotolerant alga Dunaliella salina using sulfur hodamine B as a probe</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Sheffer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Avron</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">857</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="164" />
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Seed specific overexpression of phytoene synthase: increase in carotenoids and other metabolic effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Shewmarker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="412" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The light harvesting and protective functions of carotenoids in photosynthetic membranes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Siefermann-Harms</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiol. Plantarum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="561" to="568" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloning and functional analysis of the β-carotene hydroxylase of Arabidopsis thaliana</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Sun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">271</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24349" to="24352" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Tamura</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1596" to="1599" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Binding site selection for the plant MADS-domain protein AGL15: an in vitro and in vivo study</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Tang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Perry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">278</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28154" to="28159" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and regulation of mammalian squalene synthase</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Tansey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Shechter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1529" to="1578" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>btr371. .tex]</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2208" to="2201" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y.-M</forename>
				<surname>Lao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Light-regulated transcription</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Terzaghi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Cashmore</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Plant Physiol. Plant Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="474" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An update on carotenoid biosynthesis in algae: phylogenetic evidence for the existence of two classes of phytoene synthase</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Tran</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Planta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">229</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="723" to="729" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contrasting effects of UV-A and UV-B on photosynthesis and photoprotection of beta-carotene in two Dunaliella spp</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>White</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Jahnke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Cell Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="877" to="884" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of enhanced ultraviolet-B radiation on algae and cyanobacteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Xue</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Crit. Rev. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="89" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloning and sequence analysis of the phytoene synthase gene from a unicellular chlorophyte, Dunaliella sanlia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Yan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Agric. Food Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1466" to="1469" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Construction of a genomic DNA library of Dunaliella salina</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Phytophysiol. Sinica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biosynthesis and regulation of carotenoids in Dunaliella: progresses and prospects</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Ye</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotech Adv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="352" to="360" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rice TATA binding protein interacts functionally with transcription factor IIB and the RF2a bZIP transcriptional activator in an enhanced plant in vitro transcription system</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Zhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="795" to="803" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isolation and characterization of phytoene desaturase cDNA involved in the β-carotene biosynthetic pathway in Dunaliella salina</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Zhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Agric. Food Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5593" to="5597" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>