
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics Inclusion of dyad-repeat pattern improves topology prediction of transmembrane b-barrel proteins</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sikander</forename>
								<surname>Hayat</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New York City</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christoph</forename>
								<surname>Peters</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Stockholm Bioinformatics Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">E-Science Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stockholm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10691</postCode>
									<settlement>SciLifeLab, Swedish, Stockholm</settlement>
									<region>SE</region>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nanjiang</forename>
								<surname>Shu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Stockholm Bioinformatics Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">E-Science Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stockholm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10691</postCode>
									<settlement>SciLifeLab, Swedish, Stockholm</settlement>
									<region>SE</region>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Sweden Bioinformatics Infrastructure for Life Sciences (BILS)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stockholm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Konstantinos</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Tsirigos</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Stockholm Bioinformatics Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">E-Science Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stockholm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10691</postCode>
									<settlement>SciLifeLab, Swedish, Stockholm</settlement>
									<region>SE</region>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Arne</forename>
								<surname>Elofsson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Stockholm Bioinformatics Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">E-Science Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stockholm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10691</postCode>
									<settlement>SciLifeLab, Swedish, Stockholm</settlement>
									<region>SE</region>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics Inclusion of dyad-repeat pattern improves topology prediction of transmembrane b-barrel proteins</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw025</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on 1 July 2015; revised on 14 November 2015; accepted on 14 January 2016</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Burkhard Rost is available at http://boctopus.bioinfo.se/ Contact: arne@bioinfo.se Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Accurate topology prediction of transmembrane b-barrels is still an open question. Here, we present BOCTOPUS2, an improved topology prediction method for transmembrane b-barrels that can also identify the barrel domain, predict the topology and identify the orientation of residues in transmembrane b-strands. The major novelty of BOCTOPUS2 is the use of the dyad-repeat pattern of lipid and pore facing residues observed in transmembrane b-barrels. In a cross-validation test on a benchmark set of 42 proteins, BOCTOPUS2 predicts the correct topology in 69% of the proteins, an improvement of more than 10% over the best earlier method (BOCTOPUS) and in addition, it produces significantly fewer erroneous predictions on non-transmembrane b-barrel proteins. Availability and implementation: BOCTOPUS2 webserver along with full dataset and source code</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Transmembrane b-barrels (TMBs) are located in the outer membranes of bacteria, chloroplasts and mitochondria and are involved in transport of substrates across the cell membrane. Also, they are key components of translocation complexes. Bacterial TMBs consist of an even number of anti-parallel b-strands that are surrounded by long outer-loops and short inner-loops. Eukaryotic TMBs can have an odd number of strands. The residues located in transmembrane b-strands follow a dyad-repeat pattern, where alternating residues face the lipids and the pore region (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Wimley, 2003</ref>), respectively. BOCTOPUS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hayat and Elofsson, 2012</ref>), a previously published two-stage TMB topology predictor, did not predict the lipid/pore-facing orientation of residues in the transmembrane b-strands but BOCTOPUS2 does. The use of this information improves topology predictions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>Forty-two TMB sequences, culled at 20% sequence identity using the PISCES server (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Wang and Dunbrack, 2005</ref>) are divided into 10 subsets for cross-validation (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>). To ensure that no homology information is used, all proteins from the same super-family are put into the same cross-validation group. Membrane boundaries, 3D structures and super-family classification are obtained from the OPM database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Lomize et al., 2006</ref>). Residues in the transmembrane strands are labelled as pore or lipid-facing based on their sidechain orientation relative to the barrel center. In addition, a dataset (also reduced to 20% sequence identity) consisting of 370 (28 eukaryotic and 342 prokaryotic) known TMBs and 7558 non-TMBs that contain a signal peptide was downloaded from Uniprot (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Consortium et al., 2015</ref>). V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com BOCTOPUS2 consists of three layers (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>): First, the preferences and the class-probability for each residue to be in each state (i.e. outer-loop (o), inner-loop (i), pore-facing (p) or lipid-facing (l) b-strand region) are predicted using a Support Vector Machine (SVM). Secondly a filter is applied to detect the barrel region. These class-probabilities are used to create a (L Â 4) protein profile, where L is the number of residues in the input protein sequence. We then apply a filter to estimate the barrel region. In this step, we use the sum of values for the in-facing and out-facing classes over a window of 100 residues centered at the residue in question to predict the barrel region. The region where this sum is !0.3 is considered the barrel region. Residues outside this region are considered to be in the nonbarrel region and all lipid-facing (l) and pore-facing (p) probability values in that region are set to 0 and all inner-loop (i) values are set to 1, so as to suppress a false transmembrane beta-strand prediction. In the final step, the updated protein profile obtained after applying the filter is used as the input to a Hidden Markov-like Model to predict the final global topology. The advantage of this architecture is twofold; the SVM can use a window of residues to estimate the localization of a single residue, and the Hidden Markov Model does not require training as all transition probabilities can be set to 1. This is in contrast to BOCTOPUS where parameters had to be optimized. For each protein, a multiple sequence alignment is generated using 4 iterations of HHblits against Uniprot20 database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Remmert et al., 2011</ref>). Sequences with more than 60% gaps are filtered out. A position specific substitution matrix (PSSM) is then generated using blastpgp (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Altschul et al., 1997</ref>) and used as input to the next step. Optimal results were obtained using window sizes of 9, 13, 23 and 31 residues for predicting lipid-facing, pore-facing, inner and outer loops, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Filter for detecting non-TMB regions</head><p>Some TMBs contain long non-barrel regions and sporadic strand predictions can occur in these proteins causing errors in topology predictions. Earlier methods have often been trained on PDB sequences that exclude these regions making these methods less suitable for large-scale predictions. Here, we use the observation that b-strands incorrectly predicted in the non-barrel region are distantly separated from each other. A running average of the l and p probabilities (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>) over a window size of 100 is summed and an empirical threshold value of !0.3 is used to identify the transmembrane barrel region.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">HMM-architecture</head><p>The HMM consists of states for inner-and outer-loops, and lipidand pore-facing membrane strand residues. The architecture initially used in BOCTOPUS is simplified to reduce the number of parameters (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). The number of residues in a b-strand can be either 9 or 11. HMM parameters are independent of the dataset as all transition and emission probabilities in a given state are set to 1. The Viterbi algorithm is subsequently used to find the optimal topology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>BOCTOPUS2 predicts the correct topology for 29 proteins out of 42 (69%) proteins (<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>). This is better than other methods and, in addition, the performances of all earlier methods are possibly overestimated as some of the 42 proteins have been used in their training sets (Supplementary Information). One main reason for the improved results is that the filter in BOCTOPUS2 avoids incorrect prediction of strands in the non-barrel region. This filter also aids discrimination between TMBs and non-TMBs. In a dataset of 7558 non-TMBs and 370 TMBs BOCTOPUS2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Freeman and Wimley, 2010</ref>) predicts three or more strands in 81% of the TMBs at a specificity of 98.9% (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S2</ref>). Amongst the methods tested here, only HHomp (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Remmert et al., 2009</ref>) and BETAWARE have a higher Mathews correlation coefficient (MCC) for barrel/ non-barrel discrimination (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S2</ref>). The detection of eukaryotic TMBs seems to be more difficult as BOCTOPUS2 only detects 10 out of 28, possibly due to different evolutionary origins (Supplementary Table S2).Comparison of topology prediction methods. Topology-Number of proteins with the correct topology. TM – Number of proteins with correct number of predicted strands. SOV is the segment overlap (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Rost et al., 1994</ref>), Q2 is the two-state (membrane/not-membrane) prediction accuracy and Q3 is the three-state (membrane, inner-loop, outer-loop) prediction accuracy. Q4, the four state (lipid-facing, pore-facing, inner-loop, outer-loop) accuracy for BOCTOPUS2 is 89. BOCTOPUS2 results are cross-validated while all other methods have included some of the 42 proteins in their training set. The two last columns TPR and FPR describe the true and false positive rate in the discrimination dataset. BOCTOPUS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hayat and Elofsson, 2012</ref>), profTMB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bigelow and Rost, 2006</ref>), PRED-TMBB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bagos et al., 2004</ref>), BETAWARE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Savojardo et al., 2013</ref>), HHomp (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Remmert et al., 2009</ref>) and F-W b-barrel Analyzer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Freeman and Wimley, 2010</ref>) results were obtained using standalone versions. We present BOCTOPUS2, an improved topology predictor for TMBs that exploits the dyad-repeat feature of bacterial TMBs to identify transmembrane b-strands. BOCTOPUS2 can also identify the transmembrane barrel domain in long sequences and predict the correct topology in $69% proteins in our dataset. Further, BOCTOPUS2 predicts the lipid-facing or pore-facing status of residues in identified b-strands. We have recently shown that accurate topology and residue-orientation prediction is beneficial for 3D modelling of TMBs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hayat et al., 2015</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. BOCTOPUS2 pipeline – HHblits is used to obtain a position specific scoring matrix (PSSM), 4 SVMs are used to predict the location of each residue. A per-residue profile is constructed by combining the output probabilities of SVMs. Then a filter is applied to detect the likely transmembrane b-barrel region. The resulting per-residue profile is used as an input to a Hidden Markov Model to predict the topology</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>This work was supported by grants from the Swedish Research Council (VRNT 2012-5046), SSF and Vinnova through the Vinnova-JSP program. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Topology prediction and discrimination accuracy comparison</figDesc><table>Topology prediction 
Discrimination 

Method 
Topology TM Q2 Q3 SOV TPR 
FPR 

BOCTOPUS2 
29 
35 91 89 94 
81.4 
1.1 
BOCTOPUS 
24 
29 92 85 87 
88.7 
11.5 
profTMB 
20 
20 86 – 64 
82.9 
11.2 
PRED-TMBB 
11 
16 83 76 71 
66.1 
10.9 
BETAWARE 
7 
18 82 74 75 
89.9 
0.7 
HHomp 
– 
– 
– – – 
84.7 
0.2 
BOMP 
– 
– 
– – – 
71.9 
5.2 
F–W b-barrel Analyzer – 
– 
– – – 
88.2 
16.6 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">Bioinformatics, 32(10), 2016, 1571–1573 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw025 Advance Access Publication Date: 21 January 2016 Applications Note at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">S.Hayat et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gapped blast and psi-blast: a new generation of protein database search programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3389" to="3402" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PRED-TMBB: a web server for predicting the topology of {beta}-barrel outer membrane proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Bagos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">400</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PROFtmb: a web server for predicting bacterial transmembrane beta barrel proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Bigelow</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Rost</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">186</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uniprot: a hub for protein information</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<surname>Consortium</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">204</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A highly accurate statistical approach for the prediction of transmembrane b-barrels</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Freeman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Wimley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1965" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Boctopus: improved topology prediction of transmembrane b barrel proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hayat</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Elofsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="516" to="522" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">All-atom 3d structure prediction of transmembrane b-barrel proteins from sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hayat</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5413" to="5418" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OPM: orientations of proteins in membranes database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Lomize</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="623" to="625" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HHomp-prediction and classification of outer membrane proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Remmert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">446</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hhblits: lightning-fast iterative protein sequence searching by hmm-hmm alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Remmert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Redefining the goals of protein secondary structure prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Rost</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">235</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Betaware: a machine-learning tool to detect and predict transmembrane beta barrel proteins in prokaryotes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Savojardo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">728</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pisces: recent improvements to a pdb sequence culling server</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Dunbrack</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="94" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The versatile b-barrel membrane protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Wimley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="404" to="411" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>