
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:45+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression Individual-level analysis of differential expression of genes and pathways for personalized medicine</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hongwei</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Qiang</forename>
								<surname>Sun</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Genomics Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150086</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wenyuan</forename>
								<surname>Zhao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lishuang</forename>
								<surname>Qi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yunyan</forename>
								<surname>Gu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pengfei</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mengmeng</forename>
								<surname>Zhang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yang</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Shu-Lin</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Genomics Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150086</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Microbiology and Infectious Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Calgary</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>T2N 4N1</postCode>
									<settlement>Calgary</settlement>
									<region>AB</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zheng</forename>
								<surname>Guo</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>guoz@ems.hrbmu.edu.cn or slliu@ucalgary.ca</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Bioinformatics Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Bioinformatics Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Basic Medical College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Fujian Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>350004</postCode>
									<settlement>Fuzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression Individual-level analysis of differential expression of genes and pathways for personalized medicine</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="68"/>
							<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu522</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 20, 2014; revised on July 2, 2014; accepted on July 28, 2014</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Ziv Bar-Joseph Availability and Implementation: RankComp is implemented in R script that is freely available from Supplementary Materials. Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The differential expression analysis focusing on inter-group comparison can capture only differentially expressed genes (DE genes) at the population level, which may mask the heterogeneity of differential expression in individuals. Thus, to provide patient-specific information for personalized medicine, it is necessary to conduct differential expression analysis at the individual level. Results: We proposed a method to detect DE genes in individual disease samples by using the disrupted ordering in individual disease samples. In both simulated data and real paired cancer-normal sample data, this method showed excellent performance. It was found to be insensitive to experimental batch effects and data normal-ization. The landscape of stable gene pairs in a particular type of normal tissue could be predetermined using previously accumulated data, based on which dysregulated genes and pathways for any disease sample can be readily detected. The usefulness of the RankComp method in clinical settings was exemplified by the identification and application of prognostic markers for lung cancer.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The differential expression analysis methods on intergroup comparison for identifying disease-related genes can be classified into two broad categories: the intensity-based methods such as T-Test (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Rice, 1995</ref>), SAM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Tusher et al., 2001</ref>) and Limma (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Smyth, 2004</ref>), and the rank-based methods such as Wilcoxon signed rank test (<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Wilcoxon, 1945</ref>), Wilcoxon rank sum test (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Hollander and Wolfe, 1973</ref>) and RP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Breitling et al., 2004</ref>). Of the rankbased methods, there is a special type of method using the foldchange ordering information, such as RP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Breitling et al., 2004</ref>), RcoS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Navon et al., 2009</ref>) and FCROS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Dembele and Kastner, 2014</ref>). In general, these methods first entail ranking fold-change values within each pairwise comparison between two types of samples, then calculate a fold-change rank ordering statistic for each gene. The significance of the observed statistic could be determined by using a permutation test (e.g. RP) or probability distribution function (e.g. FCROS). The rank-based methods usually have some advantages in comparison with the intensity-based methods, such as robustness against outlier values and favorable power efficiency in some cases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Lehmann, 1975</ref>). However, both the above-mentioned intensity-based and rankbased methods are designed to detect the population-level DE genes and cannot provide patient-specific differential expression information. Taking the heterogeneous nature of disease into account, several outlier detection methods, including COPA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Tomlins et al., 2005</ref>), OS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Tibshirani and Hastie, 2007</ref>), ORT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Wu, 2007</ref>), MOST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Lian, 2008</ref>) and others (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">de Ronde et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hu, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Wang et al., 2012</ref>), are developed to detect genes that are dysregulated in subsets of disease samples. However, they are more sensitive to various technical artifacts, especially experimental batch effects caused by differences in laboratory conditions, reagent lots and personnel (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Leek et al., 2010</ref>). In general, batch effects can introduce serious problems in translating experimental findings to clinical settings. For example, because of this problem, an optimized threshold value of the risk score summarizing the expression levels of signature genes determined from a set of training samples cannot be directly applied to other samples. Usually, in validation studies, data normalization is required for independently extracted samples to make all data having nearly the same scale as the training samples. However, current normalization methods that are used to adjust for systematic technical artifacts are usually not able to remove batch effects (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Lazar et al., 2012</ref>). They may even distort biological signals (<ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Wang et al., 2011</ref>). More fundamentally, large interindividual variation in gene expression will exacerbate the problem of threshold setting for risk stratification. To tackle this difficult problem, researchers have proposed to make use of the relative ordering information of gene expression within each sample, considering that the relative ordering of gene expression within each sample would be rather robust against batch effects and insensitive to data normalization (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Geman et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Tan et al., 2005</ref>). The relative ordering of gene expression is overall stable in a particular type of normal human tissue but widely disturbed in diseased tissue. Taking this into account, a method of detecting *To whom correspondence should be addressed. DE genes in individual disease samples is here proposed. Using both simulated data and real paired cancer–normal data, this method was shown to have excellent performance for individual-level analyses of dysregulated genes and pathways. The use of this method in clinical contexts was exemplified by the identification and application of prognostic markers to risk stratification of lung cancer patients according to the dysregulation status of signature in each patient rather than a predefined risk threshold value.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data and preprocessing</head><p>Multiple microarray datasets of gene expression, generated with the Affymetrix platform (HG-U133 Plus2.0), were downloaded from Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO;<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Edgar et al., 2002</ref>). Notably, normal samples of each type of tissue (lung or breast) were collected from datasets for studying different disorders on this tissue, as described in detail in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. Paired cancer–normal samples taken from the same patients were used to evaluate the performance of RankComp. The cancer sample data with survival information were used for survival analysis. More detailed clinical information on survival data can be found in the Supplementary Material. The use of relative expression obviates the need of between-chip normalization because all direct comparisons between genes occur within individual samples and inter-chip normalization can preserve order (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Heinaniemi et al., 2013</ref>). For this reason, the raw data (.CEL files) for each dataset was processed using the RMA algorithm for background adjustment without quantile normalization (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Irizarry et al., 2003</ref>). Then, each probeset ID was mapped to Entrez gene ID with the custom CDF file. If multiple probesets were mapped to the same gene, the expression value for the gene was summarized as the arithmetic mean of the values of multiple probesets (on the log2 scale).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">The MSigDB pathway</head><p>The 674 canonical Reactome pathways were downloaded from the C2CP collection of the Molecular Signatures Database (MSigDB version 4.0, updated May 31, 2013;<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>). These pathways covered 6025 unique genes for pathway enrichment analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Rank comparison</head><p>First, each gene expression value is converted to its rank within each sample (the smallest expression value corresponding to the minimum rank, and the largest expression value corresponding to the maximum rank). Then, pairwise comparisons are performed for all genes to identify gene pairs with stable ordering in accumulated normal samples for a particular type of tissue from different data sources. For each gene pair (G i , G j ), being viewed as an event with only two possible outcomes (G i 4G j or G i 5G j ), the frequency of samples in normal samples for which the rank of G i is greater (or less) than that of G j is estimated as follows:</p><p>Pwhere n 1 is the total number of normal samples and I is the indicator function. Stable gene pairs are defined as gene pairs with P norm (G i 4G j )40.99 or P norm (G i 5G j )40.99. Next, reversal gene pairs are defined for each disease sample as gene pairs with reversal ordering in comparison with their stable ordering in normal samples (G i 4G j !G i 5G j or G i 5G j !G i 4G j ). Afterwards, the Fisher's exact test is used to determine whether a given gene (G i ) is differentially expressed in a given disease sample (k) by testing the null hypothesis that the numbers of reversal gene pairs supporting its upregulation and downregulation are equal. For G i , if its ordering is consistently lower (or higher) than that of G j in normal samples but the opposite in the disease sample k, then this reversal gene pair is considered to support upregulation (or downregulation) of G i in that sample. Let G denote the set of stable gene pairs including G i in normal samples, a and b denote the numbers of gene pairs belonging to G with ordering patterns {G i 4G j } and {G i 5G j' } and c and d denote the corresponding numbers of gene pairs belonging to G with ordering patterns {G i 4G j } and {G i 5G j' } in the disease sample k. To this end, the proportions of gene pairs with orderingin the rank of a gene detected as an up-or downregulated DE gene: if and only if it is still significant after excluding the downregulated (or upregulated) partner genes involved in the reversal gene pairs supporting its upregulation (or downregulation), it will be retained. Notably, besides its major application for detecting DE gene at the individual level, the RankComp method could also be applied to identify DE genes at the subpopulation level by using the binomial test to find a non-randomly high percentage (f) of disease samples sharing certain DE genes. Here, the minimum value of f (f = k/n 2 ) that meets a prespecified significance level for the binomial test can be determined as follows:</p><formula>P= X n2 k C k n2 p 0 k 1 À p 0 ð Þ n2Àk ð Þ</formula><p>where k is the number of the observed dysregulated samples for each gene, n 2 is the total number of disease samples and p 0 is the probability of observing a gene being differentially expressed in a disease sample by chance, calculated as the average of the frequencies of DE genes among all the genes on the array for individual disease samples.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Evaluation of performance</head><p>First, a simulation is performed to evaluate the performance of the RankComp method. To retain the intrinsic structure of real microarray data, the simulations were conducted based on real microarray dataset rather than beginning by assuming normal distribution (see Section 3 for detailed description of simulation experiments). The simulation experiment enables us to know both the DE genes and non-DE genes and facilitate the calculation of sensitivity, specificity and F-score. For each simulation scenario, the sensitivity, specificity and F-score of the RankComp method for detection of DE genes are estimated at different FDR control levels. Here, the sensitivity is defined as the ratio of correctly identified DE genes to all DE genes and the specificity is defined as the ratio of correctly identified non-DE genes to all non-DE genes. The F-score, a harmonic mean of sensitivity and specificity, is calculated as follows:</p><formula>F À score= 2 sensitivity Â specificity ð Þ sensitivity+specificity ð Þ</formula><p>Then, the real microarray data of paired cancer–normal samples, as described in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>, is used as a benchmark to evaluate the performance of the RankComp method. For a paired samples of cancer and normal tissues, a gene is defined as up-regulated if its expression level in the cancer sample is larger than that in the normal sample, and defined as down-regulated if its expression level in the cancer sample is smaller than that in the normal sample, regardless of whether the changes in its expression level are significant or not. Taking the change directions (up-or down-regulation) of genes observed in the paired cancer-normal samples as the golden standard, we then define a DE gene, detected by the RankComp method in the same cancer sample, whose change direction is consistent with the golden standard as a consistent DE gene. For each cancer sample, the consistency score, as representative of the precision of DE detection, is calculated as the ratio of the consistent DE genes to all DE genes, and the number of DE genes is used to access the detection power of the method. Notably, the corresponding paired normal tissue samples are not used to determine stable gene pairs in normal tissues.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Pathway analysis at the individual level</head><p>The hypergeometric distribution model was used to determine the significance of biological pathways enriched with up-and downregulated DE genes separately (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Hong et al., 2013</ref>). The P-values were adjusted using the Benjamini and Hochberg procedure, controlling FDR at the 5% level (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Hochberg and Benjamini, 1995</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">Survival analysis and pathway signature selection</head><p>The overall survival was calculated from the date of surgery until death or last follow-up contact. To avoid the bias of patient follow-up duration, patients with 4120 months of follow-up were truncated at 120 months. The survival curves were estimated by the Kaplan–Meier method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Meier, 1958</ref>) and were compared using the log-rank test (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Gray, 1988</ref>). The Cox proportional hazard model was used for univariate and multivariate survival analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Cox, 1972</ref>). The forward stepwise algorithm was used to identify an optimal pathway predictor of survival. Beginning with the pathway with the highest concordance index (C-index;<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Harrell et al., 1996</ref>) as the initial signature, candidate pathways were added one at a time to the signature until the next one to be added did not improve prognostic performance. At each step, predictive performance was gauged for all possible additions and evaluated using the c-index to select the optimal addition yielding the largest increase in the c-index value. The C-index is a measure of the probability that, given a pair of randomly selected patients, the model correctly predicts which patient will have a better outcome. This measure quantifies discriminatory ability, ranging from 0.5 (indicating random chance) to 1 (indicating perfect discrimination).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Stable expression ordering of gene pairs in normal human tissues</head><p>To determine whether relative expression ordering of gene pairs is stable in normal samples for a particular tissue, normal tissue samples from different datasets were collected for the study of different disorders. For normal lung tissue, a total of 210 samples were collected from multiple datasets of several lung diseases, including lung cancer and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. They were then divided into two groups: one group of 65 samples was derived from the GSE19188 dataset and another group of 145 samples was derived from four other datasets (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). In each group, pairwise comparisons were performed for all genes to identify stable gene pairs present in at least 99% of normal samples. More than 95% (112 970 616 over 118 725 563) of the stable gene pairs identified in the second group were included in the 135 020 175 stable gene pairs identified in the first group. Remarkably, all of the 112 970 616 overlapping gene pairs had the same ordering patterns across the two groups of samples. This was highly unlikely to happen by chance (binomial test, P51.0e-16), indicating that stable gene pairs are highly reproducible in different sets of normal tissue samples. Similar results were observed in normal breast tissue (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). Notably, all genes on the array were involved in stable gene pairs for each of the two types of tissue named above, indicating that stable gene pairs widely exist in normal human tissues and that stable gene pairs are an inherent feature of gene expression in normal human tissues. These results provide a basis for individualized differential analysis using gene ranking information. In order to further show the inherent advantage of stable expression ordering of gene pairs over distribution variations of gene expression, a pair of genes (GCKR and GATA1) with stable expression ordering obtained from normal lung tissue samples was taken as an example here. As illustrated in<ref type="figure">Figure  1</ref>, even after quantile normalization, the expression distributions of the two genes in normal samples from different datasets are still different so that the expression intensities of these genes in different datasets are incomparable. These distribution variations hamper data integration from different data sources. However, the relative ordering of gene expression within each sample is insensitive to these distribution variations and thus would facilitate multi-source data integration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Evaluation of performance</head><p>First, the performance of the RankComp method was evaluated using a simulation. To retain the intrinsic structure of the data, data were simulated for 60 disease samples and 100 disease samples on the basis of the expression profiles of 15 000 genes for 60 normal lung tissue samples and 100 normal breast tissue samples extracted from the GSE19804 and GSE26457 datasets, respectively. For each normal sample, 1500 upregulated and 1500 downregulated genes were randomly generated and used to produce a disease sample by setting these genes with different magnitudes of differential expression (e.g. log 2 FC =AE 0.8, AE 1.0 and AE 1.2). Here, the fold-change (log 2 FC) was used to quantify the difference in expression levels of each gene between the disease sample and the corresponding normal sample. For the large dataset of 100 disease samples and 100 normal samples, when the magnitude of differential expression (jlog 2 FCj) was increased from 0.8 to 1.2, the sensitivity increased from 79 to 96% at the cost of a slight decrease in specificity, from 94 to 85%. As shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>, the method exhibited rather good performance with sensitivity 490%, specificity 485% and F-score 490% when the magnitude of differential expression was not too small (jlog 2 FCj ! 1.0). To determine the effect of normal sample size, the performance of the method was studied in the small dataset of 60 disease samples and 60 normal samples. As expected, a slight decline in sensitivity, specificity and F-score was observed for each scenario. Similar results were observed for the scenarios with 5% FDR level. Then, the real microarray data of paired cancer-normal samples was used as a benchmark to evaluate the performance of the method. Using the stable gene pairs obtained from the 210 normal lung tissue samples, with 5% FDR control, DE genes for each lung cancer sample from an independent paired cancernormal sample dataset (GSE27262) were detected using the RankComp method described in Section 2.3. To ensure the association between the individualized DE genes and cancer, the analysis was restricted to genes that were dysregulated in a non-randomly high percentage of cancer samples. For each cancer sample, average 2722 DE genes showing dysregulated in at least 44% of samples were identified with an average precision of 90.35%, as indicated by the consistency between the detected dysregulation directions of the DE genes and their actual dysregulation directions observed in the paired samples. In particular, when focusing on the analysis of the top 100 ranked DE genes for each cancer sample, the average precision reached 99.80%. Similar evaluation results were observed in an independent paired cancer–normal sample dataset for breast cancer (GSE10780; Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table S2</ref>). These results indicated that the RankComp method can reliably capture differential expression signals, especially the top-ranked signals, in cancer patients based on the landscape of stable gene pairs obtained in advance using previously accumulated data. Notably, the criteria for identifying stable gene pairs in normal samples may affect the results of differential expression analysis. When the criteria were decreased from strict control (99%) to loose control (95%), the average number of DE genes for lung cancer increased by about 44% and the average precision decreased by about 5%. Similar results were observed for breast cancer (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table S3</ref>). A strict control of 99% would minimize false positives. In principle, the RankComp method is an incremental learning process, during which its performance can be improved along with the accumulation of normal samples for a particular type of tissue by setting an increasingly reliable landscape of stable gene pairs. This advantage here was demonstrated by investigating the impact of normal samples on the performance. From the<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. An example of a pair of genes showing stable relative expression orderings in normal samples of lung tissue. The plot illustrates that the expression distributions of two genes (GCKR and GATA1) in normal samples from different datasets are still different even after quantile normalization. For example, the expression intensities of these two genes in all normal samples of GSE19804 are always higher than those in GSE19188. However, the relative expression ordering of these two genes within each sample is insensitive to the distribution variations from different datasets: the expression intensity of gene GCKR keeps larger than that of gene GATA1 within each sample in any of the datasets210 normal lung tissue samples, subsets of different sample sizes, ranging from 50 samples per group to the highest sample size, were randomly extracted. As shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, when the normal sample size increased from 50 to 210, the average precision increased from 88.78 to 90.35% at the cost of a decline in average number of DE genes, from 3726 to 2722. However, the rate of decline gradually decreased, indicating a stably improving trend of DE genes detection as the normal sample size increased. The same trend was observed for breast cancer (<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Use of individual-level DE analysis for outlier detection</head><p>overexpression of CENPA gene involved in this pathway promotes cancer progression by increasing genome instability (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Amato et al., 2009</ref>). Dysregulation of the latter pathway can trigger replicative stress and replication-associated DNA damage, favoring the accumulation of genetic alterations in cancer cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Allera-Moreau et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bartkova et al., 2006</ref>). For instance, the overexpression of PLK1 gene involved in this pathway promotes cancer progression by increasing resistance to replication stress respectively (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Allera-Moreau et al., 2012</ref>). These studies provided the additional evidence to support our findings from the aspect of biological importance. Taken together, these analyses demonstrated the capacity of the RankComp method to add value in a prognostic setting and provide patient-specific information for personalized medicine.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>The overall stable ordering of gene expression in a normal human tissue may reflect the biological reality that the normal state should be robust against various perturbations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Shiraishi et al., 2010</ref>). During the transition from the normal state to a disease state, the ordering of gene expression residing in a diseased tissue may be subject to extensive changes, which could be sufficient to reveal patient-specific differential expression information, as demonstrated by the results based on both simulated data and real paired cancer–normal sample data. One unique advantage of the present relative ordering-based method is that it is insensitive to batch effects and data normalization and thus can directly use microarray data from different data sources. In particular, the landscape of stable gene pairs in a particular type of normal tissue can be pre-determined using previously accumulated data of normal samples collected for the study of different disorders on the tissue and could become increasingly stable and reliable along with data accumulation of normal samples. Based on the landscape, dysregulated genes and pathways for an individual disease sample of this tissue can be readily detected. Analysis of individualized DE genes could have important applications. First, it can be of value in the practice of personalized medicine. For prognostic risk stratification, the present method can directly stratify patients at the individual level based on the dysregulation status of signature in each patient. Optimal risk threshold value that is determined from a set of training samples using a risk-scoring method usually needs to be redetermined in independent samples because of technical and biological variations. Another possible application of the RankComp method is in addressing the scarcity of normal tissue samples, which are often rare because of the invasive nature of sample collection. Fortunately, normal samples for a particular type of tissue, generated in different laboratories for the study of different disorders, are often collected in public repositories. Using these normal samples, this method can be used to predetermine the landscape of stable expression ordering of gene pairs for that particular type of tissue. Then, based on this landscape, dysregulated genes and pathways for any disease sample of this tissue can be readily detected. In this way, the present method makes it possible to maximize the reuse of accumulated data for normal tissue samples and facilitate the research of human disease. Nevertheless, the present method also has several limitations. First, the RankComp method may have insufficient power to detect genes whose differential expression causes minor changes in the gene ranking profile. Fortunately, even if a certain number of DE genes go undetected in a given disease sample, shifting the focus of the analysis from individual genes to pathways tends to produce relatively robust results despite insufficient power (<ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Yang et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Zou et al., 2012</ref>). Second, the analysis presented here was performed only on microarray data from the same platform because the ordering of gene expression is sensitive to microarray platforms to some degree. One possible way of addressing this limitation is to filter out gene pairs with unstable ordering in datasets produced by different platforms.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: The Natural Science Foundation of China (91029717, 81071646, 81372213, 81201822 and 81030029) and Research Fund for the Doctoral Program of Higher Education of China (20112307110011). Conflict of interest: none declared. REFERENCES Alimonti,A. et al. (2010) Subtle variations in Pten dose determine cancer susceptibility. Nat. Genet., 42, 454–458.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Kaplan–Meier estimates of overall survival according to the optimal two-pathway signature in the training and validation cohorts. (A) Overall survival curves in the training cohort. (B) Overall survival curves in the validation cohort</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1.</figDesc><table>Description of normal sample data, paired cancer–normal 
sample data and survival data used in this study 

Tissue 
GEO Acc 
Number 
of 
Normal a 

Number 
of 
Cancer 

Reference 

The normal sample data used for identifying stable gene pairs 
Lung 
GSE18842 
45 
(Sanchez-Palencia et al., 
2010) 
GSE19188 
65 
(Hou et al., 2010) 
GSE31210 
20 
(Lu et al., 2010) 
GSE19804 
60 
(Okayama et al., 2011) 
GSE37768 
20 
– 
Breast 
GSE3744 
7 
(Alimonti et al., 2010) 
GSE7307 
2 
– 
GSE7904 
7 
(Richardson et al., 2006) 
GSE10780 
60 
(Chen et al., 2009) 
GSE10810 
27 
(Pedraza et al., 2009) 
GSE20711 
2 
(Dedeurwaerder et al., 
2011) 
GSE21422 
5 
(Kretschmer et al., 2011) 
GSE22544 
4 
(Hawthorn et al., 2010) 
GSE26457 
113 
(Russo et al., 2011) 
GSE29431 
12 
– 
GSE30010 
107 
– 
GSE42568 
17 
(Clarke et al., 2013) 

The paired cancer–normal sample data used for evaluating the performance 
of RankComp 

Lung 
GSE27262 
25 
25 
(Wei et al., 2012) 
Breast 
GSE10780 
11 
11 
(Chen et al., 2009) 

The data with survival information used for survival analysis 

Lung 
GSE31210 
204 
(Okayama et al., 2011) 
GSE29013 
8 
(Xie et al., 2011) 
GSE30219 
83 
(Rousseaux et al., 2013) 
GSE31546 
13 
– 
GSE37745 
78 
(Botling et al., 2012) 

Note: a To determine stable gene pairs on a particular type of normal tissue, only 
normal samples were collected from datasets for studying different disorders on this 
tissue. Thus, the information of disease samples in each dataset was not presented. </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. Sensitivity, specificity and F-score for the RankComp method in simulated data</figDesc><table>Dataset 
100 versus 100 
60 versus 60 

jlog 2 FCj 
FDR 
1% 
5% 
1% 
5% 

0.8 
Sensitivity 
0.7915 
0.8329 
0.7098 
0.7539 
Specificity 
0.9439 
0.9311 
0.9304 
0.9120 
F-score 
0.8610 
0.8793 
0.8053 
0.8254 
1.0 
Sensitivity 
0.9153 
0.9384 
0.8520 
0.8836 
Specificity 
0.9078 
0.8742 
0.8793 
0.8345 
F-score 
0.9115 
0.9052 
0.8654 
0.8583 
1.2 
Sensitivity 
0.9633 
0.9748 
0.9248 
0.9452 
Specificity 
0.8527 
0.7859 
0.7970 
0.7163 
F-score 
0.9046 
0.8702 
0.8562 
0.8150 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Individual-level analysis of differential expression at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">H.Wang et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">As described in the Methods, besides the individual-level analysis of DE genes, the RankComp method can be applied to identify DE genes at the subpopulation level, similar to outlier detection methods such as COPA, OS, ORT and MOST. Because it has been shown that COPA and MOST for outlier detection perform relatively better in comparison with several other methods such as OS and ORT (Karrila et al., 2011), we compared only RankComp with COPA and MOST in simulation data. The detailed descriptions of simulation experiments and parameter settings were presented in the Supplementary Material, and the detailed results were presented in Supplementary Table S4. Briefly, the F-score comparison results showed that RankComp performed similarly with COPA and better than MOST at j = 5%, 10% and 20%, but obviously better than COPA and slightly worse than MOST at j = 50% and 80%. These results demonstrated that the RankComp method for detecting DE genes in subsets of disease samples can perform better in many scenarios, indicating a potential advantage of applying the RankComp method for detecting DE genes in various proportions of disease samples. In addition, we mimicked systematic batch effects in the simulated datasets to evaluate the robustness of the RankComp method against systematic batch effects. As shown in Supplementary Table S5, the RankComp method had the advantage of insensitivity to systematic batch effects (for details, see Supplementary Material). Notably, we could also apply the RankComp method to identify the population-level DE genes, defined as the combination of subpopulation-level DE genes, considering that the populationlevel DE genes might not be dysregulated in all samples. In this sense, we compared RankComp with the Wilcoxon signed-rank test and Limma. As shown in Supplementary Table S4, the Fscore comparison showed that RankComp performed better than both the Wilcoxon signed-rank test and Limma for all the scenarios with j =5% and still better than Limma for the scenarios with j =10%, but worse than both the Wilcoxon signed-rank test and Limma for all the scenarios with j =20, 50 and 80%. These results suggested that RankComp is generally uncompetitive for detecting the population-level DE genes. Thus, we do not recommend using the RankComp method to detect DE genes at the population level. 3.4 Use of individual-level DE analysis in survival analysis Individualized DE gene analysis provides a basis for individuallevel pathway analysis, which could be readily applied in clinical contexts. To exemplify this application, a publicly available microarray dataset of 204 early-stage lung adenocarcinoma samples with survival data was analyzed (GSE31210). Using the landscape of stable gene pairs obtained from the 235 normal lung tissue samples, dysregulated genes were detected for each of 204 cancer samples at the FDR level of 0.05. Focusing on these cancer-associated genes for each cancer sample, biological pathways that were significantly enriched with up-and down-DE genes in this sample were detected at the FDR level of 0.05. The results indicated that the dysregulation of biological pathways in lung cancer patients is heterogeneous (Supplementary Fig. S1). For example, the &apos;deposition of new CENPA-containing nucleosomes at the centromere pathway&apos; was significantly dysregulated in 50% of cancer patients but not in the others. Dividing the cohort of 204 patients into two groups according to the dysregulation status of this pathway showed that the dysregulation of this pathway was significantly associated with poor overall survival in lung cancer patients (Log-rank test, P = 1.29e-05). Multivariate analysis showed that high-risk and low-risk designation remained statistically significant after adjustment for age, gender and smoking status (Supplementary Fig. S2A and Supplementary Table S6). This result was validated in an independent pooled cohort of 182 lung cancer samples (Supplementary Fig. S2B and Supplementary Table S6). Many other pathways whose dysregulation status was predictive for survival of lung cancer patients were also found (Supplementary Table S7). To look into this further, a forward stepwise algorithm was used to select an optimal set of pathways with the highest predictive power for prognosis. A two-pathway signature consisting of the &apos;deposition of new CENPA-containing nucleosomes at the centromere pathway&apos; and &apos;DNA replication pathway&apos; was generated in the training cohort (Fig. 3A), with a poor prognosis for patients with simultaneous dysregulation of these two pathways confirmed in the validation cohort (Fig. 3B). Multivariate analysis showed that the two-pathway signature remained significantly associated with overall survival after adjustment for age, gender and stage (Supplementary Table S8). It has been found that dysregulation of the former pathway can cause ectopic formation resulting in multicentric chromosomes and consequential genome instability that drives tumor progression (Amato et al., 2009). For instance, the Fig. 2. Impact of normal sample size on the performance of the RankComp method. Blue bars represent the average precision, and orange line represents the average number of DE genes per sample</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">DNA replication stress response involving PLK1, CDC6, POLQ, RAD51 and CLASPIN upregulation prognoses the outcome of early/mid-stage non-small cell lung cancer patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Allera-Moreau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page">30</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CENPA overexpression promotes genome instability in pRbdepleted human cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Amato</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oncogene-induced senescence is part of the tumorigenesis barrier imposed by DNA damage checkpoints</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Bartkova</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">444</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="633" to="637" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biomarker discovery in non-small cell lung cancer: integrating gene expression profiling, meta-analysis, and tissue microarray validation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Botling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="194" to="204" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rank products: a simple, yet powerful, new method to detect differentially regulated genes in replicated microarray experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Breitling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEBS Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">573</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proliferative genes dominate malignancy-risk gene signature in histologically-normal breast tissue</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Breast Cancer Res. Treat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="346" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlating transcriptional networks to breast cancer survival: a large-scale coexpression analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Clarke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Carcinogenesis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2300" to="2308" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regression Models and Life-Tables</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Cox</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B Methodol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="220" />
			<date type="published" when="1972" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying subgroup markers in heterogeneous populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>De Ronde</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">200</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA methylation profiling reveals a predominant immune component in breast cancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Dedeurwaerder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO Mol. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="726" to="741" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fold change rank ordering statistics: a new method for detecting differentially expressed genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Dembele</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Kastner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array data repository</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Edgar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classifying gene expression profiles from pairwise mRNA comparisons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Geman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Appl. Genet. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A class of K-sample tests for comparing the cumulative incidence of a competing risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Gray</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inst. Math. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1141" to="1154" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multivariable prognostic models: issues in developing models, evaluating assumptions and adequacy, and measuring and reducing errors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Harrell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Jr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="361" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integration of transcript expression, copy number and LOH analysis of infiltrating ductal carcinoma of the breast</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Hawthorn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">460</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene-pair expression signatures reveal lineage control</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Heinaniemi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="577" to="583" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Hochberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Benjamini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B Methodol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonparametric Statistical Methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hollander</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Wolfe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Separate enrichment analysis of pathways for up-and downregulated genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Hong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Soc. Interface</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression-based classification of non-small cell lung carcinomas and survival prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Hou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10312</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancer outlier detection based on likelihood ratio test</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Hu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2193" to="2199" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploration, normalization, and summaries of high density oligonucleotide array probe level data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Irizarry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="264" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of methods for data-driven cancer outlier discovery, and an application scheme to semisupervised predictive biomarker discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Karrila</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of early molecular markers for breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Kretschmer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Batch effect removal methods for microarray gene expression data integration: a survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Lazar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="469" to="490" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tackling the widespread and critical impact of batch effects in high-throughput data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Leek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="733" to="739" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonparametrics: Statistical Methods Based on Ranks. HoldenDay</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Lehmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
			<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MOST: detecting cancer differential gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Lian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="418" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of a novel biomarker, SEMA5A, for non-small cell lung carcinoma in nonsmoking women</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Lu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Epidemiol. Biomarkers Prev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2590" to="2597" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonparametric estimation from incomplete observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Meier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Kalpan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="481" />
			<date type="published" when="1958" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel rank-based statistical methods reveal microRNAs with differential expression in multiple cancer types</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Navon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8003</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of genes upregulated in ALK-positive and EGFR/KRAS/ALK-negative lung adenocarcinomas</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Okayama</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression signatures in breast cancer distinguish phenotype characteristics, histologic subtypes, and tumor invasiveness</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Pedraza</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="486" to="496" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mathematical Statistics and Data Analysis, second edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Rice</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>Duxbury Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Belmont, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">X chromosomal abnormalities in basal-like human breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Richardson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ectopic activation of germline and placental genes identifies aggressive metastasis-prone lung cancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Rousseaux</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Transl. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pregnancy-induced chromatin remodeling in the breast of postmenopausal women</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Russo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1059" to="1070" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression profiling reveals novel biomarkers in nonsmall cell lung cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Sanchez-Palencia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="364" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale analysis of network bistability for human cancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Shiraishi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000851</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linear models and empirical bayes methods for assessing differential expression in microarray experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Smyth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Appl. Genet. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Subramanian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15545" to="15550" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simple decision rules for classifying human cancers from gene expression profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Tan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3896" to="3904" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Outlier sums for differential gene expression analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Tibshirani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Hastie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recurrent fusion of TMPRSS2 and ETS transcription factor genes in prostate cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Tomlins</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">310</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="644" to="648" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Significance analysis of microarrays applied to the ionizing radiation response</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Tusher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5116" to="5121" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extensive increase of microarray signals in cancers calls for novel normalization assumptions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="130" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Weighted change-point method for detecting differential gene expression in breast cancer microarray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">29860</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein arginine methyltransferase 5 is a potential oncoprotein that upregulates G1 cyclins/cyclin-dependent kinases and the phosphoinositide 3-kinase/AKT signaling cascade</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1640" to="1650" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Individual comparisons by ranking methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Wilcoxon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometr. Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="1945" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancer outlier differential gene expression detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="566" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust gene expression signature from formalin-fixed paraffinembedded samples predicts prognosis of non-small-cell lung cancer patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Xie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5705" to="5714" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gaining confidence in biological interpretation of the microarray data: the functional consistence of the significant GO categories</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="271" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Revealing weak differential gene expressions and their reproducible functions associated with breast cancer metastasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Zou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>