
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Inferring sequence regions under functional divergence in duplicate genes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yi-Fei</forename>
								<surname>Huang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">McMaster University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hamilton</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">G</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Brian</forename>
								<surname>Golding</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">McMaster University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hamilton</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Inferring sequence regions under functional divergence in duplicate genes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="176" to="183"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr635</idno>
					<note type="submission">Sequence analysis Advance Access publication November 26, 2011 Received on September 6, 2011; revised on November 10, 2011; accepted on November 11, 2011</note>
					<note>[17:39 20/12/2011 Bioinformatics-btr635.tex] Page: 176 176–183 Associate Editor: David Posada Contact: golding@mcmaster.ca Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: A number of statistical phylogenetic methods have been proposed to identify type-I functional divergence in duplicate genes by detecting heterogeneous substitution rates in phylogenetic trees. A common disadvantage of the existing methods is that autocorrelation of substitution rates along sequences is not modeled. This reduces the power of existing methods to identify regions under functional divergence. Results: We design a phylogenetic hidden Markov model to identify protein regions relevant to type-I functional divergence. A C++ program, HMMDiverge, has been developed to estimate model parameters and to identify regions under type-I functional divergence. Simulations demonstrate that HMMDiverge can successfully identify protein regions under type-I functional divergence unless the discrepancy of substitution rates between subfamilies is very limited or the regions under functional divergence are very short. Applying HMMDiverge to G protein α subunits in animals, we identify a candidate region longer than 20 amino acids, which overlaps with the α-4 helix and the α4-β6 loop in the GTPase domain with divergent rates of substitutions. These sites are different from those reported by an existing program, DIVERGE2. Interestingly, previous biochemical studies suggest the α-4 helix and the α4-β6 loop are important to the specificity of the receptor–G protein interaction. Therefore, the candidate region reported by HMMDiverge highlights that the type-I functional divergence in G protein α subunits may be relevant to the change of receptor–G protein specificity after gene duplication. From these results, we conclude that HMMDiverge is a useful tool to identify regions under type-I functional divergence after gene duplication. Availability: C++ source codes of HMMDiverge and simulation programs used in this study, as well as example datasets, are available at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>An important challenge in the post-genomic era is the identification of biological sequences that contribute to functional divergence of * To whom correspondence should be addressed. duplicate genes. After gene duplication, homologous regions, e.g. protein motifs or protein domains, may evolve at different rates between two duplicates because of the discrepancy of functional constraints that results from functional divergence. Therefore, the difference of substitution rates between two duplicate subfamilies can be used as a proxy of functional divergence, which is referred to as type-I functional divergence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Gu, 1999</ref>) or rate shifting (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Abhiman and Sonnhammer, 2005b</ref>). Alternatively, substitution rates in both duplicate genes may increase immediately after gene duplication due to relaxed functional constraints, but decrease at a late stage due to increased functional constraints. The sequence regions or sites that are conserved within subfamilies but diverged between them may be relevant to functional divergence, which is referred to as type-II functional divergence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Gu, 1999</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Gu, , 2006</ref>), conservationshifting (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Abhiman and Sonnhammer, 2005b</ref>) or 'constant but different' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Gribaldo et al., 2003</ref>). A number of statistical models have been proposed to detect protein regions or amino acid sites relevant to functional divergence based on the heterogeneity of substitution rates in duplicate genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Abhiman and Sonnhammer, 2005b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Arnau et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bielawski and Yang, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Blouin et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Dorman, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Gu, 1999</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Gu, , 2001a</ref><ref type="bibr">Gu, , b, 2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Knudsen and Miyamoto, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Knudsen et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Marin et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Nam et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Neuwald, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Pupko and Galtier, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Susko et al., 2002</ref>). The idea of these existing methods is to detect the discrepancy of substitution rates using an extended phylogenetic model in which the substitution rates could be different between different branches. A common drawback of the existing methods is that any autocorrelation of substitution rates along sequences is not modeled. Most phylogenetic methods assume that every site evolves independently. However, this simple assumption is frequently violated. In a recent work,<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Callahan et al. (2011)</ref>performed a whole-genome level study on the correlated evolution of nearby residues in Drosophilid proteins. A strong autocorrelation was found between non-synonymous substitutions but not between synonymous substitutions, which suggests autocorrelation at protein level (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Callahan et al., 2011</ref>). In addition, it has been found that positive selection varies between protein secondary structures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Ridout et al., 2010</ref>). Therefore, a number of neighboring pairs of sites may show correlated substitution patterns, such as the correlated substitution rates. Unfortunately, most existing methods for identifying functional divergence do not model the autocorrelation of substitutions. Instead, independence of substitution rates across sites is assumed in most of the existing methods (<ref type="bibr">Abhiman and Sonnhammer, 2005a, b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Blouin et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Dorman, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Gu, 1999</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Gu, , 2001a</ref><ref type="bibr">Gu, , b, 2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Knudsen and Miyamoto, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Knudsen et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Susko et al., 2002</ref>). These methods<ref type="bibr">[17:39 20/12/2011 Bioinformatics-btr635.tex]</ref>Page: 177 176–183</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detecting regions under functional divergence</head><p>may be useful to detect critical sites contributed to functional divergence, because these critical sites may evolve independently in terms of spatial distribution. However, if substitution rates are autocorrelated along sequences, these methods may be less powerful than a method which can model the autocorrelation correctly, because the evolutionary signals in individual sites are very limited. In addition, these methods may not be able to correctly infer the boundaries of regions under functional divergence. In a few studies, the autocorrelation of heterogeneous substitution rates along sequences are considered but are detected by heuristic methods, such as the sliding window method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Arnau et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Gao et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Nam et al., 2005</ref>). It has been argued that the sliding window method is not a desired method to study the spatial distribution of evolutionary patterns. First, failure to correct for the multiple testing problem can lead to incorrect conclusions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Schmid and Yang, 2008</ref>). Second, the resolution of the sliding window method is coarse, since the patterns are averaged over multiple sites. Third, a predefined window size typically needs to be assigned before analyses and it is not clear how to define a universally optimized window size. A short window may not be suitable to detect long regions with weak signals in each site, whereas a long window may ignore short regions with strong signals in each site (<ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Zhang and Townsend, 2009</ref>). In this article, we propose a phylogenetic hidden Markov model (phylo-HMM) for identifying protein regions under type-I functional divergence, which explicitly models the autocorrelation of substitution rates along sequences by a hidden Markov model. A C++ program, HMMDiverge, has been developed to implement this phylo-HMM. Simulations suggest that HMMDiverge can efficiently identify protein regions under functional divergence unless the discrepancy of substitution rates between subfamilies is very weak or the regions relevant to functional divergence are very short. By applying this method to G protien α subunits, we identify a candidate region longer than 20 amino acids that may contribute to the diversity of receptor specificity in G protein α subunits.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MODEL AND IMPLEMENTATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Motivation of the phylo-HMM</head><p>Consider a gene family in which the evolutionary relationships among members are known. If the root of the phylogenetic tree corresponds to a duplication event, we may divide the family into two subfamilies, i.e. Subfamily 1 and Subfamily 2, by removing the root. After gene duplication, some regions may evolve at different rates in the two subfamilies due to differentiated functional constraints. To detect this heterogeneous pattern, a model should be able to capture at least two features: the heterogeneity of substitution rates between two subfamilies and the autocorrelation of substitution rates along sequences. Phylo-HMM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Siepel and</ref><ref type="bibr">Haussler, 2004, 2005</ref>) is an extension of standard phylogenetic models, which can naturally capture both of these features (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Siepel and Haussler, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Yang, 1995</ref>). In phylo-HMM, the changes of evolutionary patterns along alignments are described by an unobserved Markov chain, which can be inferred from observed alignments. We design a simple phylo-HMM to identify protein regions under type-I functional divergence in duplicate genes. We focus on protein sequences rather than DNA sequences because a large number of duplicate genes are so old that it is difficult to infer nucleotide substitution rates accurately. Our phylo-HMM is similar to a phylo-HMM used for identifying DNA sequences under lineage-specific selection (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Siepel et al., 2006</ref>). However, there were only two discrete substitution rate categories in this model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Siepel et al., 2006</ref>). This simple assumption may not be flexible enough to describe rate variation very well. Since the functional elements under diverged selection may be very short in proteins, it is desirable to model the substitution rates with a higher resolution so that short regions with a strong discrepancy of substitution rates can be detected. In our phylo-HMM, an arbitrary number of rate categories can be used by modeling the rate variation with a discrete Gamma distribution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Notation of the phylo-HMM</head><p>To describe the phylo-HMM, we adopt a notation similar to that described by<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Siepel and Haussler (2005)</ref>. Formally, we define the proposed phylo-HMM to be a four-tuple, θ = (R,ψ,A,b), consisting of a set of hidden states, R, a set of associated phylogenetic models, ψ, a one-step state transition matrix, A, and a vector of initialstate probabilities, b (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Siepel and Haussler, 2005</ref>). ψ determines the emission probability, i.e. the probability that we observe a column in the alignment given a hidden state. A and b specify the transition probabilities among hidden states and the initial distribution of the hidden Markov chain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Definition of hidden states and associated phylogenetic models</head><p>The first step in designing a phylo-HMM model is to define the set of hidden states, R, and the set of associated phylogenetic models, ψ. We assume the substitution process of amino acids can be described by a fixed continuous time-reversible Markov model. We also assume the phylogenetic tree with branch lengths is known. To fully define the phylogenetic models, we only need to know the relative substitution rates in branches, which are used as scale factors to rescale corresponding branches. We assume the substitution rate is a constant within each subfamily but the substitution rates can be different between two subfamilies. In addition, we assume the rate variation can be described by a discrete Gamma distribution with k substitution rate categories (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Yang, 1994</ref>). We set the shape parameter, α, equal to the scale parameter, β, to ensure that branch lengths can be interpreted as the expected number of substitutions per site. We may define all the possible pairs of the k rate categories between the two subfamilies to be the members in R, and the corresponding phylogenetic models to be the members in ψ. Clearly, there are k 2 possible pairs of the k rate categories, so there are totally k 2 hidden states and k 2 associated phylogenetic models. We define r ij as a hidden state, in which the substitution rate in Subfamily 1 is in the i-th category and that in Subfamily 2 is in the j-th category. If i = j, the substitution rates are equal between the two subfamilies. In this scenario, there is no difference in terms of evolutionary constraints, so type-I functional divergence is not relevant. If i &gt; j, the substitution rate in Subfamily 1 is higher than that in Subfamily 2, which implies type-I functional divergence. If i &lt; j, the substitution rate in Subfamily 1 is lower than that in Subfamily 2, which also implies type-I functional divergence but the divergence is in the opposite direction. Therefore, we divide the members in R into three state groups: M 0 ={r ij : i = j} in which there is no evidence of type-I functional divergence, M 1 ={r ij : i &gt; j} and M 2 ={r ij : i &lt; j} in which there is evidence of type-I functional</p><p>Page: 178 176–183In this simple example, k = 3. The tree topologies are exactly the same in all of the hidden states, in which the left subtree corresponds to Subfamily 1, whereas the right subtree corresponds to Subfamily 2. However, the two subtrees are rescaled by different factors (relative substitution rates). In model group M 0 , there is no difference in terms of relative substitution rates. Therefore, there is no functional divergence in this case. In model group M 1 , the substitution rate is higher in Subfamily 1. In model group M 2 , the substitution rate is lower in Subfamily 1. There is functional divergence in the last two cases.divergence (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). The key goal of the phylo-HMM is to infer the probability of each state group for each site.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Y.-F.Huang and G.B.Golding</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A B C D</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Parameterization of state transition matrix and initial probability vector</head><p>To probabilistically describe the spatial distribution of hidden states in the alignment, we adopt a hierarchical framework to specify the one-step transition matrix, A. First, we can model the transitions among three state groups (M 0 , M 1 and M 2 ) by a simple Markov chain (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2A</ref>). This Markov chain describes switches between 'type-I functional divergence relevant regions'and 'type-I functional divergence irrelevant regions'. We assume (i) both the one-step transition probability from M 0 to M 1 and that from M 0 to M 2 are p 0 ; (ii) both the one-step transition probability from M 1 to M 0 and that from M 2 to M 0 are p 1 ; (iii) one-step transitions between M 1 and M 2 are impossible and any transition between them must go through M 0. The three assumptions define a symmetric Markov chain, but this symmetric Markov chain can only describe the transitions among three state groups. To fully define the transition probabilities among k 2 states, the transition process conditional on staying in each state group must be defined. We use a strategy similar to that described by Siepel and Haussler (2004). We introduce parameter λ 0 to describe the autocorrelation of states conditional on M 0 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2B</ref>) and parameter λ 1 to describe the autocorrelation of states conditional on M 1 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2C</ref>) or M 2 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2D</ref>). The transition process within each state group is well defined by the two autocorrelation parameters. Conditional on staying in a state group, with probability λ 0 (or λ 1 ) the state in site i will be assigned to the same state in site i−1 and with probability 1−λ 0 (or 1−λ 1 ) it will be assigned to a state randomly drawn from all states in the same group with equal probabilities. By combining the transition probabilities among state groups and transition probabilities among states conditional on model groups, we can specify the unconditional transition probabilities between two states in the same group. For example, the transition probabilities between two states in M 0 can be defined to be</p><formula>P(r i j |r ij ) = ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ (1−2p 0 )·(λ 0 + 1−λ 0 k ) if r ij ,r i j ∈ M 0 and r ij = r i j , (1−2p 0 )· 1−λ 0 k if r ij ,r i j ∈ M 0 and r ij = r i j .</formula><formula>(1)</formula><p>In the products, the first components, 1−2p 0 , correspond to the probabilities of staying in M 0 and the second components, λ 0 + 1−λ 0 k and 1−λ 0 k , correspond to the transition probabilities between two states conditional on staying in M 0. Similarly, the transition probabilities between two states in M 1 (or two states in M 2 ) can be defined to be</p><formula>P(r i j |r ij ) = ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ (1−p 1 )·(λ 1 + 2(1−λ 1 ) k(k−1) ) if r ij ,r i j ∈ M 1 (M 2 ) and r ij = r i j ,</formula><formula>(1−p 1 )· 2(1−λ 1 ) k(k−1) if r ij ,r i j ∈ M 1 (M 2 ) and r ij = r i j .</formula><formula>(2)</formula><p>The first components, 1−p 1 , correspond to the probabilities of staying in M 1 or M 2 , whereas the second components,</p><formula>λ 1 + 2(1−λ 1 ) k(k−1) and 2(1−λ 1 ) k(k−1)</formula><p>, correspond to the transition probabilities between two states conditional on staying in M 1 or M 2. Based on this hierarchical structure, we can also specify the transition probabilities between two states in different state groups. It is easy to show the stationary probability of a state conditional on the corresponding state group is equal to one over the number of states in this group, i.e<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Siepel and Haussler, 2004</ref>). Therefore, when the hidden Markov chain transits from one state group to another group, it is natural to draw one state from all the states in the new state group with equal probabilities as the new state. The transition probabilities between two states inPage: 179 176–183</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detecting regions under functional divergence</head><p>different state groups can be defined to be</p><formula>P(r i j |r ij ) = ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ p 0 · 2 k(k−1) if r ij ∈ M 0 and r i j ∈ M 1 ∪M 2 , p 1 · 1 k if r ij ∈ M 1 ∪M 2 and r i j ∈ M 0 .</formula><formula>(3)</formula><p>In the products, the first components, p 0 and p 1 , correspond to the transition probabilities between two state groups, whereas the second components, 2 k(k−1) and 1 k , correspond to the probabilities of randomly drawing a state from the new state group. Now, all the transition probabilities among k 2 states are fully defined. We define the initial probability vector, b, to be the stationary distribution of the one-step transition matrix, A. As shown in the Supplementary Material, the stationary distribution is</p><formula>π(r ij ) = p 1 (2p 0 +p 1 )k if r ij ∈ M 0 , 2p 0 (2p 0 +p 1 )(k−1)k if r ij ∈ M 1 ∪M 2 .</formula><formula>(4)</formula><p>In summary, the phylo-HMM is fully parameterized by five free parameters (p 0 , p 1 , λ 0 , λ 1 and Gamma shape parameter, α).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Computational implementation</head><p>We used a model comparison method to test whether the alignment contains any sequence region under type-I functional divergence. In our phylo-HMM, if p 0 is equal to 0 and p 1 is a constant which is not equal to 0, the hidden Markov chain always stays in M 0 and our phylo-HMM degenerates to the model described by<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Siepel and Haussler (2004)</ref>with two parameters (λ 0 and Gamma shape parameter, α). This was the null model in which the duplicate genes are not under functional divergence. The full model with five parameters served as the alternative model. If the null model was rejected, we concluded that the two subfamilies evolved at different rates and might be relevant to functional divergence. We used a naïve empirical Bayesian framework to estimate how likely a site is relevant to type-I functional divergence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Yang, 2006</ref>). In this framework, parameters estimated in the full model were treated as true parameters and the posterior probability of each state group in each site was estimated using the forward–backward algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Durbin et al., 1998</ref>). We have developed a C++ program, HMMDiverge, to implement the proposed phylo-HMM. HMMDiverge was based on Bio++ (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Dutheil et al., 2006</ref>), a set of libraries designed for phylogenetics and population genetics. In principle, the topology and branch lengths of the phylogenetic tree should be considered as free parameters and be estimated in the phylo-HMM. However, in practice it may be infeasible to estimate so many parameters. A preliminary simulation suggested standard phylogenetic software, such as PhyML (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Guindon and Gascuel, 2003</ref>), could infer the tree topology and branch lengths with a high accuracy in the simulated data generated by HMMDiverge, if the regions under functional divergence are not very long (data not shown). Therefore, when we analyzed real data, we assumed that the phylogenetic trees estimated by PhyML (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Guindon and Gascuel, 2003</ref>) were true trees and fixed them in HMMDiverge. The JTT model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Jones et al., 1992</ref>) was used to describe the transitions among amino acids and the number of rate categories, k, was set to 4. Maximum likelihood method was used to estimate parameters given a protein tree and an alignment. The emission probability, i.e. the probability of an observed column pattern in the alignment given r ij , was calculated by the pruning algorithm proposed by Felsenstein (1981). The gaps were treated as 'missing data' or equivalently ambiguous amino acids (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Felsenstein, 1981</ref>). Then, the likelihood of the observed alignment was calculated by the forward–backward algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Durbin et al., 1998</ref>). Parameters were estimated by maximizing the likelihood function using conjugate gradient method with multiple initial values (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Press et al., 1992</ref>), in which the derivatives are calculated numerically. To identify regions under functional divergence, the marginal probability of each state in each site was calculated by the forward– backward algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Durbin et al., 1998</ref>) using parameters estimated in the full model. The probability of each state group was calculated by summing the probabilities of states in the group. We are especially interested in the sites in which the probabilities of M 1 or those of M 2 are very high, since these sites are likely to be located in regions under type-I functional divergence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">SIMULATION STUDY</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Assumptions and implementation of simulations</head><p>To verify the usefulness and robustness of HMMDiverge, we performed a simulation study. In general, we do not assume the proposed phylo-HMM captures all aspects of functional evolution, because the real evolutionary process is too complicated to be fully described by any model. However, a useful model should be powerful enough to detect strong patterns even if the model itself is only a rough approximation of the true mechanism. Therefore, the reference simulation datasets are based on a set of assumptions, which are simple but very different from those in HMMDiverge: (i) Lengths of 'type-I functional divergence relevant regions' and 'irrelevant regions' are both fixed rather than described by a Markov chain in each simulation. In the reference simulations, five lengths (5 amino acids, 10 amino acids, 20 amino acids, 50 amino acids and 100 amino acids) and three lengths (50 amino acids, 100 amino acids and 200 amino acids) were used for the 'type-I functional divergence relevant regions' and 'irrelevant regions', respectively. (ii) 'Type-I functional divergence relevant regions' and 'irrelevant regions' are distributed alternatively in alignments while the first region is always irrelevant to functional divergence in every alignment. For a 'functional divergence relevant region', one subfamily is randomly selected to be the subfamily that evolves at lower rate. (iii) In a 'type-I functional divergence relevant region', the branches in the slowly evolved subfamily are rescaled by a constant, ρ 1 , and the branches in the rapidly evolved subfamily are rescaled by another constant, ρ 2 (ρ 1 &lt;ρ 2 ). In the reference simulations, three pairs of scale factors were used. In the first pair, ρ 1 = 0.5 and ρ 2 = 1.5, which corresponds to a weak discrepancy of substitution rates between two subfamilies. In the second pair, ρ 1 = 0.25 and ρ 2 = 1.75, which corresponds to an intermediate discrepancy of substitution rates. In the third pair, ρ 1 = 0.125 and ρ 2 = 1.875, which corresponds to a strong discrepancy of substitution rates. (iv) The standard discrete Gamma mixture model is used to describe rate variation across sites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Yang, 1994</ref>). We emphasize that the Gamma shape parameter, α, in the simulations has a different meaning from the α in the phylo-HMM. In the reference simulations, α was set to 0.5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Page: 180 176–183</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Y.-F.Huang and G.B.Golding</head><p>(v) The substitution process of amino acids is described by the JTT model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Jones et al., 1992</ref>). We have developed a C++ program to generate the simulation datasets. The protein phylogenetic tree of a set of 30 G protein α subunits (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>) was used in the simulation, which will be described in more detail in the Section 4. To explore parameter space, we generated 20 alignments for each combination of the mentioned parameters in the reference simulations. The length of each alignment was set to 420 amino acids, which is the approximate length of the G protein α subunit alignment. Then, the simulated alignments and the true phylogenetic tree were fed to HMMDiverge to estimate parameters and the probabilities of state groups in all sites. If the probability of M 1 or that of M 2 is higher than a given probability cutoff, the site may be considered to be relevant to functional divergence. In this way, given a probability cutoff, we get a binary classification which indicates whether a given site is relevant to functional divergence. Comparing the classifications with the true states, we evaluated the performance of HMMDiverge. Since the probability cutoff could significantly influence true positive rates and false positive rates, we summarized the results by receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>) generated by the ROCR package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Sing et al., 2005</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Performance of HMMDiverge in simulations</head><p>In the reference simulations, the performance of HMMDiverge is strongly influenced by the discrepancy of substitution rates and the lengths of 'functional divergence relevant regions' (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>). If the discrepancy of substitution rates between two subfamilies is very limited, i.e. the scale factors of branch lengths are 0.5 in the slowly evolved subfamily and 1.5 in the rapidly evolved subfamily, the performance of HMMDiverge is not very strong due to lack of sufficient signal, represented as ROC curves very close to the main diagonals (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>). However, if the discrepancy of substitution rates is intermediate, i.e. the scale factors of branch lengths are 0.25 in the slowly evolved subfamily and 1.75 in the rapidly evolved subfamily, the performance is fairly good unless the 'type-I functional divergence relevant regions' are very short, e.g. 5 amino acids (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>). If the discrepancy of substitution rates is very strong, i.e. the scale factors are 0.125 in the slowly evolved subfamily and 1.875 in the rapidly evolved subfamily, the performance is even better (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>). The lengths of 'functional divergence irrelevant regions' also influence the performance but are less important than the lengths of 'functional divergence relevant regions' and the discrepancy of substitution rates (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>). In summary, HMMDiverge can accurately identify regions under type-I functional divergence unless the rate shift is very limited or regions under functional divergence are very short. The results coincide with our intuition that it is easier to identify long regions in which substitution rates are very different between two subfamilies and highlight that HMMDiverge may be a useful tool to detect type-I functional divergence. The reference simulations do not address whether the variability of substitution rates across sites influences the performance of HMMDiverge. Therefore, we performed two sets of additional simulations, in which all parameters were the same as these in the reference simulations except the shape parameter, α. In the first set of additional simulations, α was set to 0.2, which implied the substitution rates were highly variable across sites. In thisof the ROC curves of multiple simulations having the equal length of divergence relevant regions (L1), which are 5 aa, 10 aa, 20 aa, 50 aa, and 100 aa, increasing from top to bottom. Each column consists of the ROC curves of multiple simulations having the equal length of divergence irrelevant regions (L2), which are 50 aa, 100 aa, and 200 aa, increasing from left to right. Three types of curves represent three pairs of branch scale parameters. Dotted curves: the scale factor is 1.5 in the rapidly evolved subfamily and 0.5 in the slowly evolved subfamily. Dashed curves: the two scale factors are 1.75 and 0.25 respectively. Solid curves: the two scale factors are 1.875 and 0.125 respectively. The shape parameter α is 0.5 in all simulations. scenario, the performance of HMMDiverge is quantitatively worse than that reported in the reference simulations (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S5</ref>). In contrast, in the second set of additional simulations, α was set to 1.0, which suggested the variability of substitution rates across sites was low. In this scenario, HMMDiverge performs better than that reported in the reference simulations (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6</ref>). The results are fairly intuitive, because low variation means low noise, which in turn positively influences the performance. Thus, the variability of substitution rates does indeed influence the performance of HMMDiverge, but its influence is relatively small Page: 181 176–183</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detecting regions under functional divergence</head><p>compared with the discrepancy of substitution rates and the size of 'functional divergence relevant regions'. DIVERGE2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Zheng et al., 2007</ref>) is an existing program to identify 'functional divergence relevant sites', in which independence of substitution rates across sites is assumed. If evolutionary signals in individual sites are strong, ignoring the autocorrelation of substitution rates along sequences may not significantly reduce the power to detect sequence regions under type-I functional divergence. To compare the power of DIVERGE2 with that of HMMDiverge in the context of detecting regions under functional divergence, we applied the 'Gu99' method in DIVERGE2 to the alignments in the reference simulations. The 'Gu99' method is a fast method to identify 'type-I functional divergence relevant sites', which gave similar results as the more advanced 'Gu2001' method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Gu, 2001a</ref>). As shown in Supplementary Figures S7–S9, seldom can DIVERGE2 identify sites in 'type-I functional divergence relevant regions', since the ROC curves of DIVERGE2 are very close to the main diagonals. Therefore, at least in the reference simulations, HMMDiverge is more powerful than DIVERGE2. To compare the performance of HMMDiverge with that of DIVERGE2 in the context of identifying individual sites under functional divergence, we performed the third set of additional simulations. The simulations adopted the same set of assumptions as the reference simulations. However, the length of 'functional divergence relevant regions' was set to 1, which implies that individual sites rather than regions are units of functional divergence. Three lengths, 19, 9 and 4, were used for 'functional divergence irrelevant regions'. Besides, six pairs of branch scale factors were used (0.5 versus 1.5, 0.25 versus 1.75, 0.125 versus 1.875, 0.1 versus 5.0, 0.1 versus 10.0 and 0.1 versus 15.0). In the first three pairs, evolutionary signal in each site is weak while in the last three pairs it is strong. The Gamma shape parameter, α, was set to 0.5. In total, 18 combinations of parameters were examined. 20 alignments were generated for each combination of parameters and then both HMMDiverge and DIVERGE2 were used to identify sites under type-I functional divergence. As shown in Supplementary Figures S10 and S11, the power of HMMDiverge is very close to that of DIVERGE2 in the context of identifying individual sites under type-I functional divergence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CASE STUDY OF G PROTEIN α SUBUNITS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Parameter estimation in G protein α subunits</head><p>Heterotrimeric guanine nucleotide-binding proteins (G proteins) are a family of protein complexes important to signal transduction (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kaziro et al., 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Neer, 1995</ref>). There are three subunits in a typical G protein, a Gα subunit, a Gβ subunit and a Gγ subunit (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Cabrera-Vera et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Lambright et al., 1994</ref>). The Gα subunits, which have GTPase activity, are key factors in signal transduction pathways relevant to heterotrimeric G proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kaziro et al., 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Neer, 1995</ref>). Based on sequence similarities, Gα can be divided into four major subfamilies: Gs alpha, Gio alpha, Gq alpha and G12 alpha (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kaziro et al., 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Simon et al., 1991</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">). Zheng et al. (2007</ref>studied the functional divergence of Gα subunits in animals using their software, DIVERGE2, and detected a number of candidate sites under type-I or type-II functional divergence after the splitting of Gq alpha subunits and Gs alpha subunits.However, DIVERGE2 assumes that substitution rates are not autocorrelated along sequences. Thus, it is highly desirable to reanalyze the functional divergence in G protein α subunits using HMMDiverge and check whether the phylo-HMM could uncover any new evidence on the functional divergence of G protein α subunits. We therefore reanalyzed the data provided by<ref type="bibr">Zheng et al.</ref>(2007) and compared the results from HMMDiverge with the results reported by<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Zheng et al. (2007)</ref>. We downloaded the 16 Gq alpha protein sequences and 14 Gs alpha protein sequences analyzed by<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Zheng et al. (2007)</ref>from NCBI. To be consistent with the notation in the previous sections, Gq alpha class is labeled as Subfamily 1 while Gs alpha class is labeled as Subfamily 2. MUSCLE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Edgar, 2004</ref>) was used to align the 30 protein sequences. A maximum likelihood tree (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>in the Material) was reconstructed by PhyML (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Guindon and Gascuel, 2003</ref>) with the JTT + model. The maximum likelihood tree is essentially the same as the neighbor-joining tree reported by<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Zheng et al. (2007)</ref>, which can be divided into two subfamilies, Gq alpha subunits and Gs subunits (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). We rooted the phylogenetic tree at the middle of the longest path. Then, the maximum likelihood tree and the alignment were fed to HMMDiverge to estimate parameters and log likelihoods in both the null and the alternative (full) model. As shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>, the log likelihood ratio of the alternative model and the null model is 21.5. Hypothesis testing was performed by a parametric bootstrap. We generated 1000 alignments based on the parameters estimated in the null model and HMMDiverge was applied to these alignments. We do not find any log likelihood ratios larger than 21.5 in the 1000 simulations (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S2</ref>). Therefore, the null model can be rejected and we conclude Gq subfamily and Gs subfamily are functionally diverged. The same conclusion is attained by performing a likelihood ratio test in which we assume the log likelihood ratio follows χ 2 distribution with 3 degrees of freedom (p &lt; 0.001). We found that the χ 2 test is more conservative than the parametric bootstrap (data not shown).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Identification of regions under functional divergence</head><p>We can gain more insights on functional divergence by identifying the locations of the sequence regions relevant to functional divergence. The site-specific probabilities of the three model groups (M 0 , M 1 and M 2 ) can be calculated by HMMDiverge (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref>). To choose a reasonable cutoff for classifying sites, we generated 50 simulated alignments using parameters estimated in the full model and then applied HMMDiverge to these alignments. The ROC curve Page: 182 176–183is shown in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S3</ref>. We empirically choose 0.8 as the probability cutoff. In this case, the false positive rate is 1.6%, whereas the true positive rate is 48.2% (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S3</ref>). This cutoff is relatively conservative because typically we are less tolerant to false positives than false negatives. As shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref>, we do not find evidence of type-I functional divergence in most sites, since neither probabilities of M 1 nor those of M 2 are higher than the cutoff, 0.8, in most of sites. However, two regions do show evidence of functional divergence. The first region consists of site 80 and site 81. In this region, M 2 is strongly supported, which suggests the two sites evolve faster in Gs class. More interestingly, the second candidate region, in which M 1 is highly supported, is fairly long, ranging from site 364 to 386. As suggested by our simulations, HMMDiverge might not be able to identify short regions very well, so we focus on the second region. Deeper insights on molecular adaptation can be gained by the combination of evolutionary evidence and structure information (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Golding and Dean, 1998</ref>). We downloaded Protein Data Bank (PDB) entry 1AZS, which contains the Gq alpha subunit in Bos taurus, and then mapped the second candidate region onto chain C in PDB entry 1AZS using Jalview (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Clamp et al., 2004</ref>). The second candidate region overlaps with the α4-helix and the α4-β6 loop (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. S4</ref>). Experimental studies have suggested both the α4-helix and the α4-β6 loop are critical to mediating receptor–G protein specificity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bae et al., 1997</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bae et al., , 1999</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Cabrera-Vera et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Lee et al., 1995</ref>). The sequence region under functional divergence predicted by HMMDiverge may imply that functional divergence of receptor–G protein specificity after the splitting of Gq subfamily and Gs subfamily is related to the change of functional constraints in the α4-helix and the α4-β6 loop.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Y.-F.Huang and G.B.Golding</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Comparison with previous studies</head><p>To gain some insights on how modeling the autocorrelation of evolutionary patterns along sequences influences prediction, we compared the sites predicted by HMMDiverge to those reported by DIVERGE2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Zheng et al., 2007</ref>). Both site 80 and site 81 in the first candidate region predicted by HMMDiverge were identified by DIVERGE2 as well. However, DIVERGE2 only identified sites 362, 374, and 376 close to the second candidate region. The inability of DIVERGE2 to identify most of the sites in the second candidate region reported by HMMDiverge might be due to the weak evolutionary signal per site in this region. In turn, for thePage: 183 176–183</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detecting regions under functional divergence</head><p>existing biochemical evidence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bae et al., 1997</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bae et al., , 1999</ref><ref type="bibr">CabreraVera et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Lee et al., 1995</ref>). Most of the sites within this candidate region have not been identified by DIVERGE2, an existing program for functional divergence, which suggests HMMDiverge can identify some new candidates under functional divergence. In addition, the regions reported by HMMDiverge may not include the sites identified by DIVERGE2, because the former concentrates on regions while the latter examines only sites. We believe HMMDiverge is a useful supplement to existing methods for identifying regions under functional divergence. New insights can be gained by applying HMMDiverge to real data as we have shown in the case study of G protein α subunits.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The definition of hidden states and associated phylogenetic models. In this simple example, k = 3. The tree topologies are exactly the same in all of the hidden states, in which the left subtree corresponds to Subfamily 1, whereas the right subtree corresponds to Subfamily 2. However, the two subtrees are rescaled by different factors (relative substitution rates). In model group M 0 , there is no difference in terms of relative substitution rates. Therefore, there is no functional divergence in this case. In model group M 1 , the substitution rate is higher in Subfamily 1. In model group M 2 , the substitution rate is lower in Subfamily 1. There is functional divergence in the last two cases.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. The hierarchical parameterization of the one-step transition matrix. The number of rate categories, k, is set to 3 in this example, because it is the simplest non-trivial case. Nodes represent states or state groups while formulas beside arcs represent one-step transition probabilities. (A) transitions among three state groups (M 0 , M 1 , and M 2 ); (B) transitions conditional on staying in M 0 ; (C) transitions conditional on staying in M 1 ; (D) transitions conditional on staying in M 2 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>[17:39 20/12/2011 Bioinformatics-btr635.tex]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. The performance of HMMDiverge in the reference simulations. X axes represent false positive rates while Y axes represent true positive rates. Each row consists of the ROC curves of multiple simulations having the equal length of divergence relevant regions (L1), which are 5 aa, 10 aa, 20 aa, 50 aa, and 100 aa, increasing from top to bottom. Each column consists of the ROC curves of multiple simulations having the equal length of divergence irrelevant regions (L2), which are 50 aa, 100 aa, and 200 aa, increasing from left to right. Three types of curves represent three pairs of branch scale parameters. Dotted curves: the scale factor is 1.5 in the rapidly evolved subfamily and 0.5 in the slowly evolved subfamily. Dashed curves: the two scale factors are 1.75 and 0.25 respectively. Solid curves: the two scale factors are 1.875 and 0.125 respectively. The shape parameter α is 0.5 in all simulations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. The site-specific prediction for type-I functional divergence in G protein α subunits. The X-axis represents locations of sites, while the Y-axis represents the probability of each model group. Red dots represent model group M 1 and blue dots represent model group M 2 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><figDesc>[17:39 20/12/2011 Bioinformatics-btr635.tex]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>. 1 k for M 0 and 2 k·(k−1) for M 1 and M 2 (</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Estimation of parameters in G protein α subunits</figDesc><table>Parameter 
Estimation in null model Estimation in alternative model 

p 0 
0 a 
0.0311 
p 1 
– b 
0.153 
λ 0 
0.858 
0.944 
λ 1 
– b 
2.03×10 −5 
α 
0.808 
0.771 
Likelihood ratio −4824.28 
−4813.52 

a Fixed parameters. 
b Unused parameters. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="25"> sites under type-I functional divergence reported by DIVERGE2, 20 sites are not related to the candidate regions reported by HMMDiverge. The 20 sites may contain strong evolutionary signal so that DIVERGE2 can detect them. However, these individual sites may be too short to be detected by HMMDiverge, because the parameters estimated by HMMDiverge may mostly reflect the patterns in the long regions under functional divergence. Therefore, DIVERGE2 and HMMDiverge may uncover different aspects of type-I functional divergence after duplication. DIVERGE2 may be more powerful to detect scattered critical amino acids relevant to type-I functional divergence. In contrast, HMMDiverge may be more powerful to detect regions under divergence, and may be able to find the boundaries of these regions. Nevertheless, the long regions reported by HMMDiverge, e.g. the second candidate region, may more likely be related to functional divergence, since the parallel shift of substitution rates in multiple sites in a region is strong evidence of functional divergence. 5 DISCUSSION Here we report a customized phylo-HMM for identifying protein regions under type-I functional divergence. A C++ implementation of this phylo-HMM, HMMDiverge, has been developed. Given an alignment and a phylogenetic tree, HMMDiverge first estimates parameters by maximum likelihood estimation and then decodes the probabilities of underlying state groups by treating estimated parameters as true parameters. This is a naïve Bayesian method (Yang, 2006). In the case study of G protein α subunits, HMMDiverge needs about 1 cpu hour to finish the analysis. Therefore, it is fast enough to perform whole genomic analyses. Extensive simulations have been performed to test HMMDiverge. As shown in Figure 3, HMMDiverge can identify candidate regions under type-I functional divergence unless the discrepancy of substitution rates between two subfamilies is very limited or the regions relevant to type-I functional divergence are very short, both of which suggest that the pattern of functional divergence is weak. Since the simulated datasets were generated by a set of assumptions different from the assumptions in the phyloHMM, the phylo-HMM may be a robust method to identify regions under functional divergence. In the case study of G protein α subunits, HMMDiverge detected a long candidate region under type-I functional divergence. This long region may be important to the specific receptor–G protein interaction based on</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We are grateful to Ben Evans, Jonathon Stone, Jonathan Dushoff and three anonymous reviewers for their helpful comments on the manuscript. We thank Julien Dutheil, Sylvain Gaillard, Wilson Sung and Hui Zhao for technical help.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FunShift: a database of function shift analysis on protein subfamilies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Abhiman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Sonnhammer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale prediction of function shift in protein families with a focus on enzymatic function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Abhiman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Sonnhammer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="758" to="768" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uvpar: fast detection of functional shifts in duplicate genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Arnau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">174</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular determinants of selectivity in 5-hydroxytryptamine1b receptor-g protein interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Bae</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">272</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32071" to="32077" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two amino acids within the α4 helix of Gi1 mediate coupling with 5-Hydroxytryptamine1B receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Bae</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14963" to="14971" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximum likelihood methods for detecting adaptive evolution after gene duplication</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Bielawski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Struct. Funct. Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inferring functional constraints and divergence in protein families using 3D mapping of phylogenetic information</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Blouin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="790" to="797" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Insights into G protein structure, function, and regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Cabrera-Vera</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocrine Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="765" to="781" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlated evolution of nearby residues in drosophilid proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Callahan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1001315</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Jalview java alignment editor</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Clamp</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="426" to="427" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying dramatic selection shifts in phylogenetic trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Dorman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Biological Sequence Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Durbin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, UK.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bio++: A set of C++ libraries for sequence analysis, phylogenetics, molecular evolution and population genetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Dutheil</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">188</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Edgar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1792" to="1797" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolutionary trees from DNA sequences: a maximum likelihood approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Felsenstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="368" to="376" />
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SplitTester: Software to identify domains responsible for functional divergence in protein family</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Gao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">137</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structural basis of molecular adaptation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Golding</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Dean</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional divergence prediction from evolutionary analysis: a case study of vertebrate hemoglobin</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Gribaldo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1754" to="1759" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical methods for testing functional divergence after gene duplication</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Gu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1664" to="1674" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximum-likelihood approach for gene family evolution under functional divergence</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Gu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="453" to="464" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A site-specific measure for rate difference after gene duplication or speciation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Gu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2327" to="2330" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple statistical method for estimating Type-II (cluster-specific) functional divergence of protein sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Gu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1937" to="1945" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Guindon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Gascuel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="696" to="704" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The rapid generation of mutation data matrices from protein sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Appl. Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and function of signal-transducing GTP-binding proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Kaziro</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="400" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A likelihood ratio test for evolutionary rate shifts and functional divergence among proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Knudsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Miyamoto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14512" to="14517" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using evolutionary rates to investigate protein functional divergence and conservation: a case study of the carbonic anhydrases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Knudsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">164</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1261" to="1269" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural determinants for activation of the α-subunit of a heterotrimeric g protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Lambright</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">369</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="621" to="628" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple regions of G alpha 16 contribute to the specificity of activation by the C5a receptor</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="218" to="223" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting changes in the functional constraints of paralogous genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Marin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple method for predicting the functional differentiation of duplicate genes and its application to MIKC-type MADS-box genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Nam</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heterotrimeric G proteins: organizers of transmembrane signals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Neer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="257" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian classification of residues associated with protein functional divergence: Arf and Arf-like GTPases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Neuwald</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Direct</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">66</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Numerical Recipes in C, 2nd edn</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Press</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A covarion-based method for detecting molecular adaptation: Application to the evolution of primate mitochondrial genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Pupko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Galtier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">269</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1313" to="1316" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positive selection differs between protein secondary structure elements in Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Ridout</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="166" to="179" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The trouble with sliding windows and the selective pressure in BRCA1</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Schmid</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3746</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combining phylogenetic and hidden markov models in biosequence analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Siepel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Haussler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="413" to="428" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic hidden markov models Statistical Methods in Molecular Evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Siepel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Haussler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics for Biology and Health</title>
		<editor>Nielsen,R.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New methods for detecting lineage-specific selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Siepel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lect. Notes Comput. Sc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3909</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diversity of G proteins in signal transduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Simon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">252</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="802" to="808" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ROCR: visualizing classifier performance in R</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Sing</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3940" to="3941" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Testing for differences in rates-across-sites distributions in phylogenetic subtrees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Susko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1514" to="1523" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximum likelihood phylogenetic estimation from DNA sequences with variable rates over sites: Approximate methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="306" to="314" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A space-time process model for the evolution of DNA sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="993" to="1005" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Computational Molecular Evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximum-likelihood model averaging to profile clustering of site types across discrete linear sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Townsend</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000421</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional divergence after gene duplication and sequencestructure relationship: a case study of G-protein alpha subunits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Zheng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Zoolog. B Mol. Dev. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">308</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>