
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:44+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Inter-functional analysis of high-throughput phenotype data by non-parametric clustering and its application to photosynthesis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Qiaozi</forename>
								<surname>Gao</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Elisabeth</forename>
								<surname>Ostendorf</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Energy Plant Research Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Cruz</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Energy Plant Research Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rong</forename>
								<surname>Jin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Kramer</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Energy Plant Research Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Michigan State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>48824</postCode>
									<settlement>East Lansing</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jin</forename>
								<surname>Chen</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>jinchen@msu.edu, kramerd8@cns.msu.edu or rongjin@cse.msu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Energy Plant Research Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Inter-functional analysis of high-throughput phenotype data by non-parametric clustering and its application to photosynthesis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv515</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 12, 2015; revised on August 25, 2015; accepted on August 25, 2015</note>
					<note>Systems biology *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Availability and implementation: Software is available at www.msu.edu/~jinchen/NPM. Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online. Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Phenomics is the study of the properties and behaviors of organisms (i.e. their phenotypes) on a high-throughput scale. New computational tools are needed to analyze complex phenomics data, which consists of multiple traits/behaviors that interact with each other and are dependent on external factors, such as genotype and environmental conditions, in a way that has not been well studied. Results: We deployed an efficient framework for partitioning complex and high dimensional phenotype data into distinct functional groups. To achieve this, we represented measured phenotype data from each genotype as a cloud-of-points, and developed a novel non-parametric clustering algorithm to cluster all the genotypes. When compared with conventional clustering approaches, the new method is advantageous in that it makes no assumption about the parametric form of the underlying data distribution and is thus particularly suitable for phenotype data analysis. We demonstrated the utility of the new clustering technique by distinguishing novel phenotypic patterns in both synthetic data and a high-throughput plant photosynthetic phenotype dataset. We biologically verified the clustering results using four Arabidopsis chloroplast mutant lines.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The plummeting cost of genome sequencing has ushered genomics into a new era. However, using genomics data alone is insufficient to answer most major questions in biology, because genomics data cannot explain how genes control complex behaviors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cobb et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Shendure and Ji, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Wagner and Zhang 2013</ref>). The next wave in biology will be to phenotype organisms and then integrate genomes with phenomes to identify genes that may govern phenotype and responses to the varying environment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Butte and Kohane, 2006</ref>). Especially, progress in phenotyping technologies is required to accelerate genetic mapping and gene discovery in genome-wide association studies for dissecting the genetic architecture of important traits underlying phenotypes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Yang et al., 2014</ref>). It thus is important to develop computational methods to examine potentially interacting phenotypes (i.e. measurable traits/behaviors) of a genetically diverse population for a given species in order to identify meaningful differences in biological function. The database PhenomicDB has been built to collect phenotypes of multiple species in free-text format with the goal to gain insights into the genetic origin of diseases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Groth et al., 2007</ref>). Phenoclustering was then V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com proposed to perform meta-analysis on PhenomicDB using advanced natural language processing methods, resulting in clusters of genes by the similarity of their phenotypes that can be further explored for genotype–phenotype interaction analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Groth et al., 2010</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Groth et al., , 2011</ref>). However, since high-throughput phenotyping quantitatively assesses multiple phenotypes of many traits simultaneously, it often generates a large amount of data rather than qualitative descriptions. New approaches to analyze quantitative phenomics data are needed. One application is in bioenergy research, where computational techniques have been developed to detect, collect and study photosynthesis and related traits, such as growth, under non-laboratory conditions and in high throughput (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Cruz et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Tessmer et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Xu et al., 2015</ref>). In general, photosynthesis phenotypes can be altered in two ways, either through the changes of peripheral processes of the photosynthesis regulatory network or the modification of central components of the network (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Diner and Rappaport, 2002</ref>). Changes in peripheral processes tend to preserve regulatory relationships within the network. In contrast, altering the central components of photosynthesis is likely to perturb the relationships between key regulatory processes, leading to a different correlation among photosynthesis phenotypes. In this study, we focus on data analysis for the second case, to which we refer as inter-functional analysis for photosynthesis phenotypes data. By taking advantage of the systematic knockout of genes encoding chloroplast-targeted proteins in Arabidopsis thaliana, a model plant, we have conducted a large-scale phenotype screen on the single knockouts and the references to understand the underlying molecular functions of the knockout genes in plant photosynthesis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Cruz et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Lu et al., 2011</ref>). In our experiment, plants with single gene knockouts have been profiled by non-invasively measuring three key photosynthetic parameters, i.e. / II , q E and q I (that reflect photosynthesis efficiency in photosystem II, active energy dissipation, and photoinhibition, respectively), in response to fluctuating light conditions, resulting in a large volume of plant phenotyping data that allow us to determine the downstream effects of the knockout genes on photosynthesis in dynamic conditions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kramer and Evans, 2011</ref>). More specifically, multiple fluorescence images (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1a</ref>) are taken for every plant as the light intensity is varied over time and the photosynthesis parameters (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>) are derived from each image. As a result, each plant is characterized by a sequence of three-dimensional vectors with each dimension corresponding to a different photosynthesis parameter. The objective of this study is to automatically identify gene groups with their photosynthesis phenotypes significantly different from reference based on the collected data. A natural first step is to examine the extremes, i.e. mutant lines that exhibit significantly different photosynthesis characters from the wild type in all of the three photosynthesis parameters. Although this simple technique has been shown to be effective for identifying potential biomarkers and drug targets, it is not an effective approach for exploiting the full potential of experimental results (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Eisen et al., 1998</ref>). In this work, we take a holistic approach for inter-functional photosynthesis data analysis. We develop an efficient workflow to effectively identify novel phenotypes based on mutant lines sharing similar measurements of photosynthesis parameters. The identified gene groups and their associated phenotypes are used to derive insight into the functions of and interactions between related genes. Based on existing annotations and literature for the well-studied genes, we can associate biological processes with each phenotype pattern, which in turn can be used to reveal the functions for the poorly characterized genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Jaqaman et al., 2007</ref>). Although numerous clustering algorithms have been developed, most of them require vector representation of data and thus cannot be applied directly to our problem where each plant is represented by a sequence of vectors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bar-Joseph, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">McNicholas and Murphy, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Nascimento et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Qian et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Schliep et al., 2003</ref>). One simple way to handle the challenge is to run standard clustering algorithms (e.g. k-means and hierarchical clustering) against all the vectors measured for different plants, and determine the cluster member for each plant by taking the major vote among the measured vectors. Another approach is to concatenate the sequence of vectors measured for each plant into a single vector, and apply standard clustering algorithms to the derived vectors. The main problem with these two approaches is that they are unable to effectively explore the correlation among different photosynthesis parameters revealed by the set of vectors measured for each plant. This is particularly important for photosynthesis data analysis because it is the correlation between photosynthesis parameters that helps understand the regulatory role of the mutated genes on the photosynthesis processes. We propose to address the above challenges of phenotype data analysis by developing a novel clustering technique named Non-parametric modeling, or NPM for short. We introduce a<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>. The process of extracting data from photosynthesis phenotype experiment. (a) a series of fluorescence images, (b) the derived photosynthesis parameters (/ II Â light, q E , q I ) for two genotypes, i.e. mutant line AT3G17830 and the wild type (used as reference) under dynamic environmental conditions, (c) the photosynthesis parameters of the same plants in 3D space. / II Â light refers to a more advanced photosynthesis parameter named Linear Electron Flux cloud-of-points representation for each mutant line, with each point corresponding to a vector in the sequential phenotype measurements taken for the mutant line, where the correlation among photosynthesis parameters is captured by the 'shapes' of clouds. Based on the theory of kernel density estimation (KDE), we then apply a nonparametric clustering technique to group plants into the same cluster if their clouds share similar shapes (<ref type="bibr">Cybakov, 2009</ref>). When compared with the existing clustering algorithms, the key advantage of NPM is that it does not make any assumption about the underlying data distribution and thus is particularly suitable for phenotype data analysis. Our empirical study shows promising results of the proposed clustering technique on both synthetic and real photosynthesis datasets. We have biologically verified the clustering results using four Arabidopsis mutant lines for nuclear encoded chloroplast proteins. The experimental results demonstrate that NPM is able to generate testable hypotheses, which lead to new biological discoveries. We emphasize that although our empirical study is limited to photosynthesis data, the non-parametric clustering algorithm developed in this work is general and can be applied to other domains (e.g. gene expression data analysis).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Related work</head><p>Clustering algorithms have been widely used in biological data analysis. One well known example is gene expression clustering (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Eisen et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Herwig, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Tamayo et al., 1999</ref>). Numerous clustering algorithms have been designed to exploit temporal correlations and trends in gene expression time series (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bar-Joseph 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">BarJoseph et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Costa et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Qian et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">McNicholas and Murphy, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Nascimento et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Ramoni et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Schliep et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sivriver et al., 2011</ref>). Clustering algorithms have also been successfully applied to biological network analysis, which aims to discover and identify gene functional groups (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Cingovska et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Wang et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Wu et al., 2002</ref>), and to sequence analysis [e.g. sequence alignment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Corpet, 1988</ref>), motif detection (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Lones and Tyrrell, 2007</ref>) and protein/DNA sequence clustering (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Enright and Ouzounis, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Li and Godzik, 2006)]</ref>. Most previous studies of clustering algorithms in biological data analysis are based on parametric models (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bakar and Watada, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Ben-Dor et al., 1999</ref>). In contrast, the proposed method adopts nonparametric density estimation for data clustering that does not make parametric assumptions about the underlying distribution. A well-known non-parametric clustering method is mean-shift (Carreira-Perpiñ a ´ n,<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Comaniciu, 2002</ref>), which is widely used in computer vision and image processing. Other examples of nonparametric clustering are the scale-space method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Roberts, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Wilson and Spann, 1990</ref>) and spectral clustering (<ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Von Luxburg, 2007</ref>). The scale-space clustering method was pioneered in<ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Wilson and Spann (1990)</ref>, and further studied in Roberts (1997) using density estimation. Spectral clustering is mostly based on the theory of manifold learning (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Ma and Fu, 2012</ref>), and has been widely used for image segmentation. However, since most non-parametric clustering algorithms require vector representation of data, they cannot be applied directly to our problem. The theoretical foundation of the proposed work is based on KDE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Parzen, 1962;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Rosenblatt, 1956</ref>). KDE was first introduced in the 1950s (<ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Rosenblatt, 1956</ref>). The consistency of KDE was shown initially in Parzen (1962) and its convergence rate for finite samples was later proved (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Nadaraya, 1965;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Stute, 1982</ref>). A more complete literature review for KDE can be found in Cybakov (2009).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Non-parametric clustering for phenotypic data analysis</head><p>In this work, we develop a novel clustering algorithm NPM for inter-functional phenotype data analysis. Below, we will present phenotype data representation and framework of non-parametric clustering, and then describe an efficient algorithm for solving the related optimization problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Data representation</head><p>The center of NPM is a cloud-of-points representation. Let M 1 ;. .. ; M m be a collection of m genotypes. Let p be the number of photosynthesis parameters. For each genotype M i , we denote by x i 1 ;. .. ; x i ni the sequence of multi-dimensional vectors measured for M i , where n i is the number of valid measurements for M i and each x i j 2 R p includes the measurements of p photosynthesis parameters derived from the jth measurement for M i. Because the focus of this study is to examine the dependence among different photosynthesis parameters, we will ignore the sequential order among vectors fx i j g ni j¼1 and simply characterize the photosynthesis property of genotype M i by the set of data points D i ¼ fx i 1 ;. .. ; x i ni g, which we refer to as cloud-of-points representation.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1c</ref>shows examples of the cloud-of-points representation for the sequence of / II , q E and q I measurements that are given in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1b</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">A framework for non-parametric clustering</head><p>Following the standard framework of mixture models (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">McLachlan and Peel, 2004</ref>), we assume that there are K different underlying distributions, where each distribution is introduced to capture a different 'shape' of the cloud-of-points representation, and all the data points observed in the cloud-of-points representation are drawn independently from one of the K distributions. More specifically, let f 1 ðÁÞ;. .. ; f K ðÁÞ be the density functions for the K underlying distributions, and let P ¼ ðP 1 ;. .. ; P K Þ be the prior probabilities for choosing each distribution. Then, for mutant line M i , the likelihood of observing the cloud-of-points representation</p><formula>D i ¼ fx i j g ni j¼1</formula><p>is then given by</p><formula>PrðD i Þ ¼ X K j¼1 P j PrðD i jf j Þ ¼ X K j¼1 P j Y nj k¼1 f j ðx i k Þ:</formula><formula>(1)</formula><p>Following the framework of maximum likelihood estimation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Scholz, 1985</ref>), we find the optimal density functions ff j ðÁÞg K j¼1 by solving the optimization problem</p><formula>max f1;...;fK;P X m j¼1 logPrðD i Þ (2)</formula><p>where PrðD i Þ is given in Equation (1). The main challenge arises from solving the optimization problem in<ref type="bibr">Equation (2)</ref>, in which the variables to be optimized are functions (or vectors of infinite dimension). This is in contrast to most optimization problems where the variables are of finite dimension (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fletcher, 2013</ref>). The type of optimization problem in Equation (2) is often referred to as variational optimization in the literature of operations research. One simple approach towards variational optimization is to make specific assumptions about the density functions ff j ðÁÞg K j¼1 , a common approach adopted in the study of mixture models (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">McLachlan and Peel, 2004</ref>). In the simple approach, a parametric family of distributions, e.g. the well-known Gaussian mixture model, is specified assuming that each f j ðÁÞ is a Gaussian Inter-functional analysis of high-throughput phenotype datadistribution. However, this simple approach could be problematic in our study, since the complicated shaped cloud-of-points representation (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4</ref>) may not fit well to any member in the specified distribution family. Therefore, we adopt the non-parametric density estimation approach, because the key advantage of non-parametric approach is that it avoids the parametric assumption of the underlying distribution (<ref type="bibr">Cybakov, 2009</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Efficient computational algorithm</head><p>We propose to solve the optimization problem in Equation (2) by exploring the theory of KDE. Our approach is based on the Nadaraya-Watson method for density estimation (<ref type="bibr">Cybakov, 2009</ref>). More specifically, let ^ x 1 ;. .. ; ^ x ' be the ' landmark points, where landmark points are randomly sampled from the collection of data points for all mutant lines. Using the landmark points, we approximate each density function f j as:</p><formula>f j ðxÞ ¼ 1 ' Â X ' q¼1 a q j jðx À ^ x q Þ (3)</formula><p>where a j ¼ ða 1 j ;. .. ; a ' j Þ are parameters to be determined for f j , jðxÞ ¼ ðph 2 Þ Àp=2 expðÀjxj 2 =h 2 Þ is a multi-variate Gaussian distribution and h is the kernel bandwidth. Since f j is a density function, we have a q j !0;</p><formula>q 2 ½1; ' and P ' q¼1 a q j ¼ a &gt; j 1 ¼ 1</formula><p>, where 1 is a vector of all ones. Using the approximation in (3), the likelihood function PrðD i Þ is rewritten as:</p><formula>PrðD i Þ ¼ X K j¼1 P j Y nj k¼1 1 ' X ' q¼1 a q j jðx i k À ^ x q Þ ! : (4)</formula><p>We can approximate the variational optimization problem in</p><p>Equation (2) into the following normal optimization problem:</p><formula>max a1;...;aK;P Lðfa i g K i¼1 ; PÞ ¼ X m i¼1 logPrðD i Þ (5)</formula><p>where a 1 ;. .. ; a K 2 fa j 2 R p þ : a &gt; 1 ¼ 1g and PrðD i Þ is given in (4). We developed an EM algorithm to efficiently optimize the objective function in Equation (5). For each mutant line M i , we introduce a hidden variable Z i 2 ½K to indicate which cluster (or density function) M i belongs to. In the E-step, we estimate the posterior probability PrðZ i ¼ jjD i Þ as:</p><formula>PrðZ i ¼ jjD i Þ / P j Y nj k¼1 X ' q¼1 a q j jðx i k À ^ x q Þ (6)</formula><p>In the M-step, we update the prior probabilities P and parameters fa j g K j¼1 by:</p><formula>P j ¼ 1 n X m i¼1 PrðZ i ¼ jjD i Þ (7) a q j / X n i¼1 PrðZ i ¼ jjD i Þ X nj k¼1 ~ a q j jðx i k À ^ x q Þ P ' q 0 ¼1 ~ a q 0 j jðx i k À ^ x q 0 Þ (8)</formula><p>where ~ a 1 ;. .. ; ~ a K are parameters obtained in the previous iteration of EM algorithm. Algorithm 1 highlights the key steps of our EM algorithm. In line 2–5, data are first normalized to prevent large measurement dominating others. In line 7, the landmark points are sampled. Then, the EM iteration part is in line 9–17. E-and M-step are repeated until the log-likelihood converges. The output are K density functions f 1 ;. .. ; f K. Each mutant line is assigned to one density function that contributes the largest likelihood to its data points.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>shows how the log-likelihood function Lðfa i g K i¼1 ; PÞ is improved over iterations, when running our EM algorithm on photosynthesis data (see details in Section 4). Because it is wellknown that an EM algorithm could be trapped in a bad local optimum, we run Algorithm 1 multiple times and choose the solution with the largest log-likelihood.the kth photosynthesis parameter 4: Normalize the kth photosynthesis measures to ½0; 1 by subtracting them by minimum value and dividing them by the difference between maximum and minimum value 5: end for 6: // Select landmark points 7: Randomly sample ' data points from the collection of data points for all mutant lines, denoted by ^ x 1 ;. .. ; ^ x ' 8: // EM algorithm 9: Initialize ~ a 1 ;. .. ; ~ a K with numbers randomly chosen from ½0; 1 10: Initialize ~ L ¼ À1 and DL ¼ þ1 11: while DL &gt; e do 12: Update posterior probability PrðZ j ¼ kjD j Þ using (6) for every mutant line M j and every cluster k 13: Update the coefficients a 1 ;. .. ; a K using (8) and P using (7) 14: Set ~ a j ¼ a j ; j ¼ 1;. .. ; K 15: Compute the log-likelihood, L ¼ P m i¼1 logPrðD i jFÞ 16: Update DL ¼ L À ~ L and ~ L ¼ L 17: end while Return f 1 ;. .. ; f K with f j ðxÞ ¼ P ' q¼1 a q j jðx À ^ x q Þ=' One fundamental assumption of NPM is that density function f j ðÁÞ can be approximated by Equation (3). Theoretic study of KDE can easily show that any smooth bounded density function can be well approximated by<ref type="bibr">Equation (3)</ref>provided that the number of sampled landmark data points ' is sufficiently large. Please refer to Theorem S1 in Supplementary Material. We finally note that the density functions for most well-known distributions (e.g. Gaussianand Laplacian distributions) are smooth and bounded, and thus assuming density functions to be smooth and bounded is a very minor assumption in real-world applications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Experiments</head><p>For performance evaluation, we compared NPM with a series of baselines that adopt two different data representation methods other than the cloud-of-point representation used in NPM. The first method is to use concatenated vectors, i.e. concatenating the set of data vectors measured for each genotype into a single vector, and then applying to the derived vectors three standard clustering algorithms: (i) k-means (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">MacQueen, 1967</ref>) (Kmeans), (ii) hierarchical clustering (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Johnson, 1967</ref>) (Hierarchy) and (iii) using principal component analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Jolliffe, 1986</ref>) to reduce the dimensionality of the concatenated vectors and then applying k-means (PCA þ Kmeans), where the reduced dimensionality was set to 3 in our experiments. The second data representation method is to simply use the original vectors: clustering all the vectors measured for different genotypes, and then determining the cluster membership for each genotype by taking the majority vote among the vectors measured for that genotype. Two baseline algorithms were developed based on this method: (i) applying k-means to all the measured vectors (Kmeans-split) and (ii) applying Gaussian mixture model to all the measured vectors (GMM-split). Except for the number of clusters K, there are three parameters to be specified in NPM: the stopping criterion for EM process, the kernel bandwidth h for KDE and the number of landmark points '. Within a cross-validation dataset (see Section 4.2 for details), a grid search was applied to find the best kernel bandwidth h that resulted in the maximal log-likelihood. A similar approach is applied to determine the number of landmark points '. For parameter , we simply set ¼ 1 in our experiment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Plant photosynthesis phenotyping experiment</head><p>Photosynthesis involves the net movement of electrons generated from the oxidation of water through a series of electron carriers to a chemical reductant NADPH (LEF, linear electron flux). These reactions are driven by light energy that is funneled to two chlorophyll containing complexes, Photosystem II (PSII) which extracts electrons from water and Photosystem I (PSI) which donates electrons to the terminal acceptor Ferredoxin and ultimately NADPþto form NADPH. Electron transfer between PSII and PSI is essentially connected by the cytochrome b6f complex (cyt b 6 f ) and mobile electron carriers, plastoquinone/plastoquinol (PQ/PQH 2 ) and plastocyanin. LEF is tightly coupled to the formation of an electrochemical proton gradient (pmf, proton motive force) between the lumen (inner thylakoid compartment) and the stroma. First, the oxidation of water by PSII releases protons into the lumen. Second, during the sequential reduction of PQ to PQH 2 in the stroma-localized quinone binding sites of PSII and b 6 f , protons are taken from the stroma and are released into the lumen upon oxidation of PQH 2 to PQ at the lumen-localized quinol binding site on cyt b 6 f. Pmf has an electric field component (Dw) and a chemical gradient component (DpH), which are thermodynamically equivalent but kinetically separable. Its dissipation through the chloroplast ATP synthase is coupled to the phosphorylation of ADP to form ATP. The amplitude of pmf depends on the rate of proton accumulation and on the resistance (inverse of the proton conductivity, gH þ ) of the chloroplast ATP synthase to proton flux. Both NADPH (reducing power) and ATP (chemical bond energy) are used by downstream metabolism, primarily the fixation of carbon dioxide into sugars. The formation of high energy states and reactive intermediates during photosynthesis can lead to damage to the photosystems (photoinhibition) and/or formation of reactive oxygen species. Indeed, photoinhibited PSII centers accumulate in a light intensity dependent manner and have been linked to the long-lived component of nonphotochemical quenching (q I ). However, LEF is self-regulating; as excitation pressure increases, electron transfer slows (in effect photosynthetic efficiency, / II , decreases) and excess is energy actively dissipated (quenching increases) to minimize the accumulation of reduced intermediates. More specifically, the DpH component of pmf (acidification of the lumen) slows the oxidation of PQH2 at cyt b 6 f and at the same time induces two pH sensitive components of q E quenching. Under stress, inhibition of LEF may limit the formation of pmf. For example, under severe CO 2 limitation, as the acceptor pool (NADPþ) diminishes in the absence of carbon fixation, LEF will slow to a rate that cannot support a significant DpH. In such cases, a higher DpH can be sustained by:</p><p>(i) alternative pathways that supplement proton uptake such as cyclic electron flux, (ii) increasing the fraction of pmf stored as DpH, and/or 3) decreasing proton conductivity through the ATP synthase, gH þ [as reviewed in<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baker (2008)</ref>;<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Kramer et al. (2004)]</ref>. In our experiment, we screened a total of 338 chloroplast-targeted single mutant lines in A. thaliana. To ensure the reliability of the results, multiple biological replicates (four or more) were examined for each mutant line, so the total number of plants added up to 1, 499, which is also the number of instances used in follow-up analysis. A sample of the phenotype dataset is available at Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>. For each plant, three photosynthesis parameters (/ II , q E and q I ) were measured (P ¼ 3 for our algorithm). The photosynthetic parameter, U II (quantum yield of photochemistry), when multiplied by the ambient light intensity (light) yields a quantity proportional to the LEF rate. The quenching parameters, q E (rapidly relaxing in the dark, Dph dependent) and q I (slowing relaxing, related to photoinhibition), are two separate photoprotective mechanisms that dissipate excess light energy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Cruz et al., 2015</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Clustering results using NPM</head><p>Given the photosynthesis phenotype data, we adopted the crossvalidation method suggested in Smyth (2000) to decide the number of clusters K. We used 3-fold cross-validation, i.e. at each time, NPM was fit on two thirds of the data (as training set), and the likelihood of the fitted model on the remaining one third data (as test set) was computed. Higher log-likelihood means that the model is better fitted to data.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>shows that when K is larger or equal to 3, the cross-validation likelihood is near its maximum value. Therefore, we set K to be 3. Subsequently, three clusters of plants were identified by NPM. For the convenience of visualization, we plotted the clustering results in 2D spaces, with coordinates corresponding to twoInter-functional analysis of high-throughput phenotype dataparameters each time (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4</ref>). To better understand the overall properties of each cluster, we focus on the q E versus (/ II Â light) plot in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4a</ref>. For all plants, changes in q E and (/ II Â light) are positively correlated with the changes in light intensity. The clustering results of the sampled phenotype dataset are available at Supplementary Table S2. The first cluster (green) in this plot contains 87% of plants, including all the wild type plants. We refer to it as the cluster of wt-like. When compared with the other two clusters, the wt-like cluster exhibits a stronger correlation between q E and (/ II Â light), which reflects the sigmoidal relationship between the DpH component of pmf generated by photosynthetic electron flux and lumen pH-dependent processes required for q E quenching, i.e. violaxanthin deepoxidase activation and PsbS protonation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Takizawa et al., 2007</ref>). When compared with the first cluster, the mutant lines in the second cluster (red) tend to have significantly higher q E sensitivity to electron flux, suggesting that in these mutant lines pmf builds to a larger extent due to more restricted proton flux through the ATP synthase lower gH þ ) or that the fraction of pmf stored as DpH is larger. We refer to it as the cluster of qE-sensitive. On the other hand, mutant lines in the third cluster (blue) show normal (/ II Â light) values but significantly lower q E values than the wt-like cluster, indicating that these mutant lines may lack the capacity to accumulate a significant DpH or other biochemical components essential for q E. We refer to it as the cluster of low-q E. Similar phenotype partition can be found in the q I À (/ II Â light) space (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4b</ref>) and q I À q E space (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4c</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Performance evaluation</head><p>Because a significant portion of the chloroplast-targeted proteins have unknown functions, the optimal gene grouping is unknown, making it difficult to directly measure the clustering performance of NPM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Lamesch et al., 2012</ref>). To perform objective evaluation of the clustering results, we computed the gene-to-gene similarities based on the clustering result, denoted as photosynthesis phenotype-based similarity (PPS). In parallel, we derived another kind of gene-to-gene similarity score based on the biological knowledge from metabolic pathways or existing gene expression data, denoted as extra information-based similarity (EIS). We then measured how well the two sets of similarities are aligned with each other. Our assumption is that a good clustering result of mutant lines should lead to a PPS that well aligns with the EIS. Below we describe the computation of PPS and EIS, respectively. For each mutant line, there are at least four biological replicates and each replicate may be grouped into a different cluster. By taking the average of the cluster membership vectors for the replicates, we derived a three dimensional vector representation z i for each mutant line M i. The PPS between any two mutant lines M i and M j was then computed as the similarity between their vector representations:</p><formula>PPSðM i ; M j Þ ¼ z &gt; i z j : (9)</formula><p>The biological knowledge base AraCyc (<ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Zhang et al., 2010</ref>), (a manually curated database providing the metabolic pathway information for 46 out of the 338 genes in our study) was used as the extra information. More precisely, two genes form a similar gene pair if they are in the same metabolic pathway and we get a total number of 91 similar gene pairs. Therefore two mutant lines have a high EIS value if they form a similar gene pair: EIS ¼ ( 1; ðM i ; M j Þ 2 similar gene pairs 0; otherwise :</p><formula>(10)</formula><p>Next, we measure how well the PPS is aligned with the EIS derived from AraCyc. For each mutant line M i that appears in the similar gene pairs, we ranked all the other genes in descending order of their PPS with M i , and recorded the percentage of the AraCycbased similar gene pairs that were recovered by the top ranked genes with the cutoff rank varied from 10 to 100. Based on our assumption, the larger the percentage of recovered similar gene pairs, the better the clustering result will be.</p><formula>(b) (a)</formula><formula>2D spaces: (a) q E À (/ II Â light) space, (b) q I À (/ II Â light) space, (c) q I À q E space</formula><p>included in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5a</ref>the result of random selection for each mutant line as the baseline (highlighted by a dashed line). It shows that the performance of NPM is significantly better than the other clustering methods and the random ranking (Kolmogorov-Smirnov test, see P-values in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Press et al., 1992</ref>). Because the EIS computed using AraCyc only covers a portion of the genes in our study, we repeated the same evaluation steps with the gene co-expression scores in the ATTED-II database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Obayashi et al., 2011</ref>). Although gene co-expression data is not as accurate as manually curated data, it includes most of the genes in our study, and has been well recognized as a reliable source for performance evaluation (Harr and Schlö tterer, 2006). We used the mutual rank (MR) scores to compute EIS from ATTED-II. More specifically, we set the threshold of MR to be 20, and gene pairs with MR scores above this threshold are considered to be ATTED-based similar gene pairs. We get a total number of 465 similar gene pairs. The results in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5b</ref>indicate that the clustering result generated by NPM has a better correlation with the biological similarities derived from transcriptional co-expressions than the other clustering methods. A Kolmogorov-Smirnov test verifies that NPM is statistically significantly better than all baselines with a significance level of 0.01 on the ATTED-II database (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). In summary, the performance evaluations using both the metabolic pathways and the gene co-expression values show that the clustering result generated by NPM better correlates with external biological information than the other clustering methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Biological significance</head><p>We examined the biological significance of selected clustering results, as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>. Dozens of interesting mutant lines were discovered from the inter-functional clustering analysis. As a demonstration, we discuss two mutant lines in the following text. The first one is cfq (AT3G24530; coupling factor quick recovery). The cfq mutant line harbors a point mutation on the gamma subunit of the chloroplast ATP synthase, which alters its regulation. In our analysis, cfq belongs to the qE-sensitive cluster (red) which showed lower values of both / II and q E than wild type. This phenotype is consistent with excess enzymatic activity of the chloroplast ATP synthesis (high gH þ ), which minimizes pmf formation and subsequently the capacity for photoprotection via the q E mechanism and the ability to slow electron transfer through the cyt b6f complex. Consequently, Photosystem I in these plants is more susceptible to photodamage particularly under fluctuating light, as confirmed by independent biochemical and spectroscopical methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Wu et al., 2007</ref>). The second example is the t-DNA insertion line AT1G44575 (npq4) of the pigment-binding protein PsbS. It is associated with photosystem II antenna complexes of higher plants and part of the qE mechanism. In our data, the mutant line had normal / II but very low q E. Its biased distribution was assigned by NPM to the low-qE cluster (blue). This is reasonable because it is an essential component of the qE mechanism, but does not affect the regulation of lightinduced electron transfer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Lamesch et al., 2012</ref>). These two examples demonstrate that the clustering approach can distinguish mutant lines with overlapping effects on multiple phenotypes. In this case, both cfq and npq4 showed low q E but had distinct effects on electron transfer. We observe in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4a</ref>that the mutant lines in the qE-sensitive cluster have restricted proton flux through the ATP synthase, resulting in high q E sensitivity, and the mutant lines in the low-qE cluster (blue) have low quenching capacity, causing significantly low q E but normal / II values. Therefore, we hypothesize that skew from the wtlike cluster in the q E versus (/ II Â light) plot may be used as an indicator for altered activity or regulation of the ATP-synthase. To verify the hypothesis, we chose four function unknown mutant lines from the cluster results with the most distinct phenotypes to further explore the relationships among multiple photosynthesis parameters. From the qE-sensitive cluster, we chose the lines SALK 106162 and SALK 072581, which are T-DNA insertion mutagen of AT2G29180 and AT4G33520, respectively. AT4G33520 encodes a putative metal-transporting P-type ATPase, and is involved in copper ion transmembrane transport. AT2G29180 is a function unknown chloroplast-targeted protein. From the low-qE cluster, we chose SALK 114469, a T-DNA insertion mutagen of AT1G79040, which encodes for the PsbR subunit of photosystem II. For comparison, we also chose SALK 044616 (AT1G65230) from the wild-type like cluster. We first repeated / II and q E measurements under several light intensities using an Integrated Diode Emitter Array (IDEA) spectrophotometer, which also allows high-resolution absorbance measurements of other photosynthetic parameters that are not yet possible to perform using high throughput methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hall et al., 2013</ref>).<ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>shows the re-measured plants have the same relationships between q E and (/ II Â light) as our high-throughput phenotype values, indicating the reproducibility of our data is high. We also measured proton-flux across the thylakoid membrane, thus the ATP-synthase activity using the same device (<ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>). As expected, wt-like candidate shows no difference in ATP synthase activity compared with wild type (Col-0). Both candidates from the qE-sensitive cluster have a decreased proton-flux, vH þ , compared with wild type. The lower proton conductivity, gH þ , compared with wild-type, observed in SALK 072581 is consistent with downregulation of ATP synthase activity to limit proton flux and favor pmf formation. Contrary to expectations, SALK 106162 shows marginally higher gH þ despite lower vH þ , consistent with lower steady state pmf in this mutant compared with wild-type. In this case, the sensitivity of the q E response may be due either an increase in the fraction of pmf stored as DpH or increased sensitivity of the quenching response to lumen pH. The candidate from the low-qE cluster showed similar proton flux rates and conductivities compared with wild type, indicating the loss of q E may be due to other factors, e.g. a decrease in DpH=pmf ratio or loss of a component that influences quenching efficiency. In summary, the behavior of the distinctInter-functional analysis of high-throughput phenotype dataclusters relative to the wt-like cluster may be indicative of the functions (or loss of function) responsible for the phenotype.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Experimental results for simulated data</head><p>In the second experiment, we created a synthesized dataset with 120 instances. The cloud-of-points representation for each instance M i is generated as follows: we randomly chose two out of the three Gaussian distributions (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8a</ref>), and sampled n data points from the two Gaussians, where n is varied from 20, 30 to 40. There are totally 3 classes, i.e. Gaussian 1&amp;2, Gaussian 2&amp;3 and Gaussian 1&amp;3. For example, if the two chosen distributions are Gaussian 1 and Gaussian 2, we label this instance M i as Gaussian 1&amp;2. The synthetic dataset is available at Supplementary Table S3. We measured the clustering performance by Normalized Mutual Information (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Priness et al., 2007</ref>) defined as NMIðX; CÞ ¼ 2IðX; CÞ=ðHðXÞ þ HðCÞÞ, where X is the ground truth class label partition, C is the data partition generated by a clustering algorithm, IðX; CÞ measures the mutual information between the two partitions, and HðXÞ and H(C) measure the entropy of the two partitions, respectively.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8b</ref>summarizes the clustering performance for NPM and baseline algorithms. As expected, we observed that the clustering performance of all algorithms improves with increasing number of samples. We also observe that NPM significantly outperforms the baseline algorithms. The poor performance of Kmeans-split and GMM-split suggests that applying clustering algorithms directly to the measured vectors is not appropriate for the cloud-of-points representation. The fact that PCA þ Kmeans does not significantly outperform Kmeans suggests that blind dimensionality reduction may not be sufficient for handling high dimensionality in data clustering.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusion</head><p>Sophisticated phenomics measurements are becoming increasingly important for the discovery of important biological functions and genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bilder et al., 2009</ref>). Due to the complexity of phenomics datasets, the conventional clustering approaches often fail to identify genes of distinguished functions because they have to make parametric assumptions about the underlying data distribution. There is thus an urgent need for new tools to analyze large and complex phenomics datasets. The NPM method presented here represents an important advance over existing clustering algorithms because it avoids the parametric assumption of data distribution. A demonstration of our method on plant photosynthesis data shows that the proposed technique is effective in capturing mutant lines with similar photosynthesis profiles in comparison to the conventional clustering algorithms such as k-means and hierarchical clustering. In the future, we plan to further improve our analysis by (i) conducting biochemical experiments to validate novel genes with the new phenotypes, and<ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref>. Experimental verification of the gene groups identified by NPM. The proton flux vH þ and the voltage-gated proton conductance gH þ was determined for the four selected t-DNA insertion mutant lines compared with wild type (Col-0). S ALK 106162 and SALK 072581 are from the qE-sensitive cluster, SALK 044616 is from the wild-type like cluster, and SALK 114469 is from the low-qE cluster<ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref>Verification of the photosynthetic parameters for wild type (Col-0, used as the reference) and four t-DNA insertion mutant lines selected from the NPM clustering results. Measurement of q E and LEF was repeated (proportional to U II Â light) using an IDEA spectrophotometer. SALK 106162 and SAL K 072581 are from the qE-sensitive cluster. SALK 044616 is from the wildtype like cluster. SALK 114469 is from the low-qE cluster</p><formula>(c) ( d)</formula><formula>(e) ( f) (g)</formula><p>(ii) developing new clustering algorithms that also take into account the sequential order among photosynthesis measurements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Algorithm1.</head><figDesc>EM algorithm for non-parametric clustering Input: Cloud-of-points representation for mutant lines D 1 ;. .. ; D m , the number of photosynthesis parameters p, the kernel bandwidth h, the number of landmark points ', the number of clusters K, and the stop criterion. 1: // Normalize data points 2: for k ¼ 1;. .. ; p do 3: Compute the minimum and maximum values for</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Increase in log-likelihood against iteration number when running EM algorithm</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Cross-validation likelihood of different number of clusters on photosynthesis phenotype data</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><figDesc>Figure 5a summarizes the percentage of similar gene pairs recovered by different clustering algorithms using AraCyc. We alsoPercentage of recovered gene pairs Comparison to AraCyc database (metabolic pathways) Comparison to ATTED-II database (gene co-expressions)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.5</head><figDesc>Fig. 5 Evaluation results of different clustering algorithms for the photosynthesis data based on the percentage of recovered similar gene pairs (vertical axis) derived from databases AraCyc (a) and ATTED-II (b). The horizontal axis is the cutoff ranking position that is varied from 10 to 100. The dashed line represents the results of random selection</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Three clusters of Arabidopsis chloroplast mutant lines identified by NPM on the plant photosynthesis phenotype data. The data points are plotted in 2D spaces: (a) q E À (/ II Â light) space, (b) q I À (/ II Â light) space, (c) q I À q E space</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><figDesc>( h) SALK-106162 vs. Col-0 (vH+) SALK-072581 vs. Col-0 (vH+) SALK-044616 vs. Col-0 (vH+) SALK-114469 vs. Col-0 (vH+) SALK-114469 vs. Col-0 (gH+) SALK-044616 vs. Col-0 (gH+) SALK-072581 vs. Col-0 (gH+) SALK-106162 106162 vs. Col-0 (gH+)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig.8.</head><figDesc>Fig. 8. The three Gaussian distributions used in the simulated experiment and the clustering results for NPM and five baseline clustering methods</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Results of Kolmogorov-Smirnov test on the photosynthesis data using extra information derived from databases AraCyc and ATTED-II</figDesc><table>Database 
Eval. criterion 
Kmeans 
Hierarchy 
PCA þ Kmeans 
Kmeans-split 
GMM-split 
Random selection 

AraCyc 
Same pathway 
9:4 Â 10 À10 
1:5 Â 10 À14 
5:7 Â 10 À9 
1:7 Â 10 À9 
4:0 Â 10 À29 
1:9 Â 10 À50 
ATTED-II 
Co-expression 
1:3 Â 10 À5 
1:2 Â 10 À10 
4:7 Â 10 À8 
2:0 Â 10 À21 
7:3 Â 10 À13 
3:0 Â 10 À51 

The P-values indicate the statistical differences between NPM and other clustering methods 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">Q.Gao et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Biological clustering method for logistic place decision making Knowledge-Based Intelligent Information and Engineering Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B A</forename>
				<surname>Bakar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Watada</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Lovrek,I. et al</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="143" />
			<pubPlace>Berlin Heidelberg</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chlorophyll fluorescence: a probe of photosynthesis in vivo</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Baker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Plant Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Continuous representations of time-series gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Bar-Joseph</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="356" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing time series gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Bar-Joseph</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2493" to="2503" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustering gene expression patterns</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ben-Dor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="297" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cognitive ontologies for neuropsychiatric phenomics research</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Bilder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cogn. Neuropsychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="450" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Creation and implications of a phenomegenome network</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Butte</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Kohane</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast nonparametric clustering with Gaussian blurring mean-shift</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A ´</forename>
				<surname>Carreira-Perpiñ A ´n</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on Machine Learning</title>
		<meeting>the 23rd International Conference on Machine Learning<address><addrLine>Pittsburgh PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="160" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Next-generation phenotyping: requirements and strategies for enhancing our understanding of genotype-phenotype relationships and its relevance to crop improvement</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Cobb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theor. Appl. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="867" to="887" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein Function Prediction by Clustering of Protein-Protein Interaction Network</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Cingovska</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ICT Innovations</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image segmentation using clustering with saddle point detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Comaniciu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Image Processing</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE International Conference on Image Processing<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="300" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple sequence alignment with hierarchical clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Corpet</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10881" to="10890" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative analysis of clustering methods for gene expression time course data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Costa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="623" to="631" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic environmental photosynthetic imaging (DEPI) reveals emergent phenotypes related to the environmental responses of photosynthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Cruz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotech</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in. press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Structure, dynamics, and energetics of the primary photochemistry of photosystem II of oxygenic photosynthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Diner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Rappaport</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Plant Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="551" to="580" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cluster analysis and display of genome-wide expression patterns</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Eisen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14863" to="14868" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeneRAGE: A robust algorithm for sequence clustering and domain detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Enright</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Ouzounis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="451" to="457" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Practical Methods of Optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Fletcher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Chichester</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd. ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PhenomicDB: a new cross-species genotype/phenotype resource</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Groth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="696" to="699" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phenoclustering: online mining of cross-species phenotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Groth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1924" to="1925" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Phenotype mining for functional genomics and gene discovery. Silico Tools for Gene Discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Groth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="173" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Photosynthetic measurements with the idea spec: An integrated diode emitter array spectrophotometer/fluorometer Photosynthesis Research for Food, Fuel and the Future</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Hall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="188" />
			<pubPlace>Berlin Heidelberg</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of algorithms for the analysis of Affymetrix microarray data as evaluated by co-expression of genes in known operons</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Harr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Schlö Tterer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Large-scale clustering of cDNA-fingerprinting data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Herwig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1093" to="1105" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phenotypic clustering of yeast mutants based on kinetochore microtubule dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Jaqaman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1666" to="1673" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hierarchical clustering schemes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Johnson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="254" />
			<date type="published" when="1967" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principal Component Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Jolliffe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The importance of energy balance in improving photosynthetic productivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Kramer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Evans</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic flexibility in the light reactions of photosynthesis governed by both electron and proton transfer reactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Kramer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Plant Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="357" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The arabidopsis information resource (tair): improved gene annotation and new tools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Lamesch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1202" to="1210" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cd-hit: a fast program for clustering and comparing large sets of protein or nucleotide sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Godzik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1658" to="1659" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulatory motif discovery using a population clustering evolutionary algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Lones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Tyrrell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Trans. Comput. Biol. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="414" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chloroplast 2010: A database for large-scale phenotypic screening of Arabidopsis mutants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Lu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1589" to="1600" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manifold Learning Theory and Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Ma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Fu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some methods for classification and analysis of multivariate observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Macqueen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 5th Berkeley Symposium on mathematical statistics and probability</title>
		<meeting>the 5th Berkeley Symposium on mathematical statistics and probability</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1967" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="297" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Finite Mixture Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Mclachlan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Peel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model-based clustering of microarray expression data via latent Gaussian mixture models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Mcnicholas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Murphy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2705" to="2712" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On non-parametric estimates of density functions and regression curves</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Nadaraya</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theor. Probab. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="1965" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian model-based clustering of temporal gene expression using autoregressive panel data approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nascimento</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2004" to="2007" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ATTED-II updates: Condition-specific gene coexpression to extend coexpression analyses and applications to a broad range of flowering plants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Obayashi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Cell. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On estimation of a probability density function and mode</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Parzen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Math. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1065" to="1076" />
			<date type="published" when="1962" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Kolmogorov-Smirnov Test In: Numerical Recipes in FORTRAN: The Art of Scientific Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Press</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="617" to="620" />
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, England, New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd. edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of gene-expression clustering via mutual information distance measure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Priness</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">111</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond synexpression relationships: local clustering of time-shifted and inverted gene expression profiles identifies new, biologically relevant interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Qian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">314</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1053" to="1066" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cluster analysis of gene expression dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Ramoni</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9121" to="9126" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parametric and non-parametric unsupervised cluster analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Roberts</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recogn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="261" to="272" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Remarks on some nonparametric estimates of a density function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Rosenblatt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Math. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="832" to="837" />
			<date type="published" when="1956" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using hidden Markov models to analyze gene expression time course data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Schliep</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="263" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximum likelihood estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Scholz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Encyclopedia of Statistical Sciences</title>
		<editor>Kotz,S. et al,</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4629" to="4639" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd. edn. Wiley, Hobokenm NJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inter-functional analysis of high-throughput phenotype data Next-generation DNA sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Shendure</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Ji</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Biotech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1135" to="1145" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrative clustering and modeling algorithm for dynamical gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Sivriver</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="392" to="400" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model selection for probabilistic clustering using cross-validated likelihood</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Smyth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A law of the logarithm for kernel density estimators</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Stute</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Probab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="414" to="422" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interpreting patterns of gene expression with selforganizing maps: Methods and application to hematopoietic differentiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Tamayo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2907" to="2912" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The thylakoid proton motive force in vivo. Quantitative, non-invasive probes, energetics, and regulatory consequences of light-induced pmf</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Takizawa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BBA-Bioenergetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1767</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1233" to="1244" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional Approach to High-throughput Plant Growth Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Tessmer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 6</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A tutorial on spectral clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Von</forename>
				<surname>Luxburg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="416" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The pleiotropic structure of the genotype– phenotype map: The evolvability of complex organisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Wagner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Gen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="204" to="213" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Function-function correlated multi-label protein function prediction over interaction networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="322" to="343" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new approach to clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Wilson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Spann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recogn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1413" to="1425" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale prediction of Saccharomyces cerevisiae gene function using overlapping transcriptional clusters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A point mutation in atpC1 raises the redox potential of the Arabidopsis chloroplast ATP synthase c-subunit regulatory disulfide above the range of thioredoxin modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">282</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36782" to="36789" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plant photosynthesis phenomics data quality control</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Xu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1796" to="1804" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combining high-throughput phenotyping and genomewide association studies to reveal natural genetic variation in rice</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5087</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Creation of a genome-wide metabolic pathway database for Populus trichocarpa using a new approach for reconstruction and curation of metabolic pathways for plants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1479" to="1491" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>