
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:34+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Interactive software tool to comprehend the calculation of optimal sequence alignments with dynamic programming</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ignacio</forename>
								<forename type="middle">L</forename>
								<surname>Ibarra</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departamento de Genética Molecular y Microbiología</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Facultad de Ciencias Biológicas</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratorio de Bioinformática Molecular</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Alameda 340</addrLine>
									<settlement>Santiago</settlement>
									<country key="CL">Chile</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Francisco</forename>
								<surname>Melo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departamento de Genética Molecular y Microbiología</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Facultad de Ciencias Biológicas</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratorio de Bioinformática Molecular</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Alameda 340</addrLine>
									<settlement>Santiago</settlement>
									<country key="CL">Chile</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Interactive software tool to comprehend the calculation of optimal sequence alignments with dynamic programming</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1664" to="1665"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq252</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 30, 2010; revised on May 7, 2010; accepted on May 11, 2010</note>
					<note>[12:24 3/6/2010 Bioinformatics-btq252.tex] Page: 1664 1664–1665 Associate Editor: Burkhard Rost</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Dynamic programming (DP) is a general optimization strategy that is successfully used across various disciplines of science. In bioinformatics, it is widely applied in calculating the optimal alignment between pairs of protein or DNA sequences. These alignments form the basis of new, verifiable biological hypothesis. Despite its importance, there are no interactive tools available for training and education on understanding the DP algorithm. Here, we introduce an interactive computer application with a graphical interface, for the purpose of educating students about DP. The program displays the DP scoring matrix and the resulting optimal alignment(s), while allowing the user to modify key parameters such as the values in the similarity matrix, the sequence alignment algorithm version and the gap opening/extension penalties. We hope that this software will be useful to teachers and students of bioinformatics courses, as well as researchers who implement the DP algorithm for diverse applications. Availability and Implementation: The software is freely available at: http:/melolab.org/sat. The software is written in the Java computer language, thus it runs on all major platforms and operating systems including Windows, Mac OS X and LINUX. Contact: All inquiries or comments about this software should be directed to Francisco Melo at fmelo@bio.puc.cl</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Dynamic programming (DP) algorithm was first formalized by the mathematician Richard Bellman in the early 1950s (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bellman, 1952</ref>). Since then, DP has been adapted to solve many optimization problems in different areas of science (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bellman, 1966</ref>). DP, in various forms, constitutes the core of bioinformatics. It is central to several software applications, such as those comparing sequences and structures of proteins, RNA and DNA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Sankoff, 2000</ref>). The pivotal role of DP algorithm in Bioinformatics has led it to be considered as an essential topic of any undergraduate and graduate course in bioinformatics. Despite the simplicity of its formulation, DP algorithm is a subject that is not easy for the students to learn. Extensive practice is essential for students to fully appreciate it workings. Given its importance, and its mandatory presence in bioinformatics courses, there are not interactive computer * To whom correspondence should be addressed. tools designed to help students to understand the specific details of the DP algorithm. We have addressed this need by developing Sequence Alignment Teacher (SAT), a simple software application, which interactively calculates the DP matrix in real time. SAT also visually illustrates the consequences of tweaking the various parameters of the algorithm. We hope this simple software tool will not only be useful for teachers and students of bioinformatics courses but also to future bioinformatics developers as an error check tool when they start implementing this algorithm for the first time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">SOFTWARE DESCRIPTION</head><p>SAT requires that the user provide the input sequence data and select the different alignment parameters. This can be done on the graphics window that is launched on starting SAT (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). The graphic window display contains five major sections: Input Sequences, DP algorithm and Similarity Matrix (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>top left): It contains two text fields to input the DNA or protein sequences that will be aligned, and three combo boxes to select the version of DP algorithm, the similarity matrix and the maximum number of optimal solutions that should be reported. Similarity Matrix and Gap penalties (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>top middle):</p><p>The user can visualize and modify the values in the similarity matrix and the gap opening/extension penalties. Default similarity matrices include identity and transition/transversion for DNA and BLOSUM50, BLOSUM62, PAM100, PAM250 for proteins. Users can create their own custom matrices by inputting substitution values of their choice. Gap penalties can be similarly modified. Upon changing any of these values, the system will update the results of the calculations in real time. Other Actions (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>top right): The user can generate a report of the current data and results in PDF format. Brief help guidelines about how to use the software and contact information for authors are also provided. DP Matrix (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>middle): It shows the filled DP matrix along with the backtrace path of the currently selected optimal alignment. The user can click on any position of the matrix, to generate optimal sub-alignments starting from the 5 end or the amino terminus of the sequence up to the selected position in the DP matrix. The user can re-establish the original full optimal alignment by clicking a refresh button.of optimal alignments, the total number of possible alignments and the percentage of optimal solutions. By clicking on any score on the left, the corresponding optimal alignment will be shown in the window on the right. In response to this user action, the DP matrix and optimal backtrace path will also be immediately updated. Three different DP algorithm versions were implemented here (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Durbin et al., 1998</ref>), a global Needleman–Wunsch algorithm with linear and affine gap penalties and a local Smith–Waterman with linear gap penalties. It is important to note that this software is neither intended to teach the theory of DP nor constitute another sequence alignment tool, but to provide an interactive exploring/testing framework that supports the learning process of this important algorithm. For this reason, the current version of the software is limited to short sequences to facilitate the display in laptop computers and LCD projectors in the classroom. There is plenty of bibliographic material available in the literature dedicated to the theory of DP. We recommend as a general and brief primer to DP algorithm and sequence alignment the excellent vignette by Sean Eddy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Eddy, 2004</ref>). A nice source containing a detailed description of DP algorithms for sequence alignment is the book by<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Durbin et al. (1998).</ref></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Optimal Alignment(s) (Fig. 1 bottom): It displays the overall alignment score and the corresponding optimal alignment. The total number of optimal alignments displayed depends on the value specified by the user. This section also displays the total number Dynamic programming</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Screen snapshot of SAT graphical interface.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from [12:24 3/6/2010 Bioinformatics-btq252.tex]</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors would like to thank Javier Castellanos, Alex Slater and Tomás Norambuena for helpful discussions. We are also grateful to Drs Manfred Sippl, Andrej Sali, M.S. Madhusudhan and their research groups for testing the software and giving us important feedback.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the theory of dynamic programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Bellman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1952" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="716" to="719" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Bellman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Durbin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biological Sequence Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1st. edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is dynamic programming?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Eddy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="909" to="910" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The early introduction of dynamic programming into computational biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Sankoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>