
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:42+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis ISRNA: an integrative online toolkit for short reads from high-throughput sequencing data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Guan-Zheng</forename>
								<surname>Luo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory of Plant Genomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wei</forename>
								<surname>Yang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory of Plant Genomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Associate Editor: Inanc Birol</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Graduate University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100101</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ying-Ke</forename>
								<surname>Ma</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory of Plant Genomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Associate Editor: Inanc Birol</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Graduate University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100101</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xiu-Jie</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory of Plant Genomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis ISRNA: an integrative online toolkit for short reads from high-throughput sequencing data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="434" to="436"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt678</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 25, 2013; revised on November 3, 2013; accepted on November 18, 2013</note>
					<note>Contact: xjwang@genetics.ac.cn Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Integrative Short Reads NAvigator (ISRNA) is an online toolkit for analyzing high-throughput small RNA sequencing data. Besides the high-speed genome mapping function, ISRNA provides statistics for genomic location, length distribution and nucleotide composition bias analysis of sequence reads. Number of reads mapped to known microRNAs and other classes of short non-coding RNAs, coverage of short reads on genes, expression abundance of sequence reads as well as some other analysis functions are also supported. The versatile search functions enable users to select sequence reads according to their sub-sequences, expression abundance, genomic location, relationship to genes, etc. A specialized genome browser is integrated to visualize the genomic distribution of short reads. ISRNA also supports management and comparison among multiple datasets. Availability: ISRNA is implemented in Java/Cþþ/Perl/MySQL and can be freely accessed at http://omicslab.genetics.ac.cn/ISRNA/.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The wide application of high-throughput sequencing technology has given rise to significant needs for powerful bioinformatics tools to analyze the resulting data and retrieve useful information. Although there have been some web-based and standalone tools for high-throughput small RNA analysis available, many of them mainly focus on microRNA (miRNA) identification (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">An et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hackenberg et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ronen et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Sablok et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Zhao et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Zhu et al., 2010</ref>) or small RNA characterization (<ref type="bibr">Chen et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fasold et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Gupta et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Huang et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Pantano et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Stocks et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Zhang et al., 2012</ref>); few provide comprehensive feature analysis, mining as well as visualization and cross-sample comparison functions (see Supplementary Table S1 for detailed comparison). Here we introduce Integrative Short Reads NAvigator (ISRNA), an online toolkit for searching, analyzing, visualizing and comparing short sequence reads. ISRNA integrates several useful tools in a user-friendly way. Besides mapping short sequence reads to a given genome and allowing a genome browser to visualize the position and distribution of sequence reads, ISRNA also calculates nucleotide composition, identifies known miRNAs and their homologous sequences, predicts the secondary structure for the surrounding genomic region of a short sequence and reveals genomic small RNA clusters and genes producing small RNAs. It also provides versatile searching functions and allows cross-dataset comparisons. All these functions are easy to use with user-friendly outputs, making ISRNA suitable for researchers with limited bioinformatics skills.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">DESIGN AND KEY FEATURES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data processing and genome mapping</head><p>ISRNA takes raw FASTQ files or text files with sequence and read count information, which can be generated by the Perl script provided by ISRNA as inputs. For details, please refer to the online user manual. The uploaded sequences will be mapped to the corresponding genome by Bowtie (<ref type="bibr">Langmead et al., 2009</ref>) with user-defined parameters and stored in a MySQL database. Sequences with a number of mapped loci exceeding the threshold value will be discarded.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Sequence analysis</head><p>The analysis functions of ISRNA include:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1">Data overview</head><p>This module analyzes some basic features of the uploaded dataset to provide users the general information, including sequencing depth, genome mapping results, sequence length distribution, etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2">Nucleotide preference analysis</head><p>This module enables users to calculate the nucleotide composition at any defined position among sequence reads with genomic matches, in both total and non-redundant datasets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3">Sequence annotation ISRNA uses</head><p>the BLASTþ program (<ref type="bibr">Camacho et al., 2009</ref>) and Rfam (<ref type="bibr">Burge et al., 2013</ref>) database to annotate short sequence reads. The classification results of sequences will be provided in a pie chart and be downloaded via the 'Export' function.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.4">Known miRNA identification ISRNA</head><p>identifies known miRNAs as well as isomiRNAs by mapping reads to the *To whom correspondence should be addressed. mature and precursor sequences of known miRNAs collected in the miRBase. The abundance of miRNAs or isoforms of miRNAs (isomiRNAs) is estimated by the reads per million values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.5">Secondary structure prediction ISRNA</head><p>extracts the surrounding genomic regions of input sequences and predicts their secondary structures using the CentroidFold program (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Sato et al., 2009</ref>), which allows users to identify new miRNAs or other classes of small RNAs with precursors of defined structural features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Search functions</head><p>ISRNA provides powerful search functions that enable users to analyze and curate their data with different needs (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1a</ref>), including search by sequences (allowing mismatches,<ref type="figure">Fig. 1b</ref>), search by miRNA, search by short read count, search by genomic location, search by related genes/gene families and search by read coverage on genes. A detailed description of the search functions can be found in the Supplementary File.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Cross-dataset comparison</head><p>ISRNA supports comparison among multiple datasets within a project. Differentially expressed sequence reads among datasets can be identified by the implemented edgeR package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Robinson et al., 2010</ref>), with user-adjustable P-value and false discovery rate thresholds. Genome distribution of sequence reads in multiple datasets can be examined via the cross-dataset comparison function (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1c</ref>), which assists users in identifying differentially expressed genomic regions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Genomic cluster analysis</head><p>This function permits users to identify clustered short sequences on the genome, such as piwi-interacting RNAs or phased small RNAs. Comparing the genomic cluster distribution of sequence reads can also help to identify highly expressed sequence loci and sequence read production hotspots.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">Sequence read browser</head><p>In all search result display pages, a specialized genome browser is integrated to show the genomic mapping results of short sequence reads and genes. Users can easily identify the positional relationship among short sequence reads, as well as between short sequence reads and annotated genes. The ID, genomic position and annotation of genes, together with the information of sequence reads, will be displayed via mousing over the corresponding gene or sequence read. Short reads are displayed by cumulated short segments with color gradients representing the sequence abundance (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1d</ref>). The genome browser also enables users to examine the overall sequence distribution on each chromosome, and therefore to identify regions enriched or deprived of sequence reads.</p></div>
			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> CONCLUSIONS We introduce ISRNA, a piece of online software designed for storage, visualization and analysis of small RNA sequencing data produced by high-throughput sequencing technologies. The comprehensive data analysis, search and cross-dataset comparison functions, as well as the user-friendly output of ISRNA, make it a practical and easy-to-use tool for researchers with limited bioinformatics analysis skills. Funding: This work was supported by the grants from the Ministry of Science and Technology of China (number 2011CBA01101), the 863 program of China (2011AA020108) and from the Chinese Academy of Sciences (numbers XDA01020105 and KSCX2-EW-R-01-03) to X.-J.W. Conflict of Interest: none declared. REFERENCES An,J. et al. (2013) miRDeep*: an integrated application tool for miRNA identification from RNA sequencing data. Nucleic Acids Res., 41, 727–737. Burge,S.W. et al. (2013) Rfam 11.0: 10 years of RNA families. Nucleic Acids Res., 41, D226–D232. Camacho,C. et al. (2009) BLASTþ: architecture and applications. BMC Bioinformatics, 10, 421. Chen,C.J. et al. (2012) ncPRO-seq: a tool for annotation and profiling of ncRNAs in sRNA-seq data. Bioinformatics, 28, 3147–3149. Fasold,M. et al. (2011) DARIO: a ncRNA detection and analysis tool for next-generation sequencing experiments. Nucleic Acids Res., 39, W112–W117. Gupta,V. et al. (2012) shortran: a pipeline for small RNA-seq data analysis. Bioinformatics, 28, 2698–2700. Hackenberg,M. et al. (2011) miRanalyzer: an update on the detection and analysis of microRNAs in high-throughput sequencing experiments. Nucleic Acids Res., 39, W132–W138. Huang,P.J. et al. (2010) DSAP: deep-sequencing small RNA analysis pipeline. Nucleic Acids Res., 38, W385–W391. Langmead,B. et al. (2009) Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome. Genome Biol., 10, R25. Pantano,L. et al. (2011) A non-biased framework for the annotation and classification of the non-miRNA small RNA transcriptome. Bioinformatics, 27, 3202–3203. Fig. 1. Unique features of ISRNA. (a) Search functions of ISRNA. (b) Example of sequence search results with mismatches allowed. Nucleotides identical to those in the query sequence are highlighted in green, and the mismatched nucleotides are highlighted in red. (c) Multiple dataset comparison function identifies small RNA enriched regions along chromosomes among different datasets. (d) Screenshot of the sequence read browser</note>

			<note place="foot">Integrative short reads navigator at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">G.-Z.Luo et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">miRNAkey: a software for microRNA deep sequencing analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Ronen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2615" to="2616" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">isomiRex: web-based identification of microRNAs, isomiR variations and differential expression using next-generation sequencing datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Sablok</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEBS Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">587</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2629" to="2634" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CENTROIDFOLD: a web server for RNA secondary structure prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Sato</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="280" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The UEA sRNA workbench: a suite of tools for analysing and visualizing next generation sequencing microRNA and small RNA datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Stocks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2059" to="2061" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CPSS: a computational platform for the analysis of small RNA deep sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1925" to="1927" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">wapRNA: a web-based application for the processing of RNA sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Zhao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3076" to="3077" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">mirTools: microRNA profiling and discovery based on highthroughput sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Zhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="392" to="397" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>