
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:59+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">LedPred: an R/bioconductor package to predict regulatory sequences using support vector machines</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Denis</forename>
								<surname>Seyres</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">INSERM</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>UMR1090 TAGC, F-13288</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Aix-Marseille Université</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>UMR1090 TAGC, F-13288</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Elodie</forename>
								<surname>Darbo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Cancer Research UK</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">London Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>WC2A 3LY</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Laurent</forename>
								<surname>Perrin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">INSERM</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>UMR1090 TAGC, F-13288</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Aix-Marseille Université</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>UMR1090 TAGC, F-13288</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Carl</forename>
								<surname>Herrmann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Theoretical Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">DKFZ</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">IPMB</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Universität Heidelberg</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>69120</postCode>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Aitor</forename>
								<surname>Gonz Alez</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">INSERM</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>UMR1090 TAGC, F-13288</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Aix-Marseille Université</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>UMR1090 TAGC, F-13288</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">LedPred: an R/bioconductor package to predict regulatory sequences using support vector machines</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv705</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on 20 July 2015; revised on 23 November 2015; accepted on 26 November 2015</note>
					<note>Genome analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Associate Editor: Inanc Birol Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Supervised classification based on support vector machines (SVMs) has successfully been used for the prediction of cis-regulatory modules (CRMs). However, no integrated tool using such heterogeneous data as position-specific scoring matrices, ChIP-seq data or conservation scores is currently available. Here, we present LedPred, a flexible SVM workflow that predicts new regulatory sequences based on the annotation of known CRMs, which are associated to a large variety of feature types. LedPred is provided as an R/Bioconductor package connected to an online ser-ver to avoid installation of non-R software. Due to the heterogeneous CRM feature integration, LedPred excels at the prediction of regulatory sequences in Drosophila and mouse datasets compared with similar SVM-based software. Availability and implementation: LedPred is available on GitHub: https:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Transcriptional programs are tightly controlled by cis-regulatory modules (CRMs) that control gene expression. CRMs are stretches of DNA that contain specific combinations of transcription factor binding sites (TFBS) and are often associated with histone modification or nucleosome-free regions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Spitz and Furlong, 2012</ref>). A wellestablished strategy to predict CRMs is to analyze combinations of CRM features described above in a set of experimentally validated CRMs. Support vector machine (SVM) algorithms are appropriate for this task since they can learn sequence features that distinguish CRMs from background sequences. Existing tools (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>) score sequences based on k-mer discovery (KIRMES,<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Schultheiss et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">KeBABS, Palme et al., 2015</ref>; k-mer-SVM Fletez<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Brant et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">gkm-SVM, Ghandi et al., 2014</ref>), positionspecific scoring matrices (PSSMs) (CLARE,<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Taher et al., 2012</ref>) or ChIP-seq data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Tagliazucchi, 2014</ref>). The DEEP tool theoretically integrates a large palette of features but is specific to mammals, does not return a model to score new sequences and is currently unavailable (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kleftogiannis et al., 2014</ref>). Here, we present an R/Bioconductor package based on the libsvm library (<ref type="bibr">Chih</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Study cases</head><p>To illustrate our approach, we have analyzed in vivo validated Drosophila melanogaster enhancers from the CAD2 database studied in the context of mesodermal development (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bonn et al., 2012</ref>). The positive training set is a subset (80%) of these enhancers (114/143) and 10 times more random sequences as negative training set (Supplementary file 1). PSSMs from different public databases (Supplementary data), mesoderm-specific ChIP-seq data for H3K4me1 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bonn et al., 2012</ref>) and ChIP-on-CHIP data on five mesoderm transcription factors (Tinman, Zinzen et al., 2009; Dorsocross, Pangolin, phosphorylated MAD and Panier,<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Junion et al., 2012</ref>) were used as descriptive features. Best performances were obtained when 90 out of 576 of the best ranked features were used. H3K4me1 ChIP-seq data and the Pnr and dTcf ChIP-on-CHIP data, known for their mesodermal roles, were classified among the best discriminative features. The model was used to scan the whole non-coding genome split into 1500 bp regions with 750 bp overlap (116 736 regions in total) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). Of the 5848 regions predicted with an FPR cut off of 5%, we retrieved 44% of the 29 remaining CAD2 mesodermal CRMs not included in the training set (Binomial test P-value 5.3 Â 10 À09 ). Finally, we compared the performance of LedPred with other SVM-based CRM predictors using this Drosophila dataset and one from mouse in two different ways (Supplementary file 3). First, we compared the AUC returned by the software during the training (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). Second, we created a model with a training set composed of 80% sequences and drew ROC curves for the remaining 20% test sequences (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>). In the Drosophila dataset, LedPred showed equivalent best performances as gkm-SVM, kebabs and k-mer-SVM (Supplementary Figs 1 and 2A). In the mouse, we used an enhanced dataset that has experimentally been characterized as high, medium and low level activity together with vertebrate PSSMs and NGS data related to this dataset (Supplementary File 2) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Vanhille et al., 2015</ref>). We predicted enhancers using NGS data specific to this dataset, and PSSMs from the Jaspar (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Mathelier et al., 2014</ref>) and the Human Protein–DNA Interactome database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Xie et al., 2010</ref>). In this dataset, LedPred achieved the best performances (AUC0.81 in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>and AUC0.75 in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>) with a clear difference to the following classifiers (AUC0.66 in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>and AUC0.64 in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Concluding remarks</head><p>The LedPred package is a new, fast and accurate SVM workflow to predict CRMs based on PSSMs, NGS data and other features in different species. An online server facilitates the mapping of PSSMs, ChIP peaks and signals to the sequences, while the subsequent steps create an optimized SVM model and use it to score new sequences. The SVM specific steps after feature mapping can be applied to any numerical matrix, and therefore this package can be useful for other binary classification problems.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Overview of the LedPred workflow. Genomic features are mapped to the training sequence sets. The resulting data frame is used to compute optimal SVM parameters, rank the features and find the best feature number. The optimal parameters and features are used to create a model that can be stored and used in the last part to score query sequences</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Funding</head><figDesc>ANR, partner of the ERASysBioþ supported under the UE ERA-NET Plus scheme in FP7 (C.H. and L.P.). Conflict of interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Chung and Chih-Jen 2011) to model CRMs in many species and score new V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 1091 Bioinformatics, 32(7), 2016, 1091–1093 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv705 Advance Access Publication Date: 1 December 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from sequences based on PSSMs, NGS data and pre-computed custom values such as conservation. 2 Workflow The workflow is composed of five main steps: (1) numerical mapping of features to sequences, (2) tuning the SVM parameters, (3) feature selection, (4) model creation and evaluation and (5) scoring of new sequences (Fig. 1). Steps 1–4 are related to the model training, and the model is applied in Step 5. In Step 1, the user submits a BED file with positive training sequences. The negative training sequences can be generated from a set of background sequences (Bedtools; Quinlan and Hall, 2010) or submitted directly in a BED file. Users can use PSSMs (Transfac format), ChIP-seq peaks (BED) or signals (WIG or BED format) or BED files with regions and custom values (e.g. conservation scores or RNA-seq levels). Each sequence is scanned with the PSSMs using RSAT matrix-scan (Medina-Rivera et al., 2015) and scored according to binding probabilities (see Bioconductor vignette). In the case of BED peaks, positive binary values are set for an overlap of &gt;20% with the query sequence, whereas for the WIG signals, the average overlap is calculated (Java Genomics Tool Kit, Palpant, 2012). Step 1 is calculated by an online server to avoid installation of third-party programs. The numerical matrix returned by Step 1 is used in Steps 2–4 to create a model. In Step 2, the optimal SVM parameter values are computed from a grid of values. In Step 3, a ranking of the features is created using a recursive feature elimination algorithm while the optimal number of features is found by calculating Cohen&apos;s kappa coefficient for different number of features. In Step 4, an SVM model and a plot of its performance on the training sequences are created. Finally, in Step 5, the optimal features are mapped to the query sequences, which are then scored with the SVM model. The mouse example below, with around 170 positive and 1700 negative training sequences and 600 PSSMs, took around 1-h user time and 1.3-GB maximum resident set size using four CPUs (Supplementary Fig. 3). Execution time scales exponentially while memory scales linearly (Supplementary Fig. 3). Sequence and annotation data, and the workflows below, are available as Supplementary data and in the Bioconductor vignette.</note>

			<note place="foot">D.Seyres et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We acknowledge Charles Chapple for critical reading of this manuscript, Jacques van Helden for insightful discussions, Jaime Castro for advice with RSAT matrix-clustering and for PSSMs and Salvatore Spicuglia for the mouse dataset. We acknowledge the French Institute of Bioinformatics (ANR-11INBS-0013, www.france-bioinformatique.fr) for providing the bioinformatics</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tissue-specific analysis of chromatin state identifies temporal signatures of enhancer activity during embryonic development</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Bonn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="148" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LIBSVM: a library for support vector machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Chih-Chung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Chih-Jen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Trans. Intell. Syst. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">kmer-SVM: a web server for identifying predictive regulatory sequence features in genomic data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Fletez-Brant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="544" to="556" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhanced regulatory sequence prediction using gapped K-Mer features</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Ghandi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003711</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A transcription factor collective defines cardiac cell fate and reflects lineage history</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Junion</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="486" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DEEP: a general computational framework for predicting enhancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Kleftogiannis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">JASPAR 2014: an extensively expanded and updated open-access database of transcription factor binding profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Mathelier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Database. issue</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RSAT 2015: regulatory sequence analysis tools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Medina-Rivera</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KeBABS: an R package for kernel-based analysis of biological sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Palme</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="2574" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Java genomics tool kit</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Palpant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Quinlan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Hall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="841" to="842" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KIRMES: kernel-based identification of regulatory modules in euchromatic sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Schultheiss</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2126" to="2133" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcription factors: from enhancer binding to developmental control</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Spitz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E M</forename>
				<surname>Furlong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="626" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">SVM2CRM: support vector machine for cisregulatory elements detections. R package version 1.0.0. https://bioconduc tor</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Tagliazucchi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>org. /packages/release/bioc/html/SVM2CRM.html</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clare: cracking the LAnguage of regulatory elements</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Taher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="581" to="583" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-throughput and quantitative assessment of enhancer activity in mammals by CapStarr-seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Vanhille</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6905</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">hPDI: a database of experimental human protein-DNA interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Xie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="289" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combinatorial binding predicts spatio-temporal cisregulatory activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Zinzen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">462</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>