
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:49+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis MALDIquant: a versatile R package for the analysis of mass spectrometry data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sebastian</forename>
								<surname>Gibb</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Medical Informatics, Statistics and Epidemiology (IMISE)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Hä rtelstr. 16-18</addrLine>
									<postCode>04107</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Korbinian</forename>
								<surname>Strimmer</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Medical Informatics, Statistics and Epidemiology (IMISE)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Hä rtelstr. 16-18</addrLine>
									<postCode>04107</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alex</forename>
								<surname>Bateman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Medical Informatics, Statistics and Epidemiology (IMISE)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Hä rtelstr. 16-18</addrLine>
									<postCode>04107</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis MALDIquant: a versatile R package for the analysis of mass spectrometry data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2270" to="2271"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts447</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 6, 2012; revised on July 5, 2012; accepted on July 9, 2012</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: The software is distributed under the GNU General Public License (version 3 or later) and is accompanied by example files and data. Additional documen-tation is available from http://strimmerlab.org/software/maldiquant/. Contact: mail@sebastiangibb.de</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>MALDIquant is an R package providing a complete and modular analysis pipeline for quantitative analysis of mass spectro-metry data. MALDIquant is specifically designed with application in clinical diagnostics in mind and implements sophisticated routines for importing raw data, preprocessing, non-linear peak alignment and calibration. It also handles technical replicates as well as spectra with unequal resolution. Availability: MALDIquant and its associated R packages readBrukerFlexData and readMzXmlData are freely available from the R archive CRAN (http://cran.r-project.org).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Mass spectrometry profiling is increasingly becoming an important tool in clinical diagnostics, for example to identify biomarkers for cancer (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Fiedler et al., 2009</ref>). Similarly as with other high-throughput technologies, sophisticated statistical algorithms are essential in the analysis of spectrometry data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Morris et al., 2010</ref>). We have developed MALDIquant to provide a complete opensource analysis pipeline on the R platform (R Development<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Core Team, 2012</ref>) comprising all steps from importing of raw data, preprocessing (e.g. baseline removal), peak detection and non-linear peak alignment to calibration of mass spectra. MALDIquant is written as a standalone package using S4 object-oriented programming to facilitate further extension. MALDIquant was initially developed for clinical proteomics using Matrix-Assisted Laser Desorption/Ionization (MALDI) technology. However, the algorithms implemented in MALDIquant are generic and may be equally applied to other 2D mass spectrometry data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">DISTINCTIVE FEATURES</head><p>In comparison with related R packages for mass spectrometry analysis, MALDIquant features a number of unique capabilities.</p><p>In particular, it implements a sophisticated non-linear peak alignment algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">He et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Wang et al., 2010</ref>) as well as a calibration procedure for normalization of peak intensities across spectra that are modeled on a related method for sequence count data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Anders and Huber, 2010</ref>). In addition, MALDIquant allows to analyze technical replicates and spectra with unequal resolution, a crucial feature in clinical mass spectrometry where spectra from multiple sources need to be compared.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DETAILS ON ALGORITHMS</head><p>An example workflow for mass spectrometry analysis using MALDIquant is depicted in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1</ref>, starting with a raw unprocessed MALDI spectrum (A), followed by smoothing, baseline correction and peak detection (B), local alignment of peaks across spectra by warping (C–E) and merging and visualization (F). In the following, we briefly provide some background on the respective algorithms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Data import</head><p>MALDIquant is carefully designed to be independent of any specific mass spectrometry hardware. Nonetheless, native input of binary data files (as well as complete folder hierarchies) from Bruker flex series instruments and input of the mzXML data format is supported through the associated R packages readBrukerFlexData and readMzXmlData.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Data preprocessing</head><p>For preprocessing spectral data, MALDIquant offers a complete set of routines for smoothing, variance stabilization, baseline correction and peak detection. MALDIquant implements several approaches to adjust the baseline and uses per default the SNIP algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Ryan et al., 1988</ref>) that returns a smooth baseline and leads to positive corrected intensities (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1B</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Peak alignment</head><p>For comparison of peaks across different spectra, it is essential to conduct alignment. In order to match peaks belonging to the same mass,to the matched reference peaks (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1C</ref>–E). This also allows to merge aligned spectra from technical replicates. An example of a merged spectrum with identified and labeled peaks is shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1F</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Calibration</head><p>Quantitative analysis of multiple spectra, e.g. to detect differentially expressed peaks, requires calibration. In order to render peak intensities comparable across spectra, a suitable scale factor for each individual spectrum needs to be determined. Experimentally, quantification of intensities is performed by reference to spike-in samples. In absence of spike-ins, MALDIquant offers a way of calibrating relative intensities by adapting an algorithm for calibrating next generation sequencing data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Anders and Huber, 2010</ref>). In this procedure first a reference spectrum is created using the median intensity of aligned peaks from all spectra. Subsequently, a scale factor is computed for each spectrum by using a robust estimator of the overall ratio of the peak intensities of the uncalibrated spectrum versus the reference spectrum. Additionally, calibration based on total ion current is available.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Classification and feature selection</head><p>Finally, the resulting calibrated peak intensity matrix may be exported for further use in high-level statistical analysis, for instance classification and feature selection using shrinkage discriminant analysis (Ahdesma¨kiAhdesma¨ki and Strimmer, 2010).R package for the analysis of mass spectrometry data</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>MALDIquant uses a statistical regression-based approach combining the algorithms of He et al. (2011) and Wang et al. (2010). Specifically, first landmark peaks are identified that occur in most spectra. Subsequently, a non-linear warping function is computed for each spectrum by fitting a local regression *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>MALDIquant is a versatile R package providing a flexible analysis pipeline for MALDI-TOF and other mass spectrometry data. It offers a number of distinctive features, in particular for alignment by non-linear warping and simultaneous calibration of peak intensities. An overview of its capabilities is given by running the included demo</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Example of MALDIquant output: (A) raw spectrum; (B) variance-stabilized, smoothed and baseline-corrected spectrum with detected peaks; (C) fitted warping function for peak alignment; (D) four unaligned peaks; (E) four aligned peaks; and (F) merged spectrum with detected and labeled peaks.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Feature selection in omics prediction problems using cat scores and false non-discovery rate control</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ahdesma¨kiahdesma¨ki</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Strimmer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Appl. Statist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="503" to="519" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential expression for sequence count data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Anders</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Huber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Serum peptidome profiling revealed platelet factor 4 as a potential discriminating peptide associated with pancreatic cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Fiedler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3812" to="3819" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-calibrated warping for mass spectra alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical contributions to proteomic research</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Morris</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">641</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing.. R Foundation for Statistical Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Development</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Core</forename>
				<surname>Team</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<pubPlace>Vienna, Austria</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SNIP, a statistics-sensitive background treatment for the quantitative analysis of PIXE spectra in geoscience applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Ryan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucl. Instrument. Meth. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="396" to="402" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DISCO: distance and spectrum correlation optimization alignment for two-dimensional gas chromatography time-of-flight mass spectrometry-based metabolomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5069" to="5081" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>