
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:51+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining MaxLink: network-based prioritization of genes tightly linked to a disease seed set</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">18 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dimitri</forename>
								<surname>Guala</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Stockholm Bioinformatics Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Science for Life Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SE-17121</postCode>
									<settlement>Solna</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stockholm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SE-11321</postCode>
									<settlement>Stockholm</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Erik</forename>
								<surname>Sj</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">€</forename>
								<surname>Olund</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Stockholm Bioinformatics Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Science for Life Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SE-17121</postCode>
									<settlement>Solna</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stockholm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SE-11321</postCode>
									<settlement>Stockholm</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Erik</forename>
								<forename type="middle">L L</forename>
								<surname>Sonnhammer</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Stockholm Bioinformatics Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Science for Life Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SE-17121</postCode>
									<settlement>Solna</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stockholm University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SE-11321</postCode>
									<settlement>Stockholm</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Swedish eScience Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SE-10450</postCode>
									<settlement>Stockholm</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining MaxLink: network-based prioritization of genes tightly linked to a disease seed set</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2689" to="2690"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">18 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu344</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 3, 2014; revised on May 1, 2014; accepted on May 12, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Contact: dimitri.guala@scilifelab.se Supplementary information: Supplementary materials are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>MaxLink, a guilt-by-association network search algorithm, has been made available as a web resource and a stand-alone version. Based on a user-supplied list of query genes, MaxLink identifies and ranks genes that are tightly linked to the query list. This functionality can be used to predict potential disease genes from an initial set of genes with known association to a disease. The original algorithm, used to identify and rank novel genes potentially involved in cancer, has been updated to use a more statistically sound method for selection of candidate genes and made applicable to other areas than cancer. The algorithm has also been made faster by re-implementation in C++, and the Web site uses FunCoup 3.0 as the underlying network. Availability and implementation: MaxLink is freely available at http:// maxlink.sbc.su.se both as a web service and a stand-alone application for download.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The vast amount of gene and protein interaction data emanating from high-throughput experiments have been skillfully compiled into networks of functional associations, such as FunCoup (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Schmitt et al., 2014</ref>). These networks combine information on different types of protein–gene interactions from different species, data sources and data types to achieve a much higher quality and interaction coverage than pure protein–protein interaction networks. Owing to their high coverage, such networks have a high potential of yielding predictions about previously un-annotated gene function(s) and/or disease associations, through 'guilt-by-association' (GBA), i.e. assuming related functions of network neighbors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Lee et al., 2011</ref>). MaxLink ( €<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ostlund et al., 2010</ref>) applies a GBA algorithm to search the FunCoup network to identify and rank genes enriched in connections to a seed set of known disease genes. In the original implementation, the algorithm was tested and validated on a set of cancer genes. The new version of MaxLink has been implemented as a web resource and has been further generalized to identify and rank potential disease genes of any disease or condition where a seed set of implicated genes can be provided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">IMPLEMENTATION AND FEATURES</head><p>The original MaxLink Perl program has been re-implemented in C++, using the Boost library (http://www.boost.org/), for increased performance and a more general framework. The new MaxLink implementation takes as input a list of genes, i.e. known to be involved in a particular disease or condition. The web service is run using default or user-specified values for the following parameters: 'Query network' (default: Homo sapiens)—one of the 11 currently available model organism networks in FunCoup 3.0 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Schmitt et al., 2014</ref>); 'Network confidence threshold' (default: 0.75)—a confidence threshold for the links in the underlying network, known as pfc in FunCoup (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alexeyenko et al., 2011</ref>);and the 'Hypergeometric Cutoff' (default 0.1)—a hypergeometric probability cutoff to ensure that identified genes are statistically enriched in connections to the query set. These parameters can be altered according to user guidelines found at the MaxLink Web site. After searching the FunCoup network, a list of candidate genes is returned. The list is sorted by the connectivity to the query list (MaxLink score). The resulting list can also be visualized using jSquid (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Klammer et al., 2008</ref>) in the context of the searched FunCoup network (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). As an example query, we used the nine breast cancer genes from the COSMIC cancer gene census database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Forbes et al., 2011</ref>) with the highest number of network links. Running MaxLink with the example query returns the set of genes most strongly associated to the query set in the context of the underlying Funcoup network. The original implementation used a connectivity filter to only retain the genes with proportionally more connections to the query set than to other genes. Doing this avoided highly connected genes from being automatically counted as potential candidates solely based on their high number of interactions. In the new version, a statistically more sound approach has been implemented by calculating a hypergeometric probability score for each potential candidate based on its interactions with the query set and in total. Only candidates with a score below a cutoff are kept. This approach has been validated (Supplementary Material) on a set of rare disease genes from Orphanet (Aym e, 2003). In the original implementation, an 'annotation filter' was applied to remove genes having annotations to cancer, as only *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com novel potential cancer genes were of interest. This filter was removed in the new implementation to generalize the search to areas other than cancer. We here validate the new MaxLink on a set of genes associated with Alzheimer's disease (Supplementary Material) from the AlzGene database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bertram et al., 2007</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DISCUSSION</head><p>MaxLink, a network prioritization algorithm for genes, identified based on interactions with a seed set, has been improved by a statistically more sound specificity filtering. It is now released as a much faster C++ implementation, applicable to any set of seed genes, and available as an easy-to-use web resource. The tool can be used in general biological and applied biomedical research, e.g. prediction of potential disease genes, prioritization and/or analysis of results from GWAS/linkage studies. Other tools exist for candidate gene prioritization, many of which are collected at the Gene Prioritization Portal (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Tranchevent et al., 2011</ref>). These tools use various strategies, e.g. text mining (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gonzalez et al., 2008</ref>) or functional annotation analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Liekens et al., 2011</ref>), and data sources, e.g. gene expression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">van Dam et al., 2012</ref>) and PPI networks (K € ohler et al., 2008). Most of the tools require a distinct region of the genome as input (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Seelow et al., 2008</ref>) to narrow down the search space. In contrast, MaxLink prioritizes genes from the whole genome, applying a unique GBA algorithm to FunCoup that integrates information on several types of protein and gene associations from many species and data sources, and is one of the most comprehensive networks available. Furthermore, many of the tools use keywords as input, as opposed to MaxLink, which only uses gene sets. Gene set-based tools have been shown to perform better than keyword-based ones (B €<ref type="bibr">ornigen et al., 2012</ref>). Performance in general is, however, heavily dependent on the selection of evaluation datasets (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Csermely et al., 2013</ref>), but tools relying on more comprehensive data integration appear to be more powerful (B € ornigen et al., 2012). Performance benchmarking remains non-trivial owing to the diversity of the ways the tools are to be used, lack of solid experimental validation and knowledge contamination when statistical methods such as cross-validation are used (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Moreau and Tranchevent, 2012</ref>). A future extension of MaxLink could be to use other functional networks than FunCoup, to evaluate the algorithm on different data. This could also provide an even wider coverage of potential gene–protein functional interaction space. Furthermore, search methods such as shortest path (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Peyer et al., 2009</ref>) or PageRank (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Brin and Page, 1998</ref>) could be implemented to exploit other topological properties of the network and to test the suitability of different types of search methods and queries.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. jSquid graph of an example run of MaxLink, using default parameters and breast cancer genes from the COSMIC database (diamonds) as query. The genes identified by Maxlink in the FunCoup 3.0 network are significantly enriched (P50.1) in links to the query set, and thus predicted to be functionally important in breast cancer</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">D.Guala et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank Gabriel € Ostlund and Thomas Schmitt for contributing with ideas to the development of this resource.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative interactomics with Funcoup 2.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Alexeyenko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="821" to="828" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">[Orphanet, an information site on rare diseases]</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Aym E</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic meta-analyses of Alzheimer disease genetic association studies: the AlzGene database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Bertram</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An unbiased evaluation of gene prioritization tools</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>B€ Ornigen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3081" to="3088" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The anatomy of a large-scale hypertextual Web search engine</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Brin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Networks ISDN Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and dynamics of molecular networks: a novel paradigm of drug discovery: a comprehensive review</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Csermely</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacol. Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="408" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">COSMIC: mining complete cancer genomes in the Catalogue of Somatic Mutations in Cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Forbes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="945" to="950" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeneRanker: an online system for predicting gene-disease associations for translational research</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Gonzalez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Summit Translat. Bioinforma</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">jSquid: a Java applet for graphical on-line network exploration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Klammer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1467" to="1468" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Walking the interactome for prioritization of candidate disease genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>K€ Ohler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="949" to="958" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prioritizing candidate disease genes by network-based boosting of genome-wide association data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1109" to="1121" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioGraph: unsupervised biomedical knowledge discovery via automated hypothesis generation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M L</forename>
				<surname>Liekens</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">57</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational tools for prioritizing candidate genes: boosting disease gene discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Moreau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L.-C</forename>
				<surname>Tranchevent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="523" to="536" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network-based Identification of novel cancer genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Ostlund</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="648" to="655" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A generalization of Dijkstra&apos;s shortest path algorithm with applications to VLSI routing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Peyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Discrete Algorithms</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="377" to="390" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FunCoup 3.0: database of genome-wide functional coupling networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Schmitt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="380" to="388" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeneDistiller–distilling candidate genes from linkage intervals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Seelow</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3874</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A guide to web tools to prioritize candidate genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L.-C</forename>
				<surname>Tranchevent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeneFriends: an online co-expression analysis tool to identify novel gene targets for aging and complex diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Van Dam</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">535</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>