
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:28+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining mcaGUI: microbial community analysis R-Graphical User Interface (GUI)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wade</forename>
								<forename type="middle">K</forename>
								<surname>Copeland</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Statistics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Vandhana</forename>
								<surname>Krishnan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies (IBEST)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Daniel</forename>
								<surname>Beck</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies (IBEST)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matt</forename>
								<surname>Settles</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies (IBEST)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">James</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Foster</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies (IBEST)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kyu-Chul</forename>
								<surname>Cho</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies (IBEST)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mitch</forename>
								<surname>Day</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies (IBEST)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Roxana</forename>
								<surname>Hickey</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies (IBEST)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ursel</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M E</forename>
								<surname>Schütte</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies (IBEST)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Research in Environmental Science (CRES)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Indiana University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>47405</postCode>
									<settlement>Bloomington</settlement>
									<region>IN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xia</forename>
								<surname>Zhou</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies (IBEST)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christopher</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Williams</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Statistics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Larry</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Forney</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies (IBEST)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Idaho</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>83844</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<region>ID</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zaid</forename>
								<surname>Abdo</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>zabdo@uidaho.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Statistics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining mcaGUI: microbial community analysis R-Graphical User Interface (GUI)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2198" to="2199"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts338</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on September 6, 2011; revised on May 18, 2012; accepted on June 7, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [19:04 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts338.tex] Page: 2198 2198–2199 Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Supplementary Information: Supplementary data and figures are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Microbial communities have an important role in natural ecosystems and have an impact on animal and human health. Intuitive graphic and analytical tools that can facilitate the study of these communities are in short supply. This article introduces Microbial Community Analysis GUI, a graphical user interface (GUI) for the R-programming language (R Development Core Team, 2010). With this application, researchers can input aligned and clustered sequence data to create custom abundance tables and perform analyses specific to their needs. This GUI provides a flexible modular platform, expandable to include other statistical tools for microbial community analysis in the future. Availability: The mcaGUI package and source are freely available as part of Bionconductor at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Several graphical user interface software (GUI) packages exist for the analysis of microbial community data. These programs include InVUE, which specializes in creating interactive graphical representations for large datasets (<ref type="bibr">Ravel et al., 2011</ref>) and UniFrac, a web-based GUI that allows users to compare microbial communities using phylogenetic information (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Lozupone et al., 2006</ref>). Many of these applications were built using programming languages such as C and C++. Currently, there are few GUIs specifically available for the analysis of microbial communities that also take advantage of the R programming language. This article introduces Microbial Community Analysis GUI (mcaGUI), an R-package built to help microbial biologists harness the power of statistical analysis tools provided in R without having to learn the R programming language. Using mcaGUI, researchers can perform statistical analyses and create various interactive and analytical data representations specific to microbial ecology. * To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p><p>What distinguishes mcaGUI from similar applications is its ability to directly input aligned sequence data that provide information about microbial community composition. This allows researchers to create custom abundance tables using both sample metadata and data on operational taxonomic units (OTU). mcaGUI is modular and expandable; it provides a platform that can be extended to include more functionality in the future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>mcaGUI has a simple layout that is divided into three parts (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. S1</ref>). The left side of the screen contains the variable browser, which shows all created variables or objects that contain imported data and outcomes of data manipulations such as richness estimates. On the top right is the tabbed browser where the data can be viewed in tabular form and analyses are performed. For most operations in mcaGUI, a new tab opens where the user can input additional arguments. On the bottom right is the command window where information and output of some operations is shown. We implemented package OTUbase (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Beck et al., 2011</ref>) to simplify loading sequence data into R. These data, along with all relevant information, are stored in an R object and can be used to construct custom abundance tables. OTU abundance tables can also be loaded directly but with limited customization options.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">BIOLOGICAL APPLICATIONS</head><p>mcaGUI provides an interface to access a set of statistical tools to summarize and analyze microbial community data such as principal component analysis (PCA), cluster analysis and others (see Supplementary Table S1 for a detailed listing). A complete workflow with examples, along with detailed description of data input and output, can be found in the Supplementary material. Herein, we introduce three examples to illustrate the use of mcaGUI. The first illustrates how to input sequence data and create custom abundance tables. The second illustrates how to estimate microbial richness and evenness. The third illustrates how to perform PCA. These examples utilize the 454 pyrosequencing data presented in<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Sogin et al. (2006)</ref>that were used to study and compare the microbial community composition and diversity in seven oceanic sites. Elaborate details for each of these examples can be found in the Supplementary material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Microbial community analysis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Example 1: create a custom abundance table</head><p>To create a custom abundance table, the user must first input sequence data. This is done by navigating to the File Menu and clicking the Read OTUbase option (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>). Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S3</ref>shows an image with filled in values for reading in the<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Sogin et al. (2006)</ref>sequence data. Once the data are loaded, the user can navigate to the Data Menu and press the Abundance Table option (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S4</ref>). The user can customize the rows and columns of the abundance table by pressing the Update Feature and Sample Meta-Data button. Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S5</ref>shows the dialogue box by which the user creates an abundance table on the genus level aggregated by site. The researcher can either save this custom abundance table or use it in further analyses within the mcaGUI interface.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Example 2: richness and diversity estimation</head><p>Richness and diversity can be estimated by navigating to the Analysis Menu and Clicking the Richness Estimation or Diversity Estimation buttons, respectively (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S6</ref>). An abundance table should be specified and the output table of estimates should be assigned to a new variable (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S7</ref>). Estimates can be accessed by double clicking this new variable in the variable browser (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S8</ref>). The researcher can then use built in tools to plot these estimates or export the results to a delimited data file that can be used with other programs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Example 3: using PCA to view groups of correlated OTUs</head><p>We perform a PCA analysis by navigating to the Analysis Menu, Multivariate and then PCA. Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S9</ref>shows the dialogue window for PCA. Plot 2D displays a biplot with the first two PCA coordinates (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1</ref>).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 1</ref>indicates that Acidimicrobidae is associated with lower deep water while Cystobacteraceae is associated with Labrador seawater, for example. Plot 3D shows an interactive biplot in the first three PCA coordinates. These plots allow the user to zoom in and out and rotate the axes to identify interesting patterns in the data. Selecting Scree Plot or Elbow plot, displays a graphic used to identify which PCA directions account for most of the variation in the data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">THE GRAPHICAL VIEW</head><p>mcaGUI provides both basic and interactive graphics. When Bootstrap Interval Estimation is used (Supplementary material), mcaGUI returns histograms that show the bootstrap distribution of each statistic requested. When using PCA the user can view a biplot in the first three PCA directions and interactively explore the space. Other graphical tools include histograms, box plots, scatter plots, pairs-plots and cluster diagrams.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>Poor Man's GUI (<ref type="bibr">Verzani, 2010</ref>) provided the base layout for mcaGUI. Additional functionality was added with the gWidgets (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Verzani, 2007</ref>) and gWidgetsRGtk2 (Lawrence and Verzani 2011) R-packages. All GUI layouts were created using Widget and Handler combinations; a widget is an object that specifies a layout, and a handler is an action that is then used by the widget to run analyses. Utilizing these tools, new functionality can be added by linking pre-existing packages to this GUI.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>ABSTRACT Summary: Microbial communities have an important role in natural ecosystems and have an impact on animal and human health.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [19:04 19/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts338.tex] Page: 2199 2198–2199</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Example output of a Biplot created using mcaGUI. The data used is from Sogin et al. (2006) but the number of observations and explanatory variables were reduced to improve readability</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>1 Department of Biological Sciences, 2 Department of Mathematics, 3 Department of Statistics and 4 Institute of Bioinformatics and Evolutionary Studies (IBEST), University of Idaho, Moscow, ID 83844, USA and 5 Center for Research in Environmental Science (CRES), Indiana University, Bloomington, IN 47405, USA</figDesc><table>Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Contact: wade@kingcopeland.com; zabdo@uidaho.edu Supplementary Information: Supplementary data and figures are available at Bioinformatics online.</figDesc><table>Received on September 6, 2011; revised on May 18, 2012; accepted 
on June 7, 2012 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank John Verzani for his development and assistance with Poor Man's GUI.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OTUBase: an R infrastructure package for taxonomic unit data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Beck</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1700" to="1701" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UniFrac—an online tool for comparing microbial community diversity in a phylogenetic context</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Lozupone</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">371</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Microbial diversity in the deep sea and the underexplored &apos;rare biosphere</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Sogin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<publisher>PNAS</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12115" to="12120" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Introduction to gWidgets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Verzani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">R News</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>