
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">MEANS: python package for Moment Expansion Approximation, iNference and Simulation</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sisi</forename>
								<surname>Fan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Integrative Systems Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Quentin</forename>
								<surname>Geissmann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Integrative Systems Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eszter</forename>
								<surname>Lakatos</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Integrative Systems Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Saulius</forename>
								<surname>Lukauskas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Integrative Systems Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Angelique</forename>
								<surname>Ale</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Integrative Systems Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ann</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Babtie</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Integrative Systems Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Paul</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D W</forename>
								<surname>Kirk</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">MRC Biostatistics Unit</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB2 0SR</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P H</forename>
								<surname>Stumpf</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>: m.stumpf@imperial.ac.uk or e.lakatos13@imperial.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Integrative Systems Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">MEANS: python package for Moment Expansion Approximation, iNference and Simulation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw229</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on September 30, 2015; revised on March 23, 2016; accepted on April 21, 2016</note>
					<note>Systems biology *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Alfonso Valencia † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first four authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Many biochemical systems require stochastic descriptions. Unfortunately these can only be solved for the simplest cases and their direct simulation can become prohibitively expensive , precluding thorough analysis. As an alternative, moment closure approximation methods generate equations for the time-evolution of the system&apos;s moments and apply a closure ansatz to obtain a closed set of differential equations; that can become the basis for the deterministic analysis of the moments of the outputs of stochastic systems. Results: We present a free, user-friendly tool implementing an efficient moment expansion approximation with parametric closures that integrates well with the IPython interactive environment. Our package enables the analysis of complex stochastic systems without any constraints on the number of species and moments studied and the type of rate laws in the system. In addition to the approximation method our package provides numerous tools to help non-expert users in stochas-tic analysis. Availability and implementation: https://github.com/theosysbio/means Contacts</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Inherent stochasticity of elementary reactions affects many biochemical processes. Analytic solutions of stochastic systems are rarely available and simulations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Gillespie, 1977</ref>) can come with high computational costs making the study of such systems implausible. Numerous approximation methods have been developed recently to lighten the burden. A popular approach is to approximate the whole system by following the moments of the temporally evolving probability distribution, such as in the Moment Expansiongamma not available in other packages. Furthermore, the package is complemented with an implementation of exact stochastic simulation, as well as support for different ODE solvers and sensitivity analysis, a parameter estimation tool and specific functions for the visualization of results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Approach</head><p>For a thorough description of the moment expansion and closure algorithms we refer the user to<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ale et al. (2013) and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Lakatos et al. (2015)</ref>. In brief, given a stochastic system of N species by its stoichiometry matrix (S) and reaction propensities (a), the evolution of the species' probability distribution P(x, t) is described in terms of its moments, which can be evaluated through its moment generating function (wrt h),</p><formula>dm dt ¼ X l ðe hS l;: À 1Þ X x e hx PðxÞa l ðxÞ " # : (1)</formula><p>The expressions thus obtained are then evaluated through two subsequent Taylor expansions. Two steps are used to derive a closed ODE system: first, for an approximation based on mth order moments, the expansion is stopped at order ðm þ 1Þ; then moment closure formulae (mc k ) are used to substitute the highest order terms with expressions of means (l) and (co)variances (R) d dt Eðb x m Þ ¼ f ðl;. .. ; Eðb x m Þ; mc ðmþ1Þ ðl; RÞÞ:</p><formula>(2)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Methods</head><p>MEANS is a Python package, primarily developed to be used interactively in the IPython/Jupyter notebook framework. Pre-requisites and installation instructions are listed in the accompanying documentation. MEANS enables the definition and exact simulation of stochastic models; moment-based approximations for arbitrary stochastic system and closure order; numerical solution, sensitivity analysis and parameter inference of ODE systems generated by the approximation or defined by the user; and customizable visualization for the output. Detailed tutorial notebooks demonstrating the functionalities of the package are available from the tutorial directory. Input: The stochastic system can be supplied by manual input of a symbolic representation of the variables and reactions, all supported by the SymPy library (SymPy Development<ref type="bibr">Team, 2014</ref>); this is then converted into a specific model object. There is also a parser enabling model definition from SBML-files. Furthermore, four predefined models are available from the examples package. Our package also offers a set of routines for serialization and deserialization of the MEANS-specific objects to and from files, therefore previously defined models are easily saved and loaded. Approximation and closure: The MEA method can be called through the mea_approximation function, which requires two arguments: a MEANS model object and the closure order. The default closure method is scalar (truncation); distribution-based methods can be used by setting the closure argument of the function. MEANS supports normal, lognormal and gamma closures, the latter based on a new definition of multivariate gamma distribution designed to fit general biochemical networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Lakatos et al., 2015</ref>). When univariate distributions are desired, the parameter multivariate 5 False can be passed to the closure function. We can also generate Linear Noise Approximation expressions by calling the function lna_approximation where the model is the single argument. Simulation: MEANS uses Assimulo (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Andersson et al., 2015</ref>) as the ODE solver back-end, and supports all solvers and settings implemented in that package, which can be accessed via the optional argument solver. The default value is ode15s, which corresponds to the MATLAB function with the same name. The simulation returns a collection of Trajectory objects, each containing a list of timepoints, values and a description of the moment. Stochastic systems can be also directly simulated in MEANS by providing the model and the number of simulations as input. Furthermore, parameter sensitivities can be computed while performing the ODE simulations using the built-in support of CVODE solvers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hindmarsh et al., 2005</ref>). Sensitivity analysis returns a collection of trajectory objects with additional .sensitivity_data attribute. Inference: Parameter estimation is also available in MEANS; for this function the observed data can be entered manually or read from a file; and then converted into a Trajectory object with appropriate descriptors so that means and higher moments can be matched. Variable parameters are defined by a dictionary of the symbolic names and corresponding ranges of allowed values; range None indicates unbounded parameters, and all unspecified parameters are assumed constant. Starting values for the parameters can be user-defined or generated automatically by optimizing runs from random starting positions sampled from a defined range; we advise the latter to lower the chance of finding local minima. Visualization: Trajectory objects can be visualized in the notebook, see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>(a). A customizable .plot() method allows the use of all options of the standard matplotlib plot function. Sensitivity behaviour can be illustrated using .plot_perturbations(), which visualizes the result of perturbing a single parameter with a specified delta value,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>(b). Inferred trajectories can also be visualized using the result object's .plot() method, cf.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>(c). MEANS alsohas functions to plot the distance landscape and intermediate solutions in order to aid the analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Summary</head><p>We present MEANS, a Python package, for the approximation of the time-evolution of stochastic biochemical networks using moment expansion with moment closure formulae based on multivariate normal, lognormal and newly defined gamma distributions. Besides the derivation of moment equations, MEANS also offers several methods to simulate stochastic models, as well as tools for sensitivity analysis and parameter inference.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>QG and SL thank the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Default graphical output of MEANS. Labels are automatically generated. (a) Second order moments. (b) Outcome of sensitivity analysis: original trajectory with region covered if a single parameter is perturbed. (c) Result of inference with restarts: light lines show starting trajectories considered, dark lines show the best starting position and the final fit.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Council for PhD funding; EL acknowledges a Schrö dinger Scholarship, and AA an Medical Research Council Fellowship. ACB and MPHS acknowledge funding from the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council, and PK and MPHS through Human Frontiers Science Programme grant RGP0061/2011. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">Approximation (MEA) (Ale et al., 2013). However, for nonlinear systems the equation set arising from such methods is in principle infinite. Moment closure formulae address this problem by offering a substitute expression of moments over a certain order, based on information contained in the remaining moments and prior assumptions on the system (Gillespie, 2009). For a more detailed literature review on this technique see Lakatos et al. (2015). Here we present MEANS, a Python package for Moment Expansion Approximation, iNference and Simulation. Many existing packages with a similar function restrict the calculation to polynomial reaction rates; besides, an analysis based on them might require expensive softwares or computational skills not generally available to all potential users (Azunre et al., 2011; Schnoerr et al., 2015; see also http://www.ece.ucsb.edu/hespanha). Our package on the other hand, provides an automated moment equation generation method, suitable for arbitrary rate laws; together with the choice of distribution-based closure formulae, including a multivariate V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. 1 This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. Bioinformatics, 2016, 1–3 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw229 Advance Access Publication Date: 5 May 2016 Applications Note Bioinformatics Advance Access published June 2, 2016 at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general moment expansion method for stochastic kinetic models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ale</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assimulo: A unified framework for ode solvers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Andersson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Comput. Simul</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mass fluctuation kinetics: analysis and computation of equilibria and local dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Azunre</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IET Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">335</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moment-closure approximations for mass-action models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Gillespie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IET Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exact stochastic simulation of coupled chemical reactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Gillespie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2340" to="2361" />
			<date type="published" when="1977" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sundials: suite of nonlinear and differential/algebraic equation solvers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Hindmarsh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Trans. Math. Softw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="396" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multivariate moment closure techniques for stochastic kinetic models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Lakatos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">94107</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of different moment-closure approximations for stochastic chemical kinetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Schnoerr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SymPy: Python Library for Symbolic</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SymPy Development Team</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>