
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:31+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Mechanotransduction map: simulation model, molecular pathway, gene set</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jennifer</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Dent</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Group of Clinical Genomic Networks</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Global Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CAS-MPG Partner Institute for Computational Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2 Quintiles</addrLine>
									<settlement>Shanghai, Reading</settlement>
									<region>Berkshire</region>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China, UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Valentina</forename>
								<surname>Devescovi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Group of Clinical Genomic Networks</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Global Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CAS-MPG Partner Institute for Computational Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2 Quintiles</addrLine>
									<settlement>Shanghai, Reading</settlement>
									<region>Berkshire</region>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China, UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Han</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Group of Clinical Genomic Networks</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Global Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CAS-MPG Partner Institute for Computational Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2 Quintiles</addrLine>
									<settlement>Shanghai, Reading</settlement>
									<region>Berkshire</region>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China, UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pietro</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Di</forename>
								<surname>Lena</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Engineering -DISI</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bologna</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bologna</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Youtao</forename>
								<surname>Lu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Group of Clinical Genomic Networks</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Global Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CAS-MPG Partner Institute for Computational Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2 Quintiles</addrLine>
									<settlement>Shanghai, Reading</settlement>
									<region>Berkshire</region>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China, UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yuanhua</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Group of Clinical Genomic Networks</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Global Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CAS-MPG Partner Institute for Computational Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2 Quintiles</addrLine>
									<settlement>Shanghai, Reading</settlement>
									<region>Berkshire</region>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China, UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christine</forename>
								<surname>Nardini</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Group of Clinical Genomic Networks</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Global Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CAS-MPG Partner Institute for Computational Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2 Quintiles</addrLine>
									<settlement>Shanghai, Reading</settlement>
									<region>Berkshire</region>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China, UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Mechanotransduction map: simulation model, molecular pathway, gene set</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu776</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 30, 2014; revised on October 30, 2014; accepted on November 17, 2014</note>
					<note>Systems biology †The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first three authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Igor Jurisica Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Mechanotransduction—the ability to output a biochemical signal from a mechanical input—is related to the initiation and progression of a broad spectrum of molecular events. Yet, the characterization of mechanotransduction lacks some of the most basic tools as, for instance, it can hardly be recognized by enrichment analysis tools, nor could we find any pathway representation. This greatly limits computational testing and hypothesis generation on mechanotransduction biological relevance and involvement in disease or physiological mechanisms. Results: We here present a molecular map of mechanotransduction, built in CellDesigner to warrant that maximum information is embedded in a compact network format. To validate the map&apos;s necessity we tested its redundancy in comparison with existing pathways, and to estimate its suffi-ciency, we quantified its ability to reproduce biological events with dynamic simulations, using Signaling Petri Networks. Availability and implementation: SMBL language map is available in the Supplementary Data:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Mechanotransduction is a ubiquitous phenomenon, the importance and complexity of which has not yet been fully captured. Yet, mechanical stresses are triggers for wound healing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Cordeiro and Jacinto, 2013</ref>) and can initiate epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) in the presence of inflammation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Gomez et al., 2010</ref>). Both these phenomena are tightly related and important in the understanding of broader events like development (EMT Type 1), tissue regeneration/ healing (EMT Type 2) and tumorigenesis (EMT Type 3) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kalluri, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Kalluri and Weinberg, 2009</ref>). Therefore, the understanding of these events for applications in regenerative and cancer medicine (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Roussos et al., 2010</ref>), as well as in the treatment of inflammatory and autoimmune diseases (<ref type="bibr">Gonzá lez et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Lu et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Schä fer and Werner, 2008</ref>), is of crucial importance. In addition, given the possibility to induce mechanical stimuli in a relatively ample number of (accidental) ways (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Hattori et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Pecchi et al., 2014</ref>), understanding the extent of the phenomenon acquires practical relevance in numerous clinical areas. We observed, however, that, despite its importance, mechanotransduction is poorly represented in terms of pathways and molecular maps, which are nevertheless crucial tools when medical research is performed in the frame of omic studies as it is the case for a growing number of maladies, trying to unravel the complexity of chronic inflammatory autoimmune diseases and cancers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Shen et al., 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Wu et al., 2010</ref>). For this reason, we reconstructed the molecular map of mechanotransduction using approved standard (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Hucka et al., 2003</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hucka et al., , 2004</ref>) which allows a detailed and yet compact description of the relations ongoing among molecules, easy sharing and editing of the map as well as topological analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bonnet et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Smoot et al., 2011</ref>) and dynamic simulations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dent et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Theocharidis et al., 2009</ref>). Having built this map we were able to better quantify its overlap (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dent et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Di Lena et al., 2013</ref>) with known pathways in Reactome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Croft et al., 2011</ref>) and Panther (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Mi et al., 2005</ref>). The non-statistically significant overlaps with the pathways in these two databases imply minimum redundancy, confirming the need for a mechanotransduction pathway representation. We then validated the map's ability to reproduce known information by dynamic simulations mimicking published experimental settings (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Gomez et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Langevin et al., 2006</ref>). Given the successful tests run on the map's ability to mimic the effects of mechanical stress in relation to inflammation, relevant for example in rheumatic diseases, this network becomes an appropriate and flexible tool for the preliminary investigation in silico of therapeutic alternatives and side effects of mechanical stresses in inflammation-related contexts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Map necessity</head><p>A mechanotransduction map was built with the species (genes, transcripts, proteins, listed in SupplementaryInfo1 Table S1) collected from 15 high-quality publications reported in SupplementaryInfo1 Table S2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Chalfie, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chiquet et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Dupont et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Farge, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Gomez et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Hoffman et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Ingber, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Langevin et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Marshall and Lumpkin, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Mendez and Janmey, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Schwarz and Gardel, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Somogyi and Rørth, 2004</ref>;<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Wall and Banes, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Zebda et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Zhang and Labouesse, 2012</ref>) manually curated and reported in the CellDesigner standard (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hucka et al., 2004</ref>). The map comes in two versions both available at http://www.picb.ac.cn/ ClinicalGenomicNTW/Mechanotransduction.html, one named core, built exclusively from literature, collecting 67 species and 47 reactions (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1A</ref>) and one named basic, which includes extensions from KEGG pathways (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kanehisa and Goto, 2000</ref>) increasing the size to 234 species and 245 reactions. The maps were initially tested with MIMO (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Di Lena et al., 2013</ref>) to assess the maps' necessity in terms of redundancy with publicly available CellDesigner pathways, and namely Reactome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Croft et al., 2011</ref>) and Panther (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Croft et al., 2011</ref>). This type of test builds on classical enrichment analyses which are typically assessed by taking into account the amount of common molecules in two pathways. MIMO, however, adds to this the analysis at the reaction level, to keep into account the way in which molecules interact. Our results indicate that the overlap is limited, i.e. non-statistically significant, nor biologically relevant. In fact, at the molecular level, the overlap (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1B</ref>,<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>and SupplementaryInfo1 Tables S3–S5, column 2) concerns a very limited and scattered number of extra to intraintracellular signal effectors such as extracellular Ca 2þ intake and activation at the cell membrane level of phospholipases C, beta (PLCb 1-4), an important player in the initiation of mechano-mediated and receptor-mediated signal transduction by generation of second messengers like inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate (IP3). The transduction of the mechanical stimulus is next embodied directly in the cytosol in the RHOs family (RAC1, CDC42) and the actin protein filaments (F-actin). Finally, EMT-related molecules appear in the nucleus, marked by the epithelial adhesive cadherins. Even when extending the map (i.e. basic map) the number of overlapping molecules only slightly increases (SupplementaryInfo1 Tables S4–S5, column 2). When shifting from the overlapping molecules to the overlapping pathways, Immune System, Inflammation and several downstreamspecific signal transductions represent a higher amount of matching, but still involving only a few molecules and reactions from the core/ basic maps (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>and SupplementaryInfo1 Tables S3–S5, column 3). This overlap, not significant, nevertheless indicates where the connection of the effects of mechanical stimulation to inflammatory conditions occurs, i.e. at one subunit of the master kinase for<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Croft et al., 2011</ref>), processed by MIMO (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Di Lena et al., 2013</ref>). The names of the mapped molecules are separated by a double underscore (__), where the first portion refers to the mechanotransduction map and the second to the whole human Reactome map. The emerging overlaps are extremely fragmented and concern extracellular Ca 2þ intake, activation of phospholipases C, beta 1-4 (PLCb 1-4) signaling and generation of cytosolic inositol 3P as consequence. Mechanotransduction typical signals like RHOs family (e.g. RAC1, CDC42) activities and cytoskeletal structural protein actin filaments (F-actin) are interested at the cytosol level, whereas cell-to-cell adhesion molecules (cadherins) emerge in the nucleus NF-jB activation (nuclear factor of kappa light polypeptide gene enhancer in B-cells 1), namely conserved helix-loop-helix ubiquitous kinase, and the NF-jB inducible factor protein tyrosine kinase 2, see basic map with Reactome overlap (SupplementaryInfo1 Table S4, column 3). Globally, both molecules and pathways comparison analyses outline a lack of information about mechanotransduction as a defined signaling network in the two public databases.MIMO-detected hits were filtered by removing those involving less than three molecules or less than three reactions. Overlap between two pathways is quantified by counting the respective fraction of matched reactions. A weight is assigned to every matched reaction depending on the number of matched molecules that take part to the reaction. The Overlap score<ref type="bibr">[0,</ref><ref type="bibr">1]</ref>gives an estimation of how much the query pathway (mechanotransduction core) is contained into the target pathway (Reactome pathways). The largest overlaps, Mechanotransduction core versus Immune System pathway, involve only 6 out of 65 species and 3 out of 47 reactions. appear unchanged. With the same rationale we considered the actomyosin complex.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Map sufficiency</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Simulation relevant in autoimmunity</head><p>We then moved to test the altered condition, relevant to autoimmune diseases and injured tissues, represented by an inflamed microenvironment. In such situations both physical stresses and biochemical signals' complexities are increased, and mechanical stresses trigger wound healing where EMT occurs in cells needing to be competent (i.e. motile phenotype, cell proliferation, ECM deposition) to remodel tissue around the wound (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Cordeiro and Jacinto, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Gomez et al., 2010</ref>). To perform this simulation we observed the behavior of markers of EMT (<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>, rows 10–12): TWIST1 (twist<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. Molecules in column 1 belong to the reconstructed mechanotransduction map (core), compared with the activity observed in two experimental setting published, respectively, (<ref type="bibr">Langevin et al., 2006b</ref>) and (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Gomez et al., 2010</ref>). When the exact molecule is not shared between our map and the published results, proxies are chosen from literature. Prefix r, standing for RNA, indicates transcripts, while the absence of a prefix indicates proteins. The input of the simulation is the variation of the force. 'NA' indicates that the molecule was not tested in the corresponding experiment, '-' that the molecule shows no significant change upon force activation, ':' and ';' indicate statistically significant up and downregulation, respectively, accompanied by the t-values. In simulation the qualitative trend of activation of the gene is also presented with time blocks on the x-axis and tokens on the y-axis (for larger figures and details see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). MAL, a known early gene, bound to SRC (MAL:SRC) clearly presents the early gene pattern of activity (tokens count, y-axis) over 100 time blocks (x-axis) in simulation. Columns 5–8–9 indicate by means of ticks and crosses the agreement between the experiments and the corresponding simulation family bHLH transcription factor 1) and CDH1, also known as Ecadherin (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Lee and Nelson, 2012</ref>), which expression is considered a clear indicator of the switch to EMT program (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kroepil et al., 2012</ref>) in a computational model of tissue inflammation (100 tokens at time 0 on TGFb). In our results, the activation of the immediate early MAL and late RHOA/RAC1—actomyosin mechanotransduction signaling— matches with the activity of CDH1 and TWIST1 during the EM transition (i.e. up and down, respectively). As a final test, inflammation was also monitored with the sole molecule (IL1b; interleukin 1, beta) that behaves differentially in the two simulations settings (inflamed versus non-inflamed tissue, i.e. transforming growth factor, beta, TGFb ¼ 100 and TGFb ¼ 500, respectively,<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>, row 13). IL1b is an inflammatory cytokine that can stimulate the release of prostaglandin and collagenase from connective cells (i.e. synovial fibroblasts—Van<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Damme et al., 1985</ref>), coherently up-regulated in the second setting only.In conclusion the map can describe the TGFb-mediated EMT, and its early regulation by MAL nuclear transition and environmental mechanical forces, as previously validated in an inflammatory experimental model by<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Gomez et al. (2010)</ref>. Investigating the aspects of EMT for tissue healing in inflammation is relevant in health and disease, since this process drives tissue remodeling to protect and repair injuries; yet if the transition becomes uncontrolled, like in chronic inflamed tissues, a scarring tissue overgrowth (fibrosis) happens, resulting in organ dysfunction and eventually failure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Wynn, 2008</ref>). For this reason the information on crucial signals of mechanotransduction (RHOs Family; actomyosin and catenin beta 1, CTNN1) together with EMT (CDH1, TWIST1) and inflammation (NF-jB, TGFb and transforming growth factor beta receptor) that our map is able to gain are of great relevance for the application of mechanical stimuli as means to control EMT, the reverse phenomenon MET and to gain insight for example into treatments of tissue fibrosis, all with clinical implications in inflammatory chronic diseases, such as Arthritis and Diabetes, as well as wound healing and fibrosis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Wong et al., 2012</ref>). Overall,<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>shows high coherence with the simulation results matching experimental results for four of the five tested molecules (the exception being the failure of the simulation to match experimental results for RAC1 when considered alone and not as the synergistic RHOs family) and overall coherence summarized at 100%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Map construction</head><p>The map was designed based on the species listed in SupplementaryInfo1 Table S1 collected from 15 high-quality publications reported in SupplementaryInfo1 Table S2 and manually curated in CellDesigner (http://www.picb.ac.cn/ClinicalGenomic NTW/Mechanotransduction.html). Complexes were either treated as units, like ion channels and hemichannels, similarly to what is done in Reactome (REACT_160271.1, TPCN1/2 transport lysosomal Ca 2þ to cytosol); or explicated in a literature-based selection of their components, like the actomyosin complex, based on the functionality of the complex itself. All implementative choices are detailed in SupplementaryInfo1, column NOTES. For the map construction, genes (nodes) were all converted to human official gene symbols and for comparison with published experiments further converted to mouse homologues (http://www. ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/unigene/). In the text we used the human genes symbols for molecules when we referred to our results, and mouse genes symbols when we referred to published data. The maps come in two versions based on the origin of the nodes: the core map, contains nodes extracted exclusively from literature; the basic map includes nodes from KEGG pathways (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kanehisa and Goto, 2000</ref>). Such an extension was operated by using each of the core molecules as a query term in KEGG, and by adding the corresponding pathway into the basic map. For both maps the connections between nodes, when not explicated in literature, were based on the KEGG Orthology (KO) groups, in order to generalize evidence obtained in specific organisms to other organisms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Map overlap</head><p>The pathway comparison analysis was performed with MIMO (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Di Lena et al., 2013</ref>) against the set of human pathways annotated in the Reactome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Croft et al., 2011</ref>) and Panther (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Mi et al., 2005</ref>) repositories. The popular KEGG pathways (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kanehisa and Goto, 2000</ref>) were excluded from this analysis, since currently we did not find tools able to automatically convert in full KEGG pathways in SBML format (with the exception of the metabolic pathways). MIMO requires in input two pathways in SBML format (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Hucka et al., 2003</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hucka et al., , 2004</ref>), a list of allowed mappings between molecules in the two pathways and a maximum length-parameter N. In short, each pathway in input is spliced into a set of shortest paths, of maximum length N, between molecules. A shortest path simply identifies the shortest chain of reactions connecting two molecules. Two chains of reactions (one in each pathway) are considered equivalent if both molecules at their extremes can be matched, according to the list provided in input. The overlap is then obtained by detecting the largest set of equivalent chains in the two pathways. The analysis was performed with N ¼ 3. The list of mappings between molecules was obtained automatically by pattern matching between the names assigned to molecules in the Mechanotransduction and Reactome/Panther pathways. Since the name identifiers adopted in Reactome are usually human-readable and non-standard, the string identifiers in Reactome were extended by including all their possible synonyms (such as standard gene/protein names). The list of names/synonyms for the participating molecules in a Reactome pathway can be obtained automatically from the Reactome website (http://www.reactome.org). The core and basic mechanotrasduction maps were compared with the whole human map in Reactome to detect the largest possible set of common reactions. In addition, to allow an automated analysis of the biological meaning of such overlaps, enrichments on the entire collection of Reactome pathways (which constitute the whole map) was carried out at the reaction level (single reactions are identified by a unique internal ID, i.e. the same reaction in different pathways is identified by its unique ID) by performing a standard Fisher's exact test on the set of reactions highlighted in the overlap with the whole human Reactome map. The same approach could not be replicated on the Panther dataset, since Panther provides only a collection of single pathways and not a full map on human.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Simulations</head><p>The maps' input was identified in the Force (node: force@extracellular) and molecular modifications were simulated dynamically in the Signaling Petri Network frame after transforming the CellDesigner map into a compatible BiolayoutExpress3D input (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Theocharidis et al., 2009</ref>), using the SPNConverter plugin we recently designed (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dent et al., 2013</ref>). Based on previous approaches (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dent and Nardini, 2013</ref>), we created a set of baseline conditions, where all edge nodes were assigned 100 tokens at time 0. As the simulation model runs, and at each time point, tokens are passed through gates between molecules. As the number of tokens at a molecule rises and falls with time, we see a representation of, in the case of the mechanotransduction map, gene regulation and mechanical stress [e.g. an increase in the number of tokens representing upregulation and a decrease, downregulation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Ruths et al., 2008)]</ref>. Over the course of the simulation, most networks will reach a stable state, where the number of tokens at nodes within the network no longer fluctuates significantly. By changing the number of tokens that a molecule is assigned at time 0, we can consider the potential effect that perturbing specific molecules may have on the map. Thus, simulation reproducing the setting in<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Gomez et al. (2010)</ref>was achieved by preserving the baseline conditions of 100 tokens at time 0 at all edge nodes, with the exception of TGFB, which was assigned 500 tokens (for simulated upregulation). The number of tokens assigned to force was then increased from 100 to 500 (SupplementaryInfo1<ref type="figure">Table S6</ref>). Simulations reproducing the setting of<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Langevin et al. (2006)</ref>were performed with the baseline conditions preserved, and changing only the number of tokens assigned to 'force' (SupplementaryInfo1<ref type="figure">Table S7</ref>). One hundred time points and 1000 simulations were run for each setting. Evaluation of the statistical significance of the differentially expressed genes was computed by considering the number of molecules that were significantly different at the 100th time point, compared with the baseline conditions. To determine the statistical significance of the differentially expressed genes in the simulations the t-value was calculated at each time point for the baseline and perturbed distributions according to the equation:where l i;s and r 2 i;s represent the mean and variance of the number of tokens at node i, for the baseline (b) and perturbed (p) networks, respectively. Comparing the absolute t-value with the corresponding critical value (t0.05, 1000 ¼ 1.96) at the 100th (and thus most stable) time point, those molecules whose expression level significantly changed in each simulation were identified. Experiments to evaluate the stability of the simulation were performed by repeating simulations around force stimulation three times on both the core and basic maps (SupplementaryInfo1 Tables S8–S9). Results of Wilcoxon rank sum tests showed no statistical difference between simulations runs. Overlap between molecules significantly changed (P &lt; 0.05) in different simulation runs lead to different levels of reproducibility (percent overlap) for the core ($90%) and basic maps ($60%) with no changes when raising the number of simulations to 5000 (SupplementaryInfo1<ref type="figure" target="#tab_0">Table S10</ref>). For this reason, dynamic simulations were run on the core map only, assuming it reaches the limit size for simulations with BiolayoutExpress3D (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Theocharidis et al., 2009</ref>). The first set of simulation results was preserved as our reference. All statistical analyses were performed in R v2.13.0 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Ihaka and Gentleman, 1996</ref>).Conflict of Interest: Jennifer E. Dent declares that although all work was conducted under the EU-FP7-PEOPLE-2011-IRSES program, her current (and only) affiliation is with Quintiles, which is a public company.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. (A) Snapshot of the reconstructed Celldesigner mechanotransduction map, including 67 species and 47 reactions (the SMBL file is available at http://www.picb.ac.cn/ClinicalGenomicNTW/Mechanotransduction.html). (B) Overlap between the mechanotransduction map and the whole human set of Reactome pathways (Croft et al., 2011), processed by MIMO (Di Lena et al., 2013). The names of the mapped molecules are separated by a double underscore (__), where the first portion refers to the mechanotransduction map and the second to the whole human Reactome map. The emerging overlaps are extremely fragmented and concern extracellular Ca 2þ intake, activation of phospholipases C, beta 1-4 (PLCb 1-4) signaling and generation of cytosolic inositol 3P as consequence. Mechanotransduction typical signals like RHOs family (e.g. RAC1, CDC42) activities and cytoskeletal structural protein actin filaments (F-actin) are interested at the cytosol level, whereas cell-to-cell adhesion molecules (cadherins) emerge in the nucleus</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>This project was funded by MoST international cooperation program [no. 2013DFA30790, and NSFC n. 31070748], JED collaborated in the frame of the European Commission [FP7-PEOPLE-2011-IRSES program 31028760, project ID 294935].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>; V C The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com 1053 Bioinformatics, 31(7), 2015, 1053–1059 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btu776 Advance Access Publication Date: 25 November 2014 Original Paper</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Ranked reactome pathways overlapping with the mechanotransduction core map</figDesc><table>Pathway name 
Overlap 
score 

#Matched 
molecules 

#Matched 
reactions 

Immune system 
0.0496 
6 
3 
Innate immune system 
0.0496 
6 
3 
Adaptive immune system 
0.0496 
6 
3 
Developmental biology 
0.0390 
3 
2 
Axon guidance 
0.0390 
3 
2 
Downstream signal transduction 
0.0355 
5 
3 
Signaling by PDGF 
0.0355 
5 
3 
Signaling by GPCR 
0.0355 
4 
2 
GPCR downstream signaling 
0.0355 
4 
2 
Hemostasis 
0.0355 
4 
2 
Fcgamma receptor-dependent 
phagocytosis 

0.0355 
4 
2 

Apoptotic execution phase 
0.0355 
4 
2 
Apoptotic cleavage of 
cellular proteins 

0.0355 
4 
2 

Apoptosis 
0.0355 
4 
2 
Signaling by NGF 
0.0284 
4 
2 
NGF signaling via TRKA 
from the plasma membrane 

0.0284 
4 
2 

DAP12 signaling 
0.0284 
4 
2 
DAP12 interactions 
0.0284 
4 
2 
Signaling by the B cell 
Receptor (BCR) 

0.0284 
4 
2 

Signaling by ERBB4 
0.0284 
4 
2 
Signaling by ERBB2 
0.0284 
4 
2 
Signaling by EGFR in cancer 
0.0284 
4 
2 
Signaling by EGFR 
0.0284 
4 
2 
PLC beta mediated events 
0.0213 
3 
2 
Opioid signaling 
0.0213 
3 
2 
G-protein mediated events 
0.0213 
3 
2 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">J.E.Dent et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">The map was then tested for its sufficiency, i.e. usability in (re)producing biological phenomena triggered by mechanical stimulations, with the aim of validating the map&apos;s usage in relation to open problems where the impact of mechanical stresses is of relevance, as it is the case in arthritic diseases (Croft et al., 2011; Hattori et al., 2009). We therefore compared the effects of a mechanical stimulation on the molecules involved in our network, over time and under different inflammatory conditions. The experimental gold standard to validate the results was chosen from two articles (Gomez et al., 2010; Langevin et al., 2006) that explore diverse effects in similar, i.e. comparable, settings (mouse tissue). Jointly, the experimental set ups indicate, as effects of the mechanical stimulation in healthy tissue, the activation of RhoA/Rac1 (ras homolog family member A/ rho family, small GTP binding protein Rac1) and actomyosin, and the presence of EMT, accompanied by the (early) activation of myocardin-related transcription factors (MRTF-A/MKL1/MAL and MRTF-B/MKL2) unaffected by the inhibition of Rac1, in inflamed tissue. For validation of the ability of our map to reproduce these settings, we used the Petri Network framework [Biolayout Express3D (Theocharidis et al., 2009) and SPNconverter (Dent et al., 2013)]. In silico experiments were run assuming that 100 time blocks could cover the whole simulation time, 100 tokens could represent physiological baseline genes regulation and 500 tokens could mimic upregulation, as previously reported (Dent and Nardini, 2013). Tokens&apos; distribution as well as relevant statistics is available in SupplementaryInfo1 Tables S6–S7, evaluation of the stability of the simulations in SupplementaryInfo1 Tables S8–S10 and in Section 3. Results are presented in Figure 2 where the &apos;Summary&apos; column indicates the coherence between the outcomes of the major biological events tested by our simulations in comparison to the published experiments. More in details, the simulation referred specifically to the mechanotransduction markers (Fig. 2, rows 1–9) recapitulates the dynamics of mechanosensitive genes via pathways linked to mechanically induced cytoskeletal remodeling (Chiquet et al., 2009). Namely, tissue cells subjected to tensions from the extracellular environment sense and exert forces via their cytoskeleton, which undergo reorganization in a different shape and functionality, leading to migration and cell spreading as exemplar of these temporary cell structure modifications (Ponti et al., 2004; Theriot and Mitchison, 1991). In all cases the early steps of the process require the transient activity of MAL, one of SRF transcriptional cofactors, which is specifically induced by a mechanical stimulus (i.e. cell stretching) and, once activated, affects cytoskeletal actin dynamics (Posern and Treisman, 2006; Somogyi and Rørth, 2004). As indicated in the reference experiment by Langevin et al. (2006) the temporal sequence of events following the subconnective tissue physical stimulation resulting in active changes of fibroblasts cytoskeleton starts with the initial pulling of the extracellular matrix (ECM) on cells at precise focal adhesions complexes followed by actin rearrangement (like MAL expression induces); after focal contacts appear on cell surface stimulated by the tensile forces (Rac1 driven), RhoA activate actomyosin contraction around lamellipodia, through the stimulation of the down-stream effector Rho kinase (Rho-associated, coiled-coil containing protein kinase 1, ROCK family). All these events are reproduced in our map, and remarkably, with the correct subtle timing they present in vivo: i.e. stable late activation of the Rho kinase and early transient activation of MAL. In particular, since the whole RHOs family (RHOA; RAC1; CDC42, cell division cycle 42) action is related to mechanotransduction via its activity on actomyosin (Machacek et al., 2009; Parsons et al., 2010), and given that the inhibition of one only of the family members does not impede downstream events to occur (see Gomez et al., 2010 for EMT occurring even with inhibition of Rac1), we mark as coherent complexes/families where one or more constituent molecules do have the expected up or downregulation, and others</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BiNoM 2.0, a Cytoscape plugin for accessing and analyzing pathways using standard systems biology formats</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Bonnet</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neurosensory mechanotransduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Chalfie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From mechanotransduction to extracellular matrix gene expression in fibroblasts</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Chiquet</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1793" to="911" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of transcription-independent damage signals in the initiation of epithelial wound healing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Cordeiro</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Jacinto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reactome: a database of reactions, pathways and biological processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Croft</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="691" to="697" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From desk to bed: computational simulations provide indication for rheumatoid arthritis clinical trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Dent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Nardini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SPNConverter: a new link between static and dynamic complex network analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Dent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2507" to="2508" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MIMO: an efficient tool for molecular interaction maps overlap</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Di</forename>
				<surname>Lena</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">159</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of YAP/TAZ in mechanotransduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Dupont</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">474</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="183" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical induction of twist in the Drosophila foregut/stomodeal primordium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Farge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1365" to="1377" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tissue geometry patterns epithelial-mesenchymal transition via intercellular mechanotransduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Gomez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanotransduction and epigenetic control in autoimmune diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>González</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Autoimmun. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="179" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical effects of surgical procedures on osteochondral grafts elucidated by osmotic loading and real-time ultrasound</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Hattori</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Res. Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">134</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic molecular processes mediate cellular mechanotransduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hoffman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">475</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="316" to="323" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The systems biology markup language (SBML): a medium for representation and exchange of biochemical network models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hucka</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="524" to="531" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolving a lingua franca and associated software infrastructure for computational systems biology: the Systems Biology Markup Language (SBML) project</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hucka</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">R: a language for data analysis and graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Ihaka</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Gentleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Graph. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="314" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cellular mechanotransduction: putting all the pieces together again</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Ingber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FASEB J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="811" to="827" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EMT: when epithelial cells decide to become mesenchymallike cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Kalluri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1417" to="1419" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The basics of epithelial-mesenchymal transition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Kalluri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Weinberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1420" to="1428" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KEGG: kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kanehisa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Goto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Down-regulation of CDH1 is associated with expression of SNAI1 in colorectal adenomas</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Kroepil</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">46665</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subcutaneous tissue fibroblast cytoskeletal remodeling induced by acupuncture: evidence for a mechanotransductionbased mechanism</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Langevin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">207</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="767" to="774" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New insights into the regulation of epithelialmesenchymal transition and tissue fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Nelson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. Rev. Cell Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">294</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="221" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflammation, a key event in cancer development</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Lu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cancer Res. MCR</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coordination of Rho GTPase activities during cell protrusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Machacek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">461</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The molecular basis of mechanosensory transduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Marshall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Lumpkin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Exp. Med. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">739</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcription factor regulation by mechanical stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Mendez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Janmey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="728" to="732" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The PANTHER database of protein families, subfamilies, functions and pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Mi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="284" to="288" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cell adhesion: integrating cytoskeletal dynamics and cellular tension</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Parsons</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="633" to="643" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Induction of nerve growth factor expression and release by mechanical and inflammatory stimuli in chondrocytes: possible involvement in osteoarthritis pain</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Pecchi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Res. Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">16</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two distinct actin networks drive the protrusion of migrating cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ponti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">305</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1782" to="1786" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Actin&apos; together: serum response factor, its cofactors and the link to signal transduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Posern</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Treisman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="588" to="596" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AACR special conference on epithelial-mesenchymal transition and cancer progression and treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Roussos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7360" to="7364" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The signaling Petri net-based simulator: a non-parametric strategy for characterizing the dynamics of cell-specific signaling networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Ruths</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancer as an overhealing wound: an old hypothesis revisited</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Schäfer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Werner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="628" to="638" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">United we stand: integrating the actin cytoskeleton and cell-matrix adhesions in cellular mechanotransduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Schwarz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Gardel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3051" to="3060" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrative clustering of multiple genomic data types using a joint latent variable model with application to breast and lung cancer subtype analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Shen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2906" to="2912" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytoscape 2.8: new features for data integration and network visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Smoot</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="432" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence for tension-based regulation of Drosophila MAL and SRF during invasive cell migration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Somogyi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Rørth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network visualization and analysis of gene expression data using BioLayout Express(3D)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Theocharidis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1535" to="1550" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Actin microfilament dynamics in locomoting cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Theriot</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Mitchison</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">352</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homogeneous interferon-inducing 22K factor is related to endogenous pyrogen and interleukin-1</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Van Damme</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">314</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Early responses to mechanical load in tendon: role for calcium signaling, gap junctions and intercellular communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Wall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Banes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Musculoskelet. Neuronal Interact</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Soft tissue mechanotransduction in wound healing and fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Wong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semin. Cell Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="981" to="986" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comprehensive molecular interaction map for rheumatoid arthritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10137</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cellular and molecular mechanisms of fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Wynn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Pathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">214</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Focal adhesion kinase regulation of mechanotransduction and its impact on endothelial cell functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Zebda</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microvasc. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="81" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Signalling through mechanical inputs: a coordinated process</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Labouesse</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3039" to="3049" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>