
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:30+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology MetaboNetworks, an interactive Matlab-based toolbox for creating, customizing and exploring sub-networks from KEGG</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joram</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Posma</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Computational and Systems Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Surgery and Cancer</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Steven</forename>
								<forename type="middle">L</forename>
								<surname>Robinette</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Computational and Systems Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Surgery and Cancer</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Elaine</forename>
								<surname>Holmes</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Computational and Systems Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Surgery and Cancer</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jeremy</forename>
								<forename type="middle">K</forename>
								<surname>Nicholson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Computational and Systems Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Surgery and Cancer</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mario</forename>
								<surname>Albrecht</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Computational and Systems Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Surgery and Cancer</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology MetaboNetworks, an interactive Matlab-based toolbox for creating, customizing and exploring sub-networks from KEGG</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="893" to="895"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt612</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 18, 2013; revised on October 17, 2013; accepted on October 21, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>MetaboNetworks is a tool to create custom sub-networks in Matlab using main reaction pairs as defined by the Kyoto Encyclopaedia of Genes and Genomes and can be used to explore transgenomic interactions, for example mammalian and bacterial associations. It calculates the shortest path between a set of metabolites (e.g. biomarkers from a metabonomic study) and plots the connectivity between metabolites as links in a network graph. The resulting graph can be edited and explored interactively. Furthermore, nodes and edges in the graph are linked to the Kyoto Encyclopaedia of Genes and Genomes compound and reaction pair web pages. Availability and implementation: MetaboNetworks is available from</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Investigating the dynamic metabolic responses in living systems because of external perturbations gives complementary information to genomic and/or proteomic approaches. This field is known as metabonomics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Nicholson et al., 1999</ref>) and provides a 'top-down' view of the living system to show global changes instead of cell-specific interactions between genes, proteins and/ or metabolites. Metabolic pathway information can aid the interpretation of biological changes indicated by significant differences in metabolite concentration identified in metabonomic studies. The effective transformation of metabolic spectroscopy data to biological knowledge presents a significant bioinformatics challenge. In particular, the increased interest in clinical applications of metabolic phenotyping makes practical data visualization in a biological/medical framework of great importance. The Kyoto Encyclopaedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kanehisa and Goto, 2000</ref>) is an online resource where the interaction information of genes, proteins and metabolites is integrated and it can be used to investigate molecular networks in specific organisms or for all (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kanehisa et al., 2012</ref>). KEGG provides many static pathways and metabolic reaction networks as well as a global metabolic map. The standalone application NeAT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Faust et al., 2010</ref>) can be used to draw custom metabolic reaction sub-networks for a specific organism. However, it is useful to have the ability to edit graphs, as can be done for pathways e.g. using KEGGParser (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arakelyan and Nersisyan, 2013</ref>) in Matlab. MetaboNetworks aims to fill this gap for metabolic reaction networks and combine the ability to draw custom maps and being able to edit them. Rarely do metabolic networks and programs consider that the typical mammal is not a single organism, but a system comprising of a combination of mammalian, bacterial and potential parasitic organisms. Specifically, there is symbiosis between a host organism and its gut microbiota, and that gut microbes have functions and enzymes that are not found in mammalian organisms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Gill et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Nicholson et al., 2012</ref>). Therefore, it is important to be able to combine metabolic reaction networks for different organisms. MetaboNetworks has the option to include data from multiple organisms and investigates if reactions can occur in any of the selected organisms. In the present study, we have illustrated the new approach using an NMR-based toxicological biomarker input dataset. This is an area of particular importance as metabolic phenotyping has shown to be particularly useful for studying toxicological processes as models for human disease (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Nicholson and Wilson, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Nicholson et al., 2002</ref>). MetaboNetworks only requires the basic version of Matlab (The Mathworks, Natick, MA, USA) and does not require any additional toolbox. Although the MatlabBGL toolbox (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Gleich, 2006</ref>) has a number of graph layout algorithms in mex/cþþ code that can be used to speed up the calculation of large graphs in MetaboNetworks, all MetaboNetworks' functionalities are implemented using a simple graphical user interface and Matlab code.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS AND FEATURES</head><p>First, the appropriate data from KEGG has to be imported to Matlab. In MetaboNetworks this is done using a function that uses the KEGG REST-API to calculate a metabolite adjacency matrix that can later be used to draw the graphs. The user can select one or multiple organisms for which complete genomes are available in KEGG; for these organisms a list of enzymes (with E.C. numbers) that are associated with a gene from any of the organisms is determined. Using this enzyme list, all reactions are queried and enzymes involved in the reactions are matched against the enzyme list. Only reactions that require an enzyme from the list or that are listed as 'non-enzymatic' or 'spontaneous' are used to find their main *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. reaction pairs. The compounds from these reaction pairs are considered adjacent. Each row/column in the adjacency matrix indicates a specific compound (with a KEGG compound ID) and a list of all names for these compounds are found from the KEGG compound database. A reaction database has previously been collected using a similar approach (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Ma and Zeng, 2003</ref>) to MetaboNetworks, however, that database includes reactions from all species, whereas MetaboNetworks focusses on organisms of interest as not all reactions can occur in all organisms. Second, when the data collection is complete, MetaboNetworks can be used to create and explore custom networks. A list of metabolites, e.g. biomarkers arising from a metabonomic experiment, can be passed to MetaboNetworks and it searches for the shortest path between each of these metabolites using the breadth-first search algorithm. All compounds that are a part of a shortest path between any of the metabolites are included in the network. By default, MetaboNetworks plots the network as a circular graph. Other graph layouts include a spring-embedded layout, high-dimensional embedding and two types of uniform edgelength layouts, the last aim to place nodes with as little overlap as possible. If the Matlab statistical toolbox is installed, multidimensional scaling can also be used. Last, when the initial network layout is satisfactory the graph layout can be manually adjusted. Supported adjustments include node position, node/edge removal, highlighting nodes (see green edges of nodes in<ref type="figure">Fig.  1</ref>), and shortest paths (orange edges in<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>), node text and nodes/edge/ text properties (font, width, size, etc.). If additional data is supplied, the association of the metabolites with a response variable can be shown as node colour (see<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). Furthermore, the network can be exported as a tif, png, pdf, eps or other image formats, the network can always be reset to the original graph (all changes are lost). Another option is to click on a node to open a web browser showing the compound entry in KEGG or show reactions pairs in KEGG of selected nodes. The Supplementary Information includes a full walkthrough of the software and all the capabilities.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: Medical Research Council-Public Health England (MRC-PHE) Centre for Environment &amp; Health PhD-studentship (to J.M.P.). We thank the Medical Research CouncilNational Institute for Health Research (MRC-NIHR) National Phenome Centre for funding this and related work. Conflict of interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> DISCUSSION MetaboNetworks can be used to investigate and modify complex metabolic reaction networks. It improves the visual interpretation of metabonomic experiments with coverage across disparate metabolic pathways. The network should ideally be viewed as a connected network of probabilistic events (reactions) (Wilson and Nicholson, 2003) that lie on the shortest path between two metabolites. The database can be tailored to the study by including specific organisms, as we have done for the hydrazine toxicity network by including all bacteroidetes and firmicutes species, as it has been shown that germ-free rats react differently to hydrazine (Swann et al., 2009). MetaboNetworks can possibly also be used for identifying unknown metabolites by generating a network of metabolites correlated to the unknown metabolite. The unknown can be part of the shortest path between the known metabolites as the correlation can be due to a similarity in structure. Note that use of the KEGG-API is free for academic use; however, non-academic users should ask for permission (see http://www.pathway.jp/). Fig. 1. Shows the graphical user-interface of MetaboNetworks with a custom network drawn for significant metabolites from a hydrazine toxicity study in rats (Nicholls et al., 2001). Metabolites higher in hydrazine-dosed rats compared with controls are shown in red, and metabolites lower in hydrazinedosed rats are shown in blue. The white nodes are part of shortest paths between the coloured nodes. The edges shown in orange are part of the shortest path (four reactions) between taurine and glycine. Aside from the rat, all bacteroidetes and firmicutes species were included in the database</note>

			<note place="foot">J.M.Posma et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">MetaboNetworks at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KEGGParser: parsing and editing KEGG pathway maps in Matlab</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Arakelyan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Nersisyan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="518" to="519" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathway discovery in metabolic networks by subgraph extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Faust</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1211" to="1218" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metagenomic analysis of the human distal gut microbiome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Gill</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">312</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1355" to="1359" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">MatlabBGL library</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Gleich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-03-15" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KEGG: Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kanehisa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Goto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KEGG for integration and interpretation of large-scale molecular data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kanehisa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reconstruction of metabolic networks from genome data and analysis of their global structure for various organisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Ma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Zeng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="270" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Opinion: understanding &apos;global&apos; systems biology: metabonomics and the continuum of metabolism</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Nicholson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Wilson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Drug Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="668" to="676" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabonomic investigations into hydrazine toxicity in the rat</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Nicholls</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Res. Toxicol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="975" to="987" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabonomics: a platform for studying drug toxicity and gene function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Nicholson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Drug Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabonomics&apos;: understanding the metabolic responses of living systems to pathophysiological stimuli via multivariate statistical analysis of biological NMR spectroscopic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Nicholson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Xenobiotica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1181" to="1189" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Host-gut microbiota metabolic interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Nicholson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">336</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1262" to="1267" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gut microbiome modulates the toxicity of hydrazine: a metabonomic study</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Swann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biosyst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="355" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topics in xenobiochemistry: do metabolic pathways exist for xenobiotics? The micro-metabolism hypothesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Wilson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Nicholson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Xenobiotica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="887" to="901" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>