
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:46+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis miRTCat: a comprehensive map of human and mouse microRNA target sites including non-canonical nucleation bulges</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ka-Kyung</forename>
								<surname>Kim</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Health Sciences and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Samsung Advanced Institute for Health Sciences and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Sungkyunkwan University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Juyoung</forename>
								<surname>Ham</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Health Sciences and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Samsung Advanced Institute for Health Sciences and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Sungkyunkwan University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sung</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Wook</forename>
								<surname>Chi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Health Sciences and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Samsung Advanced Institute for Health Sciences and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Sungkyunkwan University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Samsung Research Institute for Future Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Samsung Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>81 Irwon-ro, Gangnam-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>135-710</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Samsung Biomedical Research Institute</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis miRTCat: a comprehensive map of human and mouse microRNA target sites including non-canonical nucleation bulges</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1898" to="1899"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt296</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 5, 2013; revised on May 7, 2013; accepted on May 20, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Ivo Hofacker Availability: http://ion.skku.edu/mirtcat. Contact: swchi@skku.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) regulate various biological functions by binding hundreds of transcripts to impart post-transcriptional repression. Recently, by applying a transcriptome-wide experimental method for identifying miRNA target sites (Ago HITS-CLIP), a novel non-canonical target site, named &apos;nucleation bulge&apos;, was discovered as widespread, functional and evolutionally conserved. Although such non-canonical nucleation bulges have been proven to be predictive by using &apos;pivot pairing rule&apos; and sequence conservation, this approach has not been applied yet. To facilitate the functional studies of non-canonical miRNA targets, we implement miRTCat: a comprehensive searchable map of miRNA target sites, including non-canonical nucle-ation bulges, not only mapped in experimentally verified miRNA-bound regions but also predicted in all 3 0-untranslated regions (3 0-UTRs) derived from human and mouse ($15.6% as expected false-positive results).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are small RNA molecules ($22 nt) that induce post-transcriptional repression of messenger RNAs (mRNAs), affecting various biological phenotypes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">He and Hannon, 2004</ref>). Animal miRNAs typically recognize mRNA targets through imperfect matches, making the problem of predicting miRNA target sites challenging. Among these partial pairings, it is well known that miRNAs bind canonical miRNA target sites through short consecutive pairings with their seed regions (position 2–8; called 'seed pairing rule') (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bartel, 2009</ref>). Besides sequence complementarity, evolutional conservation has been considered, improving the performance of miRNA target predictions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Lewis et al., 2005</ref>). However, a critical caveat of all seed-centric approaches is its inability to identify non-canonical miRNA target sites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Didiano and Hobert, 2006</ref>), overlooking priori recognized non-canonical target sites validated as functionally important (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Tay et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Vella et al., 2004</ref>). Recently, by applying cross-linking immunoprecipitation method (CLIP) coupled with high-throughput sequencing (HITS) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Licatalosi, 2008</ref>) to a protein called Argonaute (Ago HITS-CLIP), all miRNA-binding regions in target mRNAs were experimentally mapped in high resolution (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chi et al., 2009</ref>). However, not all miRNA-bound regions could be explained by the canonical seed pairing rule, implicating existence of non-canonical miRNA–target interactions. By performing bioinformatic analyses in such orphan regions, non-canonical sites called 'nucleation bulges' were identified and validated as widespread, functional and evolutionally conserved (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chi et al., 2012</ref>). Non-canonical nucleation bulge sites are predictable, as the mode of their interactions is generalized by 'pivot pairing rule', dictating a nucleotide in bulge (position 5 and 6) to be competent to pair with a nucleotide in position six of a miRNA, named 'pivot' to confer the thermodynamic stability on consecutive five base pairings (position 2–6, Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. S1A</ref>). Such initial five base pairings are proposed to be served as nuclei of interactions (nucleation), followed by bulge formation where originally matched pivot nucleotide in position six becomes bulged-out and propagating hybridization toward 3 0-end of the miRNA. However, such a rule based on a pivot pairing has not been applied for miRNA target prediction yet. To offer opportunities of studying non-canonical miRNA targets, here we describe miRNA target maps specialized for nucleation bulge sites, named 'miRTCat'. miRTCat provides comprehensive maps searchable for miRNA target sites including non-canonical nucleation bulges, of which locations are not only predicted in all 3 0-untranslated regions (3 0-UTRs; annotated by RefSeq in human and mouse) but also mapped in miRNA-bound regions that are experimentally verified (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chi et al., 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chi et al., , 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hafner et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kishore et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Leung et al., 2011</ref>). Such functionalities will aid to generate hypothesis starting from interactions between miRNA and non-canonical targets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>Based on the established principles: sequence complementarity and evolutional conservation (see Supplementary Material for details), miRTCat pipeline (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1A</ref>), implemented mainly by using Perl, PHP and MySQL, identifies miRNA target sites of both canonical and non-canonical types for microRNA families, which were previously defined as mostly conserved across vertebrates (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Friedman et al., 2009</ref>). For canonical seed sites, a seed pairing rule is used to find motifs46mers that match to the 5 0-end seed regions of miRNAs (position 2–8;<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1A</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. S1A</ref>). For non-canonical nucleation bulge sites, a pivot pairing rule is applied to *To whom correspondence should be addressed. search 7mer motifs of which bulged sequence (position 5 and 6) is complement to pair with pivot (position six;<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1A</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. S1A</ref>). To consider evolutional conservation, phastCons score, derived from Multiz 46 or 30 way whole-genome alignments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dreszer et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Siepel et al., 2005</ref>) is used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>As previously reported (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chi et al., 2012</ref>), nucleation bulge sites have propensity to be more conserved in miRNA-bound regions<ref type="bibr">[</ref><ref type="figure">Taking</ref>this notion, we examine the performance of miRTCat depending on the level of conservation by using experimentally identified miRNA-bound regions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chi et al., 2009</ref>), determine default cut-offs (PCS ! 0.9 for both sites) and estimate the false-positive rate (15.6%; 13.6% for seed matches and 20.1% for nucleation bulges) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1B</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. S1B</ref>–D). Validation analysis using experiment datasets of miRNA-dependant repression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alexiou et al., 2009)</ref>shows that transcripts identified by miRTCat (PCS ! 0.9) are more significantly downregulated than the targets found by simple seed matching (P ¼ 5.0 Â 10 À8 ) (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1C</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>). Furthermore, miRTCat is estimated to outperform in sensitivity ($2.6-fold increase) with comparable precision with other prediction methods (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1D</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>). Overall, miRTCat offers comprehensive mappings with increased number of target sites by identifying non-canonical nucleation bulges, predicting bona fide 245 454 sites (33 461 nucleation bulges (7mers), comparable with 47 478 7mer seed sites) in human 3 0-UTRs and mapping 263 361 sites (32 471 nucleation bulges, 44 665 7mer seed sites) in all compiled data from experimentally identified miRNA-bound regions (3272).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">FUNCTIONALITY</head><p>The miRTCat web-interface offers search functionality of both canonical and non-canonical miRNA targets sites in two species, human and mouse. Users can retrieve two types of identification: bona fide prediction in 3 0-UTR and experimentally mapping results in miRNA-bound regions, freely defining cut-off values of PCS (0.1–1.0) for both non-canonical nucleation bulge and canonical seed sites. Users are informed to decide cut-off values for their purpose of search considering experimentally estimated predictive values depending on the extent of evolutional conservation (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1B</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. S1D</ref>). Centered on target mRNAs and/or regulator miRNAs, results of the target sites are returned in the form of lists as a table providing sorting functionality and links for UCSC genome browser (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dreszer et al., 2011</ref>), enabling to browse with other genome information. In addition, all results are also available for download as an excel file format and easily used for other computational analysis. In summary, here we provide a comprehensive map of miRNA target sites including non-canonical nucleation bulges in several formats to facilitate further biological studies of miRNA regulation through non-canonical targets, which has not been offered by current approaches based on seed pairings.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>mean phastCons score (PCS) ¼ 0.59 AE 0.22] like seed sites (PCS ¼ 0.82 AE 0.17), compared with the control sites (PCS ¼ 0.32 AE 0.21) in human 3 0-UTRs.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: Korean Health Technology R&amp;D Project, Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare (A111989). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. miRTCat (A) Workflow for mapping of non-canonical nucleation bulge (Nuc) and canonical seed sites (Seed). A pivot nucleotide (position six) and pivot competent nucleotides are indicated as shade in the middle panel. (B) Number of nucleation bulges in miRNA-bound regions in the range of evolutional conservation (PhastCons cut-offs) compared with the expected number of sites in outside of miRNA-bound regions. (C) Cumulative fraction analysis for different types of targets based on the analysis of experiment datasets for miRNA-dependant repression (miR-1, miR-16, miR-30 a, miR-155 and let-7 b) (Alexiou et al., 2009); P-values, Kolmogorov–Smirnov test. (D) Comparison with average performance of other programs based on the same datasets used in (C); error bars, SD</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">miRTCat at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lost in translation: an assessment and perspective for computational microRNA target identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Alexiou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3049" to="3055" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MicroRNAs: target recognition and regulatory functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Bartel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Argonaute HITS-CLIP decodes microRNA-mRNA interaction maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Chi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">460</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="479" to="486" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An alternative mode of microRNA target recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Chi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="327" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perfect seed pairing is not a generally reliable predictor for miRNA-target interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Didiano</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Hobert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="849" to="851" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The UCSC Genome Browser database: extensions and updates 2011</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Dreszer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="918" to="923" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Most mammalian mRNAs are conserved targets of microRNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Friedman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptome-wide identification of RNA-binding protein and microRNA target sites by PAR-CLIP</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hafner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MicroRNAs: small RNAs with a big role in gene regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Hannon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="522" to="531" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A quantitative analysis of CLIP methods for identifying binding sites of RNA-binding proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kishore</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="559" to="564" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide identification of Ago2 binding sites from mouse embryonic stem cells with and without mature microRNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Leung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="244" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conserved seed pairing, often flanked by adenosines, indicates that thousands of human genes are microRNA targets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Lewis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HITS-CLIP yields genome-wide insights into brain alternative RNA processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Licatalosi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">456</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="464" to="469" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolutionarily conserved elements in vertebrate, insect, worm, and yeast genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Siepel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1034" to="1050" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MicroRNAs to Nanog, Oct4 and Sox2 coding regions modulate embryonic stem cell differentiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Tay</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">455</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1124" to="1128" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The C. elegans microRNA let-7 binds to imperfect let-7 complementary sites from the lin-41 3 0 UTR</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Vella</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="132" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>