
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:32+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies Molecular signatures database (MSigDB) 3.0</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Arthur</forename>
								<surname>Liberzon</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Aravind</forename>
								<surname>Subramanian</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Reid</forename>
								<surname>Pinchback</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Helga</forename>
								<surname>Thorvaldsdóttir</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pablo</forename>
								<surname>Tamayo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jill</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Mesirov</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alex</forename>
								<surname>Bateman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02142</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies Molecular signatures database (MSigDB) 3.0</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1739" to="1740"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr260</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on January 13, 2011; revised on April 4, 2011; accepted on April 12, 2011</note>
					<note>[14:02 14/5/2011 Bioinformatics-btr260.tex] Page: 1739 1739–1740 Associate Editor: Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Well-annotated gene sets representing the universe of the biological processes are critical for meaningful and insightful interpretation of large-scale genomic data. The Molecular Signatures Database (MSigDB) is one of the most widely used repositories of such sets. Results: We report the availability of a new version of the database, MSigDB 3.0, with over 6700 gene sets, a complete revision of the collection of canonical pathways and experimental signatures from publications, enhanced annotations and upgrades to the web site. Availability and Implementation: MSigDB is freely available for non-commercial use at http://www.broadinstitute.org/msigdb.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Microarrays and other high-throughput genomic technologies typically produce long lists of potentially interesting genes, which are not always easily interpreted. Recognizing the importance of coordinately expressed sets of genes, our seminal paper (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Mootha et al., 2003</ref>) introduced Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) to discover metabolic pathways altered in human type 2 diabetes mellitus. GSEA and other analytical enrichment tools summarize genomic data in prioritized lists of higher-level biological features. As underscored by a recent survey of 68 enrichment tools, they critically depend on 'backend annotation databases' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Huang et al., 2009</ref>). Typically, such databases focus on a particular domain of knowledge or annotation procedure. For example, Gene Ontology (GO) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ashburner et al., 2000</ref>) represents a hierarchy of controlled terms to describe individual gene products, while TRANSFAC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Matys et al., 2006</ref>) stores information about transcription factor binding sites. A growing number of databases obtain sets from gene expression signatures reported in the literature. These include SignatureDB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Shaffer et al., 2006</ref>), GeneSigDB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Culhane et al., 2009</ref>), CCancer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Dietmann et al., 2010</ref>) and L2L and LOLA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cahan et al., 2007</ref>). Molecular Signatures Database (MSigDB) differs from these resources in several distinguishing aspects. (i) MSigDB is explicitly designed to provide gene sets for enrichment analysis methods. As such, it is natively and seamlessly integrated with our GSEA software (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>). (ii) MSigDB covers a substantially more diverse and wider range of gene set sources and types. These include signatures extracted from original research * To whom correspondence should be addressed. publications, and entire collections of sets derived from specialized resources such as GO, KEGG (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Kanehisa and Goto, 2000</ref>), TRANSFAC and L2L. (iii) MSigDB gene sets are acquired both through manual curation and by automatic computational means, whereas other databases emphasize only one of these approaches.<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Matthews et al., 2009)]</ref>, and sets corresponding to chemical and genetic perturbations from 786 scientific publications.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>shows the growth of the MSigDB collections and database since the initial release (see also online Release Notes). Gene set annotations: each MSigDB gene set is a list of genes with relevant annotations and links to external resources. MSigDB focuses on human gene sets. However, we do include sets from some model organisms and gene set annotations include organism identification. We use HUGO gene symbols and, as of version 3.0, human Entrez Gene IDs serve as universal identifiers. These Entrez IDs are guaranteed to be unique and stable, can easily be mapped into a variety of other identifiers and are natively integrated with the GenBank resources of primary nucleic and protein sequences. We also preserve whatever original identifiers were used in the gene set source. All sets have unique database identifiers and names, and include brief and full descriptions. Other annotations depend on the type of gene set. Annotations linking to external resources are especially important as they allow researchers to place the sets inthe context of a specific study and facilitate decisions on follow-up experiments. Gene sets from publications are the most richly annotated. Their annotations include the PubMed ID of the publication, pointers to other gene sets from the same publication, and now also details on the exact table or figure from which the gene set was extracted. For version 3.0, we updated the names of these gene sets to make them more descriptive and standardized and the accompanying brief descriptions to follow a more uniform and consistent format. Other annotation features introduced with version 3.0 include links to source datasets in Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Barrett et al., 2009</ref>) and ArrayExpress (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Parkinson et al., 2009</ref>). Canonical pathway sets include links to the pathway at the source web site. File formats: MSigDB gene set files are available for download in plain text and XML formats. The plain text files contain simple listings of gene set membership, while the XML files also include the annotations. To ensure reproducibility of GSEA results, older versions of the MSigDB files are always available. Note that users of our GSEA software do not need to download the MSigDB files as the tool directly and automatically retrieves the gene sets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.Liberzon et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">MSigDB ONLINE RESOURCE</head><p>In version 3.0, we updated the MSigDB web site. First introduced in July 2007, the site allows users to view the annotated gene sets and perform simple search and analysis tasks. Each gene set and all of its annotations are presented on a separate web page (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1</ref>). Embedded hyperlinks connect annotations to corresponding external web resources, including PubMed, GEO and ArrayExpress, PubChem and Entrez Gene. The MSigDB web site allows users to find gene sets by searching for keywords in the annotations. The online analysis tools allow users to: (i) compute overlaps between gene sets; (ii) view a heat map of a gene set in one of the reference expression compendia; and (iii) categorize the genes in a set by gene families. Gene families offer a quick view of a gene set by grouping its members into a small number of informative categories. We have updated the gene families and they now include: oncogenes, tumor suppressors, translocated cancer genes, transcription factors, proteinkinases, homeodomain proteins, cell differentiation markers and cytokines/growth factors.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>(iv) Finally, MSigDB contains the largest number of gene sets overall. The initial MSigDB database, released in 2005 with GSEA software, contained 1325 sets. In contrast, MSigDB 3.0, released in September 2010, includes 6769 sets and a richer set of annotations. Here, we describe the MSigDB 3.0 sets in more detail and the accompanying online resource.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Gene set collections: gene sets in MSigDB 3.0 are organized into five collections according to their derivation: C1: Genes located in the same chromosome or cytogenetic band. C2: Gene sets representing canonical pathways from pathway resources [including 430 new sets contributed by Reactome (</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. A typical gene set page on the MSigDB web site. The list of genes has been abbreviated from 41 to 2 for the purposes of this figure.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. MSigDB versions and changes in the number of gene sets</figDesc><table>Gene set category 
1.0 (2005) 
2.5 (2008) 
3.0 (2010) 

C1: positional 
319 
386 
326 a 
C2: curated (total) 
522 
1892 
3272 
C2: chemical and 
genetic perturbations 

50 
1186 
2392 

C2: canonical pathways 
472 
639 
880 
C2: uncategorized 
0 
66 
0 
C3: motifs (total) 
57 
837 
836 a 
C3: transcription factor 
targets 

57 
500 
615 

C3: micro-RNA targets 
0 
222 
221 a 
C3: uncategorized 
0 
115 
0 
C4: computational 
427 
883 
881 a 
C5: GO terms 
0 
1454 
1454 
MSigDB total 
1325 
5452 
6769 

a Decrease in number due to the removal of sets with too few genes to run GSEA. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from [14:02 14/5/2011 Bioinformatics-btr260.tex]</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank J. Roberston, L. Saunders and L. Kazmierski for gene set collection; H. Kuehn and J. McLaughlin for documentation; and M. Wrobel for web site development.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NCBI GEO: archive for high-throughput functional genomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Barrett</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meta-analysis of microarray results: challenges, opportunities, and recommendations for standardization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Cahan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">401</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeneSigDB – a curated database of gene expression signatures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Culhane</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="716" to="725" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CCancer: a bird&apos;s eye view on gene lists reported in cancerrelated studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Dietmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="118" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Da</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KEGG: Kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kanehisa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Goto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reactome knowledgebase of human biological pathways and processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Matthews</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="619" to="622" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TRANSFAC and its module TRANSCompel: transcriptional gene regulation in eukaryotes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Matys</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="108" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PGC-1alpha-responsive genes involved in oxidative phosphorylation are coordinately downregulated in human diabetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Mootha</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ArrayExpress update – from an archive of functional genomics experiments to the atlas of gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Parkinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="868" to="872" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A library of gene expression signatures to illuminate normal and pathological lymphoid biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Shaffer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunol Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">210</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Subramanian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15545" to="15550" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>