
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:48+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining Mouse model phenotypes provide information about human drug targets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Robert</forename>
								<surname>Hoehndorf</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Aberystwyth</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Old College</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>King Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>SY23 2AX</postCode>
									<settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Tanya</forename>
								<surname>Hiebert</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Biochemistry and School of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carleton University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1125 Colonel By Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>K1S 5B6</postCode>
									<settlement>Ottawa</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nigel</forename>
								<forename type="middle">W</forename>
								<surname>Hardy</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Aberystwyth</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Old College</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>King Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>SY23 2AX</postCode>
									<settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Paul</forename>
								<forename type="middle">N</forename>
								<surname>Schofield</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physiology, Development and Neuroscience</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cambridge</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Downing Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>CB2 3EG</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Georgios</forename>
								<forename type="middle">V</forename>
								<surname>Gkoutos</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Aberystwyth</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Old College</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>King Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>SY23 2AX</postCode>
									<settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michel</forename>
								<surname>Dumontier</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Biochemistry and School of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carleton University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1125 Colonel By Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>K1S 5B6</postCode>
									<settlement>Ottawa</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining Mouse model phenotypes provide information about human drug targets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="719" to="725"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt613</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 26, 2013; revised on October 2, 2013; accepted on October 18, 2013</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Methods for computational drug target identification use information from diverse information sources to predict or prioritize drug targets for known drugs. One set of resources that has been relatively neglected for drug repurposing is animal model phenotype. Results: We investigate the use of mouse model phenotypes for drug target identification. To achieve this goal, we first integrate mouse model phenotypes and drug effects, and then systematically compare the phenotypic similarity between mouse models and drug effect profiles. We find a high similarity between phenotypes resulting from loss-of-function mutations and drug effects resulting from the inhibition of a protein through a drug action, and demonstrate how this approach can be used to suggest candidate drug targets. Availability and implementation: Analysis code and supplementary data files are available on the project Web site at https://drugeffects.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>A major challenge currently faced by pharmacological research is the high rate of attrition in the development of new compounds, the increased cost of drug development and increased regulatory concern about drug safety and efficacy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Sleigh and Barton, 2010</ref>). As a result, pharmacological research is beginning to focus on repurposing existing drugs for new indications, and several large national and international research initiatives have begun to systematically address drug repurposing on a broad scale (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Allison, 2012</ref>). Strategies for drug repurposing can be divided into two main types: identification of new targets for known drugs and identification of new indications for a known mechanism of action (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Sleigh and Barton, 2010</ref>). Approaches to drug repurposing include database-driven bioinformatics approaches, in vivo and ex vivo studies and high-throughput screening methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Sleigh and Barton, 2010</ref>). Examples of computational approaches to drug repurposing include side effect-based approaches, in which similarity between drug effects is used to suggest drug targets and drug indications (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Campillos et al., 2008</ref>), data mining of clinical records (<ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Tatonetti et al., 2012</ref>) and approaches based on analysis of GWAS data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Sanseau et al., 2012</ref>). Computational approaches to drug repurposing have the highest chance of succeeding if multiple independent data sources and analysis approaches are combined so that data from several independent domains and studies can be used to identify strong evidence for novel drug indications. Based on integrating multiple complementary datasets, integrative computational approaches can use multiple measures to prioritize candidate targets and drugs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chen et al., 2012b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gottlieb et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Thorn et al., 2010</ref>). One set of resources that has been relatively neglected for drug repurposing is animal model phenotype (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hoehndorf et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Hurle et al., 2013</ref>). The use of non-human species to investigate physiology and pathobiology, and the creation of animal models of human diseases amenable to experimental investigation, has become a successful paradigm in the biomedical sciences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Rosenthal and Brown, 2007</ref>). The development of highthroughput phenotyping has further increased the available amount of phenotype data resulting from targeted mutations in animal models, and pan-genomic projects such as the International Mouse Phenotyping Consortium (IMPC) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Brown and Moore, 2012</ref>) aim to delete every protein-coding gene in an organism and to identify the phenotypes resulting from these mutations. It has now become a challenge to systematically analyze the resulting data and use them to provide insights into human health and novel intervention strategies. In the past, several studies have used animal model data to suggest candidate genes for genetically based diseases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chen et al., 2012a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hoehndorf et al., 2011b</ref>), and one study also suggests that mouse model phenotypes can be used to provide insights into drug actions and drug effects in humans despite experimental differences between the two species (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Kuhn et al., 2013</ref>). Here, we use a phenome-wide approach to systematically compare drug effects with mutant mouse phenotypes (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). We provide strong supporting evidence for the hypothesis that the similarity between drug effects and mouse phenotypes that result from loss of protein function indicates a similarity in the *To whom correspondence should be addressed ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. mechanism of action, i.e. an inhibition of the protein through the drug. We evaluate our results with experimentally validated lists of known drug targets and demonstrate on a genomic scale that a similarity between drug effects and mutant mouse phenotypes can reveal drug targets. Our approach opens the possibility for a systematic analysis of animal model phenotypes for candidate drug targets, and has a significant impact for integrative computational approaches to drug repurposing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MATERIAL AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Mouse model phenotypes</head><p>We use the Mammalian Phenotype (MP) Ontology (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Smith et al., 2004</ref>) and the Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Robinson et al., 2008</ref>), both downloaded on February 14, 2013 from the OBO Foundry Web site (http://obofoundry.org). We obtain the entity-quality definitions attached to MP and HPO from https://phenotype-ontologies.googlecode.com (downloaded on February 14, 2013). We downloaded mouse phenotype data from the Mouse Genome Informatics (MGI) database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Blake et al., 2011</ref>) on February 14, 2013. We obtained only mouse model phenotypes associated with models resulting from loss-of-function mutations in single genes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Drug effect profiles and drug targets</head><p>Drug effect profiles were obtained from SIDER 2 (released on March 16, 2012) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kuhn et al., 2010</ref>). For each drug, we identify the STITCH identifier associated with the drug. We ignore all drugs for which no STITCH identifier has been identified in the SIDER dataset. STITCH identifiers are based on the STITCH database, version 3.1 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kuhn et al., 2012</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Integrating drug effects and phenotypes</head><p>We used a combination of lexical mapping, manual curation and exploitation of cross-references to map the Unified Medical Language System (UMLS) terms used to characterize SIDER's drug profiles to the Human and Mammalian Phenotype Ontologies. Using exact lexical matching of UMLS terms to term names and synonyms in ontologies, we mapped 597 terms from SIDER to the HPO (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Robinson et al., 2008</ref>) and 262 terms from SIDER to the MP Ontology (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Smith et al., 2004</ref>). HPO already contains cross-references to terms from the UMLS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bodenreider, 2004</ref>), 3858 of which can be found in SIDER's drug effect profiles. We sorted the remaining SIDER terms for which we could not obtain a mapping to HPO or MP based on the frequency of their occurrence in SIDER drug effect profiles and manually mapped 953 of the most frequently occurring terms to HPO and 240 of the most frequently occurring terms to MP. The mappings are available on the project Web site.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Cross-species integration of phenotypes</head><p>Although we have annotated SIDER with both MP and HPO terms, mouse phenotypes are represented exclusively using MP. To make HPO and MP phenotype terms comparable, we use the PhenomeNET system of integrating phenotypes across species (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hoehndorf et al., 2011b</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Hoehndorf et al., , 2013</ref>). PhenomeNET enables the direct comparison of phenotypes across multiple species (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hoehndorf et al., 2011b</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Hoehndorf et al., , 2013</ref>), including mouse model phenotypes (describing using the MP) and human drug effects (described using the UMLS and mapped to HPO using our approach). PhenomeNET uses an ontology-based integration framework that integrates phenotypes in different species based on species-independent ontologies and the PATO framework (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Gkoutos et al., 2005</ref>). In particular, PhenomeNET uses the large number of entity-quality-based definitions that have been created for species-specific phenotype ontology (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Mungall et al., 2010</ref>) and integrates them with species-independent ontologies. Entity-quality definitions of phenotypes decompose phenotype terms in an affected entity and a quality that characterizes how the entity is affected. For example, the phenotype term proximal fibular overgrowth (HP:0007126) is decomposed into the entity proximal epiphysis of fibula (FMA:33729) and the quality hypertrophic (PATO:0000584). Similarly, the mouse phenotype term abnormal fibula morphology (MP:0002187) is decomposed into the entity fibula (MA:0001360) and the quality morphology (PATO:0000051) with the qualifier abnormal (PATO:0000460). Phenotypes in which biological processes, functions or cellular components are affected can then be integrated across species based on the Gene Ontology (GO) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Ashburner et al., 2000</ref>), and phenotypes in which anatomical structures are affected are integrated based on homologous anatomical structures represented in the UBERON ontology (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Mungall et al., 2012</ref>). Using automated reasoning (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kazakov et al., 2011</ref>), it then becomes possible to systematically identify equivalent, more specific and more general phenotypes across multiple species. For example, based on axioms in the combined ontology, we can infer that proximal fibular overgrowth is a more specific phenotype term than abnormal fibula morphology using the information thatAdditional details for integrating phenotype ontologies across species using the Web Ontology Language (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Grau et al., 2008</ref>) are discussed in prior work (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Hoehndorf et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">2011a, b</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Semantic similarity</head><p>Traditional semantic similarity measures are symmetrical, i.e. the similarity between X and Y is the same as the similarity between Y and X. As drugs may bind to multiple targets to elicit their effects (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Kuhn et al., 2013</ref>), we designed a novel non-symmetrical similarity measure based on the well-known SimGIC measure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Pesquita et al., 2009</ref>). SimGIC is a group-based measure of semantic similarity, i.e. it compares two sets of annotations directly and is based on the Jaccard index weighted by the information content of ontology terms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Pesquita et al., 2009</ref>).the different datasets we exploit. We aim to infer inhibition actions between drugs and their targets based on the similarity between drug effect profiles and mouse model phenotypes resulting from single gene knockouts. We test the hypothesis whether the phenotypic effects of a perturbation of a gene/protein through a drug action bears some similarity to the phenotypic effects of a targeted mutation of that gene/protein observed in a model organism. As drugs often perturb multiple genes/ proteins, we systematically compute how well a drug effect profile covers observed phenotypes in a mouse model using a non-symmetrical measure of semantic similarity</p><p>We first select all phenotypes observed for single gene deletions in mice. For each gene G for which phenotype data are present in the MGI database, we then generate the union of the phenotypes observed in all models in which G has been deleted. The resulting phenotypes for a gene G are all phenotypes observed in mouse models in which G (and only G) has been deleted and provides a global view on the phenotypes associated with deletions of G. We then add the super-classes of the phenotype annotations of each mouse model and drug to their set of annotations. In particular, if the HPO or MP phenotype P is a phenotype annotation associated with gene or drug X, and the super-classes of X in MP are the classes Sup(X), we add Sup(X) as annotations to X. To compute super-classes, we use the combined ontology of MP and HPO that forms part of PhenomeNET and enables cross-species comparisons of phenotypes (i.e. a class in MP may be a super-class of a class in HPO and vice versa) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hoehndorf et al., 2011b</ref>). We make the MP-based representation of drug effects in SIDER based on which we compute the similarity available on the project Web site. We then define the information content IC(t) of an MP phenotype term t based on the probability PðX ¼ tÞ that a drug or mutant mouse model is characterized with t:</p><formula>ICðtÞ ¼ À logðPðX ¼ tÞÞ ð1Þ</formula><p>The probability PðX ¼ tÞ is empirically derived within the corpus of mouse models and drug profiles. We use only the structure of the MP to compute semantic similarity based on prior work that has shown that MP-based similarity measures outperform measures that use HPO or the combination of HPO and MP for analyzing mouse phenotype data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Oellrich et al., 2012</ref>). Given a drug effect profile D and a mutant mouse model M, where D is characterized by the ontology classes ClðDÞ ¼ D 1 ,. .. , D n and M is characterized by the classes ClðMÞ ¼ M 1 ,. .. , M m , we define the similarity between D and M as:</p><formula>simðD, MÞ ¼ P x2ClðDÞ\ClðMÞ ICðxÞ P y2ClðDÞ ICðyÞ ð2Þ</formula><p>As a result, we obtain a similarity matrix between drug effect profiles and mouse model phenotypes (resulting from deletions of one gene). The similarity measure used is non-symmetrical and determines the amount of information about a drug effect profile D that is covered by a set of mouse model phenotypes M.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">Evaluation datasets</head><p>Our approach is based on identifying a similarity between drug effect profiles and mouse model phenotypes. The STITCH database provides us with a set of drug–protein interactions in the mouse. We filter these interactions for those in which the mode of action is 'inhibition' (in the STITCH file actions.v3.1.tsv) and use this dataset directly as evaluation dataset 'STITCH (mouse)'. As we primarily aim to predict drug targets in human, we use the human–mouse orthology provided by the MGI database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Blake et al., 2011</ref>) to obtain the mouse ortholog for each human gene that is a target of a STITCH compound, and use the mouse ortholog of the human drug target as a positive hit for the STITCH compound. We use the human drug–protein interactions provided by STITCH in which the mode of action is 'inhibition' as evaluation dataset 'STITCH (human)', and the human drug targets provided by DrugBank in which the mode of action is 'inhibition' as evaluation dataset 'DrugBank'. The STITCH database accumulates data from multiple sources and contains a confidence value for each interaction. The confidence ranges between 0 and 1, with an implicit cutoff value of 0.15. To evaluate the results of our analysis under different degrees of confidence, we generated evaluation datasets for STITCH in which we require a confidence of at least 0.5, and another dataset in which we require a confidence of at least 0.7. The evaluation datasets we used are available on the project Web site.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7">Receiver operating characteristic analysis and approximation of confidence intervals</head><p>To compute true-and false-positive rate, we iterate through the ranks of the generated similarity matrix (between drugs and mouse models) and compute, for each rank, the proportion of known drug targets in each of our evaluation datasets identified up to this rank (true-positive rate) as well as the proportion of targets not in the evaluation dataset included up to this rank (false-positive rate). We then use an analysis of the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve to evaluate and quantify the results. An ROC curve is a plot of the true-positive rate as a function of the falsepositive rate and can be used to evaluate the performance of a classifier (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Fawcett, 2006</ref>). Confidence intervals for the area under the ROC curve (ROCAUC) are computed under the assumption of a normal distribution of ROCAUC values and using an estimate of the maximum variance of the ROCAUC as 2 max ¼ AUCð1ÀAUCÞ minfm, ng , with m and n being the number of positive and negative instances in the evaluation dataset (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Birnbaum and Klose, 1957</ref>). We then use AUC AE 2 as an estimate of the 95% confidence interval (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Cortes and Mohri, 2005</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Mouse model phenotypes provide information about drug targets</head><p>The hypothesis we test is whether a similarity between drug D's effects and phenotypes resulting from knock-out/knockdown of a single gene (product) in an animal model can be used to indicate that D inhibits the gene (product) or its human ortholog, and whether phenotype similarity between mouse models and drug effects can be used to provide insights relevant for discovery of targets for known drugs. To test these hypotheses, we first made drug effects and mouse phenotypes comparable by mapping the drug effects described in the SIDER database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kuhn et al., 2010</ref>) with human and mouse phenotype terms, and then integrating human and mouse phenotypes across species (see Section 2). Once mouse model phenotypes and human drug effects are made directly comparable, we use a measure of semantic similarity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Pesquita et al., 2008</ref>) to compare drug effect profiles with mutant mouse phenotypes. We systematically compare the sets of phenotypes that have been observed in mice with single gene deletions with drug effect profiles obtained from the SIDER database, and use their similarity to prioritize candidate drug–protein interactions. To account for drugs' binding to multiple targets, we developed a novel similarity measure between drug effect profiles and mouse model phenotypes that determines how much of the information in the drug effect profile can be explained through a set of mouse model phenotypes (Section 2). A schematic overview of the approach is shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>. We evaluate the results using three datasets: the human drug targets available in DrugBank (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Knox et al., 2011</ref>), the human drug targets available in the STITCH database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kuhn et al., 2012</ref>) and the mouse drug targets available in the STITCH database. DrugBank contains experimentally validated drug targets 721 PhenoDrug</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>and includes information</head><p>on the mode of action. Similarly, STITCH accumulates information about human and animal drug targets from multiple sources and includes the mode of action, if known. For our evaluation, we select only drug targets for which the mechanism of action is inhibition, as we aim to test whether these provide a similar phenotypic response as a knockout/knock-down of the target. For each drug, we identify the similarity between its pharmacological effects and the phenotypes observed in mouse models with a single gene deletion and rank the mouse models, for each drug, based on their similarity to the drug effect profile. We then evaluate the resulting ranks using positive instances of drug-target interactions, and<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>shows the resulting ROC curves for the three main datasets we used. The ROCAUC values are 0:739 AE 0:011 for mouse targets (STITCH), 0:709 AE 0:009 for human targets (STITCH) and 0:723 AE 0:040 for human targets (DrugBank). We further restricted the STITCH evaluation datasets for human and mouse to high-confidence drug–protein interactions. With a confidence cutoff of 0.5, the resulting AUCs are 0:760 AE 0:010 for human targets and 0:797 AE 0:016 for mouse targets, and with a cutoff of 0.7, the AUCs are 0:762 AE 0:011 for human and 0:820 AE 0:024 for mouse targets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Targets in different protein families can be predicted with different accuracy</head><p>We further investigated whether our approach is more successful for particular protein families or particular drug categories. For this purpose, we performed our analysis for each of the top-level InterPro (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Mulder et al., 2005</ref>) protein families. To maintain statistical significance, we restrict our analysis to protein families in which we could identify 45 positive instances from our evaluation datasets, resulting in only six protein families for which we perform the analysis using the two STITCH-based evaluation datasets. The resulting ROCAUCs are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>and<ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. The ROC AUCs range from 0:222 AE 0:339 (for NAD(P)-binding domain proteins) to 0:927 AE 0:083 (for Steroid hormone receptor proteins). We further performed our analysis for different categories of drugs to test whether our approach is more successful for some classes of drugs than for others. For this purpose, we divide drugs into different groups based on their top-level category in the anatomical therapeutic classification (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Miller and Britt, 1995</ref>) and evaluated each group individually (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Example prediction: diclofenac</head><p>One example of our method's predictive power is the identification of similar effects between PPARg (MGI:97747) and the drug diclofenac (STITCH:000003032). Diclofenac is a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug acting primarily as a cyclooxygenase (preferential COX-2) inhibitor and is used to treat a variety of acute and chronic pain and inflammatory conditions. In recent years, additional modes of action have been discerned which in many cases have no known mechanism. For example, diclofenac has been shown to inhibit the thromboxane-prostanoid receptor, affect arachidonic acid release and uptake, inhibit lipoxygenase enzymes and activate the nitric oxide-cGMP antinociceptive pathway (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Gan, 2010</ref>). Using our approach, we have compared the drug effect profile of diclofenac across theDrugBank STITCH (mouse) STITCH (human) x<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. The ROC curves for our three evaluation datasets. DrugBank consists of experimentally verified and manually annotated drug-target interactions. STITCH integrates drug-target relations from multiple databases (including DrugBank), applies text mining and network-based inference approaches to infer drug-target relations. We used human–mouse orthology available from the MGI database to map human proteins in the DrugBank and STITCH (human) dataset to mouse proteinsgathered phenotypic data and found a high similarity to phenotypes produced by Pparg knockout mice. Using our method, 49% of the information content associated with diclofenac's pharmacological effects can be explained through the hypothesis that it inhibits Pparg or its pathway in mice. Pparg is a member of the steroid hormone receptor superfamily, which includes the estrogen and thyroid hormone receptors, and regulates the expression of genes involved in inflammation and lipid homeostasis. Despite its anti-inflammatory indications, diclofenac is associated with the induction of dermatitis, alopecia, erythema, exfoliative dermatitis and eczema, along with hepatitis and other widespread systemic phenotypes. Several of these phenotypes can also be identified in mice (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Harries and Paus, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Wahli, 2002</ref>). In 2002, diclofenac was implicated as a partial agonist of Pparg, acting as a competitive antagonist and inhibiting PPARg signaling at normal therapeutic doses (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Adamson et al., 2002</ref>), suggesting that a significant proportion of diclofenac's side effects might be explained through this mechanism. The apparent pro-inflammatory effects of diclofenac seen, for example, in the skin are, therefore, likely to be a consequence of the effects on the Pparg pathway in non-immune cells, and recent research suggests that it is the effect on the inhibition of PPARg in the pilosebaceceous unit itself that underlies primary cicatricial alopecia, rather than a primary effect on the inflammatory response (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Karnik et al., 2009</ref>). We would expect the effects of diclofenac to be concordant with loss of function phenotypes in mutants of its established target, cyclooxygenase 2 (COX-2). A substantial proportion (46%) of the IC associated with the side effects of diclofenac can be explained through COX-2 (Ptgs2) knockout phenotypes in mice. For example, the main gastrointestinal effects of diclofenac (inflammation, gastritis, constipation, upper GI tract pain) are consistent with the phenotypes of COX2 knockout mice, as evidenced by the sensitization to inflammatory processes such as induction of colitis, the induction of GI edema and peritonitis seen in COX-2 knockout mice (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Morteau et al., 2000</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Choice of semantic similarity measure</head><p>The semantic similarity measure we developed for our application has some disadvantages in comparison with symmetric measures, and these are evidenced in the low performance of our approach for low false-positive rates. In particular, for very low false-positive rates, our approach performs worse than random. This lack of performance is a result of our similarity measure, which does not take mismatches between phenotypes into consideration but is based exclusively on coverage. A small portion of mouse genes is associated with a large number of phenotypes which almost always cover a large portion of observed drug effects for any drug, and a small portion of drugs is similarly associated with a large number of drug effects in SIDER that cover most observed mouse model phenotypes. For example, the genes Gt(ROSA) 26Sor (gene trap ROSA 26, Philippe Soriano) (MGI:104735), phosphatase and tensin homolog (Pten, MGI:109583), apolipoprotein E (Apoe MGI:88057) or leptin receptor (Lepr, MGI:104993) are associated with a large number of phenotypes covering most branches of the MP and are ranked among the first mouse genes for most compounds in SIDER. Similarly, drugs such as pregabalin (STITCH:005486971) or fluoxetine (STITCH:000003386) are associated with a large number of drug effects in SIDER and are ranked in the first places for most mouse genes. These artifacts of our similarity measure result in a decreased performance when analyzing the complete dataset and not applying any additional filtering. In particular, the highest-ranking associations resulting from our approach are, in most cases, false positives due to the artifacts generated by the similarity measure, and these artifacts result in a worse-thanrandom performance in the ROC analysis for low false-positive rates. However, our measure also has significant advantages over symmetric similarity measures. We have evaluated commonly applied groupwise similarity measures (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Pesquita et al., 2009</ref>. The major difference between our similarity measure and groupwise measures such as SimGIC is the symmetry property. In particular, symmetric groupwise similarity measures score mismatches negatively. In our application, we compare large sets of phenotypes observed as drug effects with the phenotypes observed for single gene deletions in mice. If different drug effects are caused by different proteins with which the drug interacts, we expect only a small portion of the effects to be covered by the phenotypes of a single gene knockout. Negatively scoring all non-matching drug effects introduces noise that increases with the number of drug effects and leads to the significantly lower performance in the ROC analysis. Furthermore, symmetric similarity measures are applicable when comparing essentially similar entities. As most chemical compounds in SIDER interact with many proteins, we compare sets of phenotypes resulting from perturbations of many proteins (drug effects) with sets of phenotypes resulting from perturbations of single proteins, and in the case of comparing non-similar entities such as drug effects and knockout phenotypes, our non-symmetric similarity measure seems to perform better than symmetric groupwise measures.</p><formula>) 0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1 G P C RA S 1 A S H R V d P C N g I C N A D P ROCAUC</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Applications in drug repurposing and target discovery</head><p>The results of our analyses support the hypothesis that the systematic analysis of similarity between drug effects and mouse model phenotypes can be used to provide insights into drug actions. Although experimental validation is required to determine the suitability of such an approach for the discovery of novel drug targets, our computational evaluation shows that, at least for some protein families, our approach is highly successful (up to 0:927 AE 0:083 ROCAUC), and therefore may prove promising for integrative approaches toward computational drug repurposing. Our approach is less successful for some protein classes, such as voltage-dependent potassium channel or NAD(P)-binding domain proteins. However, our evaluation datasets contain relatively few positive instances for such classes, indicated by the confidence intervals in<ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. Our work further confirms the hypothesis of Kuhn et al.</p><p>(2013), who mapped 116 mouse phenotype terms to drug effect terms and evaluated 398 knockout mice in an effort to identify proteins that underlie particular drug effects. Kuhn et al. formulated the hypothesis 'that a deletion of a protein in mice is likely to elicit the same phenotype as inhibiting the respective ortholog in humans despite species and methodology differences'. However, while Kuhn et al. used this approach in the context of investigating the role of proteins in eliciting drug side effects, our approach provides evidence for the potential of applying mouse models for revealing novel drug-target interactions. Additionally, we systematically evaluated the whole mouse phenome and provide a ranked list of candidate drug targets spanning all drugs in the SIDER database and every protein for which phenotypes have been created in the mouse. Integrative approaches to drug repurposing and drug target identification take advantage of multiple independent data sources to provide high-confidence predictions of novel indications or novel targets for known drugs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Dudley et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Hurle et al., 2013</ref>). Our approach will be most useful as a component in integrative approaches to drug repurposing or target identification. In both tasks, the use of animal models is currently largely under-represented despite its potential to provide novel, independent information that strengthens already successful systems (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Hurle et al., 2013</ref>). Furthermore, our method is neither based on the 'guilt-byassociation' principle (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Gillis and Pavlidis, 2012</ref>) as is applied in side effect-based approaches to drug repurposing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Campillos et al., 2008</ref>) or other similarity-based approaches (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gottlieb et al., 2011</ref>) nor is our method based on data mining clinical records (<ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Tatonetti et al., 2012</ref>); instead, it uses experimental data from genetically modified animal organisms. Our evaluation demonstrates that our method may even be used independently for some categories of targets, particularly steroid hormone receptors, although additional experimental validation is required to further support this hypothesis. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fibula</head><figDesc>(MA:0001360) is homologous to fibula (FMA:24479) (from the UBERON ontology), Proximal epiphysis of fibula (FMA:33729) is a part-of fibula (FMA:24479) (from the FMA) and Hypertrophic (PATO:0000584) is a more specific quality than morphology (abnormal) (PATO:0000460).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The figure illustrates our basic workflow and the connections between the different datasets we exploit. We aim to infer inhibition actions between drugs and their targets based on the similarity between drug effect profiles and mouse model phenotypes resulting from single gene knockouts. We test the hypothesis whether the phenotypic effects of a perturbation of a gene/protein through a drug action bears some similarity to the phenotypic effects of a targeted mutation of that gene/protein observed in a model organism. As drugs often perturb multiple genes/ proteins, we systematically compute how well a drug effect profile covers observed phenotypes in a mouse model using a non-symmetrical measure of semantic similarity</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1.</figDesc><table>The ROCAUC values we obtain for different protein families, including the 95% confidence interval 

InterPro family 
ROCAUC 
(STITCH mouse) 

ROCAUC 
(STITCH human) 

ROCAUC 
(DrugBank) 

G protein-coupled receptor, rhodopsin-like (IPR000276) 
0 :800 AE 0:028 
0:758 AE 0:030 
Peptidase S1A, chymotrypsin-type (IPR001314) 
0 :892 AE 0:089 
0:874 AE 0:099 
Steroid hormone receptor (IPR001723) 
0 :916 AE 0:078 
0:927 AE 0:083 
Voltage-dependent potassium channel (IPR003091) 
0 :485 AE 0:119 
0:486 AE 0:236 
0:477 AE 0:278 
Neurotransmitter-gated ion-channel (IPR006201) 
0 :581 AE 0:074 
0:581 AE 0:226 
NAD(P)-binding domain (IPR016040) 
0 :567 AE 0:375 
0:336 AE 0:262 
0:222 AE 0:339 

Note: We only analyzed protein families with45 positive drug-target associations. </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">R.Hoehndorf et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">PhenoDrug at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diclofenac antagonizes peroxisome proliferatoractivated receptor-signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J A</forename>
				<surname>Adamson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NCATS launches drug repurposing program</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Allison</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="571" to="572" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bounds for the variance of the mannwhitney statistic</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Birnbaum</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Klose</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Math. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="933" to="945" />
			<date type="published" when="1957" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Mouse Genome Database (MGD): premier model organism resource for mammalian genomics and genetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Blake</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="842" to="848" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Unified Medical Language System (UMLS): integrating biomedical terminology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Bodenreider</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="270" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards an encyclopaedia of mammalian gene function: the international mouse phenotyping consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Brown</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Moore</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dis. Model. Mech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="292" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug target identification using side-effect similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Campillos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">321</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mousefinder: candidate disease genes from mouse phenotype data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C.-K</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mutat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="858" to="866" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Personal omics profiling reveals dynamic molecular and medical phenotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1293" to="1307" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confidence intervals for the area under the ROC curve</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Cortes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Mohri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploiting drug–disease relationships for computational drug repositioning</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Dudley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Briefings Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An introduction to ROC analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Fawcett</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="861" to="874" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diclofenac: an update on its mechanism of action and safety profile</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Gan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Med. Res. Opin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1715" to="1731" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guilt by Association&apos; is the exception rather than the rule in gene networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Gillis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Pavlidis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002444</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using ontologies to describe mouse phenotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Gkoutos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PREDICT: a method for inferring novel drug indications with application to personalized medicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Gottlieb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">496</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OWL 2: the next step for OWL</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Grau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Web Semant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scarring alopecia and the ppar-gamma connection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Harries</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Paus</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Invest. Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1066" to="1070" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interoperability between phenotype and anatomy ontologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Hoehndorf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3112" to="3118" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interoperability between biomedical ontologies through relation expansion, upper-level ontologies and automatic reasoning</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Hoehndorf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">22006</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phenomenet: a whole-phenome approach to disease gene discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Hoehndorf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linking PharmGKB to phenotype studies and animal models of disease for drug repurposing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Hoehndorf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pac. Symp. Biocomput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="388" to="399" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrative, translational approach to understanding rare and orphan genetically based diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Hoehndorf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Interface Focus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational drug repositioning: from data to therapeutics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Hurle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clini. Pharmacol. Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="341" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hair follicle stem cell-specific ppargamma deletion causes scarring alopecia</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Karnik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Invest. Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1243" to="1257" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concurrent classification of EL ontologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Kazakov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ontologies Proceedings of the 10th International Semantic Web Conference (ISWC&apos;11). Vo. 7032 LNCS</title>
		<editor>Aroyo,A. et al.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bonn, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drugbank 3.0: a comprehensive resource for&apos;omics&apos; research on drugs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Knox</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1035" to="1041" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A side effect resource to capture phenotypic effects of drugs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kuhn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">343</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">STITCH 3: zooming in on protein-chemical interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kuhn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="876" to="880" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic identification of proteins that elicit drug side effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kuhn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">663</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new drug classification for computer systems: the ATC extension code</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Miller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Britt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Biomed. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impaired mucosal defense to acute colonic injury in mice lacking cyclooxygenase-1 or cyclooxygenase-2</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Morteau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="469" to="478" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">InterPro, progress and status in 2005</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Mulder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Integrating phenotype ontologies across multiple species</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Mungall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uberon, an integrative multi-species anatomy ontology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Mungall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving disease gene prioritization by comparing the semantic similarity of phenotypes in mice with those of human diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Oellrich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">38937</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metrics for GO based protein semantic similarity: a systematic evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Pesquita</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 5</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semantic similarity in biomedical ontologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Pesquita</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000443</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human phenotype ontology: a tool for annotating and analyzing human hereditary disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="610" to="615" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mouse ascending: perspectives for humandisease models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Rosenthal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Brown</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="993" to="999" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of genome-wide association studies for drug repositioning</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Sanseau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="317" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Repurposing strategies for therapeutics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Sleigh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Barton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmaceut. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mammalian phenotype ontology as a tool for annotating, analyzing and comparing phenotypic information</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data-driven prediction of drug effects and interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Tatonetti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Transl. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pharmacogenomics and bioinformatics: PharmGKB</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Thorn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacogenomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="501" to="505" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptors (ppars): from metabolic control to epidermal wound healing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Wahli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Swiss Med. Wkly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>