
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:38+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis MToolBox: a highly automated pipeline for heteroplasmy annotation and prioritization analysis of human mitochondrial variants in high-throughput sequencing</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">. 21 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Claudia</forename>
								<surname>Calabrese</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Domenico</forename>
								<surname>Simone</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biosciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Milan</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20133</postCode>
									<settlement>Milan</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Maria</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Angela</forename>
								<surname>Diroma</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biosciences, Biotechnologies and Biopharmaceutics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bari</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70126</postCode>
									<settlement>Bari</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mariangela</forename>
								<surname>Santorsola</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Sciences and Technologies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Sannio</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>82100</postCode>
									<settlement>Benevento</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Cristiano</forename>
								<surname>Guttà</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biosciences, Biotechnologies and Biopharmaceutics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bari</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70126</postCode>
									<settlement>Bari</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Giuseppe</forename>
								<surname>Gasparre</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ernesto</forename>
								<surname>Picardi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biosciences, Biotechnologies and Biopharmaceutics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bari</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70126</postCode>
									<settlement>Bari</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biomembranes and Bioenergetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Research Council</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70126</postCode>
									<settlement>Bari</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute of Biostructures and Biosystems</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>00136</postCode>
									<settlement>Rome</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Graziano</forename>
								<surname>Pesole</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biosciences, Biotechnologies and Biopharmaceutics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bari</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70126</postCode>
									<settlement>Bari</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biomembranes and Bioenergetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Research Council</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70126</postCode>
									<settlement>Bari</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Center of Excellence in Genomics for Biomedicine and Agri-food (CEGBA)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bari</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70126</postCode>
									<settlement>Bari</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="institution">Italy Associate Editor: Inanc Birol</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Marcella</forename>
								<surname>Attimonelli</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>marcella.attimonelli@uniba.it</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biosciences, Biotechnologies and Biopharmaceutics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bari</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>70126</postCode>
									<settlement>Bari</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical and Surgical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bologna</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>40138</postCode>
									<settlement>Bologna</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis MToolBox: a highly automated pipeline for heteroplasmy annotation and prioritization analysis of human mitochondrial variants in high-throughput sequencing</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="3115" to="3117"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">. 21 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu483</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 19, 2014; revised on July 8, 2014; accepted on July 9, 2014</note>
					<note>Contact: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The increasing availability of mitochondria-targeted and off-target sequencing data in whole-exome and whole-genome sequencing studies (WXS and WGS) has risen the demand of effective pipelines to accurately measure heteroplasmy and to easily recognize the most functionally important mitochondrial variants among a huge number of candidates. To this purpose, we developed MToolBox, a highly automated pipeline to reconstruct and analyze human mito-chondrial DNA from high-throughput sequencing data. Results: MToolBox implements an effective computational strategy for mitochondrial genomes assembling and haplogroup assignment also including a prioritization analysis of detected variants. MToolBox provides a Variant Call Format file featuring, for the first time, allele-specific heteroplasmy and annotation files with prioritized variants. MToolBox was tested on simulated samples and applied on 1000 Genomes WXS datasets. Availability and implementation: MToolBox package is available at https://sourceforge.net/projects/mtoolbox/.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Emerging discoveries in human mitochondrial genetics, driven by the advent of next-generation sequencing, have revealed that individuals exhibit a complex mixture of mitochondrial genotypes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">He et al., 2010</ref>) and carry low-level heteroplasmic variants (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Payne et al., 2013</ref>). On the other hand, the deeper the sequencing coverage, the higher the number of mitochondrial DNA</p><p>(mtDNA) variants and the variety of heteroplasmic ranges found per individual (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Diroma et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">He et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Payne et al., 2013</ref>). In this frame, the deep sequencing of mtDNA raises the demand of effective pipelines to accurately measure heteroplasmy and to easily recognize the most functionally important variants among a huge number of candidates. To this purpose, we developed MToolBox, a highly automated bioinformatics pipeline to reconstruct and analyze human mtDNA from high-throughput sequencing (HTS) data. The MToolBox workflow includes a computational strategy to assemble mitochondrial genomes from whole-exome sequencing (WXS) and/or whole-genome sequencing (WGS) data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Picardi and Pesole, 2012</ref>), which was further updated to detect insertions and deletions (ins/dels) and to assess the heteroplasmic fraction (HF) of each variant allele with the related confidence interval (CI), reported as sample-specific meta-information in an enhanced version of the Variant Call Format (VCF) file (version 4.0). The MToolBox pipeline analyzes the reconstructed genomes for haplogroup assignment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Rubino et al., 2012</ref>) and variant prioritization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Mitochondrial reads extraction, genome reconstruction and VCF file generation</head><p>The MToolBox pipeline integrates in a unique automatic workflow a computational strategy for mtDNA data extraction from WXS and WGS data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Picardi and Pesole, 2012</ref>), where new important features have been added. MToolBox can accept as input raw data or prealigned reads (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1a</ref>). In both cases, reads are mapped/remapped by the mapExome.py script (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1b</ref>) at user's choice either onto the Reconstructed Sapiens Reference Sequence (RSRS;<ref type="bibr">Behar et al., 2012</ref>) or the revised Cambridge Reference Sequence (rCRS;<ref type="bibr">Andrews et al., 1999</ref>). Subsequently, reads mapped on mtDNA are realigned onto the nuclear genome (GRCh37/hg19), to discard Nuclear mitochondrial Sequences (NumtS; Simone et al., 2011;<ref type="figure">Fig. 1c</ref>) and amplification artifacts. The resulting Sequence Alignment/Map (SAM) file (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1d</ref>) can be optionally processed for ins/dels realignment around a set of *To whom correspondence should be addressed. yThe authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded asknown ins/dels, annotated in HmtDB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Rubino et al., 2012</ref>) and MITOMAP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ruiz-Pesini et al., 2007</ref>), and for putative PCR duplicates removal (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1e</ref>–h and Supplementary Information). This step generates a dataset of highly reliable mitochondrial aligned reads, which is used to reconstruct a complete mitochondrial genome by the assembleMTgenome.py script (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1i</ref>), now integrating the mtVariantCaller.py module for nucleotide mismatches and ins/dels detection. All the genomic variants are filtered based on the quality scores and read depth, and annotated in a VCF file (v.4.0), with the corresponding HF and CI values (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1j</ref>and Supplementary Information).<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. The main steps of the MToolBox workflow: (a–d) read mapping and NumtS filtering; (e–h) post-mapping processing; (i–m) genome assembly, haplogroup prediction and variant annotation. In brackets, programs or modules particularly important for the associated process. Solid connectors indicate mandatory pipeline steps; dashed connectors (e–g) indicate that the corresponding post-mapping steps can be optional, otherwise the OUT2.sam file directly undergoes the assembly process (h). Please refer to Supplementary Information for a detailed description of MToolBox workflow steps</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Haplogroup prediction and prioritization analysis of mitochondrial variants</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Joint First Authors.</figDesc><table>ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which 
permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">MToolBox provides an output file with reconstructed contig sequence(s) (Contigs.fa) (Fig. 1k and Supplementary Information). Each set of contigs is subjected to haplogroup prediction, relying on the RSRS-based Phylotree resource (van Oven and Kayser, 2009), by mt-classifier (Fig. 1l), an updated version of the fragment-classify tool (Rubino et al., 2012), which now includes a module to perform functional annotation and prioritization of mitochondrial variants (Fig. 1m and Supplementary Information). This latter analysis is carried out by aligning each sample-specific reconstructed contig against the related macrohaplogroup-specific consensus sequence (Supplementary Information) to recognize, via a prioritization process, private variants, deserving further clinical investigation. The prioritization takes into account also the pathogenicity of each mutated allele, determined with different algorithms, and the nucleotide variability of each variant site; amino acid variability is also considered if the variant site is codogenic (Supplementary Information). For each mutated allele, additional annotations are also reported, i.e. annotation from HmtDB and MITOMAP resources and their occurrence among 1000 Genomes Project samples (Supplementary Information). Variants of assembled genomes are also reported with respect to rCRS (Supplementary Information), to ensure a full compatibility of the resulting annotation with the current clinical literature (Bandelt et al., 2014). 3 RESULTS The MToolBox performance in heteroplasmy detection was tested on four artificial heteroplasmic samples, whose sequencing was simulated at different mean depth (Supplementary Information). MToolBox showed high specificity and sensitivity in detecting all the artificial heteroplasmy tested, with an average coverage depth equal or above 1000Â. MToolBox was extensively applied on WXS data from 1000 Genomes (Genomes Project et al., 2012 and Supplementary Information), to obtain a VCF file of mtDNA variants from 2419 individuals (available at https://sourceforge.net/projects/mtoolbox/files/1000Genomes_ data/). Reliability of reconstructed mitochondrial genomes was confirmed by their haplogroup predictions, the majority of which coherent with the ancestry of the related individual (Supplementary Information). The accuracy in heteroplasmy detection and quantification was confirmed by the results from four mother–child pairs that showed the expected pattern of mtDNA inheritance (Supplementary Information). 4 DISCUSSION A highly automated pipeline for mtDNA analysis from HTS data is not available to date. To fill this gap, we developed MToolBox, an effective workflow with customizable parameters and able to analyze multiple samples in a single run. MToolBox is the only tool that generates as output a VCF file, the standard format for large-scale genotyping information, suitably customized for mitochondrial data, by including the heteroplasmy fraction and its related CI. In fact, also the MitoSeek tool (Guo et al., 2013) performs mitochondrial HTS data analyses, including somatic and structural variant recognition. Additionally, MToolBox provides the user with essential analyses of reconstructed mitochondrial genomes, i.e. haplogroup assignment and variant prioritization, exploiting a broad collection of annotation resources. Thus, MToolBox may provide a valuable support for the recognition of candidate mitochondrial mutations in clinical studies. Funding: This work was supported by Progetto Strategico &apos;Invecchiamento&apos; e &apos;Medicina Personalizzata&apos; (CNR, Italy) and the PRIN2009 fund assigned to M.A. The computational work has been executed on the IT resources made available by the ReCaS project (PONa3_00052). Conflicts of interest: none declared. REFERENCES Andrews,R.M. et al. (1999) Reanalysis and revision of the Cambridge reference sequence for human mitochondrial DNA. Nat. Genet., 23, 147. Bandelt,H.J. et al. (2014) The case of the continuing use of the revised Cambridge Reference Sequence (rCRS) and the standardization of notation in human mitochondrial DNA studies. J. Hum. Genet., 59, 66–77. Behar,D.M. et al. (2012) A &quot; Copernican &quot; reassessment of the human mitochondrial DNA tree from its root. Am. J. Hum. Genet., 90, 675–684.</note>

			<note place="foot">C.Calabrese et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">MToolBox at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extraction and annotation of human mitochondrial genomes from 1000 Genomes Whole Exome Sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Diroma</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 3</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated map of genetic variation from 1,092 human genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Genomes</forename>
				<surname>Project</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">491</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MitoSeek: extracting mitochondria information and performing high-throughput mitochondria sequencing analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Guo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1210" to="1211" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heteroplasmic mitochondrial DNA mutations in normal and tumour cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>He</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">464</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="610" to="614" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Universal heteroplasmy of human mitochondrial DNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Payne</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mol. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="384" to="390" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mitochondrial genomes gleaned from human whole-exome sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Picardi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Pesole</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="523" to="524" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HmtDB, a genomic resource for mitochondrion-based human variability studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Rubino</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1150" to="1159" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An enhanced MITOMAP with a global mtDNA mutational phylogeny</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Ruiz-Pesini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="823" to="828" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The reference human nuclear mitochondrial sequences compilation validated and implemented on the UCSC genome browser Updated comprehensive phylogenetic tree of global human mitochondrial DNA variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Simone</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics Hum. Mutat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="386" to="394" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>