
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:34+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology Multi-omics enrichment analysis using the GeneTrail2 web service</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Daniel</forename>
								<surname>Stö Ckel</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saarland University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Saarbrü cken</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-66041</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Tim</forename>
								<surname>Kehl</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saarland University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Saarbrü cken</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-66041</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Patrick</forename>
								<surname>Trampert</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saarland University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Saarbrü cken</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-66041</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lara</forename>
								<surname>Schneider</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saarland University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Saarbrü cken</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-66041</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christina</forename>
								<surname>Backes</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saarland University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Saarbrü cken</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-66041</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nicole</forename>
								<surname>Ludwig</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Medical School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saarland University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D-66421</postCode>
									<settlement>Homburg</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andreas</forename>
								<surname>Gerasch</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eberhard-Karls-University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Tü bingen</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-72076</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<surname>Kaufmann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eberhard-Karls-University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Tü bingen</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-72076</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Manfred</forename>
								<surname>Gessler</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Developmental Biochemistry, and Comprehensive Cancer Center Mainfranken</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Theodor-Boveri-Institute/Biocenter</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Wü rzburg University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Wü rzburg</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-97074</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Norbert</forename>
								<surname>Graf</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Pediatric Oncology and Hematology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Medical School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saarland University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D-66421</postCode>
									<settlement>Homburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eckart</forename>
								<surname>Meese</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Medical School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saarland University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D-66421</postCode>
									<settlement>Homburg</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andreas</forename>
								<surname>Keller</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saarland University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Saarbrü cken</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-66041</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hans-Peter</forename>
								<surname>Lenhof</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saarland University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Saarbrü cken</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-66041</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology Multi-omics enrichment analysis using the GeneTrail2 web service</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv770</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on 19 October 2015; revised on 17 December 2015; accepted on 28 December 2015</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Gene set analysis has revolutionized the interpretation of high-throughput transcrip-tomic data. Nowadays, with comprehensive studies that measure multiple-omics from the same sample, powerful tools for the integrative analysis of multi-omics datasets are required. Results: Here, we present GeneTrail2, a web service allowing the integrated analysis of transcrip-tomic, miRNomic, genomic and proteomic datasets. It offers multiple statistical tests, a large number of predefined reference sets, as well as a comprehensive collection of biological categories and enables direct comparisons between the computed results. We used GeneTrail2 to explore patho-genic mechanisms of Wilms tumors. We not only succeeded in revealing signaling cascades that may contribute to the malignancy of blastemal subtype tumors but also identified potential bio-markers for nephroblastoma with adverse prognosis. The presented use-case demonstrates that GeneTrail2 is well equipped for the integrative analysis of comprehensive-omics data and may help to shed light on complex pathogenic mechanisms in cancer and other diseases. Availability and implementation: GeneTrail2 can be freely accessed under https://genetrail2.bioinf.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The advent of high-throughput analysis technologies during the last decades has revolutionized biology and medicine and has lead to a tremendous increase in the amount of available, high-dimensional biological data. However, technologies like microarrays, next-generation sequencing or mass spectrometry are highly sensitive to changes in the experimental conditions or protocols, giving rise to technological noise that must be carefully accounted for (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Leek et al., 2010</ref>). Due to the above reasons, the development of automated and robust statistical analysis methods for high-throughput data has become a necessity. Enrichment methods are one fundamental class of analysis procedures for the study of pathogenic mechanisms and the identification of deregulated pathways and categories. Widely-applied enrichment methods are Over Representation Analysis (ORA) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">DraˇghiciDraˇghici et al., 2003</ref>) and Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>). Other approaches, e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kim and</ref><ref type="bibr">Volsky (2005), Newton et al. (2007)</ref>,<ref type="bibr">et al. (2005)</ref>, employ straightforward averaging methods that, despite their simplicity, offer competitive performance. Building upon such averaging approaches, Efron and<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Tibshirani (2007)</ref>presented the maxmean statistics. More specialized approaches, which complement the generally applicable methods presented above, are e.g. topGO (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alexa et al., 2006</ref>) and GO-Bayes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Zhang et al., 2010</ref>), which operate on the Gene Ontology (GO) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Ashburner et al., 2000</ref>) and account for its hierarchical structure. Another class of algorithms uses the topology of known biological networks to improve the computed enrichments. Examples are GGEA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Geistlinger et al., 2011</ref>) and EnrichNet (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Glaab et al., 2012</ref>). Due to the popularity of enrichment methods, many implementations are available, both as stand-alone applications and as web services. Some focus on a certain database while others are limited to one or two algorithms (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). Examples for available tools are the Broad Institute's GSEA implementation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>) or the GSEA-SNP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Holden et al., 2008</ref>) R package. Also a wide variety of web services for enrichment analysis exists, which we discussed briefly in Supplementary Note S1. Moreover, a comprehensive collection of enrichment tools can be found in the OMICtools database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Henry et al., 2014</ref>). Extensive reviews on enrichment methods (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ackermann and Strimmer, 2009</ref>; Efron and<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Tibshirani, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Huang et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Hung et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Khatri et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Naeem et al., 2012</ref>) have been published and reveal that no real gold standard exists. This is due to the fact that each of the proposed methods is based on differing definitions of enriched categories (differing null hypotheses), making their results incomparable in general. Instead of using a single 'magic bullet', an appropriate algorithm needs to be chosen carefully for each individual research task. Finally, as heterogenous datasets, e.g. datasets comprised of genomic variations, miRNA and mRNA expression measurements, are becoming increasingly common, integrative platforms for enrichment analyses are needed. Unfortunately, only few such tools are readily available. Examples are miRTrail (<ref type="bibr">Laczny et al., 2012</ref>), which links mRNA, miRNA and disease phentotypes, Genevar (<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Yang et al., 2010</ref>), focusing on the association between SNPs and eQTLs, or RAMONA using a Bayesian Model for linking arbitrary-omics to ontology terms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Sass et al., 2014</ref>). In this study, we present GeneTrail2, a new web server for the analysis of multi-omics datasets, with which we provide one of the most comprehensive tools for enrichment analysis. For human alone, it features over 46 000 categories collected from over 30 databases including KEGG, Reactome, GO, WikiPathways, DrugBank, Pfam, miRWalk and miRDB (cf. Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S12</ref>). It natively supports transcriptomics, miRNomics, proteomics, and genomics data and can convert between 32 common identifier types. In total, we implemented 13 identifier-level statistics, 10 set-level statistics (see Section 2.3), two Pvalue computation strategies and eight P-value adjustment methods. Data from all major-omics are supported, making it possible to analyze and explore heterogeneous datasets in an interactive fashion using GeneTrail2's web interface. The web interface is built on top of modern web technologies with special attention to usability. Non-expert users can quickly perform comprehensive analyses using the predefined workflow, which is complemented with thorough documentation. Moreover, the interface enables users to integrate enrichments obtained from multiple-omics using the integrated mapping procedures and our side-by-side view. For further analysis tasks, we offer a deep integration into existing applications like the network visualization tool BiNA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Gerasch et al., 2014</ref>) or the NetworkTrail (<ref type="bibr">Stöckel et al., 2013</ref>) web service. Another key feature of GeneTrail2 is its RESTful API, through which power users can script the web service. This scripting interface allows the seamless integration of GeneTrail2 into workflow systems such as Galaxy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Goecks et al., 2010</ref>) or Taverna (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Wolstencroft et al., 2013</ref>). The backend of GeneTrail2 relies on highly optimized C þþ code leading to excellent computation times. GeneTrail2 can be accessed under https://genetrail2.bioinf.uni-sb.de. We demonstrate the capabilities of GeneTrail2 by applying it to a Wilms tumor expression dataset with the goal of identifying molecular determinants for the increased malignancy of certain Wilms tumor subtypes. Further use cases are discussed on the website.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>Since GeneTrail2 is a comprehensive software platform comprising more than 31 000 lines of code, we start with a short introduction to the architecture of our web service. Then, we present an example workflow serving as guide through the available functionality and implemented methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Architecture</head><p>GeneTrail2 is a complete rewrite of its predecessor, the GeneTrail (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Backes et al., 2007</ref>) web service, with the goal to provide more, readily available identifier-and set-level statistics and to greatly increase its flexibility. Furthermore, it supports user accounts and, for increased reproducibility, fully automatic documentation of all used parameters. To accommodate this, the new server is based on a modular architecture (cf.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>) allowing to easily add new features, exchange implementation details or perform general maintenance. We implemented a user interface based on HTML5 and JavaEE technology using the Thymeleaf template engine and JQuery. This interface interacts with the web service using a RESTful API. This API allows access to the complete functionality of GeneTrail2. It offers interfaces for starting and managing computationallyintensive analysis tasks as well as querying computed results. Providing a RESTful API has the additional advantage that users can write custom scripts in any programming language, e.g. for batch processing. All compute-intensive tasks were implemented using highly optimized C þþ code in order to achieve maximum performance. This code relies on the Boost library for the implementation of probability distributions and auxiliary algorithms. Eigen 3 is used for matrix–vector algebra and the GMP library provides multi precision integer and floating point operations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Workflow</head><p>GeneTrail2 offers a considerable number of analysis workflows (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3</ref>). Due to space constraints, we only discuss one common scenario. First, the user uploads the data to be analyzed, e.g. a matrix containing normalized expression measurements. Then, the data can be divided into sample and reference sets in order to enable the computation of identifier-level scores. After score computation, a set-level statistic must be selected. The user can then choose biological categories that should be analyzed. For each step the user can adjust the parameters of the employed method. As this usually requires considerable expert knowledge, we provide defaults that should be applicable for most use-cases and that have been chosen conservatively in order to prevent false discoveries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Method overview</head><p>GeneTrail2 accepts the following simple, tab-delimited text files as inputs: identifier lists, score lists and data matrices. In addition, it is possible to analyze microarray expression datasets from the Gene Expression Omnibus repository (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Barrett et al., 2013</ref>) directly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1">Identifier and organism estimation</head><p>A key challenge when dealing with uploaded data is the automatic detection of the identifiers used in the dataset. We solved this problem by creating a MapDB-based database of supported identifiers, against which user data are validated. In addition, the database supports mapping between different identifier types such as UniProt Accessions and Entrez Gene Ids. Coupled with automated file type detection, no user intervention should be required when uploading data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2">Identifier-level statistics</head><p>Whereas identifier lists and score lists can be directly used as input for computing enrichments, expression matrices need to be processed to (identifier-level) scores first. To this end, we provide a comprehensive set of statistics (see Supplementary Note S2.1). Among these are the fold-change, Wilcoxon test and a (regularized) version of the t-test. If possible and applicable, paired versions of the statistics are provided. For supporting count data we integrated the DESeq2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Love et al., 2014</ref>), edgeR (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Robinson et al., 2010</ref>) and RUVSeq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Risso et al., 2014</ref>) approaches. Simple transformations such as absolute value, square, square root or logarithm can be applied to computed scores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3">Set-level statistics and categories</head><p>Once the input data have been prepared, one of the following setlevel statistics can be applied: the weighted and unweighted Kolmogorov-Smirnov (KS) test, the Wilcoxon test, ORA, sum-, mean-, median-and maxmean statistics, as well as the one and two sample t-test. After choosing an algorithm, the user can select categories for which an enrichment should be computed. The categories integrated into GeneTrail2 were collected from many, commonly used biological databases (cf. Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S12</ref>). Among others, these databases cover signaling pathways, genomic features, transcription factor (TF) targets, miRNA targets, drug targets and (disease) phenotypes. In addition, user-defined categories can be uploaded in gene matrix transposed (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>) format. For ORA, it is also required to select a reference (background) set. For human alone, we offer over 40 predefined reference sets (see Supplementary Tables S13–S17) covering many experimental platforms. If no applicable reference set is available, a custom set can be uploaded.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.4">P-value computation</head><p>For determining the significance levels of the computed set-level scores, GeneTrail2 offers the gene set and the phenotype strategy. While the gene set strategy is based on permuting the identifier-level scores, the phenotype strategy randomly redistributes the measurements between the sample and reference group. An advantage of the gene set strategy is that it allows the direct computation of P-values for some methods and thus avoids costly permutation tests (seeSupplementary Note S2.2). This leads to a higher resolution of the computed P-values and very low computation times (see Section 2.4). For an in-depth discussion of the advantages and disadvantages of the respective methods we refer the reader to<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Tian et al. (2005)</ref>. The phenotype strategy always requires that a permutation test is performed. As new identifier-level scores must be derived for every permutation, the method can only be used if a data matrix was supplied. Finally, a method for multiple testing correction must be chosen. To this end, we provide a large set of correction methods (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S6</ref>) including the popular Benjamini– Hochberg FDR adjustment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.5">Examining computed results</head><p>Enrichments can be visualized online or downloaded as compressed archives and MS Excel tables. When viewing an enrichment online, we provide detailed statistics about significant categories and their members, which are fully sort-and searchable. Besides the traditional list of significant categories, we also offer an inverse enrichment view, which for every gene displays the significant categories it is a member of. In addition, the user can select a set of enrichments that can be viewed side-by-side, providing a compact and clearly arranged overview. This allows to quickly detect similarities and differences with respect to the detected categories. Here, two view modes are available. While the union mode displays all categories that are significant in at least one enrichment, the intersection mode only displays categories that are significant in all enrichments. Whereas the union is useful for detecting variability between related enrichments, the intersection can be used to reduce the number of false positives by computing and comparing two or more enrichments using different algorithms. Using these modes, the user is able to effectively balance the sensitivity and specificity of an analysis in a straightforward manner. Combining the side-by-side view with GeneTrail2's mapping features allows for an integrated analysis of gene lists obtained from different-omics. For example, given transcriptomics and proteomics data, protein abundance scores can be mapped onto the corresponding genes allowing to compute enrichments using gene categories for both score lists. Via the union mode it is possible to spot similarities and differences between the enrichments obtained from both-omics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Performance</head><p>The performance of basic tools such as enrichment methods is critical, as good performance significantly shortens the development cycles of data analysis workflows. To this end, GeneTrail2 uses a C þþ implementation to guarantee optimal performance. In general, the gene set strategy is one order of magnitude quicker to compute than the phenotype strategy (see<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). The used set-level statistics has little influence on the computation time. GeneTrail2 significantly outperforms the Broad Institute GSEA application (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Subramanian et al., 2005</ref>) for both, the gene set and the phenotype strategy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Case study: Wilms tumors</head><p>Wilms tumors (WTs), or nephroblastomas, are childhood renal tumors. While in general WTs are associated with survival rates &gt;90%, some subtypes with much higher relapse rates are known (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Sredni et al., 2009</ref>). For proper risk-assessment and therapy stratification it is thus crucial to identify and understand the differences in the pathogenic processes between the tumor subtypes. We used GeneTrail2 to analyze a WT expression dataset in order to determine key players influencing the malignancy of WTs. The dataset consists of 40 mRNA and 47 miRNA expression profiles from 47 tumor biopsies from 39 patients, containing four healthy tissue samples as well as 17 blastemal, nine mixed type and 17 miscellaneous tumor samples (cf. Supplementary Section S3.1). As our dataset stems from a study following the SIOP protocol, patients underwent chemotherapy before surgery and sample collection. Approximately 25% of initial blastemal predominant tumors do not respond to preoperative chemotherapy and have a poor prognosis. Hence, special attention was put on identifying factors leading to an increased resistance to chemotherapy in this blastemal subtype, which accounts for 10% of all WTs. In the following, we refer to those tumors as blastemal tumors. We describe the results of our WT analysis as a learning process that was guided by the computed enrichments, simple statistical analyses and the study of literature. For a review of the implemented enrichment algorithms, we refer the reader to the available, extensive literature (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ackermann and Strimmer, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Efron and Tibshirani, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Huang et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Hung et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Khatri et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Naeem et al., 2012</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1">Consensus of enrichment approaches</head><p>We used GeneTrail2 to examine the differences between blastemal and non-blastemal tumors using the independent shrinkage t-test (Opgen<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rhein and Strimmer, 2007</ref>) to compute scores for all genes and miRNAs (see Supplementary Note S3.5). For P-value computation the gene set strategy with Benjamini–Hochberg adjustment was chosen. In order to compare the implemented set-level statistics based on our data, we applied all available set-level statistics excluding ORA to the score lists. The resulting enrichments are given in Supplementary Tables S18 and S19 and under https://genetrail2.bio inf.uni-sb.de/results.html?session¼a9e84e92-ea41-42ab-9ee7c0f8515f9234. We observed that, despite a considerable overlap, the differences between the enrichments are substantial (cf. Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>). For example, while the union of all enrichments contains 1436 GO-Biological Process categories, only 343 categories are contained in their intersection. As expected, this effect is especially pronounced for databases containing categories close to the significance level, which may indicate that these categories were only reported due to idiosyncrasies of the corresponding method.For comparison the KS implementation of the Broad GSEA package was used. Mean run times over five runs are given in seconds; standard deviations are provided in parenthesis. In the comparison, the t-test was used as scoring method, no P-value correction has been performed, and 10 000 iterations were used for permutation tests. Results marked with a * used an exact P-value computation method. Timings were obtained on an Intel Core i7-3770 processor</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The GeneTrail2 web service</head><p>The number of significant categories per method can be found in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. In order to focus on highly relevant processes, we only consider categories consistently reported by at least seven of nine set-level statistics, which can be easily achieved using our comparative enrichment view. Further discussion only considers this intersection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">General observations</head><p>For mRNA the upregulation of categories like mRNA Processing, Cell Cycle and DNA Replication suggest a clear increase in mitotic activity in blastemal tumors. For miRNA, categories associated with various cancer types, including HMDD-renal cell carcinoma, are significantly enriched. The same is true for miRNA categories involved in hormone regulation, immune response, apoptosis and tumor suppression. None of the miRNA families is significant in all enrichments; however, the families miR-302, miR-515, miR-30, miR-17 and let-7 are significant for at least seven out of nine tests. The miR-302 and miR-515 families are associated with the activation of the canonical WNT pathway (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Anton et al., 2011</ref>). In addition, the miR-17 family is known for its oncogenic role in cancer and stem cell development (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Mogilyansky and Rigoutsos, 2013</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.3">Deregulation of let-7 via LIN28B and TRIM71</head><p>The let-7 miRNA family has previously been reported to play a vital role in WT suppression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Urbach et al., 2014</ref>). However, many high abundant family members are upregulated (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table  S3</ref>), which is unexpected due to let-7 miRNAs acting as tumor suppressors. A possible explanation for this behavior may be provided by TRIM71, which is among the top-scoring genes. TRIM71 degrades LIN28B via ubiquitin-mediated proteosomal degradation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Lee et al., 2014</ref>) (cf.<ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>). LIN28B in turn suppresses the maturation of prilet-7 miRNA. Hence, the upregulation of TRIM71 induces an upregulation of the let-7 family, which, in theory, promotes cell differentiation. However,<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chang et al. (2012)</ref>found that TRIM71 can promote rapid embryonic stem cell (ESC) proliferation in mice and report that it represses the expression of CDKN1A, a cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor, which acts as a cell-cycle regulator. As high expression levels of TRIM71 are commonly observed in undifferentiated cells, the authors conclude that TRIM71 is an important factor for maintaining proliferation in stem cells.<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Urbach et al. (2014)</ref>report that LIN28B is able to induce WTs under certain conditions and note that in these tumors the cap mesenchymal (CM) specific stem cell markers CITED1, EYA1 and SIX2 are upregulated. In general, this trend is present in our data, however, we find that the marker's expression is more consistent with TRIM71's expression pattern (<ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>and Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. S2</ref>). In summary, our initial results indicate that miRNA and genes associated with stem cell fate play an essential role in blastemal tumors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.4">Activation of cancer-related WNT signaling</head><p>Deregulation of the WNT signaling pathway is often prevalent in cancer samples (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Polakis, 2012</ref>). Indeed, our enrichment analysis contains categories associated with the WNT pathway (see Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S5</ref>). This is consistent with its previously reported central role in most WTs and especially in blastema-rich WTs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Fukuzawa et al., 2009</ref>). The activation of the canonical WNT pathway usually leads to degradation of the destruction complex that, as long as it is functional, degrades the transcriptional coactivator b-catenin. Thus, degradation of the destruction complex leads to higher amounts of b-catenin in the cytoplasm that is transported to the nucleus where it builds complexes with TCF/LEF proteins. Degradation of the destruction complex lies at the core of developmental processes, ESC self-renewal and differentiation and changes the transcriptional landscape of the cell dramatically. 3.1.5 TCF3 as potential WT master regulator We argued that factors associated with stem cell fate and the canonical WNT pathway play an essential role in blastemal tumors. A well-known link between the WNT pathway and the core regulatory<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 4. TRIM71</ref>degrades LIN28B using ubiquitin-mediated proteosomal degradation. LIN28B regulates the maturation of let-7 miRNAs (<ref type="bibr">Piskounova et al., 2011</ref>), which promote cell differentiation and act on TRIM71 and LIN28B via a negative feedback loop (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Marson et al., 2008</ref>). TRIM71 as well as AGO2 in complex with miR-290/302 miRNAs repress CDKN1A expression leading to increased proliferation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Lee et al., 2014</ref>). TCF3 acts on most of the above players (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Marson et al., 2008</ref>), effectively amplifying the currently predominant signal in the feedback loop<ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>. Expression of TRIM71 and LIN28B in comparison with the cap mesenchyme stem cell markers CITED1, EYA1 and SIX2. Samples are classified as normal, necrotic (NE), regressive, epithelial (E), stromal (S), focal anaplasia (FA), diffuse anaplasia (DA) and blastemal. The size of a colored bar represents the absolute expression strength of the associated gene<ref type="bibr">et al., 2008</ref>). If the WNT pathway is inactive, TCF3 is mainly repressing pluripotency factors and promoting differentiation, however, if the WNT pathway is activated, the repressive complex converts to an activating complex, promoting pluripotency (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cole et al., 2008</ref>). To study the influence of ESC master regulators, we constructed a new set of gene categories that we subjected to the KS test using the blastemal versus non-blastemal scores as input. For each of the four transcription factors (TFs), we defined two categories containing genes for which 'strong evidence' exists that they are regulated by the respective TF. In particular, we add a gene to a category for a TF if the TF occupies a site in the gene's promoter region and the correlation between the TF's and the gene's expression is &gt;0.5 (positive category) or smaller than À0.5 (negative category). For the identification of the promoters occupied by the master regulators, we used the mouse ESC ChIP<ref type="figure" target="#tab_0">Table S20</ref>, https:// genetrail2.bioinf.uni-sb.de/results.html?session¼cbc86903-424847a2-b916-bc682924c242) revealed that genes positively regulated by TCF3 (p % 10 À40 ) and NANOG (p % 10 À13 ) are strongly enriched, whereas genes negatively regulated by TCF3 (p % 10 À40 ) are strongly depleted. Conversely, genes positively regulated by OCT4 are strongly depleted, and genes negatively regulated by OCT4 are strongly enriched. This is consistent with a correlation of TCF3 with OCT4 of À0.7. SOX2 and NANOG both seem to be of lesser importance in our data. However, the four master regulators do not only regulate protein coding genes.<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Marson et al. (2008)</ref>revealed that they are also 'associated with promoters for miRNAs that are preferentially expressed in ESCs'. Examples are the miR-302, miR-515 and let-7 families which we previously discussed (cf.<ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>). In addition, our data indicate that TCF3 regulates the expression of the miR-17 cluster (all correlations &gt;0.5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.6">IGF2 as putative WNT activator</head><p>In the above section, we have outlined how the ESC regulatory circuitry is driven by TCF3 through the WNT pathway. However, the mechanisms that activate WNT signaling still remain unclear. Whereas certain genetic mutations occur with relatively low frequency ( 30%), among them genes that may induce WNT signaling, epigenetic lesions and especially loss of imprinting at the IGF2/ H19 locus have been found for 81% of all blastemal subtype WTs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Wegert et al., 2015</ref>) leading to an overexpression of IGF2.<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">In 2001</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">, Morali et al. (2001</ref>showed that IGF2 can induce the expression and import of b-catenin and TCF3 into the nucleus even in the absence of WNT proteins. This triggers a switchover from the epithelial to mesenchymal cell state, which is in accordance with the expression patterns of the CM stem cell markers shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>. In addition, TCF3 binding sites have been found in the IGF2 gene (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cole et al., 2008</ref>). Remarkably, we observe an extreme correlation of 0.9 between the TCF3 and IGF2 expression (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S3</ref>). This suggests that TCF3 in turn regulates IGF2 leading to a self-sustaining feedback loop which is likely to be causal for the stem cell character of, e.g. blastemal tumors. compare multiple enrichment results from the same or different-omics allows to identify differences and similarities between experiments. These capabilities are central for modern in silico analyses and set GeneTrail2 apart from other approaches.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by the<ref type="bibr">[SPP 1335]</ref>(Scalable Visual Analytics) of the DFG and by the DFG projects [LE 952/5-1] and<ref type="bibr">[LE 952/3-2]</ref>; the p-medicine project with funding from the European Union's 7th Framework Program for research, technological development and demonstration<ref type="bibr">[270089]</ref>; the SIOP2001/GPOH clinical trial received financial support by 'Deutsche Krebshilfe'<ref type="bibr">[50-2709-Gr2]</ref>. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. A comparison of selected enrichment tools. The number of supported databases refers to the number of unique data sources from which categories have been obtained. Databases are counted across all supported species and-omics. The number of supported algorithms refers to the number of algorithms offered for analysis. Related methods (e.g. network algorithms) have been included. A tool was defined as supporting an-omics, if it provides dedicated biological categories for this-omics type</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Simplified flowchart of GeneTrail2. Round boxes depict start/end states. Boxes with gray background represent input file types, whereas a white background represents processing steps. Diamonds are decision nodes</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Architecture of GeneTrail2. Core algorithms are implemented as an optimized C þþ library based on Boost, Eigen 3 and GMP. On top of this library we implemented a JAX-RS-based RESTful API. The frontend is based on the Thymeleaf template engine and JQuery. As application server we use Apache Tomcat</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>Tian V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 1502 Bioinformatics, 32(10), 2016, 1502–1508 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv770 Advance Access Publication Date: 18 January 2016 Original Paper</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Performance data for enrichments computed on the KEGG categories using the (unweighted) KS and mean set-level statistics</figDesc><table>Broad GSEA 
GeneTrail 2 

KS 
Gene set 
400 s (6 7.3 s) 
9.3 s* (6 0.15 s) 
Phenotype 
428.8 s (6 4.32 s) 
84.5 s (6 0.6 s) 
Mean 
Gene set 
N/A 
3 s (6 0.02 s) 
Phenotype 
N/A 
74.8 s (6 1.7 s) 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. Number of significantly enriched (P &lt; 0.05) mRNA categories found by each enrichment method for the blastemal versus non-blastemal scores</figDesc><table>Two-sample t-test 
3866 
Sum 
3406 
One-sample t-test 
3852 
Weighted KS 
2497 
Two-sample Wilcoxon 
3685 
Maxmean 
2057 
KS 
3518 
Median 
1989 
Mean 
3424 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">D.Stö ckel et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> Discussion We presented GeneTrail2, a platform for the enrichment analysis of multi-omics datasets. GeneTrail2 was designed to offer users a maximal amount of flexibility while keeping the common workflow accessible to non-expert users. This is achieved by offering a user friendly, well-documented web interface. In turn, scripting capabilities allow expert users to conduct fully automated large-scale analyses and the integration into third-party applications. To further this flexibility, we provide, to the best of our knowledge, the largest number of enrichment algorithms (Fig. 1) available in a web service. This was motivated by the lack of gold standards for enrichment analysis and enables researchers to choose the appropriate tool for the task at hand. Through our comparative enrichment view, we additionally offer a straightforward way for balancing the sensitivity and specificity of analyses. Furthermore, we integrated an extensive collection of biological databases allowing to choose appropriate prior knowledge for a research task. Owing to today&apos;s capabilities and ubiquity of high-throughput measurement techniques, we implemented support for the analysis of multi-omics datasets. Moreover, the modular structure of GeneTrail2 ensures that new algorithms, databases, organisms and identifiers can easily be added. This allows to track the current state-of-the-art and continuously improve GeneTrail2. We demonstrated GeneTrail2&apos;s capabilities by applying it to a Wilms tumor mRNA/miRNA expression dataset. Here, the major goal was to determine key molecular features that result in lower susceptibility to preoperative chemotherapy of blastemal subtype tumors. We were able to identify a substantial amount of highly significant, cancer-associated categories that were deregulated in this subtype. The unusual expression profiles of the let-7 miRNA family lead to LIN28B, which is well studied in the context of WTs, and in turn to its upstream regulator TRIM71. We discussed the role of TRIM71 and in particular its function as a stem cell regulator and we observed that its expression is consistent with the expression of the CM stem cell markers EYA1, SIX2 and CITED1 (Fig. 5). These first results indicated that stem cell regulators play a central role in blastemal tumors. This is in agreement with the assumption that the ability of WT cells to maintain stem cell character is a main determinant for tumor malignancy. Furthermore, our results revealed an upregulation of the canonical WNT pathway. Searching for a link between WNT signaling and the regulatory circuitry of stem cells, we arrived at the TF TCF3. To examine possible effects of a TCF3 deregulation, we searched for factors influenced by TCF3. We found a large number of genes, including well-known oncogenes, with TCF3 binding sites in their promoters and exceptionally high correlations with TCF3 expression. Interestingly, IGF2 belongs to this group of genes suggesting that TCF3 regulates IGF2. Loss of imprinting at the H19/IGF2 locus is with an extreme rate of occurrence of 80% the most abundant epigenetic lesion in WTs and leads to an IGF2 overexpression that can activate the canonical WNT pathway and, hence, trigger the epithelial to mesenchymal transition (EMT). Our findings indicate that the resulting TCF3 activation closes a self-sustaining feedback loop further boosting IGF2 production. This offers a potential explanation on how malignant tumor cells maintain their stem cell character. The genes discussed above clearly separate WTs according to tumor malignancy and may hence be promising candidates for prognostic biomarkers that may also be valuable for therapy stratification. The presented use case shows that GeneTrail2 is able to uncover biologically informative signals in-omics data making it an important tool for the elucidation of pathogenic processes. The ability to The GeneTrail2 web service</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general modular framework for gene set enrichment analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ackermann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Strimmer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">47</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved scoring of functional groups from gene expression data by decorrelating go graph structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Alexa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1600" to="1607" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic screen for micro-RNAs regulating the canonical WNT pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Anton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">26257</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeneTrail—advanced gene set enrichment analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Backes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="192" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NCBI GEO: archive for functional genomics data setsupdate</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Barrett</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="991" to="995" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Benjamini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Hochberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B (Methodological)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trim71 cooperates with microRNAs to repress CDKN1a expression and promote embryonic stem cell proliferation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Chang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">923</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tcf3 is an integral component of the core regulatory circuitry of embryonic stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Cole</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="746" to="755" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global functional profiling of gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Draˇghicidraˇdraˇghici</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="98" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On testing the significance of sets of genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Efron</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Tibshirani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Appl. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Canonical WNT signalling determines lineage specificity in Wilms tumour</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Fukuzawa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncogene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1063" to="1075" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From sets to graphs: towards a realistic enrichment analysis of transcriptomic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Geistlinger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="366" to="373" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BiNA: a visual analytics tool for biological network data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Gerasch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">87397</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EnrichNet: network-based gene set enrichment analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Glaab</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="451" to="457" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Galaxy: a comprehensive approach for supporting accessible, reproducible, and transparent computational research in the life sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Goecks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">86</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Omictools: an informative directory for multi-omic data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Henry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Database</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">69</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GSEA-SNP: applying gene set enrichment analysis to SNP data from genome-wide association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Holden</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2784" to="2785" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bioinformatics enrichment tools: paths toward the comprehensive functional analysis of large gene lists</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene set enrichment analysis: performance evaluation and usage guidelines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Hung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ten years of pathway analysis: current approaches and outstanding challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Khatri</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002375</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PAGE: parametric analysis of gene set enrichment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Volsky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">144</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2012) miRTrail—a comprehensive webserver for analyzing gene and miRNA patterns to enhance the understanding of regulatory mechanisms in diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Laczny</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">36</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ubiquitin ligase human Trim71 regulates let-7 microRNA biogenesis via modulation of Lin28b protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">BBA) Gene Regulatory Mechanisms</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1839" to="374" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tackling the widespread and critical impact of batch effects in high-throughput data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Leek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="733" to="739" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Love</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">550</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Connecting microRNA genes to the core transcriptional regulatory circuitry of embryonic stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Marson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="533" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mir-17/92 cluster: a comprehensive update on its genomics, genetics, functions and increasingly important and numerous roles in health and disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Mogilyansky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Rigoutsos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Death Differ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1603" to="1614" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Igf-ii induces rapid beta-catenin relocation to the nucleus during epithelium to mesenchyme transition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Morali</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncogene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4942" to="4950" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rigorous assessment of gene set enrichment tests</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Naeem</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1480" to="1486" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Random-set methods identify distinct aspects of the enrichment signal in gene-set analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Newton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Appl. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="106" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate ranking of differentially expressed genes by a distribution-free shrinkage approach Lin28b and Lin28b inhibit let-7 microrna biogenesis by distinct mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Opgen-Rhein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Strimmer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Appl. Genet. Mol. Biol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1066" to="1079" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wnt signaling in cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Polakis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cold Spring Harb. Perspect. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8052</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Normalization of rna-seq data using factor analysis of control genes or samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Risso</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="896" to="902" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">edger: a bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ramona: a web application for gene set analysis on multilevel omics data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Sass</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subsets of very low risk Wilms tumor show distinctive gene expression, histologic, and clinical features</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Sredni</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6800" to="6809" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NetworkTrail—a web service for identifying and visualizing deregulated subnetworks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Stö Ckel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1702" to="1703" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledgebased approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Subramanian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15545" to="15550" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovering statistically significant pathways in expression profiling studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Tian</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13544" to="13549" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lin28 sustains early renal progenitors and induces Wilms tumor</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Urbach</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="971" to="982" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutations in the six1/2 pathway and the drosha/dgcr8 miRNA microprocessor complex underlie high-risk blastemal type Wilms tumors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Wegert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="298" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The taverna workflow suite: designing and executing workflows of web services on the desktop, web or in the cloud</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Wolstencroft</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="557" to="561" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genevar: a database and java application for the analysis and visualization of snp-gene associations in eqtl studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2474" to="2476" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GO-bayes: gene ontology-based overrepresentation analysis using a Bayesian approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="905" to="911" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>