
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:55+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining ncIDP-assign: a SPARKY extension for the effective NMR assignment of intrinsically disordered proteins</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kamil</forename>
								<surname>Tamiola</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biophysical Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Groningen Biomolecular Sciences and Biotechnology Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Groningen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Nijenborgh 7</addrLine>
									<postCode>9747AG</postCode>
									<settlement>Groningen</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Frans</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A A</forename>
								<surname>Mulder</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biophysical Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Groningen Biomolecular Sciences and Biotechnology Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Groningen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Nijenborgh 7</addrLine>
									<postCode>9747AG</postCode>
									<settlement>Groningen</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining ncIDP-assign: a SPARKY extension for the effective NMR assignment of intrinsically disordered proteins</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1039" to="1040"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr054</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received and revised on January 3, 2011; accepted on January 27, 2011</note>
					<note>[13:16 17/3/2011 Bioinformatics-btr054.tex] Page: 1039 1039–1040 Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Contact: ktamiola@rugnl</term>
					<term>faamulder@rugnl</term>
					<term>support@proteinnmrorg</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We describe here the ncIDP-assign extension for the popular NMR assignment program SPARKY, which aids in the sequence-specific resonance assignment of intrinsically disordered proteins (IDPs). The assignment plugin greatly facilitates the effective matching of a set of connected resonances to the correct position in the sequence by making use of IDP random coil chemical shifts. Availability: The ncIDP-assign extension is available at http://www.protein-nmr.org/.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The structural characterization of intrinsically disordered proteins (IDPs) is a rapidly growing field in structural molecular biology. Over the past decade NMR spectroscopy has proven to be singular in its capacity to provide detailed structural characterization of these dynamic entities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Eliezer, 2009</ref>). Although diverse experimental approaches have been developed (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bermel et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Mäntylahti et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">O'Hare et al., 2009</ref>), the sequential resonance assignment of &gt;10 kDa natively unfolded polypeptides is still not a trivial task. Here, we describe an enhanced version of the SPARKY (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Goddard and Kneller, 2006</ref>) sequence repositioning extension, which assist in matching, connecting and assigning consecutive residues, and is specifically designed for intrinsically disordered proteins: ncIDPassign (neighbor-corrected IDP chemical shift assignment). This tool makes use of a novel random-coil chemical shift library, enabling the accurate prediction of the chemical shifts of a queried protein on a basis of tripeptides (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Tamiola et al., 2010</ref>). Predicted sequence-specific chemical shifts are used as a template for reassignment and validation of existing resonance assignments. The newly designed ncIDP-assign greatly accelerates the process of sequential resonance assignment of large intrinsically disordered proteins by drastically reducing the level of assignment ambiguities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>The process of assignment validation and repositioning begins with the computation of the sequence-specific random-coil chemical * To whom correspondence should be addressed. shifts for the intrinsically disordered protein under study, based on its primary sequence.The random-coil chemical shift for a nucleus n ∈ { 1 H α , 1 H N , 13 C α , 13 C β , 13 C O , 15 N} of amino acid residue a, within a tripeptide x −a−y, can be expressed as,</p><formula>δ n pred (x,a,y) = n −1 (x)+δ n rc (a)+ n +1 (y) (1)</formula><p>where δ n rc (a) is the 'random-coil' chemical shift in the reference peptide Gly−a−Gly , n −1 (x) and n +1 (y), are the neighbor corrections due to the preceding and the sequential residue, respectively. Subsequently, a collection of experimentally assigned resonances in a range k ... k +l specified by the user is retrieved and compared against the predicted chemical shifts from Equation (1). All plausible locations for the fragment along the sequence of a protein are considered. Each investigated position is characterized with a chemical shift deviation score S,</p><formula>S(k,l) = k+l i=k n Z n (i) (2) where Z n (i) = δ n exp (i)−δ n pred (i) σ n pred (i)</formula><p>, δ n exp and σ n pred are experimental chemical shifts and the standard deviations of expected chemical shieldings for k ... k +l sequence combination, respectively. A score of 1.0 implies that at the queried sequence position, the experimental shifts are one standard deviation from the computed values, on average. Hence, the 'best-fit' solutions are characterized by the lowest S values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS AND CONCLUSION</head><p>To assess the performance of ncIDP-assign we used the NMR chemical shift assignments for the 140-residue intrinsically disordered, cytoplasmic domain of human neuroligin-3 (hNLG3cyt) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Paz et al., 2008</ref>). The robustness of the assignment procedure was established using the data obtained in 1 H-15 N HSQC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bodenhausen and Ruben, 1980</ref>), COCAHA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Dijkstra et al., 1994</ref>) and HNCACB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Wittekind and Mueller, 1993</ref>) experiments, providing access to backbone and 13 C β chemical shifts.<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>displays the level of completeness of the resonance assignment for hNLG3cyt, and the accuracy of the chemical shift back computation modules in the standard and ncIDP versions of the SPARKY sequence repositioning plugins. As borne out by<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>This point is demonstrated by<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>where the repositioning performance of the two methods is compared against known resonance assignments for hNLG3cyt. ncIDP-assign identifies correct solutions much more readily, and already at the level of dipeptides for the considered experiments (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1A</ref>). Further expansion of the length of a query fragment to tripeptide rapidly shifts the probability of assigning the correct solution. Consequently, the information content contained within a combination of resonance frequencies in short peptides (length ≥ 2) is unique enough to make the correct position guess in most cases.</p><p>Another critical parameter in the assignment process is the relative separation of the 'best-fit' score S best with respect to the second-best scoring suggestion S second-best , expressed here as the sensitivity S second-best /S best (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1B</ref>). Values for the sensitivity close to 1.0 indicate ambiguity. Given a sequentially assigned dipeptide, ncIDP-assign generates a list of solutions in which the 'best-fit' scenario scores appreciably better than the next considered option. Already significant improvements are observed in the analysis of 1 H15 N HSQC resonance lists, clearly demonstrating that information content of 1 H-15 N resonance pairs in sequentially connected dipeptides can be effectively used in the assignment process of an intrinsically disordered protein. In conclusion, we have shown here that ncIDP-assign is an effective tool to aid the sequential NMR resonance assignment of (intrinsically) disordered proteins.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>, ncIDP-assign offers an almost twofold improvement in the estimation of chemical shifts for hNLG3cyt. The superior predictive power of ncIDP-assign translates into detection sensitivity of chemical shift deviations from the sequencespecific 'random-coil' values due to resonance misassignment.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Comparative analysis of chemical shift back-computation for hNLG3cyt using standard chemical shift computation module available in SPARKY, and ncIDP-assign Nucleus (n) Standard a ncIDP a Assignments</figDesc><table>1 H α 
0.122 
0.044 
120 
1 H N 
0.148 
0.111 
128 
13 C α 
0.810 
0.324 
128 
13 C β 
0.410 
0.212 
120 
13 C O 
0.717 
0.393 
131 
15 N 
1.314 
0.664 
129 

a Chemical shift RMSD computed after removal of mean systematic offsets between the 

computed and experimental resonance assignments for hNLG3cyt in order to minimize 
chemical shift referencing errors. Root mean square difference (RMSD) values are 
given in ppm. 

A 

B 

Fig. 1. Comparative analysis of accuracy of standard and ncIDP SPARKY 
sequence repositioning extensions, using resonance assignments in: 1 H-15 N 
HSQC, COCAHA and HNCACB experiments, for the intrinsically 
disordered protein hNLG3cyt. (A) Normalized frequency of correct 
repositioning solutions as a function of fragment length in: standard (blue) 
and ncIDP-enhanced (green) repositioning, respectively. (B) Sensitivity 
as a function of sequence length for: standard (blue) and ncIDP (green) 
repositioning extensions. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protonless NMR experiments for sequence-specific assignment of backbone nuclei in unfolded proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Bermel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3918" to="3919" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Natural abundance nitrogen-15 NMR by enhanced heteronuclear spectroscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Bodenhausen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Ruben</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="189" />
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The COCAH experiment to correlate intraresidue carbonyl, c[alpha], and h[alpha] resonances in proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Dijkstra</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Magn. Reson. Ser. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biophysical characterization of intrinsically disordered proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Eliezer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Goddard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Kneller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HA-detected experiments for the backbone assignment of intrinsically disordered proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Mäntylahti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biomol. NMR</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="181" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incorporating 1H chemical shift determination into 13C-direct detected spectroscopy of intrinsically disordered proteins in solution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>&apos;hare</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Magn. Reson</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">200</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="354" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biophysical characterization of the unstructured cytoplasmic domain of the human neuronal adhesion protein neuroligin 3</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Paz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1928" to="1944" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequence-specific random coil chemical shifts of intrinsically disordered proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Tamiola</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18000" to="18003" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HNCACB, a High-Sensitivity 3D NMR experiment to correlate Amide-Proton and nitrogen resonances with the alpha-and Beta-Carbon resonances in proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Wittekind</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Mueller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Magn. Reson. Ser. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>