
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">nextflu: real-time tracking of seasonal influenza virus evolution in humans</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Richard</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Neher</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Developmental Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>72076 Tü bingen</addrLine>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Trevor</forename>
								<surname>Bedford</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Vaccine and Infectious Disease Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>98109</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>WA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">nextflu: real-time tracking of seasonal influenza virus evolution in humans</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv381</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 8, 2015; revised on June 15, 2015; accepted on June 16, 2015</note>
					<note>Phylogenetics *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: David Posada</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Contact: tbedford@fredhutchorg</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Seasonal influenza viruses evolve rapidly, allowing them to evade immunity in their human hosts and reinfect previously infected individuals. Similarly, vaccines against seasonal influenza need to be updated frequently to protect against an evolving virus population. We have thus developed a processing pipeline and browser-based visualization that allows convenient exploration and analysis of the most recent influenza virus sequence data. This web-application displays a phylogenetic tree that can be decorated with additional information such as the viral genotype at specific sites, sampling location and derived statistics that have been shown to be predictive of future virus dynamics. In addition, mutation, genotype and clade frequency trajectories are calculated and displayed. Availability and implementation: Python and Javascript source code is freely available from https://github.com/blab/nextflu, while the web-application is live at http://nextflu.org.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Every year, seasonal influenza infects between 10 and 20% of the global population, resulting in substantial human morbidity and mortality (<ref type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2009</ref>). Vaccination remains the most effective public health measure to combat seasonal epidemics. However, influenza viruses constantly evolve and thereby undergo antigenic drift, allowing drifted viruses to reinfect individuals with acquired immunity to previously circulating strains. Owing to antigenic drift, the seasonal influenza vaccine needs frequent updating to remain effective. In any given year, the particular choice of vaccine strain plays a major role in determining vaccine efficacy and so it is of critical importance to develop tools to analyze the ongoing evolution of the influenza virus population in order to aid vaccine strain selection. The program nextflu presents a near real-time display of genetic relationships among influenza viruses and allows investigation of currently available sequence data. By visualizing many different genetic and epidemiological features, we hope that nextflu will help vaccine strain selection. Currently, nextflu tracks all four circulating lineages of seasonal influenza: A/H3N2, A/H1N1pdm, B/Victoria and B/ Yamagata.</p><p>In implementation, nextflu consists of a processing pipeline written in Python called augur that analyzes virus sequence data and a JavaScript-based browser visualization called auspice that displays this processed information. As input, augur requires a FASTA file of sequences with header labels containing relevant information such as strain name, sampling date and passage history. For this purpose, influenza sequence data for the hemagglutinin (HA) gene is downloaded from the GISAID EpiFlu database (<ref type="bibr">Bogner et al., 2006</ref>), which contains the most up-to-date collection of seasonal influenza viruses. The first step in the processing pipeline is to automatically select a subset of representative viruses. Here, viruses without complete date or geographic information, viruses passaged in eggs and sequences &lt;987 bases are removed. In addition, local outbreaks are filtered by keeping only one instance of identical sequences sampled at the same location on the same day. Following filtering, viruses are subsampled to achieve a more equitable temporal and geographic distribution. For our standard display period of 3 years and 32 viruses per month, this typically results in 1200 viruses, for which we align full-length HA sequences where available and partial sequences otherwise, using MAFFT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Katoh and Standley, 2013</ref>). Once aligned, the set of virus sequences is further cleaned by removing V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3546</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.insertions relative to the outgroup to enforce canonical HA site numbering, by removing sequences that show either too much or too little divergence relative to the expectation given sampling date, and by removing known reassortant clusters, such as the triple-reassortant swine influenza viruses that have sporadically circulating since 2009 (<ref type="bibr">Bastien et al., 2010</ref>). As outgroup for each viral lineage, we chose a well characterized virus without insertions relative to the canonical amino-acid numbering and a sampling date a few years before the time interval of interest. From the filtered and cleaned alignment, augur builds a phylogenetic tree using FastTree (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Price et al., 2009</ref>), which is then further refined using RAxML (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Stamatakis, 2014</ref>). Next, the state of every internal node of the tree is inferred using a marginal maximum likelihood method and missing sequence data at phylogeny tips is filled with the nearest ancestral sequence at these sites. Internal branches without mutations are collapsed into polytomies. The final tree is decorated with the attributes to be displayed in the browser. In addition to the phylogenetic tree, augur estimates the frequency trajectories of mutations, genotypes and clades in the tree. Frequencies are determined by maximizing the likelihood of sampling the observed set of virus sequences. In addition, we impose a smoothing that penalized rapid changes in frequency of the frequency derivative. augur estimates frequency with up to 1-month resolution. The result is similar to 'allele dynamics' plots in Steinbrü ck and McHardy (2011), but provides frequencies of clades in the tree in addition to point mutations. The augur pipeline is run every 3–7 days in response to sequence updates in the GISAID database. At the end of the augur pipeline, JSON files are exported containing the annotated phylogenetic tree, sequence data and frequency trajectories. These JSON files are then visualized by auspice using D 3 (<ref type="bibr">Bostock et al., 2011</ref>) and a phylogenetic tree is displayed with branches scaled according to evolutionary distance across all sites (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). The user can explore the data interactively by selecting viruses from different dates or by coloring the tree by attributes such as: @BULLET epitope mutations at sites generally associated with antibody binding that have been suggested to be predictive of future clade success (Łuksza and Lä ssig, 2014), @BULLET receptor binding mutations at seven positions close to the receptor binding site that have been shown to be responsible for major antigenic transitions in the past decades (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Koel et al., 2013</ref>), @BULLET local branching index indicating the exponentially weighted tree length surrounding a node, which is associated with rapid branching and expansion of clades (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Neher et al., 2014</ref>), @BULLET HA genotype, which directly colors the tree by genotype at specific amino acid positions.</p><p>The display can also be restricted to different geographic regions. The frequency plot below the tree (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2</ref>) displays the frequency trajectory of clades in the tree whenever the mouse hovers above the branch defining the clade. Furthermore, trajectories of individual mutations, combinations of two mutations and predefined clades such as 3c3.a can be plotted. A second plot shows the variability of the alignment. On mouse-click on a variable position in this plot, auspice will color the tree by amino-acid at this position and plot its mutation frequencies. We built nextflu to facilitate the analysis and exploration of seasonal influenza sequence data collected by laboratories around the world. By using the most recent data and integrating phylogenies with frequency trajectories and predictors of successful clades, we hope that nextflu can inform the choice of strains used in seasonal influenza vaccines. nextflu was designed to be readily adapted to other rapidly evolving viruses and we see significant room for future developments in this area.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by the ERC though Stg-260686 and by the NIH through U54 GM111274.<ref type="figure">1</ref>. The nextflu website with the user interface on the left and the phylogenetic tree on the right</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Bioinformatics, 31(21), 2015, 3546–3548doi:10.</head><figDesc>1093/bioinformatics/btv381 Advance Access Publication Date: 26 June 2015 Applications Note</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Conflict of Interest: none declared. References Bastien,N. et al. (2010). Human infection with a triple-reassortant swine influenza A (H1N1) virus containing the hemagglutinin and neuraminidase genes of seasonal influenza virus. J. Infect. Dis., 201, 1178–1182. Bogner,P. et al. (2006). A global initiative on sharing avian flu data. Nature, 442, 981–981. Bostock,M. et al. (2011). D 3 : data-driven documents. IEEE Trans. Vis. Comput. Graph., 17, 2301–2309.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. The nextflu website with the user interface on the left and the phylogenetic tree on the right</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. The frequency diagram allows geography-specific plotting of frequencies of individual mutations, pairs of mutations and clades in the tree</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">R.A.Neher and T.Bedford at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: improvements in performance and usability</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Katoh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Standley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="772" to="780" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Substitutions near the receptor binding site determine major antigenic change during influenza virus evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Koel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">342</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="976" to="979" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A predictive fitness model for influenza</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Łuksza</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Lässig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">507</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting evolution from the shape of genealogical trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Neher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">eLife Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3568</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FastTree: computing large minimum evolution trees with profiles instead of a distance matrix</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Price</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1641" to="1650" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and post-analysis of large phylogenies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Stamatakis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1312" to="1313" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Allele dynamics plots for the study of evolutionary dynamics in viral populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Steinbrü Ck</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Mchardy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influenza Fact Sheet Accessed at http:// www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Health Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">fs211</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009-06-23" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>