
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:34+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis NGSþþ: a library for rapid prototyping of epigenomics software tools</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alexei</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Nordell</forename>
								<surname>Markovits</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Sherbrooke</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>J1K 2R1</postCode>
									<settlement>Sherbrooke</settlement>
									<region>Quebec</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Charles</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Joly</forename>
								<surname>Beauparlant</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Centre de Recherche du CHU de Quebec</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Laval</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>G1V 4G2</postCode>
									<settlement>Quebec</settlement>
									<region>Quebec</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dominique</forename>
								<surname>Toupin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Sherbrooke</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>J1K 2R1</postCode>
									<settlement>Quebec</settlement>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Shengrui</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Sherbrooke</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>J1K 2R1</postCode>
									<settlement>Quebec</settlement>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Arnaud</forename>
								<surname>Droit</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Centre de Recherche du CHU de Quebec</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Laval</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>G1V 4G2</postCode>
									<settlement>Quebec</settlement>
									<region>Quebec</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nicolas</forename>
								<surname>Gevry</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>Contact: nicolas.gevry@usherbrooke.ca or arnaud.droit@crchuq. ulaval.ca</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Sherbrooke</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>J1K 2R1</postCode>
									<settlement>Sherbrooke</settlement>
									<region>Quebec</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis NGSþþ: a library for rapid prototyping of epigenomics software tools</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1893" to="1894"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt312</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on November 12, 2012; revised on May 23, 2013; accepted on May 27, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Michael Brudno</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The development of computational tools to enable testing and analysis of high-throughput–sequencing data is essential to modern genomics research. However, although multiple frameworks have been developed to facilitate access to these tools, comparatively little effort has been made at implementing low-level programming libraries to increase the speed and ease of their development. Results: We propose NGSþþ, a programming library in Cþþ11 specialized in manipulating both next-generation sequencing (NGS) data-sets and genomic information files. This library allows easy integration of new formats and rapid prototyping of new functionalities with a focus on the analysis of genomic regions and features. It offers a powerful, yet versatile and easily extensible interface to read, write and manipulate multiple genomic file formats. By standardizing the internal data structures and presenting a common interface to the data parser, NGSþþ offers an effective framework for epigenomics tool development. Availability: NGSþþ was written in Cþþ using the Cþþ11 standard. It requires minimal efforts to build and is well-documented via a complete docXygen guide, online documentation and tutorials. Source code, tests, code examples and documentation are available via the website at http://www.ngsplusplus.ca and the github repository at https://github.com/NGS-lib/NGSplusplus.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Previous years have witnessed an explosion in the amount of data produced using next-generation sequencing (NGS) technologies, as exemplified by the ENCODE project (ENCODE Project<ref type="bibr">Consortium et al., 2012</ref>). However, analysis of these enormous datasets (easily 4100 GB) requires the use of a new generation of computational tools. As the quantity of data produced by NGS machines increases, so will the time spent on developing new tools. Although substantial efforts have been made at integrating them into user-friendly frameworks such as Galaxy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Giardine et al., 2005</ref>) or GeneSpace (Genome Space), relatively little effort has gone into providing the groundwork needed to increase the productivity of NGS developers, such as libraries and using standardized formats. Improvement in these areas would allow developers to greatly accelerate the speed at which they design and deploy new analysis software. Although certain tool suites, such as BEDtools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Quinlan and Hall, 2010</ref>) and BAMtools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Barnett et al., 2011</ref>), offer a library or API to assist developers, these are generally aimed at giving access to the existing tool functionality rather than facilitating development of new ones. As such they are highly specialized. The SeqAn library (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Do¨ringDo¨ring et al., 2008</ref>) offers functionality for the developmental of future tools, but it specializes in sequence analysis rather than genomic regions and features. Our proposed library, NGSþþ, aims to fill this gap by offering a powerful set of generic and flexible options to accelerate development and prototyping of epigenomics analysis tools.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">APPROACH</head><p>It is impossible to predict the entirety of future needs for NGS data analysis. As such, NGSþþ focuses on being a customizable and generic library that facilitates the prototyping and implementation of new functionalities via a transparent data interface. In this section, we summarize the three main components of NGSþþ: (i) file format management, (ii) data manipulation and (iii) functional operators. Dealing with the wealth of existing file formats is a time consuming task. NGSþþ offers a simple interface to parse and write in many frequently used genomics file formats (BED, GFF/ GTF, Sam, Wig, bedGraph) using a generic data structure named Tokens that contain a number of standard features of genomic data entries (eg: Start/End positions, position value and mapping quality). Additionally, the user can define 'onthe-fly' custom formats to deal with the plethora of datasets that do not respect format specifications, and BAM format is supported via integration of the BamTools API. The conversion between most supported formats is a trivial task:*To whom correspondence should be addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>y</head><p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors.</p><p>The internal structure of the library is divided into a three-tiers hierarchy separating a genomic dataset by unique scaffolds with each of them containing any number of contigs. This hierarchy is represented in (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>), and each level offers a number of functions that can be extended via inheritance for specialized data manipulation. Loading datasets is done through integration with our Parser class and allows the user to easily load data:NGSþþ offers a powerful set of generic functions to compare, sort, merge and modify the previously loaded data. These include typical operations such as overlapping, merging and comparing that allows the user to easily filter his data as needed. The following would return tags overlapping a BED file: auto fExp¼TagExp.getOverlapping(RegionExp); Additionally, the majority of these operators can be used on any given feature of the data objects, including features added by the user via inheritance. This example sorts and counts a subset based on a new object feature: RegionExp.sortSites(<ref type="bibr">[ ]</ref>(uRegion item1, uRegion item2){return item1.Score 5 item2.Score}, &amp; uRegion::getScore, &amp;uRegion::getScore) int count ¼ RegionExp.getSubsetCount(0.5,0.8);</p><p>As shown earlier in the text, this is greatly facilitated by the inclusion of anonymous lambda functions in the Cþþ11 standard. Using these flexible operators allows the experienced developer to implement powerful modifications, whereas the default genomic interval operators are easily usable by all. Finally, to accommodate specific analysis needs, NGSþþ offers an interface to run developer defined functions and transformations on the selected data. This allows the developer to concentrate on the function he wishes to implement without having to spend time on the underlying structure that will support it. Borrowing heavily from the functional programming paradigm, this allows for rapid prototyping and implementation. In the following we define and execute a function that allows us to trivially generate a histogram of contig sizes: map5int,int4 sizeOfContigs; uTagsExp.applyOnSites(<ref type="bibr">[&amp;]</ref>(uTag Elem){sizeOfContigs<ref type="bibr">[Elem.getSize()]</ref>þþ;});</p><p>Additional functional operators exist, allowing a variety of different operations on the dataset. This interface wraps many of the STL algorithms, enabling rapid parallelism via the OpenMP standard (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dagum and Menon, 1998</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>NGSþþ is written in Cþþ using the Cþþ11 standard. It offers a complete exception handling interface using the Boost exception class. A complete test suite is implemented using the Google test platform. It has been designed for a Linux environment using a Cþþ11 compatible gcc compiler. Complete user guide, tutorial and discussion are available on the web page. Source code is hosted on GitHub.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUSION</head><p>Progress in the development of advanced bioinformatics analysis tools has undoubtedly been hindered by the lack of available programming frameworks. Our library aims to assist in filling this gap for the community of Cþþ epigenomic developers by giving them access to robust building blocks, thus reducing the time spent on development significantly. Our efforts are now focused on including additional genomic formats and on increasing the breath of our tutorials. Future developments will include the integration of mid-level reusable functions, such as similarity functions and normalization methods. The website provides a list of tutorials and commented working code examples, to assist developers in getting started with the library. Finally, theParsing interface then filtered as needed. User-defined functions are executed via our operators, and the transformed data are stored via our Writer interface</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>uParser parser(''filename.sam'', ''SAM''); uWriter writer(''filename.bed'', ''BED''); while (!parser.eof()) writer.writeToken(parser.getNextEntry());</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Typical workflow of the NGSþþ library. Data are read by our Parsing interface then filtered as needed. User-defined functions are executed via our operators, and the transformed data are stored via our Writer interface</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">A.N.Markovits et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">should facilitate the integration of suggestions and feedback from the community</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Funding: Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) (to S.W.); Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR) (to N.G.);Ministè re du De´veloppementDe´veloppement E ´ conomique, Innovation et Exportation (MDEIE)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>to. A.D.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">holds a Chercheur boursier (junior 1) award from the Fond de Recherche en Sante´duSante´du Que´becQue´bec (FRSQ). A.D. holds a Re´seauRe´seau de me´decineme´decine ge´ne´tiquege´ne´ge´ne´tique appliqueé (RMGA) salary award</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Centre de Recherche en Endocrinologie et Ge´nomiqueGe´nomique Humaine (CREMOGH) award. Conflict of Interest: none declared</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BamTools: a Cþþ API and toolkit for analyzing and managing BAM files</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">References</forename>
				<surname>Barnett</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1691" to="1692" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OpenMP: an industry standard API for sharedmemory programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Dagum</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Menon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Comput. Sci. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SeqAn an efficient, generic Cþþ library for sequence analysis ENCODE Project Consortium et al. (2012) An integrated encyclopedia of DNA elements in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Do¨ringdo¨ring</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">489</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Galaxy: a platform for interactive large-scale genome analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Giardine</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1451" to="1455" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Genome</forename>
				<surname>Space</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-06-18" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>date. last accessed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Quinlan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Hall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="841" to="842" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>