
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:59+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Normalization and noise reduction for single cell RNA-seq experiments</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bo</forename>
								<surname>Ding</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lina</forename>
								<surname>Zheng</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yun</forename>
								<surname>Zhu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nan</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Haiyang</forename>
								<surname>Jia</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">College of Computer Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jilin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>130012</postCode>
									<settlement>Changchun</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rizi</forename>
								<surname>Ai</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andre</forename>
								<surname>Wildberg</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wei</forename>
								<surname>Wang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cellular and Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Normalization and noise reduction for single cell RNA-seq experiments</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv122</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on December 15, 2014; revised on February 1, 2015; accepted on February 19, 2015</note>
					<note>Gene expression *To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors Associate Editor: Ziv Bar-Joseph Availability and implementation: The software is implemented by R and the download version is available at http://wanglab.ucsd.edu/star/GRM. Contact: wei-wang@ucsd.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>A major roadblock towards accurate interpretation of single cell RNA-seq data is large technical noise resulted from small amount of input materials. The existing methods mainly aim to find differentially expressed genes rather than directly de-noise the single cell data. We present here a powerful but simple method to remove technical noise and explicitly compute the true gene expression levels based on spike-in ERCC molecules.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Single-cell RNA-seq is a promising technology with broad applications and discerning biological noise from technical noise is critical for correctly interpreting the data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Jaitin et al., 2014</ref>). Recently, statistical methods are developed to model the technical noise from spike-in ERCC molecules, whose concentrations are presumably same across the samples, and then identify differentially expressed genes, whose variations across samples are significantly larger than technical noise (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Brennecke et al., 2013</ref>). A limit for such an approach is that the true gene expression level is not explicitly calculated, which is needed for many analyses based on quantification of transcriptions. Here we propose a novel strategy to normalize and de-noise single cell RNA-seq data. This method calculates RNA concentrations from the sequencing reads, which is opposite to the other published methods that model sequencing reads from RNA concentrations; it is much simpler than the existing methods but importantly it allows to remove technical noise and explicitly compute gene expression. Specifically, we fit a gamma regression model (GRM) between the sequencing reads (RPKM, FPKM or TPM) and the concentration of spike-in ERCC molecules. The trained model is then used to estimate the de-noised molecular concentration of the genes from the reads. GRM shows great power of reducing technical noise and superior performance compared to several popular normalization methods such as FPKM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Tu et al., 2012</ref>), TMM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Robinson and Oshlack, 2010</ref>) and FQ (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bullard et al., 2010</ref>) in analyzing single cell RNA-seq data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Fit a GRM from read counts to RNA concentrations</head><p>Spike-in ERCCs can be added equally to each sample during the library preparation to calibrate measurements of single cell RNA-seq. A natural approach is to train a model to compute read counts such as FPKM from the concentrations of ERCC (FPKM ¼ function concentration ð Þ ). This model is then used to calculate the expression level or molecular concentration of each gene from its FPKM using the reversed relationship(concentration ¼ function FPKM ð Þ ). However, substantial technical noise in single cell RNA-seq makes it non-trivial to construct such a model(<ref type="bibr">Grun et al., 2014</ref>). In addition, it can be challenging to analytically or numerically solve the reverse model. We therefore propose to fit the " reverse " model directly (concentration ¼ function FPKM ð Þ ) using ERCCs. This way, gene expression levels can be directly computed from FPKM. Such a strategy is novel and much simpler than the published methods that model noise distribution without explicitly computing the de-noised gene expression levels. We choose to use gamma distribution to model the distribution of molecular concentrations because of its flexibility to fit diverse shapes. As the values of molecular concentration (10 À2 –10 4 ) and FPKM (always 0–10 4–5 ) vary in a large range, we first perform log transformation of these data, x ¼ log ðFPKMÞ (log-R) and y ¼ logðconcentration) (log-C). Instead of fitting a GRM between x and y directly, we model the non-linearity of single cell signals using a polynomial function lðxÞ ¼ X n i¼0 b i x i. The model is the following:</p><formula>y $ Gamma y; l x ð Þ; u ð Þ</formula><p>with the probability density function:</p><formula>f ðyÞ ¼ 1 yCðuÞ ð uy lðxÞ Þ u exp À uy lðxÞ</formula><p>The parameters are determined using maximum likelihood estimation. The optimal value of n is determined by an empirical search: we train multiple models with n ¼ 1 to n ¼ 4 and select n with smallest average technical noise of ERCCs. Using the regression model trained from spike-in ERCCs in one single cell sample, we compute the true expression levels of genes from their FPKMs by calculating the expectation of a given FPKM,</p><formula>^ y gene ¼ E y gene À Á ¼ ^ l x gene À Á ¼ X n i¼0</formula><p>^ b i x i gene .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Successful de-noise of single cell RNA-seq data</head><p>To demonstrate the effectiveness of our strategy, we need a dataset that has a gold standard of cataloguing single cells and such a dataset is still rare.<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Treutlein et al. (2014)</ref>performed single cell experiments at four different developmental stages (GEO GSE52583). This dataset includes 198 individual mouse lung cells derived from four different developmental stages: E14.5 (45 samples), E16.5 (27 samples), E18.5 (80 samples) and adult (46 samples). We first perform gamma regression on all the spike-in ERCCs. Our model achieves an average Pearson correlation between the predicted and true concentrations of 0.866 over all the 198 samples (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1a</ref>), significantly higher than a value of 0.119 if using a linear regression model fit between log-R and log-C. We measure the noise for the spike-in ERCCs across all the samples using CV 2 , which is defined as the variance divided by the square of mean(<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Brennecke et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>, Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>). After de-noise, on average the CV 2 value is reduced 70%, from 1.301 to 0.408, with the largest reduction of 90% (from 0.584 to 0.056). These results suggest that our strategy can drastically reduce technical noise. We next apply the model fit in each single cell to remove technical noise of the genes in the same single cell. Treutlein et al. selected 124 Sftpc-positive cells to monitor the mature process of alveolar type 2 (AT2) cells at the four developmental stages (Sftpc is the marker of AT2 cells). Four distinct groups of cells are expected to be found corresponding to the four developmental stages. Treutlein et al. selected 10 946 genes that were observed in more than two samples and had a variance of transcript level (log2(FPKM)) across all the sample larger than 0.5. If all the cells are clustered using these genes by hierarchical clustering, single cells from different stages are mixed (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>(a)). After de-noise, distinct clusters corresponding to the four developmental stages are observed (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1d</ref>). Furthermore, the dendrogram of the hierarchical clustering correctly represent the developmental distance between the single cells. Namely, the adult cells are most distant from embryonic ones of E14.5, E16.5 and E18.5. E14.5 and E16.5 are most similar to each other and form the early progenitor branch, which is connected to E18.5. This hierarchy is consistent with the development of AT2 cells (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1c</ref>). Similarly, when PCA is applied to all the data, the de-noised data clearly show significantly better separation between the single cells derived from different developmental stages (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>(a)–(e)). Taken together, the significant lower noise in ERCCs and achievement of more biologically meaningful clusters in the AT2 cell development indicate that our de-noise strategy can successfully remove technical noise in single cell RNA-seq.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Conclusion</head><p>We present here a simple but powerful method for removing technical noise of single cell RNA-seq data. This method is distinct from the existing approaches as it derives the relationship between RNA concentrations and sequencing read counts from ERCC molecules and then applies this relationship to calculate gene expression from read counts. We demonstrated the success of normalization and noise reduction of single cell RNA-seq data by showing significantly improved clustering of single cells after denoise. Furthermore, this method is general and also applicable to bulk RNA-seq data with spike-in ERCCs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This study was supported by NIH (U01 MH098977). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. (a) The correlation between the true and predicted molecular concentrations for the spike-in ERCCs in one sample. (b) Noise represented by CV 2 before and after de-noise using GRM. (c) The dendrogram of the hierarchical clustering of de-noised data correctly correspond to the four developmental stages. (d) Hierarchical clustering on 124 Sftpe þ single cells after de-noise</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 2225 Bioinformatics, 31(13), 2015, 2225–2227 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv122 Advance Access Publication Date: 24 February 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">B.Ding et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accounting for technical noise in single-cell RNA-seq experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Brennecke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1093" to="1095" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of statistical methods for normalization and differential expression in mRNA-Seq experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Bullard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">94</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Massively parallel single-cell RNA-seq for markerfree decomposition of tissues into cell types</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Jaitin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">343</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="776" to="779" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A scaling normalization method for differential expression analysis of RNA-seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Oshlack</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reconstructing lineage hierarchies of the distal lung epithelium using single-cell RNA-seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Treutlein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">509</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="371" to="375" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene structure in the sea urchin Strongylocentrotus purpuratus based on transcriptome analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Tu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2079" to="2020" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Single cell RNA-seq normalization</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>