
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:34+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Ontology for medicinal materials based on traditional Korean medicine</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">2010 . 18 2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hyunchul</forename>
								<surname>Jang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Information Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Institute of Oriental Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>483 Expo-ro, Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-811</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jinhyun</forename>
								<surname>Kim</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Information Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Institute of Oriental Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>483 Expo-ro, Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-811</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sang-Kyun</forename>
								<surname>Kim</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Information Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Institute of Oriental Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>483 Expo-ro, Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-811</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chul</forename>
								<surname>Kim</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Information Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Institute of Oriental Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>483 Expo-ro, Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-811</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Soon-Hee</forename>
								<surname>Bae</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Information Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Institute of Oriental Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>483 Expo-ro, Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-811</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anna</forename>
								<surname>Kim</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Information Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Institute of Oriental Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>483 Expo-ro, Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-811</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dong-Myung</forename>
								<surname>Eom</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Information Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Institute of Oriental Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>483 Expo-ro, Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-811</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mi-Young</forename>
								<surname>Song</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Information Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Institute of Oriental Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>483 Expo-ro, Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-811</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">College of Oriental Medicine and Research Center of Traditional Korean Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wonkwang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>344-2 Shinyong-dong</addrLine>
									<postCode>570-749</postCode>
									<settlement>Iksan</settlement>
									<region>Chonbuk</region>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Ontology for medicinal materials based on traditional Korean medicine</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Bioinformatics BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2359" to="2360"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">2010 . 18 2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq424</idno>
					<note type="submission">Databases and ontologies Advance Access publication July 20, 2010 Received on January 12, 2010; revised on June 23, 2010; accepted on July 16, 2010</note>
					<note>Page: 2359 2359–2360 (10–20 s using Internet Explorer.) Contact: smyoung@kiom.re.kr Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We are constructing an ontology for traditional Korean medicine, and we started with medicinal materials to express the relationships between patients&apos; symptoms, diseases and treatments. Biological materials and mineral resources have been used traditionally for patient treatments. The ontology includes various data related to these materials, such as their scientific names, parts of materials used, effectiveness and related oriental organ of the human body.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">MOTIVATION</head><p>Although the knowledge systems of traditional medicine and modern medical science differ, comparative studies and applied approaches are valuable. Symptoms are practically identical from a patient's point of view, apart from cultural and linguistic differences. Patients' symptoms and the prescribed treatments are important fields with which to link modern medical science to traditional medicine. For these purposes, we are constructing an ontology of traditional Korean medicine (TKM) for symptoms, diseases and treatments, and we are starting out by focusing on the knowledge of medicinal materials in traditional treatments. For traditional Chinese medicine (TCM), the following related works have been done.<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Zhou et al. (2004)</ref>stored a Unified TCM Language System (UTCMLS) in relational databases, but it is not shared on the Web. To overcome the problem of semantic heterogeneity and to encode the domain knowledge in a reusable format, an integrated approach to developing and applying the largescale domain ontology was proposed (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Chen et al., 2007 and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Mao et al., 2008</ref>); however, this ontology is not available to the public. The Chinese herbal database (www.tcmbasics.com/materiamedica .htm) is available in plain text, but only 116 herbs are currentlyincluded; the botanical names used in China are listed in this database. We included more medicinal materials in China and Korea. This resource is available to the public and viewable in the Web Ontology Language. It will be available in a public ontology repository as soon as it is ready.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>We used Protégé (protege.stanford.edu) for the design of the ontology. We then extracted individual medicines and their property values and wrote them using Jena (jena.sourceforge.net). Knowledge was acquired by domain experts without using natural language processing. More than 60 000 triples were extracted verbatim from the Korean Pharmacopoeia (Korea Food and Drug<ref type="bibr">Administration, 2008</ref>), traditional medical books and textbooks adopted by most Korean universities. Errors in the extraction and writing processes have not been measured so far.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Medicinal materials and properties</head><p>We have acquired data about traditional medicinal materials, as shown ineffectiveness; and the chief virtue of the medicinal materials are included in this ontology. Compared to the Chinese Herbal Database, the most basic property types are similar and the property values of many medicinal materials used in Korea are similar to those of the materials used in China. However, the scientific names of the original materials are quite different according to their local characteristics. To clarify the difference between Korean and Chinese medicines, the names of the original material in the languages of the two countries, including the botanical, zoological and mineralogical names, have been included. Chinese data was acquired by referring to the Chinese Pharmacopoeia (Chinese Pharmacopoeia<ref type="bibr">Commission, 2005</ref>). More than 800 materials between the two countries are included (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Indication: mapping symptoms and disease</head><p>Most medicinal treatments of TKM use a combination of a number of medicinal materials that are known as formulas. Even so, each medicinal material has information pertaining to the curing symptoms or particular conditions that indicate the advisability or necessity of a specific medical treatment or procedure. An indication of a medicinal material can be a disease, a pattern or a symptom. Essentially, a material is recorded to treat complex cases, including compound symptoms, symptoms by a certain disease or pattern, symptoms or diseases due to a certain cause and a disease that exists given in a particular condition of a patient, among others. These complex cases from materials cannot be simply mapped onto a single disease or symptom. It is necessary to understand the effect and functions of a material and the treatment method of a disease pattern (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Translation of the property values into English</head><p>The property values of individual medicines, including the names, were written in Chinese and Korean first and were then translated<ref type="bibr">, 2007</ref>). Values in Chinese or Korean that are recorded in neither the dictionary nor the standard will be translated by domain experts of traditional medicine and by medical information experts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>into English in reference to the Korean–English Dictionary of Oriental Medicine (Compilation Committee of Dictionary, 2004) and the WHO International Standard Terminologies on Traditional Medicine in the Western Pacific Region (World Health Organization</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Example of medicinal material data</figDesc><table>Items 
Examples 
Items 
Examples 

Names 
(Ma Hwang) 
Ephedrae Herba 

Reference 
(Shin Nong Bon 
Cho Kyung) (Do, 6th 
century) 
Scientific 
name 

Ephedra sinica Stapf 
Nature 
Warm 

Medicinally 
useful part 

Stalk like grass 
Flavor 
Hot and slightly bitter 

Alias 
(Yong So) 
Toxicity 
extremely, slightly, mild, etc. 
Contraindi-
cation 

Weakness or exterior 
deficiency 

Meridian 
Entry 

Lung, bladder 

Effect 
Promotes sweating to 
dissipate cold 

Major 
Indication 

Common cold by wind-cold 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1,</figDesc><table>from the literature. 
Most medicinal materials are biological materials, but by-
products of living things and mineral resources are also used. 
Chinese, Korean and Latin names; scientific names; the medicinal 
part used; family names; nature; flavor; toxicity; meridian entries; </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2. Botanical names for Acanthopanacis Cortex in the Korean and Chinese Pharmacopoeias Botanical names Pharmacopoeia Textbooks Korean Chinese A B C Acanthopanax sessiliflorum Seeman @BULLET @BULLET @BULLET @BULLET Acanthopanax gracilistylus W.W. Smith @BULLET @BULLET @BULLET Acanthopanax chiisanensis Nakai et al. @BULLET A, Herbal Medicine Study (Joint Text Compilation Committee, 2004); B, Shin's Herbal Medicine Study (Shin,G., 1988); C, Clinical Herbal Medicine Study (Shin,M., 1997).</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 3. Examples of indication</figDesc><table>Indication 
Materials 

(diarrhea) 
(protracted diarrhea or chronic diarrhea) 
et al. 
(infantile retention of 
undigested food and diarrhea) 
(diarrhea due to hypofunction of 
the spleen) 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org 2359 at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION Most terms and concepts from oriental medicine, including TKM, must be understood and mapped out carefully. Moreover, the knowledge represented in this ontology must be interpreted with an understanding of oriental medicine. Every value in it is from written records, but the representation does not include everything. The contents represented as RDF triples in this ontology are facts based on the books used, but some combined knowledge may express incorrect information. Studies of the measurement and correction of these entries are required. Plants, animals and minerals can be connected to a proper ontology, and the treatment information should be linked to the disease ontology of traditional medicine as well as to the disease ontology of modern medical science. Knowledge of medicinal treatments in traditional medicine will be useful due to their relationship to diseases, and this knowledge should be supported by analyses of the relationships between traditional diseases and modern diseases. By comparing other traditional medicines and applying clinical data, knowledge from relevant books can be assessed and a model for it can be modified practically.</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards semantic e-science for traditional Chinese medicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 3</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pharmacopoeia of the People&apos;s Republic of China. People&apos;s Medical Publishing House</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Chinese Pharmacopoeia Commission</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Beijing</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Korean-English Dictionary of Oriental Medicine</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Compilation Committee of Dictionary</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1st. edn. Jimoon-dang, Paju</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Do</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<editor>century) Shin Nong Bon Cho Kyung , Yang</editor>
		<imprint>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ancient. China</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Herbal Medicine Study</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Joint Text Compilation Committee Young Lim Sa, Seoul. Korea Food and Drug Administration</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Korea Pharmacopoeia. Shinil Books Company</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<publisher>Korea Pharmacopoeia. Shinil Books Company</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic sub-ontology evolution for traditional Chinese medicine web ontology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Mao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biomed. Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="790" to="805" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shin&apos;s Herbal Medicine Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Shin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Paju. Shin,M</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Soo Moon Publishing</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<publisher>Soo Moon Publishing</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WHO International Standard Terminologies on Traditional Medicine in the Western Pacific Region. World Health Organization Regional Office for the Western Pacific</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Health Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ontology development for unified traditional Chinese medical language system</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Zhou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Artif. Intell. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>