
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:58+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Pasha: a versatile R package for piling chromatin HTS data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Romain</forename>
								<surname>Fenouil</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>rfenouil@gmail.com or jean-christophe.andrau@igmm.cnrs.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Icahn Institute for Genomics and Multiscale Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nicolas</forename>
								<surname>Descostes</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Howard Hughes Medical Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">New York University Langone School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lionel</forename>
								<surname>Spinelli</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Centre D&apos;Immunologie De Marseille-Luminy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aix Marseille Université UM2</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>U1104</postCode>
									<settlement>Inserm</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS UMR7280</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13288</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Frederic</forename>
								<surname>Koch</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Developmental Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Muhammad</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Ahmad</forename>
								<surname>Maqbool</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Molecular Genetics of Montpellier (IGMM)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>UMR5535, 34293</postCode>
									<settlement>Montpellier</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Touati</forename>
								<surname>Benoukraf</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Cancer Science Institute of Singapore</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National University of Singapore</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Singapore, Singapore</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pierre</forename>
								<surname>Cauchy</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Cancer and Genomic Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Birmingham</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>B15 2TT</postCode>
									<settlement>Birmingham</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<surname>Charlè Ne Innocenti</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Regenerative Medicine and Biotherapy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">CHU Montpellier</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INSERM U1203</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Montpellier</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pierre</forename>
								<surname>Ferrier</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Centre D&apos;Immunologie De Marseille-Luminy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aix Marseille Université UM2</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>U1104</postCode>
									<settlement>Inserm</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS UMR7280</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13288</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jean-Christophe</forename>
								<surname>Andrau</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Molecular Genetics of Montpellier (IGMM)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>UMR5535, 34293</postCode>
									<settlement>Montpellier</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Pasha: a versatile R package for piling chromatin HTS data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw206</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on December 18, 2015; revised on April 7, 2016; accepted on April 8, 2016</note>
					<note>Sequence analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first three authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. Associate Editor: John Hancock Contacts: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We describe an R package designed for processing aligned reads from chromatin-oriented high-throughput sequencing experiments. Pasha (preprocessing of aligned sequences from HTS analyses) allows easy manipulation of aligned reads from short-read sequencing technologies (ChIP-seq, FAIRE-seq, MNase-Seq,. . .) and offers innovative approaches such as ChIP-seq reads elongation, nucleosome midpoint piling strategy for positioning analyses, or the ability to subset paired-end reads by groups of insert size that can contain biologically relevant information. Availability and implementation: Pasha is a multi-platform R package, available on CRAN repositories under GPL-3 license (https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/Pasha/).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Transcription regulation analyses benefited from the transition to High Throughput Sequencing (HTS) technology, which offers an unprecedented coverage by sequencing a large number of small sequences in parallel. However, while library preparation protocols recommend the selection of sheared DNA fragments ranging from less than 100 bp to more than 500 bp, the read size generated by the sequencing process is often shorter (25–100 bp). As a consequence, typical single-end sequencing reads will display a gap between enrichments on both strands after alignment to the reference genome. In most analyses scenarios, peak detection algorithms are making use of the lag between the strands to infer the theoretical center of enrichment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Liu, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Valouev et al., 2008</ref>). However, while the localization of binding events is a crucial step for analyzing stable binding factors in ChIP-seq experiments, an additional layer of qualitative and quantitative analyses are often required for an exhaustive description of transient or dynamic chromatin association (e.g. RNA Polymerase). To characterize such profiles, it is critical torestore the missing coverage information from read sequences in order to preserve the qualitative and quantitative aspect of the data. Here, we describe a piling tool that addresses this question by transforming aligned reads to piled enrichment scores. The modular structure of this pipeline makes it adaptable to most experimental scenarios for chromatin-oriented analyses, as well as short RNA sequencing. Pasha pipeline is for instance able to process seamlessly paired-ends or single-ends dataset by loading appropriate module, and allows the user to focus on biologically relevant parameters. Importantly, a versatile set of options decorates the core pipeline and enables innovative approaches for downstream analyses, such as an alternative midpoint piling strategy often used for nucleosome positioning analyses, or the ability to subset paired-end reads by groups of insert size for a finer analysis of fragments population. Finally, in order to maximize the compatibility with public tools and facilitate the integration to existing pipelines, a broad range of input and output file formats were implemented (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Description</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Elongating from the edges</head><p>We developed an original method to estimate the original DNA fragments size from the observed lag between both strands. Because it relies on a simple multiplicative operation on piled scores, most represented fragment sizes are given more importance during elongation estimation, which confers a significant advantage for samples displaying a vast heterogeneity in fragments size as compared to concurrent techniques often based on cross-correlation. By applying this method, and adjusting the coordinates of the region covered by reads, we were able to restore the crucial information required for an accurate representation of reads coverage (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Paired-ends and orphan reads</head><p>Alternative paired-end sequencing technique waives the requirement for elongation estimation by performing the simultaneous sequencing of both ends of each DNA fragment. Their subsequent alignment to the reference genome provides direct information about the initial fragment length. In some cases—because of insufficient sequence quality, insertions/deletions events, or repeated regions on the genome—one read from a pair fails to align to the reference genome. These broken pairs can represent a considerable amount of information that is lost when the orphan reads are discarded. In an attempt to provide a thorough handling of paired-end experiments to our pipeline, we developed additional options to rehabilitate orphan reads by elongating them to the median fragment size represented by the remainder of the sample.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Midpoint piling</head><p>A common theme in nucleosomal studies (MNase-seq) is to represent data as midpoint to emphasize positioning. Whereas densities (generated by tag elongation) will allow better characterization of nucleosome apparent depletion, midpoints will give a better view of the precise positioning of nucleosome more specifically at promoters (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Pugh, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Seila et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Weiner et al., 2010</ref>). This type of analysis reduces reads coverage to a single base footprint, centered on the theoretical region covered by the initial DNA fragment. While this compromises the quantitative and qualitative aspect of the observations, it allows a more resolutive outlook for factors with a high density of binding events, and is particularly suited for analyzing binding patterns in large scale analyses (e.g. average profiles). This method is available as an alternative piling method in our package and provides additional options (summarized in Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>) such as the possibility to highlight borders of binding events rather than their centered position, as seen in (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Schones et al., 2008</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">MultiReads</head><p>Some genomic regions (eventually large, e.g. telomeric and centromeric) are composed of repeated sequences that can interfere with the assignment of unambiguous coordinates during alignment. These reads are often discarded although they can sum a precious amount of information. Our pipeline integrates specific strategies designed to rehabilitate signal in these regions: one affects a weight divided by the number of candidate positions for each read, while the other iterative algorithm preferentially affect reads to positions showing surrounding enrichments (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Chung et al., 2011</ref>). In both cases, the complexity threshold is determined by adjusting the maximal number of candidate regions reported during the alignment step. Although their use prevents a strict quantitative comparison between genomic regions, these methods have proven to highlight some signal on relevant repeated genomic features (i.e. miRNAs, snRNAs; Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>) and centromeric and telomeric regions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Size segregation</head><p>Because chromatin fragmentation process is likely to be affected by biological factors (e.g. MNase treatment is less efficient where nucleosomes are bound to DNA), it is expected that subpopulations of reads in the fragmented population can reflect relevant biological features. This approach has been used in several studies coupled with MNase-Seq approach to probe for subnucleosomal structures linked to chromatin (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Henikoff et al., 2011</ref>). Our pipeline allows for isolation of fragments size subpopulations in paired-end samples and automatically generates reports for specified ranges, possibly revealing relevant biological information in ChIP-seq experiments (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>). Other specific protocols targeting small populations of RNAs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Core et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Fenouil et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Seila et al., 2008</ref>) can also benefit from this option as RNA populations can be are characterized by their size (ie. MicroRNAs, tRNAS).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 2528 Bioinformatics, 32(16), 2016, 2528–2530 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw206 Advance Access Publication Date: 22 April 2016 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> Conclusion The described pipeline is a versatile tool that summarizes chromatinoriented HTS data to enrichment scores using various strategies. It integrates several options allowing a seamless adaptation to various experimental setups. Additionally, the R package provides several tools for programmers that need to develop or integrate additional features.</note>

			<note place="foot">R.Fenouil et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovering transcription factor binding sites in highly repetitive regions of genomes with multi-read analysis of ChIP-Seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Chung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002111</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nascent RNA sequencing reveals widespread pausing and divergent initiation at human promoters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Core</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1845" to="1848" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">CpG islands and GC content dictate nucleosome depletion in a transcription-independent manner at mammalian promoters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Fenouil</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2399" to="2408" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epigenome characterization at single base-pair resolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Henikoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18318" to="18323" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use model-based Analysis of ChIP-Seq (MACS) to analyze short reads generated by sequencing protein-DNA interactions in embryonic stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1150</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A preoccupied position on nucleosomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Pugh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">923</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic regulation of nucleosome positioning in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Schones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="887" to="898" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Divergent transcription from active promoters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Seila</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1849" to="1851" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide analysis of transcription factor binding sites based on ChIP-Seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Valouev</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="829" to="834" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-resolution nucleosome mapping reveals transcription-dependent promoter packaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Weiner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="100" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>