
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:54+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression pathClass: an R-package for integration of pathway knowledge into support vector machines for biomarker discovery</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011 . 2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Marc</forename>
								<surname>Johannes</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">German Cancer Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Cancer Genome Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Im Neuenheimer Feld 460</addrLine>
									<postCode>69120</postCode>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Holger</forename>
								<surname>Fröhlich</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Bonn-Aachen International Center for IT</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Algorithmic Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Dahlmannstrasse 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>53113</postCode>
									<settlement>Bonn</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Holger</forename>
								<surname>Sültmann</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">German Cancer Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Cancer Genome Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Im Neuenheimer Feld 460</addrLine>
									<postCode>69120</postCode>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Tim</forename>
								<surname>Beißbarth</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>tim.beissbarth@ams.med.uni-goettingen.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Medical Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Göttingen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>37099</postCode>
									<settlement>Göttingen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression pathClass: an R-package for integration of pathway knowledge into support vector machines for biomarker discovery</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Bioinformatics BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">27 10</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="63"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011 . 2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr157</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received and revised on February 5, 2011; accepted on March 23, 2011</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: David Rocke</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Prognostic and diagnostic biomarker discovery is one of the key issues for a successful stratification of patients according to clinical risk factors. For this purpose, statistical classification methods, such as support vector machines (SVM), are frequently used tools. Different groups have recently shown that the usage of prior biological knowledge significantly improves the classification results in terms of accuracy as well as reproducibility and interpretability of gene lists. Here, we introduce pathClass, a collection of different SVM-based classification methods for improved gene selection and classfication performance. The methods contained in pathClass do not merely rely on gene expression data but also exploit the information that is carried in gene network data. Availability: pathClass is open source and freely available as an R-Package on the CRAN repository at http://cran.r</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Microarray studies are commonly used in clinical cancer research to investigate molecular profiles associated with tumor development and progression. Several thousand genes are measured to identify predictive or prognostic gene signatures comprising only a couple of genes. The goal is to use these gene signatures for stratification of patients according to clinical relevant endpoints. Classification algorithms are frequently used to identify gene signatures. The support vector machine (SVM,<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Boser et al. 1992</ref>) is a well-known example of such a classification algorithm. Several groups have proposed the so-called feature / gene selection methods for the SVM since the algorithm does not offer an embedded feature selection mechanism. Despite the identification of biomarkers, the aim of feature selection is to reduce the dimensionality of the feature space in order to avoid the so-called curse of dimensionalty (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bellman, 1961</ref>), that is overfitting. Overfitting occurs when the number of features (genes) is large and the amount of samples (i.e. patients) is comparatively small, which is often the case when performing microarray studies. Thus, the algorithm can easily find a hyperplane that separates the training examples. However, the</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">PACKAGE FEATURES</head><p>To this end, the prior knowledge used by the algorithms implemented in pathClass is represented as a network structure or graph, i.e. it carries information on the connectivity of features. In the following sections, the different algorithms and the way they use the network data are briefly explained. For illustration purposes, we show a benchmark of all three algorithms in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. However, it is important to note, that these results are specific for this particular dataset. All steps needed to reproduce the result of<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>are given in the package vignette.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Reweighted Recursive Feature Elimination</head><p>We recently proposed an extension of SVM-RFE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Guyon et al., 2002</ref>), called Reweighted Recursive Feature Elimination (RRFE), which exploits both gene expression data as well as pathway knowledge (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Johannes et al., 2010</ref>). The assumption of RRFE is that a gene which is not differentially expressed but connected to other genes that show a differential expression should have a higherimpact on the classifier compared to those genes that do not have any connections to other deregulated genes. We used a modified version of Google's PageRank algorithm, called GeneRank (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Morrison et al., 2005</ref>), to calculate a ranking of the features based on fold change and network centrality. In a next step, this ranking is combined with the RFE ranking criterion. Based on this combination, features are ordered and 90% of the most important genes are kept for the next iteration. This procedure is then repeated until only one feature is left. Afterwards, the model with the best performance is chosen.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>pathClass: an R-package for integration of pathway knowledge into SVMs</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Network-based SVM</head><p>The approach introduced by<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Zhu et al. (2009)</ref>treat neighboring genes is called network-based SVM and uses a network-based penalty which leads to a grouped variable selection. This variable selection is archieved by penalizing the SVM objective function with an F ∞-norm, instead of the commonly used L 1 or L 2 penalization. This norm forces the simultaneous selection or elimination of a group of features from the same pathway.<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Zhu et al. (2009)</ref>treat neighboring genes in a graph as a group and construct their networkbased penalty as the sum of F ∞-norms of groups of neighboring genes pairs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Incorporating network knowledge by spectral decomposition</head><p>The method by<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Rapaport et al. (2007)</ref>defines a new metric for gene expression measurements by using diffusion kernel maps. Their assumption is that most biologically relevant information is captured in the low-frequency component of expression profiles. Hence, the projection of the low-frequency component of an expression vector on the gene metabolic network should reveal areas of positive and negative expression on the graph that are likely to correspond to the activation or inhibition of specific branches of the graph.</p><p>In pathClass, we combined this method with a recursive feature elimination, hence we allow to perform a feature selection when using this algorithm. However, the user also has the possibility to use the original version.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">SUMMARY</head><p>We introduced pathClass a comprehensive package for classification with prior knowledge of feature connectivity. Up to now, it contains three SVM-based classification methods capable of using prior knowledge in the form of network data represented as a graph. The methods can be used directly or in a repeated crossvalidation setting, which helps to estimate the average classification accuracy. The package is able to run the cross-validation in parallel and thus exploit the architecture of modern multicore computers or computing clusters. A detailed step-by-step tutorial as well as a comparison of the different methods on a cancer dataset is given in the package vignette, which is also available on CRAN.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Benchmarking of the implemented algorithms. The results were obtained by a five-times repeated 10-fold cross-validation on the dataset from Golub et al. (1999).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: This project was supported by the German Federal Ministry of Education and Science in the framework for medical genome research (NGFN, IG-Prostate Cancer, 01GS0890), further by the Clinical Research Group 179 through the DFG. The authors are responsible for the contents of this publication. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. generalization performance of such a classifier will be poor and the stability of identified gene signatures will be low (Ein-Dor et al., 2005). In order to overcome these problems, several groups have recently proposed to adapt classification methods in such a way that the algorithms can benefit from using prior biological knowledge (Chuang et al., 2007; Johannes et al., 2010; Rapaport et al., 2007). Common sources of such knowledge are databases that contain pathway information or protein–protein interactions for a review see Porzelius et al. (2011). pathClass aims at providing the user with comprehensive implementations of these methods in a unified framework in order to allow easy and transparent benchmarking. To our knowledge, it is the first package implementing several SVM-based algorithms that are capable of incorporating network knowledge into the classification process. It is, however, worth mentioning that all methods available in pathClass have previously been published and shown their predominance over standard algorithms. For benchmarking of the more &apos;classical&apos; methods not using prior knowledge, the user is referred to the packages CMA (Slawski et al., 2008) and MCRestimate (Ruschhaupt et al., 2004). A boosting approach that is capable of using prior knowledge (Binder and Schumacher, 2009) can be found in the package GAMBoost, which is also available on CRAN.</note>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from [17:45 18/4/2011 Bioinformatics-btr157.tex]</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Adaptive Control Processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Bellman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1961" />
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Princeton, New Jersey</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incorporating pathway information into boosting estimation of high-dimensional risk prediction models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Binder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Schumacher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A training algorithm for optimal margin classifiers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Boser</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">COLT &apos;92: Proceedings of the fifth annual workshop on Computational learning theory</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="144" to="152" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network-based classification of breast cancer metastasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H.-Y</forename>
				<surname>Chuang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Outcome signature genes in breast cancer: is there a unique set?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Ein-Dor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular classification of cancer: class discovery and class prediction by gene expression monitoring</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Golub</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">286</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="531" to="537" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene selection for cancer classification using support vector machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Guyon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mach. Learn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="422" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integration of pathway knowledge into a reweighted recursive feature elimination approach for risk stratification of cancer patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Johannes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2136" to="2144" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generank: using search engine technology for the analysis of microarray experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Morrison</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">233</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leveraging external knowledge on molecular interactions in classification methods for risk prediction of patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Porzelius</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biomet. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="201" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classification of microarray data using gene networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Rapaport</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A compendium to ensure computational reproducibility in high-dimensional classification tasks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ruschhaupt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Appl. Genet. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Article. 37</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cma-a comprehensive bioconductor package for supervised classification with high dimensional data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Slawski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">439</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network-based support vector machine for classification of microarray samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Zhu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. . 1</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>