
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:50+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Pinstripe: a suite of programs for integrating transcriptomic and proteomic datasets identifies novel proteins and improves differentiation of protein-coding and non-coding genes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dennis</forename>
								<forename type="middle">K</forename>
								<surname>Gascoigne</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Seth</forename>
								<forename type="middle">W</forename>
								<surname>Cheetham</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">The University of Queensland Diamantina Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Princess Alexandra Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4102</postCode>
									<settlement>Woolloongabba, Brisbane</settlement>
									<region>Queensland</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pierre</forename>
								<forename type="middle">B</forename>
								<surname>Cattenoz</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">B</forename>
								<surname>Clark</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Paulo</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Amaral</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ryan</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Taft</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dagmar</forename>
								<surname>Wilhelm</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Marcel</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Dinger</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>: m.dinger@garvan.org.au or j.mattick@garvan.org.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">The University of Queensland Diamantina Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Princess Alexandra Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4102</postCode>
									<settlement>Woolloongabba, Brisbane</settlement>
									<region>Queensland</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Garvan Institute for Medical Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>384 Victoria Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>2010</postCode>
									<settlement>Darlinghurst</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Mattick</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Molecular Bioscience</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Queensland</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4072</postCode>
									<settlement>St Lucia, Brisbane</settlement>
									<region>Queensland</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis Pinstripe: a suite of programs for integrating transcriptomic and proteomic datasets identifies novel proteins and improves differentiation of protein-coding and non-coding genes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="3042" to="3050"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts582</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 13, 2012; revised on August 30, 2012; accepted on September 21, 2012</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Comparing transcriptomic data with proteomic data to identify protein-coding sequences is a long-standing challenge in molecular biology, one that is exacerbated by the increasing size of high-throughput datasets. To address this challenge, and thereby to improve the quality of genome annotation and understanding of genome biology, we have developed an integrated suite of programs, called Pinstripe. We demonstrate its application, utility and discovery power using transcriptomic and proteomic data from publicly available datasets. Results: To demonstrate the efficacy of Pinstripe for large-scale analysis , we applied Pinstripe&apos;s reverse peptide mapping pipeline to a transcript library including de novo assembled transcriptomes from the human Illumina Body Atlas (IBA2) and GENCODE v10 gene annotations , and the EBI Proteomics Identifications Database (PRIDE) pep-tide database. This analysis identified 736 canonical open reading frames (ORFs) supported by three or more PRIDE peptide fragments that are positioned outside any known coding DNA sequence (CDS). Because of the unfiltered nature of the PRIDE database and high probability of false discovery, we further refined this list using independent evidence for translation, including the presence of a Kozak sequence or functional domains, synonymous/non-synonymous substitution ratios and ORF length. Using this integrative approach, we observed evidence of translation from a previously unknown let7e primary transcript, the archetypical lncRNA H19, and a homolog of RD3. Reciprocally, by exclusion of transcripts with mapped peptides or significant ORFs (480 codon), we identify 32 187 loci with RNAs longer than 2000 nt that are unlikely to encode proteins. Availability and implementation: Pinstripe (pinstripe.matticklab.com) is freely available as source code or a Mono binary. Pinstripe is written in C# and runs under the Mono framework on Linux or Mac OS X, and both under Mono and .Net under Windows. Contact</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Although the annotation of the human genome has undergone considerable effort, with 420 000 protein-coding loci identified, the extent to which the genome is transcribed and subsequently translated remains unclear (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Clark et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Flicek et al., 2010</ref>). As well as mRNAs, long RNAs with little or no protein-coding capacity (long non-coding RNAs or lncRNAs) are abundantly expressed from the human genome with410 000 non-coding loci currently in GENCODE (the most comprehensive annotation of the human genome). Adding to the known catalog of RNAs, transcriptomic sequencing experiments are identifying thousands of new transcripts on an ongoing basis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Trapnell et al., 2010</ref>). Confidently determining which RNAs encode proteins is difficult. Traditional approaches classify the protein-coding potential of an RNA based on the presence of long canonical open reading frames (ORFs), phylogenomic evidence of codon conservation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Dinger et al., 2008</ref>) and/or recognized functional domains. The former approach is highly dependent on ORF length, with $100 codons typically used as the threshold for the identification of mRNAs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Carninci et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Imanishi et al., 2004</ref>). However, this approach results in an unknown false negative and positive rate, as shorter proteins are known to exist, and short ORFs can occur by chance (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Dinger et al., 2011</ref>). Phylogenomic comparisons also have limitations, notably their inability to detect orphan genes lacking homologs in other lineages (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Tautz and Domazet-LosˇoLosˇo, 2011</ref>), and the tendency for recently evolved genes to encode smaller proteins than older genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lipman et al., 2002</ref>). Moreover, data from which evidence of ORF and codon conservation can be determined are limited, especially at short evolutionary distances. Annotation of protein-coding genes is further confounded by factors such as RNA editing, *To whom correspondence should be addressed. y These authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the last two authors should be regarded as joint Last Authors. z Present address: Wellcome Trust/Cancer Research UK Gurdon Institute, University of Cambridge, Cambridge CB2 1QN, UK. § Present address: Garvan Institute of Medical Research, Darlinghurst, Sydney, New South Wales 2010, Australia. genotypic variation, non-canonical start codons and ribosomal frameshifting. Although many of the transcripts identified in de novo assembled transcriptomes can be annotated through comparison with known reference databases such as GENCODE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Flicek et al., 2010</ref>) or RefSeq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Pruitt et al., 2007</ref>), this approach does not provide a means for classifying novel transcripts and is entirely dependent on the accuracy of the reference database. Even determining the protein-coding capacity of novel transcript isoforms of known genes is not straightforward, as the insertion, deletion and extension of exons may disrupt the existing ORF or establish an alternative ORF. Identifying the consequences of such events to the encoded protein sequence on a genomic scale is challenging and not addressed by existing tools. Although the comparison of transcriptomic datasets to identify overlapping/non-overlapping features is facilitated by applications such as BEDTools (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Quinlan and Hall, 2010</ref>), such applications do not consider the frame of the CDS. The classification of novel transcripts with a putative ORF can be discerned with greater confidence using proteomic data. Mapping of proteomic sequences to transcriptomic data is typically performed using software such as BLAST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Altschul et al., 1990</ref>) or BLAT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kent et al., 2002</ref>). Use of these programs with high-throughput transcriptomic datasets requires considerable pre-and post-processing. Custom nucleotide sequence dictionaries must be created from spliced genomic coordinates before BLAST comparisons, and resulting matches are reported with respect to mRNA coordinates that require transformation into genomic coordinates. After mapping, each ORF then needs to be analyzed to determine the extent of supporting proteomic data. Currently, there is no software to facilitate this process, although high-throughput proteomic–genomic comparisons in Arabidopsis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Castellana et al., 2008</ref>) and proteomic–transcriptomic integration in mice (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Brosch et al., 2011</ref>) have been undertaken. Here, we present an integrated software suite, Pinstripe, which overcomes many of the difficulties in such tasks, providing programs (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>) to analyze transcriptomes, specifically enabling: (i) ORF-aware comparison with proteincoding gene annotations identifying CDSs with in-frame overlap, (ii) mapping of proteomic data to the transcriptome (leveraging BLASTP and TBLASTN) and reporting results as genomic coordinates and (iii) annotation of ORFs supported by peptides from proteomic datasets. In addition, Pinstripe features a multitude of tools for analyzing transcriptomes, including intersection by feature name, identification of best representative transcripts for loci and extraction of DNA sequence or predicted ORFs from genomic coordinates. We demonstrate the utility of Pinstripe by analyzing transcriptomes assembled de novo from high-throughput RNA sequencing of 16 human tissues and mass spectrometry from the EMBL-EBI Proteomics Identifications Database (PRIDE) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Vizcaı´noVizcaı´no et al., 2009</ref>), finding previously unidentified protein-coding regions and providing high-confidence annotations for thousands of long ncRNAs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>Pinstripe is a multiprocessor-enabled application designed for the rapid high-throughput analysis of de novo or reference-guided transcriptome assemblies generated by tools such as Tophat (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Trapnell et al., 2009</ref>) and</p><p>Cufflinks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Trapnell et al., 2010</ref>) or Trinity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Grabherr et al., 2011</ref>). In terms of performance, Pinstripe can identify ORFs, the corresponding amino acid sequence and level of support in $5 min using a single-core 2.27 GHz Intel Xeon processor for 1 million transcripts queried against 500 000 pre-mapped peptide sequences (pepFrags). Mapped pepFrag files require 580 Mb per 1 million pepFrags. The application is programed in C#, and the compiled binary runs under Mono on Linux or MacOS X, and both Mono and .NET under Windows. Here, we demonstrate its implementation using transcriptomes assembled de novo from high-throughput RNA sequencing of 16 human tissues and mass spectrometry peptide identifications from public databases. Pinstripe uses the UCSC Browser Extensible Data (BED/BED12) format to describe the chromosomal positions of input transcripts. This format is compact, storing information regarding a single transcript's exons and CDS in a single row of data. Annotation reference files for most transcript and gene collections are readily available in BED12 format from the UCSC Table Browser. For compatibility with Pinstripe, Sequence Alignment/Map (SAM) files can be converted to, and compared with, BED files using programs such as BEDTools. Gene Transfer Format (GTF) files can be converted to BED format using a combination of tools available from UCSC, and basic command line utilities (refer Supplementary Material).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Identification of mRNA</head><p>mRNA are most easily identified by comparing transcripts with a database of validated gene annotations such as RefSeq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Pruitt et al., 2007</ref>) or GENCODE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Becker, 2011</ref>). The difficulty with this approach is that de novo transcriptomes, such as those assembled from high-throughput RNA sequencing experiments, can reveal both new transcripts that do not correspond to any annotation, and variants of known transcripts with additional exons, alternate splice sites or alternative UTRs, all of which may result in ORF disruption. Any comparison involving a novel transcript isoform requires consideration of the frame in which potential CDSs are translated. These problems are exacerbated for poorly annotated genomes or where a reference is not available. To address this challenge, Pinstripe provides two methods for identifying mRNA in CDS-naı¨venaı¨ve transcripts. First, Pinstripe annotate compares each transcript with a gene reference, annotating a CDS if the three-frame conceptual translation of the query transcript yields an ORF coincident (within tolerances defined by user options) with the reference, and in the same frame. Alternatively, Pinstripe mapPeptides takes peptide fragments (pepFrags) from mass spectrometry (or other proteomic data) and maps them to the transcriptome (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). mapPeptides creates a BLAST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Camacho et al., 2009</ref>) dictionary from the queried transcript library and maps the pepFrag amino acid sequences against the dictionary with user-definable parameters. The resultant BLAST matches are then translated from local mRNA coordinates to genomic coordinates (including those pepFrags mapping across splice junctions) and post-processed to remove redundancy (where pepFrags map to different mRNAs but resolve to the same genomic position). The original transcript library is matched to any overlapping pepFrags and potential ORFs (canonical and non-canonical) identified through in silico translation using Pinstripe buildProteins. Each transcript is reported with details of which pepFrags map to it, the amino acid sequence of the ORF and the ORF length. An example workflow is shown in<ref type="figure">Figure</ref>(2) Optionally remove pepFrags that are contained within another, or map to multiple locations: pstr deDup –exEncomp –exMisSplice – exMultiMap pepMap_results.bedx 4 pepMap_results_uq.bedx.</p><p>(</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Transcriptome assembly of the IBA2</head><p>The IBA2 is a collection of RNA sequencing experiments consisting of 2.54 billion reads across 16 human tissues: adipose, adrenal, breast, brain, colon, heart, kidney, liver, lung, lymph, ovary, prostate, skeletal muscle, testes, thyroid and white blood. Identification of mRNA and ncRNA using experimental data (Pinstripe mapPeptides, deDup and buildProteins), and by in-frame comparison to an annotation (Pinstripe annotate). Detailed flowcharts for these applications are included in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. S1</ref>cells (see Supplementary Text). We mapped the sequence reads using Tophat (<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Trapnell et al., 2009</ref>) and assembled transcriptomes for each tissue with Cufflinks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Trapnell et al., 2010</ref>) guided by GENCODE v10, finding 59.5% of the genome was transcribed across the aggregate of tissues, with an average of 39.4% transcribed in each individual tissue, varying from 31.7% (white blood) to 48.2% (testis) (Supplementary Tables S1 and S2, Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S2</ref>). Our mapping of this dataset revealed broadly similar results to those reported by<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Cabili et al. (2011)</ref>who constructed transcriptomes from the same datasets in a genome-wide study of lincRNAs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Cabili et al., 2011</ref>). However, in our analysis, we report only proper pairs (paired end) or aligned reads (single end) in our results leading to a lower mapping yield averaging 77.6% across both sets (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>). Of the 28 380 RefSeq-annotated protein-coding transcripts expressed, 56.6% (16 052) were found in 14 or more of the 16 tissues, and 14.7% (4187) were present only in a single tissue, the largest fraction (42.4%; 1775) of which were found in testis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Peptide mapping</head><p>We mapped 421 466 non-redundant pepFrags derived from the PRIDE database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Vizcaı´noVizcaı´no et al., 2009</ref>) against the composite transcriptome library using Pinstripe mapPeptides, successfully positioning 290 104 pepFrags (no mismatch, deletion or insertions), 255 825 of which mapped to a single genomic location (allowing for up to three mismatches). A further 256 pepFrags mapped to unpositioned contigs or haplotypes but were not used in subsequent analyses. The 131 106 pepFrags that could not be positioned demonstrate the unreliable nature of data from the PRIDE repository. Although the differing quality of individual submissions makes an aggregated assessment of the entire database impossible without reanalysis of the original spectra, even an estimate based on the number of pepFrags that can be positioned on the human genome demonstrates that PRIDE data alone provides unreliable evidence of a protein's existence. With a 31.1% chance that any entry from the database does not map to the human genome or transcriptome, even a superficial assessment requires an individual ORF to be supported by three pepFrags for a 5% False Discovery Rate (FDR) or four pepFrags to achieve 1% FDR. As a result, even ORFs with multiple matching pepFrags can only be considered to have a 'line of evidence' that an ORF may be translated, requiring additional support from other in silico analysis techniques such as conservation analysis, ORF probability or functional predictions, or biological validation. For our analysis, we aimed to determine whether there was evidence of ORFs with pepFrag support and additional predictors of protein-coding potential, which remain unannotated in GENCODE v10. To identify these ORFs, we used the Pinstripe ORF-aware overlap program to identify 14 630 pepFrags with no in-frame overlap to a known GCT10 CDS from the 255 825 uniquely mapping pepFrags. We then ran buildProteins with only these 14 630 non-CDS coincident GCT10 pepFrags revealing a set of 12 471 unannotated ORFs. We selected the most highly supported ORF from each locus in terms of proteomic support and ORF length using Pinstripe findBest, (default parameters) resulting in 5561 non-overlapping CDS-annotated transcripts. Pinstripe overlap revealed that 1130 of the 5561 CDSs contain an in-frame overlap to a GCT10 transcript, 129 of which had three or more mapping pepFrags. These ORFs arise from transcript isoforms of known genes that potentially encode novel protein variants, many of which are larger than the annotated product. For example, GIPC3 is a 312-amino acid protein encoded from chromosome 19 in which a previously unannotated splice site in the second last exon (PCR validation results in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S3</ref>) changes the reading frame of the final exon, extending the length of the ORF 4400% to 1350 amino acids (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4a</ref>) and incorporating six pepFrags. Although the ORF extension partially matches the 584-amino acid Uniprot record Q8N7K9, there is no independent GENCODE-annotated transcript that would encode the ORF, and there are no histone). The –v option of overlap reports non-overlapping CDSs (Dataset 4) representing completely novel ORFs. Additional processing with characterize annotates ORFs to include Kozak sequence, ORF probability and genomic context. The results of other publicly available applications such as PhyloCSF, IPRScan and Signalp can be directly appended to the annotated BED file using Pinstripe join modifications indicative of the transcription initiation necessary for an independent Q8N7K9 transcript. Similarly, AAK1 exhibits novel splicing variants resulting in omission of between one and five exons and a 9-kb region of the 3 0-UTR (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4b</ref>). The resultant novel transcript isoform (see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S3</ref>for PCR) substitutes up to 210 amino acids of the canonical protein's N-terminus with a completely different 307 amino acids and is supported by 11 pepFrags attributed to the 355-amino acid Uniprot protein Q6ZSR9, which, similarly to Q8N7K9, has no evidence to support its transcription except as the 3 0-UTR of AAK1. The reverse peptide mapping technique can also be used to provide experimental support for RefSeq genes whose status is annotated as either 'predicted', 'provisional', 'inferred' or 'unknown'. We interrogated 2213 such RefSeq genes and intersected these with the mapped PRIDE pepFrags, identifying 1100 (49.7%) ORFs having four or more pepFrags mapping to the ORF. Nineteen of these were not annotated in GENCODE v11.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Potentially novel protein-coding genes</head><p>After excluding novel isoforms of known genes, we identified 4432 canonical ORFs containing at least one uniquely mapping non-GCT10 pepFrag, of which 736 and 358 were supported by three and four or more non-GCT10 pepFrags, respectively. The majority (81.8%) of the unannotated canonical ORFs identified (excluding isoforms) are 5200 codons (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 5</ref>), consistent with larger ORFs being more easily identified by both laboratory and informatic techniques. Indeed, the impact of minimum size criteria applied by in silico gene prediction projects such as FANTOM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Carninci et al., 2005</ref>) (100 codons) and H-Invitational (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Imanishi et al., 2004</ref>) (80 codons) is evident in the size distributions with a difference in the distribution of ORF size where prediction algorithm cutoffs apply (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 5</ref>). As previously noted, matched pepFrags alone provide insufficient evidence for the identification of proteins. To identify which of these ORFs most likely represent bona fide proteincoding genes, and to demonstrate the Pinstripe join and characterize programs, we integrated data from other analyses including (i) protein-coding likelihood score across 29 mammal species from PhyloCSF (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Lin et al., 2011</ref>), (ii) the probability of the ORF occurring by chance (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Dinger et al., 2011</ref>), (iii) presence in the pseudogenes.org pseudogene database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Karro et al., 2007</ref>), (iv) signal peptide potential (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bendtsen et al., 2004</ref>), (v) similarity to known human and non-human proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Camacho et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Zdobnov and Apweiler, 2001</ref>) and (vi) Kozak sequence strength (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kozak, 1987</ref>). This data are available in Supplementary Table S5. Each candidate was also annotated by its genomic context relative to GCT10-annotated genes identifying: (i) genes annotated as non-coding yet coincident with pepFrag mapping sites, (ii) coding regions within the 3 0 or 5 0-UTR of known protein-coding genes, (iii) genes with no overlap to known</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Novel ORFs</head><p>To provide examples of potential results of Pinstripe analysis, we characterized selected potential proteins using bioinformatic and experimental tools. A BLAST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Camacho et al., 2009</ref>) comparison of the 4431 non-GCT10 canonical ORFs (excluding isoforms) against the full UniProt (<ref type="bibr">Uniprot Consortium, 2010</ref>) non-redundant database of known and predicted proteins revealed significant (E-value510 À10 ) matches for 2604 (58.8%), 601 of which had UniProt annotations of 'hypothetical' or 'predicted'. In two cases [PRAC2; (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Olsson et al., 2003</ref>) and a 5 0-UTR-derived isoform of MYC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Choi et al., 2008)]</ref>, literature searches revealed candidates matching experimentally validated proteins not recorded in UniProt. PhyloCSF scored 926 (20.9%) of the ORFs as 10 or greater, a result indicating the product is considered 10 times more likely to represent a coding RNA than an ncRNA. Signal3p (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bendtsen et al., 2004</ref>) identified 226 of the novel ORFs as having strongly predicted secretion signals, whereas the Pinstripe specificator program annotated 940 as specific to a single tissue (see Supplementary Text). Tissue-specific protein candidates are most frequently observed in testis (46.5%) in accordance with previously reported enrichments for novel and recently evolved genes in Drosophila testes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Begun et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Levine et al., 2006</ref>). Analyzing the output identified a number of novel ORFs for which translation was supported by multiple lines of evidence including RD3-like protein (RD3L;<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6a</ref>), a 198-amino acid protein encoded at 14q32.33, which is conserved in tetrapods and exhibits some similarity to RD3 (27% identity, E-value ¼ 4 Â 10 À15 ), a protein expressed in the eye and associated with retinal degeneration (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Friedman et al., 2006</ref>). Within the IBA2, RD3L is expressed in heart (the eye was not included in IBA2) at relatively low levels, whereas RD3 is not observed at all. A western blot was performed using antibodies raised against RD3L revealing the bands at the expected size (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. S4</ref>). High expression of the protein in the mouse eye (vitreous humor and retina) was confirmed by immunofluorescence imaging (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. S4</ref>). RD3L was not detected in heart by either western blot or immunofluorescence, a result possibly attributable to the lower levels of protein expression in that tissue. Subsequent to our analysis, a predicted protein sequence for RD3L was added to Uniprot. We also identified a transcript, which within its first intron hosts the well-studied microRNAs let7e, miR-125 A and miR-99B. This transcript, which we term LET7EH (Let-7e host), contains a 283-codon ORF (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6c</ref>), which is conserved in mammals and encodes immunoglobulin-like and transmembrane domains. This ORF was revealed by the identification of a previously unrecognized 5 0 exon of NCRNA00085, which contains a canonical start codon with a strong Kozak sequence, and is supported by H3K4me3 peaks signaling transcription initiation. The novel splice junction that encompasses the miRNAs was confirmed by PCR (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. S3</ref>). Our analysis revealed previously unannotated putative protein products larger than 600 amino acids. This includes a protein sequence with similarity (55% by BLASTP) to CROCC, a structural component of the ciliary rootlet, which contributes to centrosome cohesion before mitosis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bahe et al., 2005</ref>), that we term CROCC2 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6b</ref>). CROCC2 encodes a 1480-amino acid putative protein from a large conserved ORF adjacent to SNED1. Orthologs of CROCC2 are present in mammals and amphibians, with both CROCC2 and SNED1 remaining adjacent in mouse. Similarly, we identified another transcript expressed exclusively in testes that is predicted to encode a 638-amino acid protein with a helix–loop–helix DNA-binding domain and HMG-box domain that is conserved in mammals. The putative protein, which we term HMGDC (HMG domain containing,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6d</ref>), incorporates the predicted and unreviewed Uniprot entry C9JSJ3_HUMAN, adding two additional exons that form the HMG-box domain. Our Pinstripe analysis highlighted possible examples of underappreciated proteome complexity. For example, we identified a transcript that overlaps with the protein-coding gene, FIP1L1, that introduces a previously unknown ORF that is supported by four pepFrags. The putative protein encoded by this alternate reading frame, which we term FIP1L1ARF (F1P1L1 alternate reading frame), is also predicted to contain a probable signal peptide (D-score ¼ 0.908, P ¼ 0.99) and a neuroendocrine domain. Although such examples of multiple proteins originating from different ORFs are rare with only a small number previously reported in mammals (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Clark et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Nekrutenko et al., 2005</ref>), recent studies suggest this may be a much more common phenomenon (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Ingolia et al., 2011</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Non-coding, coding or dual function RNA</head><p>We examined 5325 transcripts (including isoforms) from the set of RefSeq-annotated genes with no annotated CDS. Intersecting these putatively non-coding transcripts with our uniquely mapping pepFrags identified 785 (14.7%) genes with pepFrags mapping within a canonical ORF, of which 341 had multiple pepFrag support. Although this analysis identifies those genes that may be translated, the analysis of candidates without a CDS includes, in the majority, genes whose classification as non-coding is attributable solely to a lack of evidence supporting translation. To classify genes with demonstrated or purported non-coding function, we analyzed 99 manually curated candidates from lncRNAdb (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Amaral et al., 2011</ref>) revealing that 10 of these non-coding genes H19, HAR1A, MALAT1, TUG1, MEG3, HOTTIP, LOC285194, ST7OT, WT1-as and SOX2OT have isoforms with uniquely mapping pepFrags contained within canonical ORFs, although only H19 and H19AS had three or more pepFrags, suggesting the remainder are most likely false positives. We selected four of the ncRNAs with pepFrag support, of which two were well supported (H19 and an antisense transcript to H19 and H19AS) and two poorly supported (MALAT1 and TUG1), and created antibodies against the putative proteins. The best supported of these was H19 with a large ORF (298 codons) matching seven uniquely mapping pepFrags (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. S6</ref>). H19 was the first long regulatory non-coding RNA described in mammals, classified as non-coding because of the absence of a detectable translated protein in mouse, along with poor ORF conservation between mouse and human compared with high overall DNA sequence identity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Brannan et al., 1990</ref>). The RNA is thought to be bifunctional, acting as both a miRNA and lncRNA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Smits et al., 2008</ref>). Western blots revealed no bands at the expected size for MALAT1, TUG1 or H19AS, but the predicted $26-kDa product for H19 was identified in fetal liver, K562 cells and testes (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. S5a</ref>) and appears to localize to the cytoplasm of T47D breast cancer cells (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. S5b</ref>). As there is only limited evidence for H19 action as a regulatory lncRNA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Runge et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Zhao et al., 2010</ref>), its translation suggests H19 is dual functional but possibly as a miRNA and mRNA, rather than lncRNA and miRNA. Although we did not successfully identify any of the other three candidates, H19AS has subsequently been identified by others as encoding the protein HOTS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Onyango and Feinberg, 2011</ref>). Although the lack of confirmation for MALAT1 and TUG1 is unsurprising given the lack of quality controls on the PRIDE peptide database, and only single pepFrag support, the proteincoding evidence of H19 and HOTS supports the hypothesis that the binary delineation of long RNA transcripts as either ncRNA or mRNA is an oversimplification, and that genes may exhibit a range of protein-coding and non-coding functionality as either small ncRNAs, long ncRNAs, mRNAs or a combination thereof (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Dinger et al., 2011</ref>). On the other hand, the vast majority of spliced transcripts from the IBA2 show no evidence of translation after integrating current transcriptomic and proteomic datasets. A total of 44 843 loci were composed only of transcripts that do not contain pepFrags, compared with 34 803 loci with at least one transcript containing one or more pepFrags. This result is consistent with recent datasets produced by GENCODE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Becker, 2011</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>Differentiating between ncRNA and mRNA is far from trivial, with traditional strategies relying on characteristics or features of known mRNAs such as codon conservation, ORF length or homology. Such strategies are effective at identifying mRNA that are well conserved, contain large canonical ORFs, are similar to known mRNA or encode known protein domains, but less reliable for detecting small poorly conserved proteins with specific non-redundant function. As a supplement to such approaches, Pinstripe provides a suite of tools designed to integrate and aggregate large sets of proteomic and transcriptomic experimental data, providing not only new tools for the identification of RNA potentially encoding proteins but also foramino acid protein and is the primary transcript for miR-LET7E, miR-125 A and miR-99B. It is conserved in mammals and contains a immunoglobulin-like and transmembrane domain. The start of transcription is supported by H3K4me3 modifications indicative of initiation. (d) HMGDC encodes a 638-amino acid testis-specific protein with helix–loop–helix DNA binding and HMG-box domains. The protein is conserved in mammals and extends a predicted Ensembl gene integrating data from in silico genomic comparisons by existing applications such as PhyloCSF, SignalP and IPRScan. There is growing evidence that large numbers of RNAs without well-conserved long canonical ORFs are actually translated. For example, the Humanin genes encode short ORFs (24–30 amino acids) and are found only in humans (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Hashimoto et al., 2001</ref>); translation of upstream ORFs is a demonstrated regulatory mechanism (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Baek et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Wen et al., 2009</ref>), and non-canonical start sites are common in mouse embryonic stem cells (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Ingolia et al., 2011</ref>). As a result, algorithms dependent on ORF length, canonical start codons, conservation or synonymous/non-synonymous substitution rates will not always be sufficient to identify and differentiate between coding and non-coding genes. This is especially true in the case of short proteins, which are challenging to identify as ORFs 5100 codons regularly occur by chance (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Dinger et al., 2008</ref>). As other methods including conservation analysis and dinucleotide content are only predictive and have shortcomings, the integration of experimental evidence supporting translation is often required for confident annotation of novel proteins. Pinstripe is designed to allow users to integrate any available experimental data in the form of gene annotations, peptide identifications or external analyses using applications such as PhyloCSF (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Lin et al., 2011</ref>) or SignalP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bendtsen et al., 2004</ref>). Although Pinstripe is entirely dependent on the integrity of the pepFrags, annotations and transcriptomes used for analysis, users can adjust the thresholds for identification to improve the probability of correct classification. The appropriate thresholds will largely depend on the quality of the data, notably the accuracy of pepFrag identifications. Most commonly, the process of correctly identifying pepFrags from spectra relies on the statistically robust concordance of the queried peptide fragment with predicted spectra from a target database. Although using pepFrags that have already been sequenced dramatically reduces the computational task, the fidelity of the original identification is lost. This can be addressed by pre-screening of spectra selecting only those with a set level of confidence, using peptides from quality-controlled sources such as the PeptideAtlas (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Deutsch et al., 2008</ref>), or at the protein identification stage by requiring an increased number of coincident pepFrags, or other supporting information such as conservation or functional prediction to identify coding genes. Our analysis of the IBA2 data demonstrates that application of Pinstripe's programs accurately maps pepFrags and integrates them with transcripts to identify supported ORFs and identifies RNA with little or no protein-coding capacity. Although not all ORFs containing mapped pepFrags represent genuine protein-coding genes, additional lines of evidence including signal peptide potential, positive PhyloCSF scores and multiple pepFrags identify potential protein-coding genes, including the validated protein RD3LP, variants of GIPC3 and AAK1 and a protein translated from the putative ncRNA H19. Pinstripe allows researchers to identify transcripts with little or no protein-coding potential, and which have no pepFrags mapping to putative ORFs, regardless of size. This is especially important, as knowledge of whether a given transcript is coding or non-coding will guide the design of any subsequent experimental work to characterize its function. Pinstripe is freely available for download at pinstripe. matticklab.com.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>2.</head><figDesc>Workflows for the main Pinstripe programs, mapPeptides, buildProteins and annotate are shown in Supplementary Figure S1. Examples of Pinstripe usage to annotate ORFs from a CDS-naı¨venaı¨ve transcriptome are as follows: (1) Map peptide fragments to a transcriptome: pstr mapPeptides [options] hg19.fa transcriptome.bed pepFrags.fa 4 pepMap_ results.bedx.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Overview of the reverse peptide mapping methodology. (a) RNA sequencing tags from heart tissue (red) are mapped to a reference genome. (b) Mapped tags are assembled into a transcript. (c) pepFrags are mapped to the same 198-codon ORF (RD3LP shown) using Pinstripe mapPeptides. (d) Full ORF is identified and annotated using Pinstripe buildProteins</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Identification of mRNA and ncRNA using experimental data (Pinstripe mapPeptides, deDup and buildProteins), and by in-frame comparison to an annotation (Pinstripe annotate). Detailed flowcharts for these applications are included in Supplementary Fig. S1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Identification of different classes of novel CDSs using Pinstripe overlap, and annotation using characterize, findBest and join. Setting parameters to require a 100% match identifies annotated genes (Dataset 1); lower settings represent potential novel transcript isoforms of annotated genes (Datasets 2 and 3). Comparing mapped pepFrags with an annotation identifies those not included in an existing CDS. These non-CDS pepFrags can be compared with the novel isoforms to identify those with novel pepFrag support (Dataset 3) and those without (Dataset 2). The –v option of overlap reports non-overlapping CDSs (Dataset 4) representing completely novel ORFs. Additional processing with characterize annotates ORFs to include Kozak sequence, ORF probability and genomic context. The results of other publicly available applications such as PhyloCSF, IPRScan and Signalp can be directly appended to the annotated BED file using Pinstripe join</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Novel isoforms encoding new proteins. (a) A novel splice junction in the second last exon (royal blue) changes the reading frame in the last exon of GIPC3, extending the RefSeq ORF (dark blue) 4400% through the UTR and incorporating the six pepFrags (light blue), predicting a novel protein coding region. (b) Several novel splicing events (royal blue) integrate a novel 3 0 exon and substituting different RefSeq exons (dark blue) in AAK1. The novel 3 0 exon is supported by 11 pepFrags (light blue). Expression data for brain (red) and testes (light green) shows different configurations are dominant in different tissues</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. Comparison of novel genes and RefSeq genes. Size distribution of ORFs in RefSeq known genes (dashed) and the novel gene candidates (solid). The distribution profile of the novel gene candidates clearly shows the 80-codon and 100-codon detection limits imposed by previous protein coding gene ORF detection methodologies</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig.6.</head><figDesc>Fig. 6. Novel protein coding genes. (a) RD3L encodes a 198-amino acid protein with some similarity to RD3. (b) CROCC2 encodes a 1480-amino acid protein and is supported by 40 pepFrags. Orthologs are identifiable in mammals and amphibians. (c) LET7EH encodes a 283-amino acid protein and is the primary transcript for miR-LET7E, miR-125 A and miR-99B. It is conserved in mammals and contains a immunoglobulin-like and transmembrane domain. The start of transcription is supported by H3K4me3 modifications indicative of initiation. (d) HMGDC encodes a 638-amino acid testis-specific protein with helix–loop–helix DNA binding and HMG-box domains. The protein is conserved in mammals and extends a predicted Ensembl gene</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Funding:</head><figDesc>This work was supported by a National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) Australia Fellowship (631668; J.S.M.), an NHMRC Career Development Award (631542; M.E.D.), and a Queensland Government Department of Employment, Economic Development and Innovation Smart Futures Fellowship (M.E.D.). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Pinstripe: a suite of programs for integrating transcriptomic and proteomic datasets at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2">.2 Classification of lncRNAs lncRNAs are defined as long mRNA-like transcripts that are not known to encode proteins, and which exhibit little or no protein-coding capacity. Because of the likelihood of long RNAs containing an ORF by chance alone, lncRNAs and mRNAs cannot be simply distinguished by the absence or presence of an ORF (Dinger et al., 2008, 2011). Pinstripe supports classification of RNAs whose coding status is unresolved using a combination of programs, and allows the incorporation of data from other applications for assessing protein-coding potential, such as PhyloCSF (Lin et al., 2011). The previously described annotate program not only identifies those RNAs with and without an in-frame CDS overlap to a reference but it also identifies RNAs without an ORF satisfying user-specified criteria—for example, an ORF length 580 codons and a start methionine. Pinstripe overlap identifies transcripts with overlapping in-frame CDSs at different tolerances, supporting identification of transcript isoforms, and characterize calculates the Kozak sequence strength, genomic context and probability of the ORF occurring by chance according to transcript length (refer Supplementary Text). Data from external programs are easily combined with Pinstripe&apos;s files using Pinstripe join, a BED format-specific program for identifying related data in different files, similar to a multiprocessor implementation of UNIX sort and UNIX join. Removal of mRNAs and those RNAs with uncertain coding potential reveals transcripts most likely to represent bona fide ncRNAs. An example workflow is shown in Figure 3. 3 RESULTS To demonstrate the efficacy of Pinstripe for annotating transcriptomic data, we mapped non-redundant human pepFrags from the PRIDE database (Vizcaı´noVizcaı´no et al., 2009) against a composite transcript library including de novo assembled transcriptomes from the Illumina Body Atlas of 16 human tissues (IBA2), ENCODE&apos;s GENCODE gene annotations (comprehensive) v10 (GCT10) and GenBank&apos;s database of human mRNA (Benson et al., 2004). The GENCODE and GenBank datasets were included to provide coverage of transcripts from tissues not included in the IBA2, an important consideration when determining whether a pepFrag maps to a single, or multiple transcribed genomic positions.</note>

			<note place="foot">D.K.Gascoigne et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basic local alignment search tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">215</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="410" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">lncRNAdb: a reference database for long noncoding RNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Amaral</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="146" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel mutation in Hr causes abnormal hair follicle morphogenesis in hairpoor mouse, an animal model for Marie Unna Hereditary Hypotrichosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Baek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mamm. Genome</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="350" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rootletin forms centriole-associated filaments and functions in centrosome cohesion</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Bahe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A user&apos;s guide to the encyclopedia of DNA elements (ENCODE)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Becker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1001046</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence for de novo evolution of testis-expressed genes in the Drosophila yakuba/Drosophila erecta clade</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Begun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">176</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1131" to="1137" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved prediction of signal peptides: signalP 3.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Bendtsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">340</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="783" to="795" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GenBank: update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Benson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The product of the H19 gene may function as an RNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Brannan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Shotgun proteomics aids discovery of novel protein-coding genes, alternative splicing, and &apos;&apos;resurrected&apos;&apos; pseudogenes in the mouse genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Brosch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="756" to="767" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrative annotation of human large intergenic noncoding RNAs reveals global properties and specific subclasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Cabili</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1915" to="1927" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BLASTþ: architecture and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Camacho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">421</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The transcriptional landscape of the mammalian genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Carninci</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">309</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1559" to="1563" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovery and revision of Arabidopsis genes by proteogenomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Castellana</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21034" to="21038" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">mrtl-A translation/localization regulatory protein encoded within the human c-myc locus and distributed throughout the endoplasmic and nucleoplasmic reticular network</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Choi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1092" to="1108" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mammalian gene PEG10 expresses two reading frames by high efficiency-1 frameshifting in embryonic-associated tissues</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Clark</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">282</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37359" to="37369" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The reality of pervasive transcription</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Clark</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1001102</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PeptideAtlas: a resource for target selection for emerging targeted proteomics workflows</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Deutsch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="429" to="434" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differentiating protein-coding and noncoding RNA: challenges and ambiguities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Dinger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of RNAs with multiple functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Dinger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochimie</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2013" to="2018" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Flicek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="800" to="806" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Premature truncation of a novel protein, RD3, exhibiting subnuclear localization is associated with retinal degeneration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Friedman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1059" to="1070" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Grabherr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="644" to="652" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanisms of neuroprotection by a novel rescue factor humanin from Swedish mutant amyloid precursor protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Hashimoto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">283</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="460" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrative annotation of 21,037 human genes validated by full-length cDNA clones</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Imanishi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">162</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ribosome profiling of mouse embryonic stem cells reveals the complexity and dynamics of mammalian proteomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Ingolia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="789" to="802" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pseudogene.org: a comprehensive database and comparison platform for pseudogene annotation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Karro</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human genome browser at UCSC</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Kent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="996" to="1006" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An analysis of 5&apos;-noncoding sequences from 699 vertebrate messenger RNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kozak</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8125" to="8148" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel genes derived from noncoding DNA in Drosophila melanogaster are frequently X-linked and exhibit testis-biased expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Levine</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9935" to="9939" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PhyloCSF: a comparative genomics method to distinguish protein coding and non-coding regions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship of protein conservation and sequence length</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Lipman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oscillating evolution of a mammalian locus with overlapping reading frames: an XLalphas/ALEX relay</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Nekrutenko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PRAC2: a new gene expressed in human prostate and prostate cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Olsson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prostate</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="130" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A nucleolar protein, H19 opposite tumor suppressor (HOTS), is a tumor growth inhibitor encoded by a human imprinted H19 antisense transcript</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Onyango</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Feinberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16759" to="16764" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NCBI reference sequences (RefSeq): a curated nonredundant sequence database of genomes, transcripts and proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Pruitt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Quinlan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Hall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="841" to="842" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">H19 RNA binds four molecules of insulin-like growth factor II mRNA-binding protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Runge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">275</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29562" to="29569" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conservation of the H19 noncoding RNA and H19-IGF2 imprinting mechanism in therians</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Smits</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="971" to="976" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolutionary origin of orphan genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Tautz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Domazet-Losˇolosˇo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="692" to="702" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TopHat: discovering splice junctions with RNA-Seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Trapnell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1105" to="1111" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Trapnell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="515" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The universal protein resource (UniProt) in 2010</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A guide to the proteomics identifications database proteomics data repository</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Vizcaı´novizcaı´no</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4276" to="4283" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Loss-of-function mutations of an inhibitory upstream ORF in the human hairless transcript cause Marie Unna hereditary hypotrichosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="228" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">InterProScan—an integration platform for the signature-recognition methods in InterPro</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Zdobnov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Apweiler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="847" to="848" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide identification of polycomb-associated RNAs by RIP-seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Zhao</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="939" to="953" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>