
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:38+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">PolyMarker: A fast polyploid primer design pipeline</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ricardo</forename>
								<forename type="middle">H</forename>
								<surname>Ramirez-Gonzalez</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">The Genome Analysis Centre (TGAC)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Norwich Research Park</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>NR4 7UH</postCode>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Cristobal</forename>
								<surname>Uauy</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">John Innes Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Norwich Research Park</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>NR4 7UH</postCode>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">National Institute of Agricultural Botany (NIAB)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CB3 0LE</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mario</forename>
								<surname>Caccamo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">The Genome Analysis Centre (TGAC)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Norwich Research Park</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>NR4 7UH</postCode>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">PolyMarker: A fast polyploid primer design pipeline</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv069</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received and revised on December 16, 2014; accepted on January 26, 2015</note>
					<note>Sequence analysis *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Alfonso Valencia Contact: Ricardo.Ramirez-Gonzalez@tgac.ac.uk Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The design of genetic markers is of particular relevance in crop breeding programs. Despite many economically important crops being polyploid organisms, the current primer design tools are tailored for diploid species. Bread wheat, for instance, is a hexaploid comprising of three related genomes and the performance of genetic markers is diminished if the primers are not gen-ome specific. PolyMarker is a pipeline that generates SNP markers by selecting candidate primers for a specified genome using local alignments and standard primer design tools to test the viability of the primers. A command line tool and a web interface are available to the community. Availability and implementation: PolyMarker is available as a ruby BioGem: bio-polyploid-tools. Web interface: http://polymarker.tgac.ac.uk.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Breeding programs rely on dense genetic maps with markers (e.g. SNPs) that can be used to identify the presence or absence of specific alleles in homozygous or heterozygous state. Standard primer design tools are designed to work in diploids, where genome duplications are rare. Wheat is a polyploid composed of three genomes (A, B and D; referred to as homoeologues) that are related (between 96 and 98% sequence identity), yet distinct. This creates a problem for the design of PCR primers specific to an individual homoeologue. A common approach to circumvent this issue is to manually design primers with a genome specific variant at the 3 0 of the primer to increase specificity. We introduce PolyMarker, a tool to automate the design of genome specific primers, thereby reducing the time invested in this process. To make PolyMarker accessible to scientists and breeders, we developed a web server where custom SNPs can be submitted for the design of genome specific assays. genotyping (LGC<ref type="bibr">Genomics, 2013</ref>), that comprises a common primer and two allele-specific primers. Since the allele-specific primers are restricted in position, the common primer is used to incorporate the chromosome specific variants when possible. To test if the primer candidates are viable Primer3 (Rozen and<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Skaletsky, 2000</ref>) is invoked using the genomic reference of the target chromosome. The starting positions of the primers to distinguish between alleles is selected with the SEQUENCE_FORCE_LEFT_END option of primer3. To design the common primer the option SEQUENCE_FORCE_RIGHT_END is used on two runs of primer3, for the chromosome specific and semi-specific primers. A final run of primer3 is executed without the SEQUENCE_FORCE_RIGHT_END option to find viable primers. After the primers are tested with Primer3, PolyMarker selects a primer pair with the highest specificity. PolyMarker is a pipeline (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>) written as a Biogem (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bonnal et al., 2012</ref>), extending bioruby (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Goto et al., 2010</ref>) to extract regions from fasta files and to support operations on nucleotide sequences with IUPAC ambiguity codes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cornish-Bowden, 1985</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Web interface</head><p>Our objective was to make PolyMarker accessible via a web interface where breeders and researchers could submit their markers to custom-design genome-specific SNP assays. A typical output is described in the supplemental material. Batch submission of several markers is possible. The web interface is implemented in java with MySQL database the markers information. The source code of the web interface and the daemon are available for the community to set up a private server.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Example results</head><p>The pipeline was developed originally to design KASP assays to validate putative SNPs from RNA-Seq data<ref type="bibr">[</ref></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>28 out of 35 assays polymorphic (80%; Ramirez-Gonzalez et al., 2014)]. PolyMarker was also used to generate KASP assays for the 81 587 markers in the iSelect array from Wang et al. (2014) (Supplemental Material).</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> Description of the tool First, PolyMarker converts the input marker information (chromosome arm, sequence adjacent to the SNP and parental alleles) into a fasta file with the sequences that can be queried to the genomic reference. The search is performed with Exonerate (Slater and Birney, 2005), with the option –ryo (roll your own format) to facilitate the parsing. The region flanking the SNP, twice the size of the maximum amplification product (200 bp for amplification products up to 100 bp), on the best hit of each chromosome is extracted. A local alignment between homoeologues and paralogues, is refined with MAFFT (Katoh and Standley, 2013), executed using the binder provided in bioruby. The local alignment is used to produce a mask containing all the variations across homoeologues and the input sequence (Supplementary Fig. S1). The mask indicates the type of variation on each position: (i) Specific: homoeologous polymorphism which is only present in the target genome; (ii) Semi-specific: homoeologous polymorphism which is found in more than one genome but it discriminates against one of the off-target genomes or when not all the homoeologous sequences were found; (iii) Non-specific: when no variation is found across homoeologues; (iv) Homoeologous: The target SNP is present across different chromosomes and; (v) Nonhomoeologous: The target SNP is not present across chromosomes. PolyMarker default is to design a three-primer assay for KASP V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> Summary PolyMarker is a pipeline that facilitates the design of primers in polyploid organisms. A web interface is available to design primers for hexaploid wheat. The use of PolyMarker reduces the time spent designing genome specific assays and highlighting homoeologous SNPs.</note>

			<note place="foot">R.H.Ramirez-Gonzalez et al.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors thank Sebastian Wilzbach for the help setting up the BioJS component for sequence alignments. The authors thank Nicholas Bird, Christopher Burt and Miroslav Valarik for feedback.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biogem: an effective tool-based approach for scaling up open source software development in bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J P G</forename>
				<surname>Bonnal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1035" to="1037" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nomenclature for incompletely specified bases in nucleic acid sequences: recommendations 1984</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Cornish-Bowden</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3021" to="3030" />
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioRuby: bioinformatics software for the Ruby programming language</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Goto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2617" to="2619" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: improvements in performance and usability</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Katoh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Standley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="772" to="780" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">LGC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA-Seq bulked segregant analysis enables the identification of high-resolution genetic markers for breeding in hexaploid wheat</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Ramirez-Gonzalez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Biotechnol. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Rozen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Skaletsky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automated generation of heuristics for biological sequence comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S C</forename>
				<surname>Slater</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Birney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterization of polyploid wheat genomic diversity using a high-density 90 000 single nucleotide polymorphism array</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant biotechnol. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="787" to="796" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">1. Implementation of PolyMarker. External programs are in squares, trapezoids represent the intermediate files and the document symbols represent inputs and outputs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Fig</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>