
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:58+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">PPDMs—a resource for mapping small molecule bioactivities from ChEMBL to Pfam-A protein domains</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Felix</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Kruger</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Anna</forename>
								<surname>Gaulton</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michal</forename>
								<surname>Nowotka</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Overington</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">EMBL-EBI</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>ChEMBL group</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hinxton</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">PPDMs—a resource for mapping small molecule bioactivities from ChEMBL to Pfam-A protein domains</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu711</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on 9 July 2014; revised on 8 September 2014; accepted on 22 October 2014</note>
					<note>Structural bioinformatics *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Alfonso Valencia</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>PPDMs is a resource that maps small molecule bioactivities to protein domains from the Pfam-A collection of protein families. Small molecule bioactivities mapped to protein domains add important precision to approaches that use protein sequence searches alignments to assist applications in computational drug discovery and systems and chemical biology. We have previously proposed a mapping heuristic for a subset of bioactivities stored in ChEMBL with the Pfam-A domain most likely to mediate small molecule binding. We have since refined this mapping using a manual procedure. Here, we present a resource that provides up-to-date mappings and the possibility to review assigned mappings as well as to participate in their assignment and curation. We also describe how mappings provided through the PPDMs resource are made accessible through the main schema of the ChEMBL database. Availability and implementation: The PPDMs resource and curation interface is available at http://compbio.ddns.comp.nus.edu.sg/%7elipidgo/index.php.
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Systematic analyses of bioactive small molecules and their molecular targets and homologues form the basis of a number of novel applications in computational drug discovery and systems and chemical biology, including methods of target prediction (<ref type="bibr">Martínez-Jiménez et al., 2013</ref>), and for the establishment of functional relationships between proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Kruger and Overington, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Lin et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">van der Horst et al., 2010</ref>). To add precision to these methods, we have previously proposed a simple mapping heuristic of small molecule bioactivities to protein domains (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Kruger et al., 2012</ref>). Here, we present a full implementation of the mapping to a relevant subset of biological assays stored in the current version of the ChEMBL database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bento et al., 2014</ref>). This implementation also accommodates edge cases that were unaddressed in the original implementation—specifically cases where more than one Pfam-A domain could mediate small molecule binding. In the refined implementation, such cases were resolved manually. The PPDMs server provides a platform to review and contribute manual assignments. Previous computational approaches exist that link small molecule binding to specific protein domains, but these approaches use information extracted from crystal structures of protein-ligand complexes to transfer binding annotations between homologous proteins V C The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>776</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.<ref type="bibr">2013</ref>). PPDMs provides an alternative approach that associates small molecule binding and protein domains based on empirical evidence from literature reported measurements in biological assays. PPDMs has generated binding-domain annotations for $770 k small molecule bioactivities which can be obtained from the main schema of the ChEMBL database.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">PPDMs enables improved mapping of ligandbinding domains</head><p>The objective of the mapping heuristic is to annotate biological assays reported in ChEMBL with the protein domain that mediates small molecule binding. The heuristic is based on protein domain annotations provided through the Pfam-A collection of sequence-based protein domains (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Punta et al., 2012</ref>). As a first step in the heuristic, a catalogue of Pfam-A domains capable of small molecule binding was constructed from small molecule bioactivities measured against single domain proteins from ChEMBL. PPDMs offers a facility to refine the original catalogue by adding Pfam-A domains that are known from other sources to interact with small molecules but which are missing from the catalogue in the original implementation. Vice-versa, Pfam-A domains can be removed from the catalogue if evidence for small molecule binding is deemed insufficient. For example, we adjusted the previously applied potency threshold of 50 mM to a more stringent threshold of 10 mM, corresponding to a pChEMBL value of 5, where pChEMBL is defined as Àlog 10 (molar IC50, XC50, EC50, AC50, Ki, Kd or Potency), see<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bento et al. (2014)</ref>. As a consequence, we removed a number of domains associated with weak and potentially non-specific binding. The catalogue and associated evidence for small molecule binding can be reviewed in the 'Evidence' section of the PPDMs resource. In a second step, this catalogue was mapped to proteins that are defined as targets in binding or functional assays where the target is either a single protein or a protein complex (defined through a relationship of type 'D') and a pChEMBL value is assigned. This resulted in three possible categories of outcomes (see also<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>):</p><p>i. A successful mapping if exactly one of the Pfam-A domain models from the catalogue matches the sequence. ii. No mapping if none of the Pfam-A domain models from the catalogue match the sequence; iii. A conflicting mapping if multiple domain models from the catalogue match the sequence.<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>summarizes the distribution of measured activities across these three categories. Despite their relatively small contribution to the total of measured activities, protein architectures associated with category iii-type outcomes form a subset of high relevance to drug discovery, for example, many tyrosine kinases and ligand-gated ion channels. In the 'Conflicts' section, PPDMs provides a facility to manually assign mappings for such architectures on a per-assay basis. For each assay, PPDMs provides an overview of the assay details, domain architecture of the associated target and a form to submit a manual assignment. Assignments can be reviewed in the 'Logs' section, with an option of revoking a previous curation decision. User profiles ensure that accidental or deliberate assignment errors can be rolled back on a per-user basis if necessary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Integration with the ChEMBL database</head><p>The PPDMs workflow is decoupled from the release cycle of the ChEMBL database. Assigned mappings can be exported from PPDMs, by downloading the pfam_maps table using a link in the logs section. Equally, an up-to-date version of the catalogue (table name: valid_domains) can be downloaded from the evidence section. For integration of mappings assigned using PPDMs into the main schema of the ChEMBL database, a standardized procedure exists. Prior to each ChEMBL release, the most recent version of the catalogue is obtained from PPDMs. In a second step, it is applied to proteins that are defined as targets in assays meeting the required criteria. Finally, the set of manually assigned mappings is obtained from the PPDMs resource and used to override mappings that have been assigned by the default procedure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Outlook</head><p>PPDMs provides a richer, domain-level perspective of small molecule binding and enriches annotation of small molecule bioactivities stored in the ChEMBL database. We anticipate that this type of annotation will improve the precision of target prediction and efficacy modelling approaches, and interpretation of the effects of natural genetic variation. PPDMs enables the refinement of domain-level annotation of small molecule bioactivities in a facile and transparent manner. The curation of conflicting mappings in PPDMs is ongoing and we are hopeful that PPDMs can engage the community in reviewing and improving domain-level annotations of small molecule bioactivities.Columns headed 'all' represent all activities, whereas columns headed 'active' represent activities from binding assays where pChEMBL is &gt;5. %, percentage relative to total.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Bioinformatics, 31(5), 2015, 776–778doi:10.</head><figDesc>1093/bioinformatics/btu711 Advance Access Publication Date: 27 October 2014 Applications Note (Davis and S ˇ ali, 2010; Finn et al., 2014; Snyder et al., 2006). More recently, such approaches have been used to associate protein domains based on ligands shared between them (Li et al., 2012; MoyaGarcía and Ranea,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Schematic illustration of homology-based transfer of binding domain annotation. The schematic shows how a catalogue of Pfam-A domains with known small molecule interactions was mapped to protein sequences in the ChEMBL target dictionary</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. The table below summarizes how activities in the current release distribute over the three possible outcomes</figDesc><table>Outcome 
# All 
% All 
# Active 
% Active 

i) Successful map 
750 653 
53.5 
269 128 
76.2 
ii) Not mapped 
625 135 
44.5 
63 010 
17.9 
iii) Conflicting map 
28 327 
2.0 
20 839 
5.9 
Total 
1 404 115 
100 
352 977 
100 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">F.A.Kruger et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors would like to thank Rita Santos and Grace Mugumbate for testing the PPDMs application. The authors thank Mark Davies for helpful discussions concerning the deployment of PPDMs.</p><formula>[... ] [...] [ ...] [ ...] [ ...]</formula><p>I. Single domain proteins II. Catalog III. Mapping</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ChEMBL bioactivity database: an update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Bento</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1083" to="1090" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The overlap of small molecule and protein binding sites within families of protein structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Davis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ali</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000668</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">iPfam: a database of protein family and domain interactions found in the Protein Data Bank</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Finn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="373" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global analysis of small molecule binding to related protein targets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Kruger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Overington</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002333</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping small molecule binding data to structural domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Kruger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing protein domain associations by smallmolecule ligand binding</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome Sci. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A pharmacological organization of G protein-coupled receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="140" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2013) target prediction for an open access set of compounds active against Mycobacterium tuberculosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Martínez-Jiménez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003253</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Insights into polypharmacology from drug-domain associations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Moya-García</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A G</forename>
				<surname>Ranea</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1934" to="1937" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Pfam protein families database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Punta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Domain-based small molecule binding site annotation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Snyder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">152</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel chemogenomics analysis of G proteincoupled receptors (GPCRs) and their ligands: a potential strategy for receptor de-orphanization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Van Der Horst</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">316</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>