
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:51+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics PPfold 3.0: fast RNA secondary structure prediction using phylogeny and auxiliary data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">20 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zsuzsanna</forename>
								<surname>Sü Kö Sd</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>Sü kö sd or zs@birc.au.dk.</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Interdisciplinary Nanoscience Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ny Munkegade 120</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology and Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">C. F. Møllers Alle</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Bioinformatics Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>C. F. Møllers Alle 8, 4 CLC bio, Finlandsgade 10-12</addrLine>
									<postCode>DK-8000</postCode>
									<settlement>Aarhus C</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bjarne</forename>
								<surname>Knudsen</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jørgen</forename>
								<surname>Kjems</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Interdisciplinary Nanoscience Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ny Munkegade 120</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology and Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">C. F. Møllers Alle</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Christian</forename>
								<forename type="middle">N S</forename>
								<surname>Pedersen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Bioinformatics Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>C. F. Møllers Alle 8, 4 CLC bio, Finlandsgade 10-12</addrLine>
									<postCode>DK-8000</postCode>
									<settlement>Aarhus C</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Aabogade 34</addrLine>
									<postCode>DK-8200</postCode>
									<settlement>Aarhus N</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics PPfold 3.0: fast RNA secondary structure prediction using phylogeny and auxiliary data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2691" to="2692"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">20 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts488</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 11, 2012; revised on July 6, 2012; accepted on July 27, 2012</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Ivo Hofacker Contact: Zsuzsanna</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>PPfold is a multi-threaded implementation of the Pfold algorithm for RNA secondary structure prediction. Here we present a new version of PPfold, which extends the evolutionary analysis with a flexible probabilistic model for incorporating auxiliary data, such as data from structure probing experiments. Our tests show that the accuracy of single-sequence secondary structure prediction using experimental data in PPfold 3.0 is comparable to RNAstructure. Furthermore, alignment structure prediction quality is improved even further by the addition of experimental data. PPfold 3.0 therefore has the potential of producing more accurate predictions than it was previously possible. Availability and implementation: PPfold 3.0 is available as a platform-independent Java application and can be downloaded from</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The Pfold package predicts (non-pseudoknotted) RNA secondary structure by combining a stochastic context-free grammar (SCFG) with an evolutionary model (<ref type="bibr">Hein, 1999, 2003</ref>). PPfold is a recent multi-threaded re-implementation of Pfold (Su¨ko¨sdSu¨ko¨<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Su¨ko¨sd et al., 2011</ref>). The Pfold model has been shown to result in highly accurate predictions when the input alignment is of high quality (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Gardner and Giegerich, 2004</ref>). In a different approach, data from high-throughput, quantitative RNA structure probing methods have also recently been used in thermodynamic prediction methods to increase prediction accuracy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Deigan et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Washietl et al., 2012</ref>). However, phylogenetic and probing data have only been used independently in RNA secondary structure prediction so far. Here, we present PPfold 3.0, which integrates these different sources of information at the level of the model. This is expected to increase prediction accuracy beyond what is possible with either evolutionary information or experimental data alone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MODEL</head><p>Pfold combines two models: (1) a SCFG model M s , which generates the prior probability distribution over secondary structures : The prior probabilities are denoted as PðjM s Þ: (2) A phylogenetic model M t , which computes the likelihood of the input alignment D, given the secondary structures. The likelihoods are denoted as PðDj, M t Þ: If an additional set of experimentally observed data, H, is available, the posterior probability of a secondary structure is</p><formula>PðjD, H, M s , M t Þ ¼ PðD, Hj, M s , M t ÞPðjM s , M t Þ PðD, HjM s , M t Þ : ð1Þ</formula><p>Expanding the expression and removing dependencies,</p><formula>PðjD, H, M s , M t Þ ¼ PðHjD, ÞPðjM s ÞPðDj, M t Þ PðD, HjM s , M t Þ , ð2Þ</formula><p>where PðDj, M t Þ are the probabilities obtained from the phylogenetic part of the algorithm, and PðjM s Þ are the prior probabilities from the SCFG calculations. The quantity PðHjD, Þ can be computed for any type of experimental data once a probabilistic model for its structure dependence is obtained. The posterior probability under the combined model can therefore be computed in the existing framework for optimization. In the case of many chemical probing methods, for example Selective 2 0-Hydroxyl Acylation Analyzed by Primer Extension<ref type="bibr">[SHAPE;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Wilkinson et al. (2009)]</ref>, the data are assumed to be independent of nucleotide identity and sequence position, and data values for nucleotides in the same pair are not correlated. For such data, PðHjD, Þ ¼ PðHjÞ, which is readily obtained by measuring known structures with the method. Let H i be the observed experimental value for position i, and P s ðiÞ and P d ði, jÞ the likelihoods of the alignment (for single-stranded and base paired columns, respectively) calculated purely on the basis of the phylogenetic model. The combined likelihood of the alignment and data, P 0 s ðiÞ (single-stranded case for alignment column i) and P 0 d ði, jÞ (base paired case for alignment columns i, j), can then be calculated asPPfold 3.0 has been written in Java 6 and consists of a single jar file. In addition to added support for experimental data, PPfold version 3.0 also features an intuitive graphical user interface. An arbitrary number of experimental data tracks can be added to each prediction. The following types of data tracks are currently supported:</p><formula>P 0 s ðiÞ ¼ P s ðiÞPðH i jj unpairedÞ ð 3Þ P 0 d ði, jÞ ¼ P</formula><p>(1) Probing data can be given in the same format as in RNAstructure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Mathews et al., 2004</ref>). The distributions PðHjÞ must also be given as histograms; a default distribution for SHAPE data is included in the application.</p><p>(2) 'Hard' constraint data can be specified for a sequence in the alignment in the same format as in mfold (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Markham and Zuker, 2008</ref>).</p><p>(3) Advanced data tracks are also supported, where the PðH i ji pairedÞ and PðH i ji unpairedÞ values are precomputed by the user for some positions i of the sequence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">TESTING</head><p>We obtained SHAPE data for the Escherichia coli 16S and 23S rRNAs from the authors of Deigan et al. (2009) (personal communication), removed invalid data points and computed the PðHjÞ distribution histograms for paired and unpaired nucleotides at a resolution of 0.01 units. SHAPE data are currently only available for few sequences with known structures, so we used the data for the E. coli 16S rRNA for testing. PPfold 3.0 is designed for structure prediction based on alignments. Nevertheless, the accuracy of single-sequence structure prediction for the E. coli 16S rRNA sequence is greatly improved on the addition of SHAPE data and is comparable to that of RNAstructure (<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>, upper block). We also examined the effect of SHAPE data on the quality of predictions of various alignments: (a) a Clustal W2 sequence alignment of the highly divergent small ribosomal subunit (SSU) sequences from E. coli (accession number K00421) and Encephalitozoon cuniculi (accession number X98467); (b) an R-coffee RNA alignment of the same two sequences; (c) the 'SSU high similarity' alignment from BRaliBase II (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Gardner and Giegerich, 2004</ref>) and (d) the 'SSU medium similarity' structural alignment from BRaliBase II. SHAPE data improved the quality of structure predictions for all alignments (<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>, lower block). The highest quality predictions can be obtained when a high-quality alignment is combined with experimental data. In these cases, prediction accuracies exceed what has been observed for a single sequence with RNAstructure with additional data, or with PPfold without additional data. However, a single-sequence structure prediction using experimental data is more accurate than a prediction using a low-quality sequence alignment alone or in combination with experimental data. The quality of the input alignment must therefore still be considered when using PPfold 3.0.</p><p>In conclusion, PPfold 3.0 enables phylogenetic RNA secondary structure prediction in conjunction with experimental data and has the potential of producing highly accurate predictions.PPV: positive predictive value; true positives as a fraction of predicted pairs. Sensitivity is the true positives as a fraction of reference base pairs. True positives are the correctly predicted base pairs. F-measure: the harmonic mean of PPV and sensitivity, and provides a measure for overall accuracy.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>d ði, jÞPðH i ji pairedÞPðH j jj pairedÞ: ð4Þ *To whom correspondence should be addressed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Evaluation of the accuracy of single-sequence (upper block) and alignment (lower block) structure prediction</figDesc><table>Program 
Input 
Data 
PPV 
Sensitivity F-measure 

RNAstructure E. coli 16S none 
0.3246 0.3462 
0.3351 
RNAstructure E. coli 16S SHAPE 0.7221 0.7329 
0.7275 
PPfold 
E. coli 16S none 
0.6358 0.2201 
0.3270 
PPfold 
E. coli 16S SHAPE 0.7560 0.6752 
0.7133 

PPfold 
Clustal W2 none 
0.3791 0.1709 
0.2356 
PPfold 
Clustal W2 SHAPE 0.6590 0.5534 
0.6016 
PPfold 
R-coffee 
none 
0.4519 0.2009 
0.2781 
PPfold 
R-coffee 
SHAPE 0.6743 0.5562 
0.6096 
PPfold 
SSU high 
none 
0.8579 0.6838 
0.7610 
PPfold 
SSU high 
SHAPE 0.8616 0.7714 
0.8140 
PPfold 
SSU med 
none 
0.8345 0.7436 
0.7864 
PPfold 
SSU med 
SHAPE 0.8721 0.8013 
0.8352 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">Z.Sü kö sd et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate SHAPE-directed RNA structure determination</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Deigan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="102" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comprehensive comparison of comparative RNA structure prediction approaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Gardner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Giegerich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">140</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA secondary structure prediction using stochastic context-free grammars and evolutionary history</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Knudsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Hein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="446" to="454" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pfold: RNA secondary structure prediction using stochastic context-free grammars</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Knudsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Hein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3423" to="3428" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UNAFold: software for nucleic acid folding and hybridization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Markham</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Zuker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">453</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incorporating chemical modificiation constraints into a dynamic programming algorithm for prediction of RNA secondary structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Mathews</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7287" to="7292" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mulithreaded comparative RNA secondary structure prediction using stochastic context-free grammars</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Su¨ko¨sdsu¨ko¨su¨ko¨sd</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA folding with soft constraints: Reconciliation of probing data and thermodynamic secondary structure prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Washietl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4261" to="4272" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of nucleotide identity on ribose 2 0-hydroxyl reactivity in RNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Wilkinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RNA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1314" to="1321" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>