
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:42+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis PReFerSim: fast simulation of demography and selection under the Poisson Random Field model</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Diego</forename>
								<surname>Ortega-Del Vecchyo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Interdepartmental Program in Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>90095</postCode>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Clare</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Marsden</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>90095</postCode>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kirk</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Lohmueller</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Interdepartmental Program in Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>90095</postCode>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>90095</postCode>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">David Geffen School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>90095</postCode>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Oliver</forename>
								<surname>Stegle</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis PReFerSim: fast simulation of demography and selection under the Poisson Random Field model</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 21, 2016; revised on June 10, 2016; accepted on July 3, 2016</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Availability and Implementation: PReFerSim is freely available at: https://github.com/LohmuellerLab/ PReFerSim Contact: klohmueller@ucla.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The Poisson Random Field (PRF) model has become an important tool in population genetics to study weakly deleterious genetic variation under complicated demographic scenarios. Currently, there are no freely available software applications that allow simulation of genetic variation data under this model. Here we present PReFerSim, an ANSI C program that performs forward simulations under the PRF model. PReFerSim models changes in population size, arbitrary amounts of inbreeding, dominance and distributions of selective effects. Users can track summaries of genetic variation over time and output trajectories of selected alleles.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Understanding the behavior of selected mutations in finite populations is important in population, medical and conservation genetics. Two main computational approaches have been used to model weakly deleterious mutations. First, under the Poisson Random Field (PRF) framework (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hartl et al., 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Sawyer and Hartl, 1992</ref>), a Poisson number of independent mutations enter the population each generation, with subsequent changes in allele frequency due to selection and drift. The PRF framework is a mainstay in population genetic inference of demography and selection (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Akashi and Schaeffer, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Boyko et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bustamante et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Desai and Plotkin, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Eyre-Walker et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gutenkunst et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Huerta-Sanchez et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Williamson et al., 2005</ref>). However, existing implementations of the PRF model do not provide the ages or selection coefficients of individual mutations or permit the user to follow allele frequency trajectories over time. Moreover, including biological complications, like inbreeding at certain time points, or dominance effects, are difficult for the average user within existing software (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Boyko et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gutenkunst et al., 2009</ref>). The second approach involves simulation of entire populations forward in time. Here, individuals reproduce each generation in proportion to their fitness. Several software programs exist to perform such simulations, including SFS_CODE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Hernandez, 2008</ref>), SLiM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Messer, 2013</ref>) and fwdpp (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Thornton, 2014</ref>). These programs are designed to simulate large regions of genetic variation with linkage and arbitrary recombination and they track chromosomal regions through time, rather than the behavior of individual mutations. Thus, unless the recombination rate is exceptionally large, they are not directly comparable to the PRF model which assumes free recombination. Further, these simulations may not be ideal for generating trajectories of selected alleles because the trajectories of V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com individual alleles may be altered through linkage to other selected sites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Felsenstein, 1965</ref>). Finally, some features, such as arbitrary amounts of inbreeding, are not included in SFS_CODE and SLiM. The recently released GO Fish (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Lawrie, 2016</ref>) also models individual mutations, but currently does not model distributions of fitness effects nor does it have a complete stand-alone software package. Here, we present a new program, PReFerSim, which combines these approaches and performs forward simulations under the PRF model for a single population. Two features distinguish PReFerSim from existing implementations of the PRF model and forward simulation programs. First, PReFerSim can track allele frequencies over time, and the ages and trajectories of individual mutations. Second, PReFerSim can simulate large amounts of genetic variation data with free recombination quickly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Implementation</head><p>PReFerSim will simulate genetic variation data under the Poisson Random Field model. Each generation a Poisson number (with mean h/2, where h is the population-scaled mutation rate) of mutations enter the population. Information about each mutation is stored in a linked list. Mutations change frequency every generation due to natural selection and genetic drift. Genetic drift is implemented through a binomial sampling step. The program in written in ANSI C and utilizes the GNU Scientific Library for random number generation. PReFerSim allows users to consider a variety of models of selection and demography. The program accepts demographic models with an arbitrary number of population size changes. Inbreeding can be modeled by specifying an inbreeding coefficient, F, which can be constant or change over time. Variable inbreeding is useful to simulate domestication events, or inbreeding following population decline, and is a unique feature of this software. Six distributions of fitness effects are included and the program allows selected mutations to have arbitrary dominance. PReFerSim will output summaries of genetic variation in the present day as well as at various times throughout the simulation. Trajectories of selected alleles can be generated and used in downstream coalescent simulations to model neutral genetic variation linked to the selected site (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Ewing and Hermisson, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Przeworski et al., 2005</ref>). Importantly, trajectories from PReFerSim can be conditioned to have any present-day frequency desired by the user. Such simulations can be used to estimate the ages of selected alleles and/or strength of selection (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Ormond et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Przeworski, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Tishkoff et al., 2007</ref>), to estimate the rate of selective sweeps (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Jensen et al., 2008</ref>), or to distinguish between hard and soft selective sweeps (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Garud et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Peter et al., 2012</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>To demonstrate the performance of PReFerSim, we generated the site frequency spectrum (SFS) under a population expansion demographic model with a gamma distribution of fitness effects (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Boyko et al., 2008</ref>). The SFS produced by PReFerSim is comparable to that generated using dadi (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). Additionally, ages of deleterious alleles obtained from PReFerSim are comparable to classical theoretical predictions made by Maruyama (1974; Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>). In sum, these results demonstrate that PReFerSim can generate predictions about the frequency spectrum and allele ages under complex models of demography and selection. Example applications of</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusion</head><p>PReFerSim is a forward-in-time population genetic simulation program that can generate data under the PRF model considering complex demography and arbitrary models of selection and dominance. Given the growing interest in studying how demography affects deleterious variation across a wide range of taxa (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Brandvain and Wright, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Henn et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Marsden et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Schubert et al., 2014</ref>), there is a need for population genetic software that can easily simulate large amounts of data under complex evolutionary models. As such, we anticipate that PReFerSim will play an important role in future studies.<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. Comparison of the SFS between PReFerSim (gray) and the diffusion approximation (black; dadi) for complex demographic models with purifying selection. Top: the SFS are similar in a sample of 2000 chromosomes. SNPs with counts greater than 22 are combined in the last bin. Bottom: SFS for a sample of 24 chromosomes. See Supplementary Text for a description of the model parameters</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>PReFerSim can be found in Marsden et al. (2016) and Robinson et al. (2016).</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">Bioinformatics, 2016, 1–3 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw478 Advance Access Publication Date: 19 July 2016 Applications Note Bioinformatics Advance Access published August 4, 2016 at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">D.Ortega-Del Vecchyo et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank Bernard Kim for the preparation of.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health<ref type="bibr">[R01 HG007089]</ref>; the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation<ref type="bibr">[BR2014-009]</ref>; UC MEXUSCONACYT doctoral fellowship<ref type="bibr">[213627]</ref>; and a UCLA Dissertation Year Fellowship. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Natural selection and the frequency distributions of &quot; silent &quot; DNA polymorphism in Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Akashi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Schaeffer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">146</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="307" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing the evolutionary impact of amino acid mutations in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Boyko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The limits of natural selection in a nonequilibrium world</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Brandvain</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">I</forename>
				<surname>Wright</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Directional selection and the site-frequency spectrum</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Bustamante</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1779" to="1788" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The polymorphism frequency spectrum of finitely many sites under selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Desai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Plotkin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">180</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2175" to="2191" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MSMS: a coalescent simulation program including recombination, demographic structure and selection at a single locus</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Ewing</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Hermisson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinf. Oxf. Engl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2064" to="2065" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The distribution of fitness effects of new deleterious amino acid mutations in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Eyre-Walker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">173</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="891" to="900" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of linkage on directional selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Felsenstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="363" />
			<date type="published" when="1965" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent selective sweeps in North American Drosophila melanogaster show signatures of soft sweeps</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Garud</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inferring the joint demographic history of multiple populations from multidimensional SNP frequency data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Gutenkunst</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000695</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selection intensity for codon bias</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Hartl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="234" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the mutation load in human genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Henn</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="343" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A flexible forward simulator for populations subject to selection and demography</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Hernandez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinf. Oxf. Engl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2786" to="2787" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Population genetics of polymorphism and divergence under fluctuating selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Huerta-Sanchez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">178</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="337" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An approximate Bayesian estimator suggests strong, recurrent selective sweeps in Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Jensen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Accelerating Wright-Fisher forward simulations on the graphics processing unit</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Lawrie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bottlenecks and selective sweeps during domestication have increased deleterious genetic variation in dogs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Marsden</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="152" to="157" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The age of an allele in a finite population</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Maruyama</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SLiM: simulating evolution with selection and linkage</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Messer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">194</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1037" to="1039" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inferring the age of a fixed beneficial allele</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Ormond</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinguishing between selective sweeps from standing variation and from a de novo mutation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Peter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the time since the fixation of a beneficial allele</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Przeworski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">164</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1667" to="1676" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The signature of positive selection on standing genetic variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Przeworski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evol. Int. J. Org. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2312" to="2323" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic flatlining in the endangered Island Fox</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1183" to="1189" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Population genetics of polymorphism and divergence</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Sawyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Hartl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1161" to="1176" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prehistoric genomes reveal the genetic foundation and cost of horse domestication</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Schubert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5661" to="5669" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A C þþ template library for efficient forward-time population genetic simulation of large populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Thornton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="0198" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convergent adaptation of human lactase persistence in Africa and Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Tishkoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneous inference of selection and population growth from patterns of variation in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Williamson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7882" to="7887" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PReFerSim</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>