
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics Rchange: algorithms for computing energy changes of RNA secondary structures in response to base mutations</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hisanori</forename>
								<surname>Kiryu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Frontier Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5-1-5 Kashiwanoha</addrLine>
									<postCode>277-8561</postCode>
									<settlement>Kashiwa</settlement>
									<region>Chiba</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kiyoshi</forename>
								<surname>Asai</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Frontier Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5-1-5 Kashiwanoha</addrLine>
									<postCode>277-8561</postCode>
									<settlement>Kashiwa</settlement>
									<region>Chiba</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Computational Biology Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology (AIST)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-42 Aomi, Koto-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>135-0064</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics Rchange: algorithms for computing energy changes of RNA secondary structures in response to base mutations</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1093" to="1101"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts097</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 26, 2011; revised on February 19, 2012; accepted on February 21, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [14:56 27/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts097.tex] Page: 1093 1093–1101 Associate Editor: Ivo Hofacker Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Measuring the effects of base mutations is a powerful tool for functional and evolutionary analyses of RNA structures. To date, only a few methods have been developed for systematically computing the thermodynamic changes of RNA secondary structures in response to base mutations. Results: We have developed algorithms for computing the changes of the ensemble free energy, mean energy and the thermodynamic entropy of RNA secondary structures for exhaustive patterns of single and double mutations. The computational complexities are O(NW 2) (where N is sequence length and W is maximal base pair span) for single mutations and O(N 2 W 2) for double mutations with large constant factors. We show that the changes are relatively insensitive to GC composition and the maximal span constraint. The mean free energy changes are bounded ∼7−9 kcal/mol and depend only weakly on position if sequence lengths are sufficiently large. For tRNA sequences, the most stabilizing mutations come from the change of the 5-most base of the anticodon loop. We also show that most of the base changes in the acceptor stem destabilize the structures, indicating that the nucleotide sequence in the acceptor stem is highly optimized for secondary structure stability. We investigate the 22 tRNA genes in the human mitochondrial genome and show that non-pathogenic polymorphisms tend to cause smaller changes in thermodynamic variables than generic mutations, suggesting that a mutation which largely increases thermodynamic variables has higher possibility to be a pathogenic or lethal mutation. Availability and implementation: The C++ source code of the Rchange software is available at http://www.ncrna.org/software/ rchange/</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Measuring the effects of base mutations has long been a standard method for studying relationships between structural RNAs and their biological functions. Molecular biologists mutate some nucleotides of the RNAs of interest in order to alter the structures, and draw various conclusions by observing whether the mutations * To whom correspondence should be addressed. disrupt biological functions [see, for example, (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Warf et al., 2009)]</ref>. Observing mutation patterns in genome evolution has also been important for detecting evolutionarily conserved functional RNAs and evolutionarily conserved structural RNAs show special types of mutation patterns that preserve their secondary structures. Several studies have used such patterns as a major feature for finding novel structural RNAs from multiply aligned genomic sequences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Knudsen and Hein, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Pedersen et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Rivas and Eddy, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Washietl et al., 2005</ref>). Investigating the structural changes due to base mutations has potentially important applications in genome-wide association studies, where many disease-associated single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) are located outside the protein coding regions in the human genome (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Halvorsen et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">International HapMap Consortium, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Manolio, 2010</ref>). It is possible that part of the disease associations of these SNPs can be explained by altered structures of the non-coding RNAs that are transcribed around those regions. Despite the widespread use of mutational analyses and the potential relevance to human diseases, very few studies have developed methods for systematically computing the changes in RNA secondary structures in response to base mutations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Barash and Churkin, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Barash, 2006, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Shu et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Waldispuhl et al., 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Waldispuhl et al., , 2009</ref>). In our previous paper, we have developed algorithms for computing the thermodynamic variables for a given sequence (Kiryu and Asai, submitted for publication) [see also the earlier works (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Clote et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Miklos et al., 2005</ref>) which developed algorithms for the mean free energy computation<ref type="bibr">]</ref>. In this article, we present algorithms for computing the changes in the ensemble free energy, mean free energy and the thermodynamic entropy of secondary structures for all the possible single and double mutations, assuming that the RNA secondary structures follow the Boltzmann distribution P(ζ|x) of the Turner energy model (TEM) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Mathews et al., 1999</ref>):</p><formula>P(ζ|x) = exp −G(ζ,x)/RT /Z(x) Z(x) = ζ∈ exp −E(ζ,x)/RT where G(ζ,x)(</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H.Kiryu and K.Asai</head><p>structures of long RNA sequences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Mathews et al., 1999</ref>) and the base pair predictions between distant nucleotide positions are particularly inaccurate for such long RNAs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Doshi et al., 2004</ref>), it is natural to restrict the maximal span of the base pairs to a fixed value W. The maximal span constraint avoids predicting large number of spurious base pairs between distant positions while still allowing global structure prediction. When the maximal span constraint is applied, includes only structures containing base pairs of span ≤ W. Using the thermodynamic model, the mean free energy U(x) and the macroscopic entropy S(x) in energy units are defined by</p><formula>S(x) =−RT ζ∈ P(ζ|x)log(P(ζ|x))</formula><formula>(1) U(x) = ζ∈ P(ζ|x)G(ζ,x) F(x) =−RT log(Z(x)) = U(x)−S(x)</formula><p>Here,<ref type="bibr">, 2006, 2008</ref>) computes the minimum free energies and the structural changes for all the possible single mutations by running the RNAfold program in the Vienna RNA package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hofacker, 2003</ref>) for each RNA mutant. RNAmute can also compute k-point mutations that are likely to cause large structural alterations by using the RNAsubopt and RNAfold programs of the Vienna package. The computational complexities are O(N 4 ) for single mutations and O(<ref type="bibr">Ne CN</ref>) (C &gt; 0), which is the complexity of RNAsubopt, for k-point mutations. RDMAS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Shu et al., 2006</ref>) also uses RNAsubopt and RNAfold to predict the most deleterious single mutations that cause large structural changes. They compute suboptimal structures (x * ) within a fixed range of free energy for each of 3N possible single point mutants x * and returns 'deleteriousness'</p><formula>D(ζ MFE (x)(x * )) defined by a Boltzmann average of structural distances d(ζ 1 ,ζ 2 ): D(ζ MFE (x),,(x * )) = ζ * ∈(x * ) P(ζ|x)d(ζ MFE (x),ζ * ) ζ MFE (x) = argmin ζ∈ E(ζ,x)</formula><p>where ζ MFE (x) is the minimum free energy (MFE) structure of the original sequence x. RDMAS provide a few options for the distance measure d(ζ,ζ * ) including free energy difference |E(ζ,x)−E(ζ * ,x * )|, edit distance between secondary structures, and difference between topological indices of secondary structures. The complexity for this procedure is O(Ne CN ). Since both RNAmute and RDMAS use either MFE structures or suboptimal structures of a fixed energy range, they do not take into account all the possible secondary structures. On the other hand, our algorithm exactly sums the contributions from all the possible secondary structures in a polynomial time. RNAmutants (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Waldispuhl et al., 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Waldispuhl et al., , 2009</ref>where M(k,x) is the set of all the k-point mutants of sequence x. The complexity for computing the partition functions is O(K 2 N 3 ). While we are generally interested in the individual effects of each mutation x * , k-point partition functions Z k (x) mix up all the contributions of the k-point mutants x * and it is not possible to extract individual partition functions Z(x * ) from Z k (x) with any simple modification to the RNAmutants algorithm. In their paper, the authors used a statistical sampling method that samples mutated sequences x * with structures from the k-point Boltzmann distribution associated with Z k (x). However, the meaning of the sampled sequences is difficult to understand from the statistical physics viewpoint; it is equivalent to a thermodynamic system where time scales of base mutations are as fast as those of RNA folding. Furthermore, sampling methods are very inefficient for long RNA sequences with large structure spaces (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kiryu et al., 2011</ref>). On the other hand our algorithm exhaustively computes the individual partition functions Z(x * ) of all the k = 1,2 points mutants x * . Finally, none of those studies have computed the differences of thermodynamic quantities such as the ensemble free energy, mean free energy and entropy for each individual mutation. In the following sections, we first derive our algorithms for a simple stochastic context-free grammar (SCFG). Next we derive similar algorithms for the more complex case in which the emission probabilities depend on the neighboring bases; this mimics the complexities encountered in the energy model. We then describe how to extend the algorithms in these simple cases to the full energy model. In Section 4, we show the run time and required memory size for several parameter settings. We then investigate basic properties of the thermodynamic changes, such as the dependencies on the sequence lengths and the GC compositions, and the choices of the maximal base pair span. We also investigate the dependencies of the thermodynamic changes on the mutated base positions. Finally, we investigate the characteristics of the thermodynamic changes of the tRNA family.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">ALGORITHMS AND IMPLEMENTATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Simple stochastic context-free grammar</head><p>The SCFG model that we consider has a single non-terminal state (S) and five transition rules (P, L, R, B, E).</p><formula>P : S −→ a &lt; Sa &gt; L : S −→ aS R : S −→ Sa B : S −→ SS E : S −→</formula><p>where (a &lt; , a &gt; ) represents a base pair, a represents an unpaired base and represents a null terminal symbol. Although this grammar is an ambiguous grammar, we can still define and compute the partition function Z 0 (x) = ξ P(x,ξ) and entropy S 0 (x) =− ξ P(ξ|x)logP(ξ|x), where the sum is over all the possible parse trees ξ. If a grammar is unambiguous, then the space of the parse trees has one to one correspondence to the space of the secondarystructures and the corresponding probability distribution is defined over the secondary structure space. Although our implementation 'Rchange' uses an unambiguous grammar called the Rfold grammar (see below and the Supplementary Material), the following algorithm works independently of the ambiguity of grammars. To compute the entropy of a single mutant for this model, we must first compute the partition function of the mutated sequence. If the emission probabilities e P (a &lt; ,a &gt; ), e L (a) and e L (a) are independent of the neighboring bases, as is usually the case, then the partition function can easily be computed. For example, we consider a mutant x * in which the original base x j at position j is replaced with base c * (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). To compute the partition function Z(x * ), we sum the probabilities P(x,ζ) over all the parse trees ζ. Each parse tree contains exactly one transition that emits base c * at position j, and we split the parse tree into two parts that are upstream and downstream of the transition. These partial parse trees are independent of the base at j, hence they also appear in the original sequence x. By collecting these partial parse trees and reorganizing the sum using the inside and outside variables, we obtain the formula</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rchange: computing energy changes for RNA secondary structures</head><formula>Z(x * ) = j+1&lt;k≤N α(j +1,k −1)e P (c * ,x k )t(P)β(j,k) (2) + 1≤k&lt;j−1 α(k +1,j −1)e P (x k ,c * )t(P)β(k,j) + j&lt;k≤N α(j +1,k)e L (c * )t(L)β(j,k) + 1≤k&lt;j α(k,j −1)e R (c * )t(R)β(k,j)</formula><p>where t(r) represents the transition probability associated with transition rule r, c * represents the mutated base, and α(u,v) and β(u,v) (u ≤ v) represent the inside and outside variables of the original sequence x (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>). The computational complexity of this calculation is O(N). Hence, the computation of all the single mutations (O(N)</p><p>) is dominated by the inside–outside algorithms and the total complexity is O(N 3 ). In our previous paper, we developed a method to calculate the entropy, the mean free energy, and the energy variance of secondary structures by using dynamic programming (DP) algorithms (Kiryu and Asai, submitted for publication). Briefly, we introduced copies of the inside variables, α 1 (i,j).<ref type="bibr">[</ref>for publication)]. In the present case, we compute Z 1 (x * ) for each singlepoint mutant x * by using α 1 (i,j) and β 1 (i,j) (which are log-score inserted outside variables analogous to α 1 (i,j)):</p><formula>Z 1 (x * ) = j+1&lt;k≤N u+v+w=1 α u (j +1,k −1)τ v P (c * ,x k )β w (j,k) + 1≤k&lt;j−1 u+v+w=1 α u (k +1,j −1)τ v P (x k ,c * )β w (k,j) + j&lt;k≤N u+v+w=1 α u (j +1,k)τ v L (c * )β w (j,k) + 1≤k&lt;j u+v+w=1 α u (k,j −1)τ v R (c * )β w (k,j)</formula><p>where u,v,w ∈{0,1}, α 0 (i,</p><formula>j) = α(i,j), β 0 (i,j) = β(i,j), τ v P (a,b) = e P (a,b) t(P)[loge P (a,b)t(P)] v , τ v L (a) = e L (a)t(L)[loge L (a)t(L)] v and τ v R (a) = e R (a) t(R)[loge R (a)t(R)] v .</formula><p>The entropy of the mutated sequence is given by</p><formula>S(x * ) =−(Z 1 (x * )/Z(x * ))+logZ(x * )</formula><p>. Once the partition function Z(x * ) and entropy S(x * ) are known the ensemble free energy F(x * ) and mean free energy U(x * ) can be computed using Equation (1). We next consider the computation of the partition function Z(x * * ) for a double mutant x * * in which bases i and j (i &lt; j) are replaced with c * * and c * , respectively. To compute Z(x * * ), we simply replace the original sequence x with x * and compute the inside and outside variables, α (i,j) and β (i,j), for sequence x * and apply Equation (2) for the partition function of double mutant x * * with the replacements</p><formula>x * ,j,c * ,α,β → x * * ,i,c * * ,α</formula><p>,β. We can economize the calculation of α and β by using the fact that parts of the inside and outside variables of sequence x * are the same as the corresponding variables of sequence x. In<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref>, the inside and outside variables of x * are the same as those of x in regions (b–c) and (a), respectively. Furthermore, it is unnecessary to compute the outside variables of x * in region (b) to compute Z(x * * ) for an arbitrary i (i &lt; j). The computational complexity is O(N 4 ) since we have to apply the outside algorithm [which has complexity O(N 3 )] to 3N single mutations, where N is the input sequence length. Note that there are three possible 1-point mutations for each base. For example, A→ C, A→ G and A→ U are the possible mutations for base A.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H.Kiryu and K.Asai</head><formula>α(i,j,(c 1 ,c 2 )) and β(i,j,(c 1 ,c 2 )</formula><p>) which depend on pairs of bases (c 1 ,c 2 ) outside of the parsing subsequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Emission probabilities dependent on neighboring bases</head><p>We now consider the case in which the emission probabilities depend on the neighboring bases:</p><formula>e P (x i ,x j |x i−1 ,x i+1 ,x j−1 ,x j+1 ), e L (x i |x i−1 ,x i+1 ) and e R (x i |x i−1 ,x i+1</formula><p>). Although such a model does not belong to the category of generative models, it approximates the essential complexities of the energy model. In such a case, the value of the inside variable α(i,j) computed for the original sequence x depends on the bases x i−1 and x j+1 , unlike in the previous subsection. Similarly, the outside variable β(i,j) depends on x i and x j. We cannot apply Equation (2) since the mutation at position j alters the values of the neighboring inside and outside variables. It is in principle possible to derive a formula similar to Equation (2) that uses only the inside and outside variables which are two bases away from position j and hence are independent of the mutation of the base at j. However, the corresponding formula would be much more complicated since it would include three layers of DP recursions, corresponding to the emissions of bases x j−1 , x j and x j+1. Instead, we introduce seven copies of the inside variables</p><formula>α(i,j,(c 1 ,c 2 )</formula><p>), where (c 1 ,c 2 ) represents one of seven types of nucleotide pairs at positions (i−1, j +1) that differ by at most one base from the original nucleotide sequence. For example, if (x i−1 , x j+1 ) = (A,G) as in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>, then (c 1 ,c 2 ) is one of the set {</p><formula>(A,G),(A,U),(A,A),(A,C),(C,G),(G,G),(U,G)}. Then α(i,j,(c 1 ,c 2 )</formula><p>) is defined to be the inside variable on the condition that the bases at i−1 and j +1 are c 1 and c 2 , respectively. Similarly, we introduce seven copies of the outside variables β(i,j,</p><formula>(c 1 ,c 2 )</formula><p>), where (c 1 ,c 2 ) represents one of seven types of nucleotide pairs at positions (i, j) that differ by at most one base from the original bases. Accordingly, β(i,j,</p><formula>(c 1 ,c 2 )</formula><p>) is defined to be the outside variable on the condition that the bases at i and j are c 1 and c 2 , respectively. Once these variables are calculated, we can apply Equation 2 by choosing the appropriate α(i,j,</p><formula>(c 1 ,c 2 )) and β(i,j,(c 1 ,c 2 )</formula><p>) depending on the mutated base.</p><formula>Z(x * ) = j+1&lt;k≤N α(j +1,k −1,(c * ,x k ))e P (c * ,x k |j,k)t(P)β(j,k,(c * ,x k )) + 1≤k&lt;j−1 α(k +1,j −1,(x k ,c * ))e P (x k ,c * |k,j)t(P)β(k,j,(x k ,c * )) + j&lt;k≤N α(j +1,k,(c * ,x k+1 ))e L (c * |j)t(L)β(j,k,(c * ,x k )) + 1≤k&lt;j α(k,j −1,(x k−1 ,c * ))e R (c * |j)t(R)β(k,j,(x k ,c * )) where e P (a,b|x u−1 ,x u+1 ,x v−1 ,x v+1 ), e L (a|x u−1 ,x u+1 ) and e R (a|x u−1 ,x u+1 ) are denoted by e P (a,b|u,v), e L (a|u) and e R (a|u), respectively. The variables α(i,j,(c 1 ,c 2 )) and β(i,j,(c 1 ,c 2 )</formula><p>) are computed by the usual inside–outside algorithms with special care taken to match the outside nucleotide pairs (c 1 ,c 2 ). For example, the inside algorithm is</p><formula>α(i,j,(c 1 ,c 2 )) = ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ α(i+1,j −1,(x i ,x j ))e P (x i ,x j |c 1 ,x i+1 ,x j−1 ,c 2 )t(P) α(i+1,j,(x i ,c 2 ))e L (x i |c 1 ,x i+1 )t(L) α(i,j −1,(c 1 ,x j ))e R (x j |x j−1 ,c 2 )t(R) i≤k&lt;j α(i,k,(c 1 ,x k+1 ))α(k +1,j,(x k ,c 2 ))t(B)</formula><p>The outside algorithm is similar to the inside algorithm and is shown in the Supplementary Material. The computational complexity of the inside– outside algorithms is simply seven times larger than that of the usual inside– outside algorithms and is given by O(N 3 ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Application to the energy model</head><p>We use the grammatical formulation called the Rfold model, which was introduced in (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kiryu et al., 2008</ref>), to derive the mean free energy and the entropy differences for TEM. The Rfold model is based on an unambiguous grammar that can generate all the secondary structures without duplication, and its transition rules are capable of accommodating the score system of TEM. The unambiguity of the Rfold grammar is described in detail in the Supplementary Material of the original article and we do not repeat it here (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kiryu et al., 2008</ref>). The model fully uses the advantage provided by the maximal span constraint and computes the inside–outside algorithms in O(NW 2 ) time and O(N +W 2 ) space (where N is sequence length, and W is the maximal span of base pairs). Although the Rfold model is not an SCFG model, it is usually straightforward to derive DP algorithms analogous to those in SCFG models (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kiryu et al., 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kiryu et al., , 2011</ref>; Kiryu and Asai, submitted for publication). In the inside–outside algorithms of the Rfold model, the dangle and terminal mismatch energies of TEM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Zuker et al., 1999</ref>) correspond to dependencies on nucleotides outside of the DP cells. Fortunately, these dependencies do not extend &gt;1 base on either side of the current DP cell. Therefore, we only need six additional DP matrices, just as described in the previous section, to accommodate arbitrary single-point mutations of DP cells that are immediately outside of the current cell. To compute the entropy and mean free energy, we double the DP matrices for computing the log-score inserted tree scores. Consequently, the memory size required for the DP matrices in the case of single-point mutations is 14 times as large as that in the usual inside–outside algorithms, although the complexities are the same O(N +W 2 ) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kiryu et al., 2008</ref>). In the case of doublepoint mutations, we use O(N +LW 2 ) memory (where L is the maximal distance of mutated base pairs) to keep track of the mutant inside–outside variables α , β. The computation times are dominated by the bifurcation calculations and there are 7×3 = 21 times as many of those as there are in the ordinary inside–outside algorithm. The factor of 7 corresponds the number of nucleotide pairs (c 1 ,c 2 ) for computing the inside–outside variables α(i,j,</p><formula>(c 1 ,c 2 )) and β(i,j,(c 1 ,c 2 )</formula><p>), and 3 corresponds to the patterns of bifurcations that mix log-score inserted DP matrices: k α u (i,k)·α v (k,j), k α u (j,k)·β v (i,k) andN is sequence length, W is maximal span and L is the maximal distance between two mutated nucleotides. L = 0 indicates that only single mutations are computed. k=kilo. computational complexity is still O(NW 2 ) for single-point mutations, and O(NW 2 L) for double-point mutations. We have described the full algorithm in the Supplementary Material. We have implemented the algorithms in C++ in a software package called 'Rchange'. The source code is freely available from our download site (http://www.ncrna.org/software/rchange/).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rchange: computing energy changes for RNA secondary structures</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DATASET AND DATA PROCESSING</head><p>We measured the run time and memory usage for random RNA sequences. The experiments were performed on a PC with an Intel Quad Core Xeon E5450 3.0 GHz processor and 32 GB of memory. Random RNA sequences of varying lengths and GC compositions were generated using a Ruby script. The tRNA sequences are taken from the Rfam database version 10 (<ref type="bibr">GriffithsJones et al., 2003</ref>). We used only the manually curated seed alignment of 967 sequences and its accompanying structure annotation. We have obtained non-pathogenic polymorphisms and pathogenic mutations from MITOMAP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Ruiz-Pesini et al., 2007</ref>). The non-pathogenic polymorphism are considered as mutations from the reference genome, which can be regarded as a collection of dominant alleles (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Ruiz-Pesini et al., 2007</ref>). The background distributions of dF/|F|, dU/|U| and dS/|S| (sample size n = 4142 for each) are defined by the distributions for all the possible single-point mutations in the 22 mitochondrial tRNA genes except the nonpathogenic polymorphisms (n = 238) and the pathogenic mutations (n = 209) of MITOMAP. In our previous work (Kiryu and Asai, submitted for publication), we have shown that the scales of mean energies U(x) are generally about 10 times higher than S(x).</p><formula>It means F(x) = U(x)−S(x) and U(x)</formula><p>are well correlated. Consistently with this finding, we found dF = dU −dS and dU are very well correlated. Therefore, we only show the figures for dU in the following section. We have shown the comparison between dF = dU −dS and dU in the Supplementary Material.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>more elaborate optimization to make Rchange a faster program to the future.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 5</ref>shows the effects of single-point mutations on the mean free energies U and the entropies S. For each random sequence generated with a specified length and GC composition, we ran Rchange to obtain the differences dU and dS for all the singlepoint mutations and we selected the largest and smallest values from these 3N difference values. We plotted the mean values of these upper and lower bounds for 100 random sequences with the same length and GC composition. The upper bound values indicate the largest energy or entropy increase caused by a single mutation; the lower bound indicates the largest energy or entropy decrease caused by a single mutation. These four figures show that the effect of varying GC compositions or maximal spans W do not have much influence on the differences. The mean free energy change dU (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 5A</ref>and B) reaches a bound of 7–9 kcal/mol in magnitude at around N = 200, while the entropy change dS (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 5C</ref>and D) gradually increases in magnitude as the sequence length increases. Interestingly, the magnitudes of the entropy changes are about half of those of the mean free energies, which is a much higher ratio than the typical ratio (about one-tenth) for the total entropies and mean free energies (Kiryu and Asai, submitted for publication). This indicates that the entropy changes might affect in the in vivo processes of mutations (such as RNA editing) on RNA transcripts. Since the dynamic range of single point mutations are bounded independently of the sequence length, base mutations have considerable impact on the thermodynamics of less stable RNAs. As the thermodynamic variables F, U and S roughly proportional to the sequence length (Kiryu and Asai, submitted for publication), smaller RNAs aremore influenced by the mutations. We have analyzed the effects of single point mutations on other Rfam families such as microRNAs (let-7) and snoRNAs (SNORA1, SNORD73) in the Supplementary Material. We have shown that any mutation to the stems of the stable RNAs (let-7 and SNORA1) generally causes a increase of energies whereas less stable RNAs have a large number of stabilizing mutations, implying selective pressures for the secondary structure stability vary considerably from family to family.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>shows a ranked list of the mutation patterns that were frequently observed to cause the maximal changes of the thermodynamic values U and S in the random sequences. We computed the mutation patterns that caused the maximal changes of U and S for each sequence, and counted the number of occurrences for 100 random sequences. We ranked the patterns by the enrichment—the ratio of the frequency of occurrence of pattern c 1 → c 2 to a simple background frequency given by {(total count of c 1 in all the sequences)×1/4}. The table indicates the maximal increases are achieved by mutating G to the other bases in many cases and the maximal decreases of the thermodynamic values are achieved by mutating a base into G. We have shown nucleotide dependencies and structural preferences of the thermodynamic change distributions in the Supplementary Material.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figure 6</ref>shows the position dependence of dU. For each position of random sequences of lengths 20 (A, C) and 200 (B, D), we obtain the upper and lower bound for energy changes.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figure 6A</ref>and B show the mean values of these upper and lower bounds for 10 000 random samples.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figure 6C</ref>and D show the standard deviations (SDs) of dU for each position calculated from the 10 000 random sequences. For shorter sequences (A, C), we observe two peaks around positions 5 and 15 which indicate the dominance of single hairpin structures over other structural configurations in short sequences. This position dependence rapidly disappears as sequence length increases, and we find no position dependence except the very small values of dUs at the ends of sequences (B, D).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figure 6B</ref>and D show that mean values are ∼ 1–2 kcal/mol whereas the SD is ∼ 2 kcal/mol, indicating the strong sequence dependence of the energy changes.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">Figure 7</ref>shows the position dependence of the upper and lower bounds of the relative changes dU/|U| and dS/S for single-point mutations of tRNA sequences. For each position of each tRNA sequence in the Rfam seed alignment, we calculated the upper bound and bound of dU/|U| and dS/S. The average values of these bounds are plotted for all the seed sequences using the alignment information. We removed alignment columns with many gaps (&gt; 30% of the number of the sequences). The figure shows that mutations in the stem regions can destabilize the structure more than those in non-stem regions. Mutations in the acceptor stem (the closing stem) influence the increase of dU/|U| the most, and a change of &gt;20% of the mean free energy can be produced by only a single mutation. On the other hand, the increase of dS/S is most affected by the T arm (the right most stem aside from the acceptor stem) on average, which might indicate that an increased probability of disruption of the T arm stem may lead to a large fluctuation of these regions, including the variable loop between the anticodon stem and the T arm stem; however, the differences from the peaks of the other stems are small. The plots of the lower bounds show sharp peaks at the unpaired bases that are next to the stem regions, which indicates that changes that extend the stem length stabilize the secondary structure the most. The upper figure shows that the secondary structures are most stabilized by changing the 5 end of the anticodon loop (the loop in the center stem). This<ref type="figure">figure also</ref>shows that any changes in the acceptor stem increaseThe position dependence of the upper bound and lower bound of the relative changes dU/|U| and dS/S for single-point mutations of tRNA sequences. We have averaged the upper bounds and the lower bounds over the 967 tRNA sequences using the seed alignment of the Rfam database. The brackets '&lt;' and '&gt;' shown at y = 0.0 represent the common secondary structure of the tRNA sequences. the mean free energy, which indicates that the sequences of the acceptor stem may be strongly optimized for secondary structure stability.<ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref>shows the position dependence of the upper and lower bounds of the relative changes dU/|U| and dS/S for double-point mutants of tRNA sequences. The upper right triangles show that the largest increases of dU/|U| and dS/S can be obtained by mutating nucleotide pairs that are both located in the stem regions. The destabilizing effects on U are larger if one mutating base is on the acceptor stem than if both nucleotides are on mean free stems, while the influence on entropies S is similar regardless of which stem regions the pairs are located in. The lower bound of dU/|U| (the lower left triangle in<ref type="figure">Fig. 8A</ref>) shows that the double mutation of a base at a stem boundary and a base in a loop region can cause &gt;30% decrease of the mean energy. On the other hand, most of the double mutations that include any base in the acceptor stem increase dU. There are no dU &gt; 0 regions (or green regions in the lower left triangles) inside the acceptor stem, even at the intersections of A B<ref type="figure">Fig. 8</ref>. These colored figures show the position dependence of the upper and lower bound of the relative changes dU/|U| (A) and dS/S (B) for double-point mutations of tRNA sequences. For each density plot, the upper right (lower left) triangle shows the density plot of the mean upper (lower) bound of dU/|U| or dS/S for all the non-trivial double-point mutations. We have averaged the upper bounds and the lower bounds over the 967 tRNA sequences using the seed alignment of the Rfam database. The positive and negative changes are displayed using green and magenta colors, respectively. The gray colored background indicates the annotated stem regions of tRNAs. different stem regions in which any double mutations are expected to destabilize both of the stem structures. This indicates that the D arm, anticodon and T arm stems are not very stable compared with the acceptor stem and there are considerable fluctuations in their secondary structures. At present, it is not clear whether this represents biophysical properties of tRNAs or is simply a limitation of TEM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Comparison of run time and memory usage</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Scales of mean free energy and entropy changes</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H.Kiryu and K.Asai</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Position dependence of mean free energy changes</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Effects of single-point mutations on tRNA</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rchange: computing energy changes for RNA secondary structures</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Effects of double-point mutations on tRNA</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.6">Mutations in human mitochondrial tRNAs</head><p>The human mitochondrial genome involves 22 tRNA genes. Mitochondrial DNA is known to have about 10 times higher mutation rate than nuclear DNA, and the mutations in the tRNA genes cause various mitochondrial diseases such as myopathy, deafness and Alzheimer's disease (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Zifa et al., 2007</ref>). We compared the distributions of dF/|F|, dU/|U| and dS/S for non-pathogenic polymorphisms and pathogenic mutations with the background distribution.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">Figure 9</ref>shows the dS/S distribution for three mutation types. It shows that non-pathogenic polymorphisms are depleted'Lowered' tests whether the dX/|X| distribution has a smaller median and 'Centered' tests whether |dX/X| distribution has a smaller median, than the background distribution</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H.Kiryu and K.Asai</head><formula>(X = F,U,S).</formula><p>from the large dS/S region and concentrated around dS/S = 0 as compared with the background mutations.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>shows the P-values that test the biases of the distributions. We do not find any significant bias for the pathogenic mutations. It is reasonable since the seriousness of symptoms vary widely from disease to disease and the carriers of pathogenic mutations are still viable with all their sickness as opposed to the cases of lethal mutations, which may obscure the relationships between the tRNA functions and the pathogenic mutations. On the other hand, the non-pathogenic polymorphisms tend to cause smaller changes, suggesting that a mutation that largely increases either dS/S, dU/|U| or dF/|F| tends to be a pathogenic or lethal mutation. It is interesting that entropy change dS/S has greater significance than the energy changes dU/|U| and dF/|F|, which might indicates that the structural fluctuations are more related to tRNA dysfunction than the energetic instabilities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">CONCLUSION</head><p>In this article, we have developed algorithms for computing changes in the ensemble free energy, mean free energy and the thermodynamic entropy of RNA secondary structures for all possible patterns of single and double mutations. The computational complexities are O(NW 2 ) (where N is sequence length and W is maximal base pair span) for single mutations and O(N 2 W 2 ) for double mutations with relatively large constant factors. We have shown that the changes in the mean free energy and entropy are relatively insensitive to GC composition and the maximal span constraint. The mean energy changes are bounded at ∼7–</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. An example parse tree. When the base A at position j (rectangle) is mutated, we decompose the tree into the inside part (i), the outside part (ii) and the transition that emits the mutating base (iii).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>These were denoted by α (i,j) in the previous paper but that symbol has a different meaning in this article.] These copies represent sums of tree scores as in the ordinary inside variables except that each parse tree score contains a single log transition score insertion [such as log(e P (c,c )t(P)), log(e L (c)t(L)), etc.] at some transition. As there is no temperature for SCFG models, we use a definition of entropy that is slightly different from Equation (1): the entropy S(x) =− ζ P(ζ|x)logP(ζ|x) is given by −(Z 1 (x)/Z(x))+logZ(x), where Z 1 (x) = α 1 (1,N) [for a detailed explanation see (Kiryu and Asai, submitted</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Schematic diagram representing the four terms that are required for calculating the mutant partition function Z(x * ) [Equation (2)].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [14:56 27/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts097.tex] Page: 1096 1093–1101</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Schematic illustration of the computation of the partition functions for double-point mutants. Left: Regions of the DP matrix. We compute the inside–outside variables α and β after mutating the j-th base. Right: Compute the double mutant partition function using α and β .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. The inside and outside variables α(i,j,(c 1 ,c 2 )) and β(i,j,(c 1 ,c 2 )) which depend on pairs of bases (c 1 ,c 2 ) outside of the parsing subsequences.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [14:56 27/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts097.tex] Page: 1097 1093–1101</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><figDesc>shows the run time and memory usage of the Rchange program. As described earlier, Rchange is at least 21 times slower than the usual inside–outside algorithms. The table shows that it is difficult to apply Rchange to genome scale sequences. Because of the complexities of the algorithm, the optimization level of our implementation is rather primitive at present. The run time can be improved by devising data structures and orders of computations, though it will require a considerable work. We would like to leave A B D C</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. The upper and lower bounds of the changes in the mean free energies (A, B) and entropies (C, D) which are caused by single-point mutations with varying maximal spans W (A, C) and GC contents (B, D). (A, C) are computed with W = 400, whereas (B, D) are computed with GC = 0.5.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [14:56 27/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts097.tex] Page: 1098 1093–1101</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig.6.</head><figDesc>Fig. 6. The position dependence of dU for random sequences. The figures show the means (A, B) and the SDs (C, D) of the upper bound (thick lines) and lower bound (thin lines) at each position for random RNA sequences of length 20 (A, C) and 200 (B, D). The random sequences were generated with GC = 0.5. The maximal span W was set to 400.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [14:56 27/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts097.tex] Page: 1099 1093–1101</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig.7.</head><figDesc>Fig. 7. The position dependence of the upper bound and lower bound of the relative changes dU/|U| and dS/S for single-point mutations of tRNA sequences. We have averaged the upper bounds and the lower bounds over the 967 tRNA sequences using the seed alignment of the Rfam database. The brackets '&lt;' and '&gt;' shown at y = 0.0 represent the common secondary structure of the tRNA sequences.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: TRJ MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER [14:56 27/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts097.tex] Page: 1100 1093–1101</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig.9.</head><figDesc>Fig. 9. dS/S distributions of mitochondrial tRNA genes. Each distribution is normalized to sum to one. Crosses, the background distribution; open circles, non-pathogenic mutations; filled circles, pathogenic mutations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>kcal/mol) represents the difference of the Gibbs energies G(ζ,x)−G(ζ 0 ,x) between a structure ζ and the structure ζ 0</figDesc><table>that contains no base pairs, is the set of all possible secondary 
structures of x, R = 1.9872×10 −3 kcal/(mol·K) is the gas constant 
and T = 310.15 K is the temperature. 
Since it is known that the secondary structure model based on the 
Turner energy parameters is less accurate for predicting secondary Copyedited by: TRJ 

MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: ORIGINAL PAPER 

[14:56 27/3/2012 Bioinformatics-bts097.tex] 
Page: 1094 1093–1101 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>U(x) is the mean free energy difference of RNA secondary structure, F(x) is the ensemble free energy difference (G(x)− G(ζ 0 ,x)) between the state of the secondary structure ensemble and the unstructured state ζ 0. Our algorithms compute the differences dF(x * ,x) = F(x * )−F(x), dU(x * ,x) = U(x * )−U(x) and dS(x * ,x) = S(x * )−S(x) for all the possible single and double mutants x * of sequence x. The computational complexities are O(NW 2 ) (where N is sequence length and W is maximal base pair span) for single mutations and O(N 2 W 2 ) for double mutations with large constant factors. RNAmute (Churkin and Barash</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>) calculates all the k-point mutant partition functions Z k (x) (for k ≤ K with a given K) which are given by the sum of all the Boltzmann factors of all the possible k-point mutants: Z k (x) = x * ∈M(k,x) ζ∈ exp −E(ζ,x * )/RT = x * ∈M(k,x) Z(x * )</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 1.</figDesc><table>Run time and memory usage 

(N, W, L) 
Run time (m:s) 
Memory (MB) 

(100, 100, 0) 
0:8 
31 
(1k, 100, 0) 
3:11 
113 
(1k, 1k, 0) 
33:9 
2659 
(10k, 100, 0) 
34:37 
118 
(100, 100, 10) 
8:12 
31 
(100, 100, 50) 
17:23 
31 
(100, 100,100) 
20:41 
31 
(1k, 100, 10) 
263:1 
113 
(1k, 100, 50) 
625:40 
124 
(1k, 100, 100) 
1061:2 
137 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2. Ranked list of mutation types that are frequently observed to cause the maximal differences of the thermodynamic values U and S Type</figDesc><table>Mutation 
Enrichment 
Mean change 

U max increase 

G→A 
6.2 
+6.4 

G→C 
3.5 
+5.9 

G→U 
3.2 
+6.1 

U max decrease 

U→G 
4.4 
−7.1 

A→G 
4.0 
−7.3 

A→C 
3.4 
−7.1 

S max increase 

G→U 
3.1 
+2.1 

C→G 
2.4 
+2.8 

G→A 
2.3 
+2.1 

S max decrease 

C→G 
2.9 
−2.6 

A→G 
2.8 
−2.8 

U→G 
2.5 
−3.1 

'Enrichment' indicates how often each specific mutation caused the maximal change 
of U and S, compared with the background frequency. 'Mean change' is the average 
change of the thermodynamic values in kcal/mol. All the random sequences are of 
length 200 and are generated with GC = 0.5. The maximal span was set to 400. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 3. P-values of Wilcoxon rank sum tests.</figDesc><table>Non-pathogenic 
Pathogenic 
Variable 
Lowered 
Centered 
Lowered 
Centered 

dF/|F| 
0.017 
5.8×10 −5 
0.48 
0.034 
dU/|U| 
1.6×10 −5 
1.1×10 −6 
0.090 
0.059 
dS/S 
6.2×10 −7 
2.0×10 −8 
0.066 
0.031 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">k α u (k,i)·β v (k,j) (for u+v ≤ 1). Despite this, the</note>

			<note place="foot" n="9"> kcal/mol in magnitude and there is only a small position dependence if sequence lengths are sufficiently large. For tRNA sequences, the most stabilizing mutations come from changes of the 5-most base of the anticodon loop. We have also shown that most base changes in the acceptor stem destabilize the structures, indicating that the nucleotide sequence in the acceptor stem is highly optimized for secondary structure stability. We have analyzed the effects of single point mutations on other Rfam families such as microRNAs (let-7) and snoRNAs (SNORA1, SNORD73) in the Supplementary Material, where we have shown that any mutation to the stems of stable RNAs generally causes a increase of energies whereas less stable RNAs have stabilizing mutations in most regions, implying selective pressures for the secondary structure stability vary considerably from family to family. We have investigated human mitochondrial tRNAs and found that non-pathogenic polymorphisms tend to cause smaller changes in thermodynamic variables as compared with a background distribution, suggesting that a mutation which largely increases thermodynamic variables has higher possibility to be a pathogenic or lethal mutation. There are several applications of our algorithms. As described in the Introduction, our algorithms can be directly used in a mutation analysis to design the most stabilizing and destabilizing mutations. They will also be useful for investigating the correlations between the evolutionary variations of RNA genes in genome sequences and the changes in their structures. The algorithms can also be of interest for investigating the disease associations of SNPs located in noncoding RNA genes. Although we only considered mutations within the standard four bases &apos;ACGU&apos; in this article, similar techniques will be used for the structural analysis of A-to-I RNA editing if there exists a complete set of nearest-neighbor parameters for the inosine residue [see Watkins and SantaLucia (2005) for DNA case].</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank their colleagues who worked on the project for discussions and comments.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutational analysis in RNAs: comparing programs for RNA deleterious mutation prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Barash</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Churkin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="104" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNAmute: RNA secondary structure mutation analysis tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Churkin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Barash</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">221</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An efficient method for the prediction of deleterious multiple-point mutations in the secondary structure of RNAs using suboptimal folding solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Churkin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Barash</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">222</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bioinformatics-bts097.tex] Page</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="83" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Rchange: computing energy changes for RNA secondary structures</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy landscape of k-point mutants of an RNA molecule</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Clote</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4140" to="4147" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of the suitability of free-energy minimization using nearest-neighbor energy parameters for RNA secondary structure prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Doshi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rfam: an RNA family database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="441" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disease-associated mutations that alter the RNA structural ensemble</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Halvorsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1001074</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vienna RNA secondary structure server</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Hofacker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3429" to="3431" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A haplotype map of the human genome</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International HapMap Consortium. Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">437</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1299" to="1320" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rfold: an exact algorithm for computing local base pairing probabilities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Kiryu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="373" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A detailed investigation of accessibilities around target sites of siRNAs and miRNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Kiryu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1788" to="1797" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pfold: RNA secondary structure prediction using stochastic context-free grammars</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Knudsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Hein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3423" to="3428" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomewide association studies and assessment of the risk of disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Manolio</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N. Engl. J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">363</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="166" to="176" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expanded sequence dependence of thermodynamic parameters improves prediction of RNA secondary structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Mathews</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">288</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="911" to="940" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moments of the Boltzmann distribution for RNA secondary structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Miklos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bull. Math. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1031" to="1047" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparative method for finding and folding RNA secondary structures within protein-coding regions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Pedersen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4925" to="4936" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Noncoding RNA gene detection using comparative sequence analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Rivas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Eddy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2 8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An enhanced MITOMAP with a global mtDNA mutational phylogeny</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Ruiz-Pesini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="823" to="828" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RDMAS: a web server for RNA deleterious mutation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Shu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">404</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient algorithms for probing the RNA mutation landscape</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Waldispuhl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNAmutants: a web server to explore the mutational landscape of RNA secondary structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Waldispuhl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="286" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The protein factors MBNL1 and U2AF65 bind alternative RNA structures to regulate splicing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Warf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9203" to="9208" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping of conserved RNA secondary structures predicts thousands of functional noncoding RNAs in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Washietl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1383" to="1390" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nearest-neighbor thermodynamics of deoxyinosine pairs in DNA duplexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Watkins</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Santalucia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6258" to="6267" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mitochondrial tRNA mutations: clinical and functional perturbations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Zifa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RNA Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="66" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithms and thermodynamics for RNA secondary structure prediction: a practical guide</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Zuker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RNA Biochemistry and Biotechnology. NATO Science Series</title>
		<editor>Barciszewski,J. and Clark,B.F.C.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>