
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:34+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis RDP3: a flexible and fast computer program for analyzing recombination</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">19 2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Darren</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Martin</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>darrenpatrickmartin@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Infectious Disease and Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Computational Biology Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cape Town</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for High Performance Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Cape Town</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Rosebank, South Africa</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Philippe</forename>
								<surname>Lemey</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Microbiology and Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Rega Institute, K.U. Leuven</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Martin</forename>
								<surname>Lott</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Infectious Disease and Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Computational Biology Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cape Town</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for High Performance Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Cape Town</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Rosebank, South Africa</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computing Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of East Anglia</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>NR4 7TJ</postCode>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Vincent</forename>
								<surname>Moulton</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computing Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of East Anglia</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>NR4 7TJ</postCode>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<surname>Posada</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry, Genetics and Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Vigo</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pierre</forename>
								<surname>Lefeuvre</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Infectious Disease and Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Computational Biology Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cape Town</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CIRAD</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Pôle de Protection des Plantes</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">PVBMT CIRAD-Université de la Réunion</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ligne Paradis</addrLine>
									<country>La Réunion</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequence analysis RDP3: a flexible and fast computer program for analyzing recombination</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2462" to="2463"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">19 2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq467</idno>
					<note>[13:51 28/8/2010 Bioinformatics-btq467.tex] Page: 2462 2462–2463 Associate Editor: Martin Bishop Availability: RDP3 is available for free from its web site Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>RDP3 is a new version of the RDP program for characterizing recombination events in DNA-sequence alignments. Among other novelties, this version includes four new recombination analysis methods (3SEQ, VISRD, PHYLRO and LDHAT), new tests for recombination hot-spots, a range of matrix methods for visualizing overall patterns of recombination within datasets and recombination-aware ancestral sequence reconstruction. Complementary to a high degree of analysis flow automation, RDP3 also has a highly interactive and detailed graphical user interface that enables more focused hands-on cross-checking of results with a wide variety of newly implemented phylogenetic tree construction and matrix-based recombination signal visualization methods. The new RDP3 can accommodate large datasets and is capable of analyzing alignments ranging in size from 1000×10 kilobase sequences to 20×2 megabase sequences within 48 h on a desktop PC. Supplementary information: The RDP3 program manual contains detailed descriptions of the various methods it implements and a step-by-step guide describing how best to use these.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">NEW FEATURES IN RPD3</head><p>Although the graphically intensive and highly interactive rpd3 interface remains superficially unchanged from that of its predecessor, rpd2 (<ref type="bibr">Martin et al., 2005a, b</ref>), it includes simple point-and-click access to a multitude of powerful new features. Among these are three new non-parametric recombination detection methods (3seq, visrd and phylpro;<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Boni et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Lemey et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Weiller, 1998</ref>), a parametric recombination rate estimation method (ldhat;<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">McVean et al., 2004</ref>), two new tree construction methods (Maximum likelihood with phyml and Bayesian with mrbayes;<ref type="bibr">Guindon and Gascual, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Ronquist and Huelsenbeck, 2003</ref>), two recombination hotspot-tests (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Heath et al., 2006</ref>), a test of recombination induced protein mis-folding (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Lefeuvre et al., 2007</ref>;<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Voigt et al., 2002</ref>), recombination-aware methods for reconstructing ancestral sequences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arenas and Posada et al., 2010</ref>) and a range of matrix methods for visualizing overall patterns of recombination within datasets (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Jakobsen and Easteal, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Lefeuvre et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">McVean et al., 2004</ref>). In addition to the new methods implemented in rpd3, another important improvement over rpd2 is the way in which rpd3 automatically scans alignments for recombination signals and then infers the minimum numbers of recombination events needed to account for these signals. rpd3 implements a range of heuristic recombinant sequence identification methods based on the phylpro (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Weiller, 1998</ref>), visrd (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Lemey et al., 2009</ref>) and subtree-prune and regraft methods (that identify recombinants sequences as those which 'jump' between the branches of phylogenetic trees constructed from different fragments of the same sequence alignment;<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Beiko and Hamilton, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Heath et al., 2006</ref>). rdp3 also automatically checks detected recombination signals to determine whether they might not be better accounted for by sequence misalignment than recombination. Misalignments introduce homoplasy and are a common cause of false positive recombination signals. Misalignments are automatically detected in rpd3 by separately realigning recombinant sequences with each of their identified parents (rpd3 uses clustalw to do this;<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chenna et al., 2003</ref>) and comparing these pair-wise alignments to those of the corresponding sequence pairs in the full multiple sequence alignment. By more accurately identifying recombinant sequences and discounting recombination signals attributable to sequence misalignments, rpd3 significantly outperforms rdp2 for overall quantitative assessments of recombination patterns such as those carried out in the new breakpoint hot-spot and protein folding disruption tests. In addition to streamlined tools for managing, testing and editing information on detected recombination events, rpd3 also provides a range of new tools for users to cross-check how accurately the program has identified (i) groups of recombinants supposedly sharing traces of the same recombination events; (ii) recombinant and parental sequences; and (iii) recombination breakpoint positions. These include heat-plots indicating how closely the recombination patterns in two recombinants resemble one another in relation to their supposed parental sequences, color coded phylogenetic trees for identifying recombinants and parental sequences and maxchi (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Maynard Smith, 1992</ref>) and lard (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Holmes et al., 1999</ref>) breakpoint matrices for manually identifying breakpoint positions. All of the automated recombination detection methods in rpd3 have been rigorously speed optimized and as a result the program is able to analyze datasets containing up to 40 million nt within 48 h on a standard 2 GHz processor with 2 GB of RAM. Such large datasets might, for example, consist of 20 full bacterial genome sequences, or 1000 full viral genome sequences. With default program settings datasets containing 100 10 kb long sequences can be analyzed within 10 min.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RDP3: a flexible and fast computer program</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>[13:51 28/8/2010 Bioinformatics-btq467.tex] Page: 2463 2462–2463</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: Wellcome Trust (to D.P.M.); Postdoctoral fellowship from the Fund for Scientific Research (FWO) Flanders (to Ph.L.); South African Centre of High Performance Computing bursary (to M.L.); European Research Council (ERC-2007-Stg 203161-PHYGENOM to D.P.); Spanish Ministry of Science and Education (BFU200908611 to D.P.); GIS CRVOI (grant NPRAO/AIRD/CRVOI/08/03 to Pi.L.); Wellcome Trust (grant number GR079127MA). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. sequence alignments with (i) recombinant sequences removed; (ii) recombinationally derived tracts of sequence removed; or (iii) recombinant sequences split into their constituent parts. An important strength of rdp3 that makes it applicable to a variety of recombination analysis problems is that, unlike many other recombination detection programs such as simplot (Lole et al.,1999), dual brothers (Minin et al., 2005), jphmm (Schultz et al., 2006) or scueal (Kosakovsky et al., 2009), it does not screen predefined sets of potentially recombinant (or query) sequences against other predefined sets of non-recombinant (or reference) sequences. rdp3 instead treats every sequence within an input alignment as a potential recombinant and systematically screens large numbers of sequence triplets and/or quartets to identify sets of three or four sequences that contain a recombinant and two sequences resembling its parents. Such an approach means that rdp3 can simultaneously detect the entire scope of recombination evident within a dataset (i.e. not just that occurring between the reference strains or species) enabling its use in the characterization of complex recombinants such as those derived through recombination between parental sequences that were themselves recombinant. The drawback of such a flexible, exploratory framework is that it can often be difficult to assess the uncertainty associated with inferred recombination patterns. However, with its wide range of cross-checking tools, rpd3 is complementary to probabilistic recombination analysis approaches.</note>

			<note place="foot">© The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of recombination on the reconstruction of ancestral sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Arenas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Posada</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">184</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1133" to="1139" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic identification of lateral genetic transfer events</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Beiko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Hamilton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An exact nonparametric method for inferring mosaic structure in sequence triplets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Boni</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">176</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1035" to="1047" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple sequence alignment with the Clustal series of programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Chenna</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3497" to="3500" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sister-scanning: a Monte Carlo procedure for assessing signals in recombinant sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Gibbs</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="573" to="582" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A. simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Guindon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Gascuel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="696" to="704" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recombination patterns in aphthoviruses mirror those found in other picornaviruses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Heath</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Virol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11827" to="11832" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic evidence for recombination in dengue virus</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Holmes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="409" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A program for calculating and displaying compatibility matrices as an aid in determining reticulate evolution in molecular sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Jakobsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Easteal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Appl. Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="295" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An evolutionary model-based algorithm for accurate phylogenetic breakpoint mapping and subtype prediction in HIV-1</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Kosakovsky</forename>
				<surname>Pond</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000581</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Avoidance of protein fold disruption in natural virus recombinants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Lefeuvre</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Pathog</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">181</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Widely conserved recombination patterns among singlestranded DNA viruses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Lefeuvre</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Virol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2697" to="2707" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying recombinants in human and primate immunodeficiency virus sequence alignments using quartet scanning</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Lemey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">126</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Full-length human immunodeficiency virus type 1 genomes from subtype C-infected seroconverters in India, with evidence of intersubtype recombination</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Lole</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Virol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="152" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RDP2: recombination detection and analysis from sequence alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Martin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="260" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A modified bootscan algorithm for automated identification of recombinant sequences and recombination breakpoints</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Martin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AIDS Res. Hum. Retrovir</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="98" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing the mosaic structure of genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Maynard</forename>
				<surname>Smith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The fine-scale structure of recombination rate variation in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Mcvean</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">304</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="581" to="584" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dual multiple change-point model leads to more accurate recombination detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Minin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3034" to="3042" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Possible emergence of new geminiviruses by frequent recombination</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Padidam</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Virology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">265</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="218" to="225" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of methods for detecting recombination from DNA sequences: computer simulations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Posada</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Crandall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 98</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13757" to="13762" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MrBayes 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference under mixed models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Ronquist</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Huelsenbeck</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1572" to="1574" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A jumping profile Hidden Markov Model and applications to recombination sites in HIV and HCV genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Schultz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">265</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein building blocks preserved by recombination</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Voigt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="553" to="558" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic profiles: a graphical method for detecting genetic recombinations in homologous sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Weiller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>