
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:38+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Real-time multi-view deconvolution</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Benjamin</forename>
								<surname>Schmid</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>bschmid@mpi-cbg.de or huisken@mpi-cbg.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>01307</postCode>
									<settlement>Dresden</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jan</forename>
								<surname>Huisken</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>01307</postCode>
									<settlement>Dresden</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Real-time multi-view deconvolution</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv387</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on March 25, 2015; revised on June 15, 2015; accepted on June 20, 2015</note>
					<note>Bioimage informatics *To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Robert Murphy Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>In light-sheet microscopy, overall image content and resolution are improved by acquiring and fusing multiple views of the sample from different directions. State-of-the-art multi-view (MV) deconvolution simultaneously fuses and deconvolves the images in 3D, but processing takes a multiple of the acquisition time and constitutes the bottleneck in the imaging pipeline. Here, we show that MV deconvolution in 3D can finally be achieved in real-time by processing cross-sectional planes individually on the massively parallel architecture of a graphics processing unit (GPU). Our approximation is valid in the typical case where the rotation axis lies in the imaging plane. Availability and implementation: Source code and binaries are available on github (https://github. com/bene51/), native code under the repository &apos;gpu_deconvolution&apos;, Java wrappers implementing Fiji plugins under &apos;SPIM_Reconstruction_Cuda&apos;. Contact:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>MV imaging is particularly useful in light-sheet microscopy where consecutive views are acquired in short succession, allowing reconstruction of entire developing organisms without artifacts (<ref type="bibr">Huisken et al., 2004</ref>). Due to the low photo-toxicity in light sheet microscopy, time-lapse experiments are oftentimes run over days and terabytes of data accumulate quickly. MV fusion is therefore particularly desirable to be performed in real-time to eliminate redundant information from different views. Best fusion results, however, are achieved by combining fusion with 3D deconvolution (<ref type="bibr">Swoger et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Verveer et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wu et al., 2013</ref>). Although efficient Bayesian MV deconvolution based on the Richardson–Lucy (RL) algorithm has been shown recently to outperform existing methods in terms of fusion quality and convergence speed, it is still too slow for real-time processing of typical data volumes (<ref type="bibr">Preibisch et al., 2014</ref>). The RL deconvolution iterations consist only of convolutions and pixel-wise arithmetic operations and could therefore be significantly accelerated using dedicated hardware such as a graphics processing unit (GPU). The large memory requirements of MV deconvolution, however, exceed the limited resources of modern GPUs even for moderate data sizes (Supplementary Note S1). Previous attempts therefore required splitting the data into blocks of appropriate size. Each block then either had to be transferred to and from the GPU in each RL iteration (<ref type="bibr">Preibisch et al., 2014</ref>), or blocks needed to share a considerable amount of overlap to avoid border artifacts (<ref type="bibr">Temerinac-Ott et al., 2011</ref>). Therefore, GPU-based implementations only achieved a three-times performance gain (<ref type="bibr">Preibisch et al., 2014</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Results</head><p>The primary goal of MV fusion is the improvement of the poor axial resolution in a single 3D dataset using the superior lateral resolution of an additional, overlapping dataset, and not necessarily to improve resolution beyond the intrinsic lateral resolution. We therefore approximated the full 3D point spread function (PSF) with a 2D PSF, neglecting one lateral component (along the rotation axis), and processed each plane orthogonal to the rotation axis independently (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1a</ref>). Memory requirements were thereby reduced by the number of lines read out from the camera chip, i.e. typically 100–1000 fold (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1b</ref>). This allowed us to implement the entire MV deconvolution on a GPU. Taking advantage of three CUDA (Compute Unified Device Architecture) streams, we interleaved GPU V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3398</head><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.computations with data transfers, such that not only expensive copying to and from GPU memory, but also reading and writing data from and to the hard drive came without additional cost (Supplementary Note S2). Compared with 3D MV deconvolution, with and without GPU support, we thereby reduced processing times by a factor of up to 25 and 75, respectively (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1c</ref>, Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>), while producing comparable results. We compared the results of our implementation to the methods commonly used in the light-sheet community, such as established 3D deconvolution (<ref type="bibr">Preibisch et al., 2014</ref>), averaging and entropybased fusion (<ref type="bibr">Preibisch et al., 2010</ref>) (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1d</ref>–i). Both averaging and entropy-based fusion were blurry and showed cross-shaped artifacts, originating from the elongated PSFs along the optical axes. Three dimensional deconvolution and our plane-wise variant reduced artifacts and enhanced the contrast, thus truly improving the resolution in the fused dataset (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1h</ref>and i; Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S1</ref>). Although registration of the different views is still required, it can be performed in pre-processing before starting a time-lapse experiment, due to the repeatability of high-quality microscope stages. Multi-view deconvolution can then be performed in real time directly as the data is transferred from the camera. We provide our software as a C library that can be directly linked to camera acquisition software for real-time processing, and as plugins for Fiji (<ref type="bibr">Schindelin et al., 2012</ref>) (Supplementary Material).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Validation</head><p>Our plane-wise deconvolution approximates 3D deconvolution by neglecting the contribution of the PSF along the rotation axis. It is therefore suited for systems with a single rotation axis lying within the imaging plane. Using artificial data (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>and<ref type="figure">Table S2</ref>), we confirmed the applicability of our approximation even if the rotation axis is slightly tilted (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>). Its validity is independent of the amount of noise (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig.   S4</ref>), but depends on the lateral extents of the PSF. Keeping its axial standard deviation fixed at eight pixels, a typical value measured on our microscopes, we found that up to a lateral standard deviation of 2–3 pixels, results from plane-wise and 3D deconvolution are undistinguishable (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S5</ref>). The measured lateral standard deviation of the PSF was typically between 1.5 and 1.8 pixels on our microscopes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusion</head><p>The photo-efficiency of light-sheet microscopy enables long timelapse imaging of living samples to study fundamental questions in developmental biology. However, its huge data rates also open new challenges for data processing. A key problem in light-sheet microscopy has been the fusion of data recorded from multiple angles. In this article, we presented a new method that performs MV deconvolution plane-wise, which reduces memory requirements compared with existing methods and thus permits an entirely GPU-based implementation. The achieved acceleration makes MV deconvolution for the first time applicable in real-time without the need for data cropping or resampling.</p><formula>(d) (f)</formula><p>Averaged</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Bioinformatics, 31(20), 2015, 3398–3400doi:10.</head><figDesc>1093/bioinformatics/btv387 Advance Access Publication Date: 25 June 2015 Applications Note</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Schindelin,J. et al. (2012)</head><figDesc>Fiji: an open-source platform for biological-image analysis. Nat. Methods, 9, 676–682. Swoger,J. et al. (2007) Multi-view image fusion improves resolution in threedimensional microscopy. Opt. Express, 15, 8029–8042. Temerinac-Ott,M. et al. (2011) Spatially-variant Lucy-Richardson deconvolution for multiview fusion of microscopical 3D images. In: Proceedings of the IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging, pp. 899–904. Verveer,P.J. et al. (2007) High-resolution three-dimensional imaging of large specimens with light sheet-based microscopy. Nat. Methods, 4, 311–313. Wu,Y. et al. (2013) Spatially isotropic four-dimensional imaging with dual-view plane illumination microscopy. Nat. Biotechnol., 31, 1032– 1038.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">B.Schmid and J.Huisken at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgement</head><p>We thank all members of the Huisken lab for stimulating discussions.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>