
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:41+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Rgb: a scriptable genome browser for R</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sylvain</forename>
								<surname>Mareschal</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>maressyl@gmail.com or fabrice.jardin@chb.unicancer.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 918</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Centre Henri Becquerel</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INSERM</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76038, Cedex 1</postCode>
									<settlement>Rouen, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Normandy University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Rouen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76821</postCode>
									<settlement>Mont-Saint-Aignan, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Research and Innovation in Biomedicine (IRIB)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Haute-Normandie</addrLine>
									<postCode>76183</postCode>
									<settlement>Rouen Cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Sydney</forename>
								<surname>Dubois</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 918</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Centre Henri Becquerel</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INSERM</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76038, Cedex 1</postCode>
									<settlement>Rouen, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Normandy University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Rouen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76821</postCode>
									<settlement>Mont-Saint-Aignan, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Research and Innovation in Biomedicine (IRIB)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Haute-Normandie</addrLine>
									<postCode>76183</postCode>
									<settlement>Rouen Cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Thierry</forename>
								<surname>Lecroq</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Normandy University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Rouen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76821</postCode>
									<settlement>Mont-Saint-Aignan, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Research and Innovation in Biomedicine (IRIB)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Haute-Normandie</addrLine>
									<postCode>76183</postCode>
									<settlement>Rouen Cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LITIS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">INSA</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4108, 76801</postCode>
									<settlement>Saint-Etienne-du-Rouvray</settlement>
									<region>EA</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Associate Editor: Inanc Birol</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Fabrice</forename>
								<surname>Jardin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 918</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Centre Henri Becquerel</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INSERM</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76038, Cedex 1</postCode>
									<settlement>Rouen, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Normandy University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Rouen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76821</postCode>
									<settlement>Mont-Saint-Aignan, France</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Research and Innovation in Biomedicine (IRIB)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Haute-Normandie</addrLine>
									<postCode>76183</postCode>
									<settlement>Rouen Cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis Rgb: a scriptable genome browser for R</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2204" to="2205"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu185</idno>
					<note type="submission">Advance Access publication April 9, 2014 Received on December 20, 2013; revised on March 3, 2014; accepted on April 2, 2014</note>
					<note>Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Thanks to its free licensing and the development of initiatives like Bioconductor, R has become an essential part of the bio-informatics toolbox in the past years and is more and more confronted with genomically located data. While separate solutions are available to manipulate and visualize such data, no R package currently offers the efficiency required for computationally intensive tasks such as interactive genome browsing. The package proposed here fulfills this specific need, providing a multilevel interface suitable for most needs, from a completely interfaced genome browser to low-level classes and methods. Its time and memory efficiency have been challenged in a human dataset, where it outperformed existing solutions by several orders of magnitude. Availability and implementation: R sources and packages are freely available at the CRAN repository and dedicated Web site: http://bio-informatics.ovsa.fr/Rgb. Distributed under the GPL 3 license, compatible with most operating systems (Windows, Linux, Mac OS) and architectures. Contact:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The growing demand from the biology community for statistically robust approaches has made the R statistics-oriented scripting language an essential part of the bioinformatics toolbox. Its graphical capabilities make it a valuable tool to produce publication-grade complex figures, whereas its computational efficiency allows it to handle huge datasets, as currently required in fields like transcriptomics or next-generation sequencing. These qualities come with an open-source licensing and various operating system ports that make it available virtually everywhere. Thanks to the Bioconductor initiative (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Gentleman et al., 2004</ref>), large amount of software is freely available as R packages for tasks as diverse as microarray processing (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Smyth, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Venkatraman and Olshen, 2007</ref>), feature annotation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Zhang et al., 2003</ref>) or sequence analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Anders and Huber, 2010</ref>). Much of this software generates genomic data, i.e. lists of chromosome regions defined by starting and ending coordinates. Such data are usually subset using chromosomal coordinates rather than row indexes, a paradigm R was not developed to deal with. Bioconductor historically addressed this issue with the RangedData class from the IRanges package, handling genomic regions as ranges of integers (base positions). Its flexibility and efficiency were extended a few years later by the GenomicRanges package, making direct use of IRanges components for the subsetting. For visualization, Bioconductor provides two solutions: rtracklayer and GViz. The former sends data to visualize to the UCSC web genome browser (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Kent et al., 2002</ref>), a model that implies frequent comings and goings between programs and consequent network burden. The latter is more integrated within Bioconductor and produces static graphics from the classes described above, in delays incompatible with user interactivity and intensive computing. The package described here reconciles these two aspects in a coherent way, thus offering an interactive interface responsive enough for comfortable browsing and atomic operations suitable for computer-intensive algorithms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>Rgb is implemented as an R package, providing various classes and methods for scripts. It makes use of the Reference class system, which offers an object-oriented framework similar to what can be found in other languages such as Java or Cþþ. It is flexible enough to suit the needs of the four categories of R users: R beginners will find in Rgb a complete graphical user interface (GUI) allowing them to convert and visualize genomic data without any command line. Stand-alone builds of Rgb can even make the R dependency totally transparent. Script writers, needing an exclusive Command Line Interface to automate analysis, will find in Rgb classes and methods able to handle their genomic data and produce high-quality graphics from them.</p><p>Console users who use R as an exploratory tool without a special need for reproducibility, will find Rgb's ability to mix the two interfaces particularly time saving.</p><p>Package developers may be interested in extending classes to handle new data storage modes or representations, a process greatly facilitated by the object-oriented design of Rgb.</p><p>The core of the subsetting system consists of a collection of C functions making direct use of R libraries, and the graphical interface relies on Tcl-tk. Both of them are natively managed *To whom correspondence should be addressed. by R, and have been successfully compiled and tested on Windows and Linux operating systems. BAM file support can be added by the Rsamtools package, which is part of Bioconductor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">PERFORMANCES</head><p>To assert Rgb's track.table class suitability for computer-intensive tasks such as responsive genome browsing or overlap computation, its time and maximal memory consumption on usual atomic tasks were compared with existing solutions: standard R data.frame, the more efficient data.table, IRanges' RangedData, GenomicRanges' GRanges and GViz's AnnotationTrack. Three tasks were monitored as the most common atomic operations in such data: genomic extraction by chromosomal coordinates, extraction and modification of consecutive rows by indexes. The 291 128 exons recorded in the CCDS database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Pruitt et al., 2009</ref>) for the human genome were used as a common dataset. Benchmarking was performed on a mid-range desktop computer (3.1 GHz Intel i3-2100 processor with 8 GB RAM) running R 3.0.2 in a 64-bit Fedora 18 distribution. Each measure was made with R functions proc.time and gc in a fresh session, to normalize garbage collection effects (scripts and dataset available as Supplementary Data).</p><p>With the genomic extraction task (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>), GViz and RangedData proved their unsuitability to intensive tasks, with computing times nearing the second for a single extraction (typical genome browser representations contain several tracks to be subset), and extravagant memory usage (hundreds of Mio for a dataset of 30 Mio). GRanges and generic R solutions perform better, but are still outperformed by Rgb by a magnitude of 50– 1500 on small genomic extractions. Similar results can be observed with the modification task, with Rgb outperforming R generic classes by a factor of 100 in time consumption and 10 in memory usage. It still outperforms bioinformatic solutions with the last task, but is overtaken here by generic solutions such as data.frame and data.table. However, as this kind of extraction is far less justified in a genomic context than the previous one, this average performance can be accepted.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Performance comparison of Rgb's track.table class with existing software. Three atomic tasks were benchmarked on a common dataset, in terms of maximal memory usage and computing time, as recorded by R</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> CONCLUSION Rgb provides several entry points to a consistent genome browsing system, which may prove equally useful to users looking for an interactive genome browser able to handle their R datasets and developers needing efficient genomic subsetting capabilities for their scripts. Its object-oriented paradigm and open-source licensing make it easily extendable, and its performances over existing solutions have been proven in a real genomic dataset.</note>

			<note place="foot">Rgb at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank Christian Bastard for his helpful comments and feedback during Rgb development and the many CGHarray datasets he provided for testing.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Anders</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Huber</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bioconductor: open software development for computational biology and bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Gentleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">80</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human genome browser at UCSC</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Kent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="996" to="1006" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The consensus coding sequence (CCDS) project: identifying a common protein-coding gene set for the human and mouse genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Pruitt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1316" to="1323" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">limma: linear models for microarray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Smyth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Gentleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics and Computational Biology Solutions Using R and Bioconductor Statistics for Biology and Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="420" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A faster circular binary segmentation algorithm for the analysis of array CGH data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Venkatraman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Olshen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="657" to="663" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An extensible application for assembling annotation for genomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Zhang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">155</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>