
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:43+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics RNA structure framework: automated transcriptome-wide reconstruction of RNA secondary structures from high-throughput structure probing data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Danny</forename>
								<surname>Incarnato</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Human Genetics Foundation (HuGeF)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10126</postCode>
									<settlement>Torino</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dipartimento di Scienze della Vita e Biologia dei Sistemi</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Università di Torino</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10123</postCode>
									<settlement>Torino</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Francesco</forename>
								<surname>Neri</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Human Genetics Foundation (HuGeF)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10126</postCode>
									<settlement>Torino</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Francesca</forename>
								<surname>Anselmi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Human Genetics Foundation (HuGeF)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10126</postCode>
									<settlement>Torino</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dipartimento di Scienze della Vita e Biologia dei Sistemi</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Università di Torino</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10123</postCode>
									<settlement>Torino</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Salvatore</forename>
								<surname>Oliviero</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Human Genetics Foundation (HuGeF)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10126</postCode>
									<settlement>Torino</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dipartimento di Scienze della Vita e Biologia dei Sistemi</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Università di Torino</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10123</postCode>
									<settlement>Torino</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural bioinformatics RNA structure framework: automated transcriptome-wide reconstruction of RNA secondary structures from high-throughput structure probing data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv571</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on June 2, 2015; revised on August 31, 2015; accepted on September 27, 2015</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The rapidly increasing number of discovered non-coding RNAs makes the understanding of their structure a key feature toward a deeper comprehension of gene expression regulation. Various enzymatic-and chemically-based approaches have been recently developed to allow whole-genome studies of RNA secondary structures. Several methods have been recently presented that allow high-throughput RNA structure probing (CIRS-seq, Structure-seq, SHAPE-seq, PARS, etc.) and unbiased structural inference of residues within RNAs in their native conformation. We here present an analysis toolkit, named RNA Structure Framework (RSF), which allows fast and fully-automated analysis of high-throughput structure probing data, from data pre-processing to whole-transcriptome RNA structure inference. Availability and implementation: RSF is written in Perl and is freely available under the GPLv3 license from http://rsf.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The advent of high-throughput methods has rapidly led to the annotation of thousands of novel transcripts (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Derrien et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Djebali et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">ENCODE Project Consortium et al., 2012</ref>), mostly lacking coding capabilities (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bá nfai et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Guttman et al., 2013</ref>). As for large ribonucleoprotein complexes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Krummel et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Nagai et al., 2001</ref>), these RNAs are thought to regulate gene expression through interactions mediated by their structure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Tsai et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wang and Chang, 2011</ref>). In the last years, a variety of methods have been developed to interrogate RNA secondary structures on a genome-wide scale (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Ding et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Incarnato et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Kertesz et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Li et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Lucks et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Rouskin et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Underwood et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Wan et al., 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Wan et al., , 2014</ref>), but no tool has been developed to enable efficient analysis of the large amount of data generated by these methods, with the exception of the SeqFold package, which has been developed to analyze PARS data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Ouyang et al., 2013</ref>). Because the analysis of these data and the subsequent inference of RNA structures constitute a bottle-neck of these protocols, we here provide the RNA Structure Framework (RSF), an open-source framework to analyze highthroughput structure probing data (SPD), and to minimize the efforts to get from raw sequencing reads to secondary structures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Implementation</head><p>RSF is implemented in Perl as a modular package. An outline of a sample RSF data analysis workflow is shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. Detailed information on the core modules is provided in the Supplementary material, as well in the package archive. RSF is composed of three core modules, and a number of other utilities. The reference-builder module builds the transcriptome reference used in the read-mapping step. This module requires an Internet connection to query the UCSC genome SQL database (http://genome.ucsc.edu) and obtain transcript annotation. Because the reference-builder module also requires the genome reference sequence for the species of interest, this can be either provided by the user in multi-FASTA format, or can be automatically downloaded from the UCSC DAS server (http://genome.ucsc.edu/cgi-bin/das/). The analyzer module is the core of the framework. It requires a reference index, and a set of at least 2 FastQ files (3 for CIRS-seq), one for each condition (e.g. non-treated control and DMS treatment). Reads are pre-processed using the FASTX Toolkit (http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit/) to clip adapter sequences, while mapping of reads on the reference index is performed using the Bowtie v1 tool (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Langmead et al., 2009</ref>). Alternatively, the user can use different tools for reads mapping, and then provide to the module the SAM files instead of FastQ files. Following the mapping step, reads are sorted and the number of reads mapping at each position of each transcript are calculated in the provided conditions. Because each read gives information only on the base immediately preceding the start mapping position (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>), the module automatically accounts for eventual trimming of bases from the 5 0 of the read. Once raw counts have been computed, the analyzer module calculates normalized raw reactivity scores using one of two possible scoring schemes. The first scheme (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Incarnato et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Kertesz et al., 2010</ref>) assumes an uniform distribution of read mappings across samples, but it is more susceptible to cross-sample variations since it uses the total number of mapped reads to normalize libraries for different sequencing depths. The second scheme (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Ding et al., 2014</ref>) instead, is less affected by sample-to-sample variations in the distribution of read mappings, as it performs per-transcript normalization by considering the average number of RT-stops across the transcript being analyzed. Finally, overall reactivities for each position of each analyzed transcript are normalized to values ranging from 0 (less singlestranded) to 1 (more single-stranded). The analyzer module actually incorporates three different normalization methods: 2–8% normalization (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Lucks et al., 2011</ref>), 90% winsorising (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Incarnato et al., 2014</ref>) and Box-plot normalization (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Low and Weeks, 2010</ref>). For each transcript being analyzed, the module reports data in a textbased SPD file (see Supplementary materials). The third, and last, core component of the toolkit is the structure-deconvolver module. This module takes a set of SPD files and de-convolutes RNA structures from experimental data, using one of three different approaches (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>): (i) Hard-constrained structure prediction using the ViennaRNA package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Lorenz et al., 2011</ref>), (ii) Soft-constrained structure prediction using the RNAstructure tool (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Reuter and Mathews, 2010</ref>) or an (iii) Iterative cluster-refinement approach. The hard constraint method uses the ViennaRNA package to predict a minimum free energy structure by imposing the constraint that RNA positions exceeding a given reactivity cutoff (default: 0.7) must be unpaired. The soft constraint approach uses instead the whole set of reactivity data for an RNA, by first converting it into a SHAPE data file (using the spd2shape utility provided with the RSF package), that can be supplied to the RNAstructure software. RNAstructure then uses this data to compute a pseudo-energy term to adjust the free energy of individual nucleotides (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Deigan et al., 2009</ref>). The third approach (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>), instead, is a variant of that employed by SeqFold (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Ouyang et al., 2013</ref>) software. Briefly, the partition folding for the RNA is computed using the ViennaRNA package, then a backtracking through the Boltzmann ensemble of structures is performed, and structures are then clustered using Hamming distance, with a low-stringency cutoff (default: distance ¼ 0.5). The base-pair probability profile for each cluster is then calculated, and the cluster that better correlates to RNA reactivity data is selected. Following the best-fitting cluster selection, the cluster is iteratively refined by performing a progressively more stringent clustering (default: distance ¼ distance À 0.01), followed by the subtraction of individual structures that contribute to lower the correlation coefficient. Finally, the higher-correlation cluster of structures (Boltzmann sub-ensemble) is returned, as well as the minimum expected accuracy structure for the RNA (defined as the structure in which only the concordant base-pairs in at least the 50% of cluster structures are reported). Predicted structures can be reported in dot-bracket or connectivity table notations, as well as in PostScript or SVG graphical formats. Additional tools and utilities are also shipped with the RSF package, and are described in the Supplementary material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Conclusion</head><p>The advent of high-througput RNA structure probing methods has provided a large amount of transcriptome-wide scale structural data, although robust tools for the rapid elaboration of this information are currently missing. RSF is a user-friendly toolkit that enables automated inference of RNA secondary structures on a transcriptome-wide scale, in a few steps. It can use data derived from many different structure probing methods, both chemical (CIRS-seq, SHAPE-seq, Structure-seq) and enzymatic (PARS). Due to the rapid evolution of the field, and to the absence of a golden standard in the analysis of high-throughput SPD, the implementation of several different scoring, normalization and structure prediction methods enables a high degree of analysis flexibility to the user. The use of high-throughput structure probing methodologies coupled to RSF provides an important toolkit for the genome-wide analysis of RNA structures.</p><p>Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Overview of the RSF pipeline</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 459 Bioinformatics, 32(3), 2016, 459–461 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv571 Advance Access Publication Date: 19 October 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">D.Incarnato et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long noncoding RNAs are rarely translated in two human cell lines</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Bá Nfai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1646" to="1657" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate SHAPE-directed RNA structure determination</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Deigan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="102" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The GENCODE v7 catalog of human long noncoding RNAs: analysis of their gene structure, evolution, and expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Derrien</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1775" to="1789" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vivo genome-wide profiling of RNA secondary structure reveals novel regulatory features</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Ding</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">505</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="696" to="700" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Landscape of transcription in human cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Djebali</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">489</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated encyclopedia of DNA elements in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Encode Project</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Consortium</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">489</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ribosome profiling provides evidence that large noncoding RNAs do not encode proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Guttman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="240" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide profiling of mouse RNA secondary structures reveals key features of the mammalian transcriptome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Incarnato</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">491</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide measurement of RNA secondary structure in yeast</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kertesz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">467</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure of spliceosomal ribonucleoproteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A P</forename>
				<surname>Krummel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">F1000 Biol. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Langmead</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global analysis of RNA secondary structure in two metazoans</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ViennaRNA Package 2.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Lorenz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Algorithms Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">26</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SHAPE-directed RNA secondary structure prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Low</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Weeks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiplexed RNA structure characterization with selective 2 0-hydroxyl acylation analyzed by primer extension sequencing (SHAPE-Seq)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Lucks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11063" to="11068" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and assembly of the spliceosomal snRNPs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Nagai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. Soc. Trans</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SeqFold: genome-scale reconstruction of RNA secondary structure integrating high-throughput sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Ouyang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="377" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNAstructure: software for RNA secondary structure prediction and analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Reuter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Mathews</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">129</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide probing of RNA structure reveals active unfolding of mRNA structures in vivo</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Rouskin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">505</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="701" to="705" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long noncoding RNA as modular scaffold of histone modification complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M.-C</forename>
				<surname>Tsai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">329</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="689" to="693" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FragSeq: transcriptome-wide RNA structure probing using high-throughput sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Underwood</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="995" to="1001" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide measurement of RNA folding energies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="181" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Landscape and variation of RNA secondary structure across the human transcriptome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Wan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">505</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="706" to="709" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular mechanisms of long noncoding RNAs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Chang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="904" to="914" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>