
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:46+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Roundup 2.0: enabling comparative genomics for over 1800 genomes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Todd</forename>
								<forename type="middle">F</forename>
								<surname>Deluca</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>todd_deluca@hms.harvard.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Center for Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard Medical School</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jike</forename>
								<surname>Cui</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Center for Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard Medical School</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jae-Yoon</forename>
								<surname>Jung</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Center for Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard Medical School</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kristian</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Che</forename>
								<surname>St</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Center for Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard Medical School</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<surname>Gabriel</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Center for Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard Medical School</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Dennis</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P</forename>
								<surname>Wall</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Center for Biomedical Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard Medical School</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02115</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Roundup 2.0: enabling comparative genomics for over 1800 genomes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="715" to="716"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts006</idno>
					<note type="submission">Genome analysis Advance Access publication January 13, 2012 Received on August 27, 2011; revised on December 23, 2011; accepted on January 3, 2012</note>
					<note>[14:13 25/2/2012 Bioinformatics-bts006.tex] Page: 715 715–716 Associate Editor:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Roundup is an online database of gene orthologs for over 1800 genomes, including 226 Eukaryota, 1447 Bacteria, 113 Archaea and 21 Viruses. Orthologs are inferred using the Reciprocal Smallest Distance algorithm. Users may query Roundup for single-linkage clusters of orthologous genes based on any group of genomes. Annotated query results may be viewed in a variety of ways including as clusters of orthologs and as phylogenetic profiles. Genomic results may be downloaded in formats suitable for functional as well as phylogenetic analysis, including the recent OrthoXML standard. In addition, gene IDs can be retrieved using FASTA sequence search. All source code and orthologs are freely available. Availability: http://roundup.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Orthologs are genes from different organisms that descend from a single ancestral gene in the most recent common ancestor (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Fitch, 1970</ref>). In comparative genomics, they are used to infer the function of novel genes from the function of well-studied ones, to construct phylogenies and explore the evolution of genes and species, and to study sequence conservation and change. They are also valuable in analyzing gene networks, studying gene gain and loss, and finding genes in model organisms that correspond to human disease genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Altenhoff and Dessimoz 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gabaldon et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kristensen et al., 2011</ref>). Advances in high-throughput genomic sequencing have made it possible to produce many datasets in a relatively short time period. For example, from 2006 to 2011, the number of complete proteomes listed in UniProtKB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Magrane and Consortium, 2011</ref>), a repository of annotated protein sequences, has increased from around 300 to over 2500. To overcome the engineering challenges of computing and publishing orthologs for such a large number of genomes, we redesigned the comparative genomics tool, Roundup (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">DeLuca et al., 2006</ref>), to scale with the rate of genome sequencing and to enable increasingly more sophisticated comparative genomics analyses. Roundup 2.0 contains orthology data for over 1800 genomes, providing one of the largest diversities among similar</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>T.F.DeLuca et al.</head><p>merging two clusters if a gene in one of the clusters is orthologous to a gene in the other one. The result is that every gene in a group is orthologous to at least one other gene in the group and to no genes in any other groups. In contrast to other orthology databases (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chen et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Schneider et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Tatusov et al., 2003</ref>), Roundup orthologous groups are built on the fly using genomes selected by the user. This allows users to include exactly their genomes of interest and to explore the effects of including different genomes on the grouping of orthologs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">GENOMES AND ORTHOLOGS</head><p>The 1807 genomes in Roundup 2.0 are from UniProtKB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Magrane and Consortium, 2011</ref>), including 226 Eukaryota, 1447 Bacteria, 113 Archaea, 21 Viruses and Viroids. The approximately 63 CPU coreyears to compute the orthologs took several weeks on our research computing cluster. Roundup used a fault-tolerant computational pipeline to compute orthologs for all 1 631 721 pairs of genomes across 12 parameter combinations selected to allow researchers access to results for a broad range of divergence and E-value threshold settings. As a result, there are over 11 billion orthologs available in Roundup. The genomes and orthologs are updated 2–4 times per year.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">WEB INTERFACE</head><p>The Roundup website provides two ways to search for orthologs. First, the Browse query is a genome-centric search that retrieves all orthologs between one genome and a set of other genomes. Results can be filtered by gene name or gene identifier. To aid users in finding gene identifiers, a FASTA sequence may be used to retrieve a gene id. The second query, Retrieve, returns all orthologs for all pairs of genomes in a set of genomes the user specifies. Query results are then clustered into groups of orthologous genes as described above. All genes in the groups are linked to UniProt and annotated with available gene names and GO Process terms provided by UniProtKB and Gene Ontology (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Ashburner et al., 2000</ref>). FASTA sequences for genes in orthologous groups are also provided for further analysis. In addition to the standard view of search results, there are summaries by GO Terms and by Gene Clusters. The orthologous groups may be downloaded in several formats: NEXUS, PHYLIP, OrthoXML, Phylogenetic Profile and Text. OrthoXML (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Schmitt et al., 2011</ref>) is provided to support interoperability with other Orthology databases and the quest for orthologs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gabaldon et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kuzniar et al., 2008</ref>). Query results are cached for up to 30 days and may be retrieved by using the initial URL. To support research and replication, we make available for download from the website: FASTA sequences for genomes; orthologs in OrthoXML and text formats; and code for RSD and Roundup. Orthologs are also available through an HTTP-based API. Roundup 2.0 is an important step forward towards keeping pace with the rate of genome sequencing. The features and flexibility of Roundup 2.0, coupled with the wide coverage of genomes, enables increasingly large-scale comparative genomics analyses that address key questions in phylogeny, genome evolution and systems biology.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>[14:13 25/2/2012 Bioinformatics-bts006.tex] Page: 716 715–716</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. orthology databases (Chen et al., 2006; Datta et al., 2009; HuertaCepas et al., 2011; Kristensen et al., 2011; Li et al., 2006; Linard et al., 2011; Ostlund et al., 2010; Rouard et al., 2011; Schneider et al., 2007; Tatusov et al., 2003). Roundup compares well to other major databases, with recent studies showing similar ortholog composition for model organisms (Altenhoff and Dessimoz, 2009; Chen et al., 2007). The data in Roundup include clusters of orthologs for a wide range of sequence conservation, allowing searches for distant orthologs, and also phylogenetic profiles that enable functional investigation, phylogenetic analysis and prediction of network organization (Cui et al., 2011). 2 ALGORITHMS We used the reciprocal smallest distance (RSD) (Wall et al., 2003) algorithm to infer orthologs. RSD improves the sensitivity of reciprocal best blast hits by considering global alignment and maximum likelihood evolutionary distance between sequences. As a pairwise orthology algorithm, RSD scales quadratically with the number of genomes in Roundup. Altenhoff et al. assessed 10 ortholog inference projects and methods, confirming the reliable performance of RSD over a wide array of genomes from the tree of life (Altenhoff and Dessimoz, 2009). For Roundup 2.0, we changed RSD to improve its speed, stability and ortholog inference. We replaced WU-BLAST (W.Gish, personal communication) with NCBI BLAST (Altschul et al., 1990). Also, we replaced ClustalW (Thompson et al., 1994) with Kalign (Lassmann and Sonnhammer, 2005). Kalign is faster than ClustalW and produces better alignments for more distantly related sequences. This change resulted in 9% closer maximum likelihood distances between orthologs computed using PAML 4.0 (Yang, 2007), and 0.3% more orthologs on average. Since the Roundup database stores orthologs for 12 combinations of divergence and E-value thresholds, RSD was modified to compute orthologs for any number of parameter combinations as quickly as for one parameter combination. This change should be of interest to researchers investigating the effect of different parameter settings and degree of global sequence similarity on ortholog inference. With the addition of other caching and file I/O changes, RSD is over six times faster than the previous version in our performance tests. In addition to housing the orthologs inferred by RSD, Roundup builds clusters of orthologous genes, i.e. ortholog groups, using deterministic single-linkage clustering. It partitions a graph into connected subgraphs by creating a cluster for every gene and then © The Author(s) 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>Computations were run on the Orchestra cluster supported by the Harvard Medical School Research Information Technology Group.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic and functional assessment of orthologs inference projects and methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Altenhoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Dessimoz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000262</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basic local alignment search tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">215</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="410" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OrthoMCL-DB: querying a comprehensive multi-species collection of ortholog groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="368" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing performance of orthology detection strategies applied to eukaryotic genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">383</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetically informed logic relationships improve detection of biological network organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Cui</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">476</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Berkeley PHOG: PhyloFacts orthology group prediction web server</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Datta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="89" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Roundup: a multi-genome repository of orthologs and evolutionary distances</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Deluca</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2044" to="2046" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinguishing homologous from analogous proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Fitch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Zool</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Joining forces in the quest for orthologs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Gabaldon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">403</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PhylomeDB v3.0: an expanding repository of genomewide collections of trees, alignments and phylogeny-based orthology and paralogy predictions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Huerta-Cepas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="556" to="560" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational methods for Gene Orthology inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Kristensen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="391" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The quest for orthologs: finding the corresponding gene across genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Kuzniar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="551" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kalign—an accurate and fast multiple sequence alignment algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Lassmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Sonnhammer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">298</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TreeFam: a curated database of phylogenetic trees of animal gene families</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="572" to="580" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OrthoInspector: comprehensive orthology analysis and visual exploration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Linard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UniProt Knowledgebase: a hub of integrated protein data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Magrane</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<surname>Consortium</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Database</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">InParanoid 7: new algorithms and tools for eukaryotic orthology analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Ostlund</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GreenPhylDB v2.0: comparative and functional genomics in plants</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Rouard</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1095" to="1102" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SeqXML and OrthoXML: standards for sequence and orthology information</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Schmitt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="485" to="488" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OMA Browser—exploring orthologous relations across 352 complete genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Schneider</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2180" to="2182" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The COG database: an updated version includes eukaryotes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Tatusov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Thompson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4673" to="4680" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting putative orthologs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Wall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1710" to="1711" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PAML 4: phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1586" to="1591" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>