
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:53+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression rSeqNP: a non-parametric approach for detecting differential expression and splicing from RNA-Seq data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yang</forename>
								<surname>Shi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Michigan Center for Translational Pathology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Arul</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Chinnaiyan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Michigan Center for Translational Pathology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pathology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Howard Hughes Medical Institute</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Computational Medicine and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>48109</postCode>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hui</forename>
								<surname>Jiang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Computational Medicine and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>48109</postCode>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression rSeqNP: a non-parametric approach for detecting differential expression and splicing from RNA-Seq data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv119</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 22, 2014; revised on February 1, 2015; accepted on February 19, 2015</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Ivo Hofacker Contact: jianghui@umich.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>High-throughput sequencing of transcriptomes (RNA-Seq) has become a powerful tool to study gene expression. Here we present an R package, rSeqNP, which implements a non-parametric approach to test for differential expression and splicing from RNA-Seq data. rSeqNP uses permutation tests to access statistical significance and can be applied to a variety of experimental designs. By combining information across isoforms, rSeqNP is able to detect more differentially expressed or spliced genes from RNA-Seq data. Availability and implementation: The R package with its source code and documentation are freely available at http://www.cs.tau.ac.il/
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>High-throughput sequencing of transcriptomes (RNA-Seq) is a widely used approach to study gene expression (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Mortazavi et al., 2008</ref>). Many statistical approaches have been developed to characterize gene expression variation across RNA-Seq experiments, and many of them are designed for testing differential expression (DE) of genes without considering their alternative spliced isoforms. For a comprehensive review, see<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Rapaport et al. (2013)</ref>. Several recent studies have shown that directly applying the DE approach for detecting differential splicing (DS) may lead to erroneous results, because those approaches do not incorporate the complexity induced by isoform expression estimation for genes with multiple isoforms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Leng et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Trapnell et al., 2013</ref>). To this end, several approaches were recently developed to detect DE at isoform level (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Glaus et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Leng et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Trapnell et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Vardhanabhuti et al., 2013</ref>). However, there are two remaining issues: (i) many existing approaches only compare between two biological conditions (such as normal versus diseased) and their usages for complex experimental designs are thus limited, and (ii) most existing approaches assume parametric distributions (Poisson or negative binomial) for observed read counts which, although can achieve good performance when the distributional assumptions hold, may have severely deteriorated performance should the distributional assumptions be violated, and that is often the case especially for large sample size RNA-Seq data where outliers usually exist (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Li and Tibshirani, 2013</ref>). Here we present rSeqNP, a non-parametric approach for testing DE and DS from RNA-Seq data. rSeqNP extends a non-parametric approach for detecting DE (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Li and Tibshirani, 2013</ref>) and aims at detecting both DE and DS. rSeqNP can be used with a variety of RNA-Seq experimental designs, including those with two (unpaired or paired) or multiple biological conditions, and those with quantitative or survival outcomes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>Data preprocessing: Before applying rSeqNP, the raw sequence reads need to be processed to obtain the expression estimates of all<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>summarizes the test statistics that are used in various study designs of RNA-Seq experiments. See Supplementary Section S1 for details. rSeqNP also reports p-values from these tests and false discovery rates (FDR) based on the Benjamini–Hochberg (BH) procedure. Testing DE and DS of genes jointly: For each gene, rSeqNP also computes an overall gene-level differential score (GDS) based on the statistics used in testing the DE of the isoforms. Suppose that a gene has J distinct isoforms, and T j is the statistic for testing the DE of the jth isoform (e.g. for two condition comparison, T j is the Wilcoxon rank-sum statistic), the GDS is computed as</p><formula>GDS ¼ X J j¼1 T 2 j .</formula><p>The GDS captures both DE and DS of the gene. For genes with a given number of isoforms, larger GDS indicates stronger evidence of DE and DS. The GDS incorporates information from all the isoforms of the gene, and therefore is more comprehensive in detecting differentially expressed and spliced genes than simply detecting genes that contain differentially expressed isoforms. Estimating P-values and FDR for GDS: Since the null distribution of the GDS is unknown, rSeqNP implements a permutation plug-in method to estimate the p-values and FDRs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Li and Tibshirani, 2013</ref>). See Supplementary Section S2 for details.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>Using simulation studies, we find that our proposed approach has well controlled type I error rate, and achieves good statistical power for moderate sample sizes and effect sizes. See Supplementary Section S3 for details. Here we apply rSeqNP to a real RNA-Seq dataset and compare it with EBSeq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Leng et al., 2013</ref>) and Cuffdiff (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Trapnell et al., 2013</ref>), which are two existing approaches for detecting DE of genes and isoforms from RNA-Seq data. The dataset was generated from paired-end RNA-Seq experiments performed on prostate cancer samples and matched benign samples from 14 Chinese prostate cancer patients (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ren et al., 2012</ref>). Since neither EBSeq nor Cuffdiff can handle paired two-group comparison, we run all three programs on the dataset under the setting of unpaired two-group comparison, i.e. treat cancer and benign samples as two distinct groups, as well as run rSeqNP under the setting of paired two-group comparison. For preprocessing, we use the programs suggested by each of the three approaches to quantify expression values for all the genes and isoforms: RSEM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Li and Dewey, 2011</ref>) for EBSeq, rSeq (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Jiang and Wong, 2009</ref>) for rSeqNP and the integrated quantification program for Cuffdiff. Nevertheless, the three programs for quantification show very similar results (see Supplementary Section S4).<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>summarizes the numbers of differentially expressed and spliced genes identified by each program. See Supplementary Section S4 for detailed steps and additional results of the analysis. We use FDR 0.05 for rSeqNP and Cuffdiff, and posterior probability of being differentially expressed (PPDE) 0.95 for EBSeq to call a differential event. PPDE is the metric reported by EBSeq and PPDE 0.95 corresponds to controlling FDR at 5%. As expected, when treating the data as two distinct groups, rSeqNP detects fewer differentially expressed genes and isoforms, but by applying the GDS, more differentially expressed or spliced genes are detected. Furthermore, when accounting for the paired two group nature of the data, rSeqNP detects even more differential events. We find that Cuffdiff detects a much smaller number of differentially expressed or spliced genes, which is consistent with report from another study (<ref type="bibr">Seyednasrollah et al., 2013</ref>).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 2222 Bioinformatics, 31(13), 2015, 2222–2224 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv119</figDesc><table>Advance Access Publication Date: 24 February 2015 
Applications Note the genes and their isoforms for each sample in the RNA-Seq study. 
This can be done using software tools like rSeq (Jiang and Wong, 
2009), RSEM (Li and Dewey, 2011) and Cuffdiff (Trapnell et al., 
2013). 
Testing DE of genes and isoforms: Using estimated expression 
values as input, rSeqNP tests for DE of genes and isoforms using 
non-parametric statistics that are constructed based on ranks of 
expression values. </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Non-parametric statistics used by rSeqNP</figDesc><table>Study design 
Test statistic 

Two condition comparison 
Wilcoxon rank-sum statistic 
Paired two condition comparison 
Wilcoxon singed-rank statistic 
Multiple condition comparison 
Kruskal-Wallis statistic 
Quantitative outcomes 
Spearman's rank correlation 
coefficient 
Survival outcomes 
Score statistic of the Cox 
proportional hazard model 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2.</figDesc><table>Numbers of genes identified by different programs 

rSeqNP 
rSeqNP 
EBSeq 
Cuffdiff 
(unpaired) 
(paired) 
(unpaired) 
(unpaired) 

Gene.DE 
3346 
4544 
2514 
14 
Isoform.DE a 
2792 
4163 
3279 
26 
(2933) 
(4453) 
(4323) 
(31) 
GDS 
4122 
6050 
– 
– 

a 

Number of genes (Number of isoforms) that are detected. 

rSeqNP: detecting differential splicing from RNA-Seq data</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> Conclusion We present rSeqNP, a non-parametric approach for detecting differentially expressed and spliced genes from RNA-Seq data. It is flexible in handling various types of experimental designs. It is worth mentioning that, as pointed out by the reviewer, our method relies on expression estimates for genes and isoforms reported from upstream programs, which are typically based on parametric approaches. The major limitation of rSeqNP is that its power is relatively low for small sample size RNA-Seq data. In simulation studies, we show that the power is decent with five or more samples in each group for two-group comparison. If the sample size is even smaller, parametric approaches would be preferred. Funding National Institute of Health (U01CA111275 and 1UM1HG006508 to A.M.C.). A.M.C. is also supported by the Alfred A. Taubman Institute, the American Cancer Society, and the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. H.J. is supported by University of Michigan (startup grant). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying differentially expressed transcripts from RNA-seq data with biological variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Glaus</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1721" to="1728" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical inferences for isoform expression in RNA-Seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Jiang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Wong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1026" to="1032" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EBSeq: an empirical Bayes hierarchical model for inference in RNA-seq experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Leng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1035" to="1043" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RSEM: accurate transcript quantification from RNA-Seq data with or without a reference genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Dewey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">323</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding consistent patterns: a nonparametric approach for identifying differential expression in RNA-Seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Tibshirani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Methods Med. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="519" to="536" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Mortazavi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="621" to="628" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive evaluation of differential gene expression analysis methods for RNA-seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Rapaport</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA-seq analysis of prostate cancer in the Chinese population identifies recurrent gene fusions, cancer-associated long noncoding RNAs and aberrant alternative splicings</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Ren</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="806" to="821" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of software packages for detecting differential expression in RNA-seq studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Seyednasrollah</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential analysis of gene regulation at transcript resolution with RNA-seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Trapnell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A hierarchical bayesian model for estimating and inferring differential isoform expression for multi-sample RNA-Seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Vardhanabhuti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>