
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:42+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression shinyGEO: a web-based application for analyzing gene expression omnibus datasets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jasmine</forename>
								<surname>Dumas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Computing and Digital Media</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">DePaul University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Gargano</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eastern Connecticut State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Willimantic</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Garrett</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Dancik</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eastern Connecticut State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Willimantic</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression shinyGEO: a web-based application for analyzing gene expression omnibus datasets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw519</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 28, 2016; revised on July 19, 2016; accepted on August 3, 2016</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate editor: Ziv Bar-Joseph Contact: dancikg@easternct.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) is a public repository of gene expression data. Although GEO has its own tool, GEO2R, for data analysis, evaluation of single genes is not straightforward and survival analysis in specific GEO datasets is not possible without bioinformatics expertise. We describe a web application, shinyGEO, that allows a user to download gene expression data sets directly from GEO in order to perform differential expression and survival analysis for a gene of interest. In addition, shinyGEO supports customized graphics, sample selection, data export and R code generation so that all analyses are reproducible. The availability of shinyGEO makes GEO datasets more accessible to non-bioinformaticians, promising to lead to better understanding of biological processes and genetic diseases such as cancer. Availability and Implementation: Web application and source code are available from http://gdan cik.github.io/shinyGEO/.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) is a public repository of genomic data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Barrett et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Edgar et al., 2002</ref>) that currently hosts &gt;50 000 gene expression datasets containing &gt;1 million samples. GEO is a valuable resource for identifying biomarkers of biological processes and disease. Its datasets have been used to identify biomarkers of HRAS and MYC pathway activity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bild et al., 2006</ref>), biomarkers of monocyte differentiation in response to viral infection (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hou et al., 2012</ref>), and prognostic biomarkers in breast (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Grinchuk et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ma et al., 2004</ref>), bladder (<ref type="bibr">Kim et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lindgren et al., 2010</ref>) and lung cancer (<ref type="bibr">Lee et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tomida et al., 2009</ref>). Biomarker evaluation in GEO datasets typically involves data retrieval and gene (probe) selection followed by an appropriate statistical analysis. A differential expression analysis determines whether the expression of a gene differs significantly across two or more groups of samples. A survival analysis determines whether gene expression is significantly associated with an event (such as death from disease), through comparison of Kaplain–Meier curves based on censored time to event data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bland and Altman, 1998</ref>). To facilitate data analysis, GEO provides an interactive web tool [GEO2R; http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/geo2r/], which allows users to identify differentially expressed genes in GEO datasets. However, GEO2R does not support survival analysis and is designed for gene discovery rather than for evaluation of individual genes. In addition, although specialized tools have been developed to facilitate gene expression analysis by non-bioinformaticians (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dancik, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gy} orffy et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rhodes et al., 2007</ref>), there are no available tools that allow a user to evaluate whether a specific gene is differentially expressed or associated with survival in a specific GEO dataset. In this paper, we describe shinyGEO, a web-based tool for performing differential expression and survival analysis on gene expression datasets in GEO. In addition, shinyGEO produces publicationready and customizable graphics, allows for sample selection, data correction, data export for custom analyses and R code generation for reproducibility.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>shinyGEO is implemented using R [https://www.r-project.org/], a free, open-source software environment for statistical computing and graphics; and shiny [http://shiny.rstudio.com/], an R package for building interactive web applications. In shinyGEO, processed gene expression datasets are downloaded from GEO using the GEOquery package (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Davis and Meltzer, 2007</ref>). P-values are calculated using a two-sample t-test or one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) for differential expression. For survival analysis, the log-rank test is used to compare samples with high expression (e.g. top 50%) to samples with low expression (e.g. bottom 50%). Optimal cut points by P-value are identified and adjusted P-values calculated using the survMisc package (Contal and O'<ref type="bibr">Quigley, 1999</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Software usage</head><p>An overview of shinyGEO is provided in Supplementary Figures S1 and S2. First, the user selects the GEO accession number for a desired dataset, followed by the platform. The user can carry out a differential expression or survival analysis, and selects the gene and probe of interest. For a differential expression analysis, the user selects the two or more groups to compare. Dot plots are dynamically generated to visualize expression differences across groups, and results from the appropriate statistical analysis are displayed. For survival analysis, the user selects the survival information (i.e. the columns from the sample data containing the time to event and outcome information), and whether to use the median or optimal cut point to define high and low expression groups. The corresponding Kaplan–Meier curves are then dynamically generated and the statistical results displayed. For both analyses, shinyGEO supports sample selection and data correction, and graphs can be formatted with respect to color and axis labels. The user can also export the data and generate the R code used for each analysis, following best practices in scientific computing (<ref type="bibr">Wilson et al., 2014</ref>) to ensure reproducibility.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Example application</head><p>We demonstrate shinyGEO by repeating a recent analysis which found that high telomerase reverse transcriptase (TERT) expression is associated with poor disease-specific survival in bladder cancer patients (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Borah et al., 2015</ref>). We analyze the dataset GSE13507, which contains expression profiles for 165 primary bladder tumors and 10 normal bladder samples obtained from the Chungbuk National University Hospital (<ref type="bibr">Kim et al., 2010</ref>). A differential expression analysis finds that TERT expression is up-regulated in primary tumors compared to normal bladder samples, with a low foldchange (FC ¼ 1.14, P ¼ 0.013,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1A</ref>). Following<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Borah et al. (2015)</ref>, we limit the survival analysis to only those patients with muscle-invasive tumors who did not receive chemotherapy or additional treatment (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref>). For our selected patients, a cancer-specific survival analysis (using the outcome column 'characteristics_ch1.9') finds that high TERT expression is associated with poor outcomes (HR ¼ 3.61, adjusted P ¼ 0.049,<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1B</ref>), consistent with the findings of<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Borah et al. (2015)</ref>. Raw data is exported (Supplementary File S1), and for reproducibility we 'Save R Code'. Within R, a notebook integrating R code and output can then be generated using the rmarkdown library (Supplementary File S2) (<ref type="bibr">Stodden et al., 2014</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>This work is supported, in part, by<ref type="bibr">Google</ref>Application for analyzing gene expression omnibus datasets</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Summer of Code 2015 funding to JD. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Example shinyGEO analysis. (A) Evaluation of TERT expression in normal bladder and tumor samples, with fold change (FC) and P-value calculated by two-sample t-test. (B) Kaplan–Meier cancer-specific survival curves for bladder cancer patients with low (lower 52.78%) and high (upper 47.22%) TERT expression, with groups chosen based on the optimal cut point. All patients have muscle-invasive tumors and did not receive chemotherapy. The hazard-ratio (HR) and log-rank and adjusted P-values are reported</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NCBI GEO: archive for functional genomics data sets– update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Barrett</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="991" to="995" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oncogenic pathway signatures in human cancers as a guide to targeted therapies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Bild</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">439</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="353" to="357" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Survival probabilities (the Kaplan-Meier method)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Bland</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Altman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">317</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1572" to="1580" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TERT promoter mutations and telomerase reactivation in urothelial cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Borah</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">347</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1006" to="1010" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An application of changepoint methods in studying the effect of age on survival in breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Contal</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Quigley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Stat. Data Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="270" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An online tool for evaluating diagnostic and prognostic gene expression biomarkers in bladder cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Dancik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Urol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">59</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GEOquery: a bridge between the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) and BioConductor</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Davis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Meltzer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinform. Oxf. Engl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1846" to="1847" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene Expression Omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array data repository</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Edgar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sense-antisense gene-pairs in breast cancer and associated pathological pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Grinchuk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncotarget</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42197" to="42221" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Online survival analysis software to assess the prognostic value of biomarkers using transcriptomic data in non-small-cell lung cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Gy} Orffy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">82241</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viral infection triggers rapid differentiation of human blood monocytes into dendritic cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Hou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3128" to="3131" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>