
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:54+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining simDEF: definition-based semantic similarity measure of gene ontology terms for functional similarity analysis of genes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ahmad</forename>
								<surname>Pesaranghader</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Dalhousie University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>B3H 4R2</postCode>
									<settlement>Halifax</settlement>
									<region>NS</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Big Data Analytics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>B3H 4R2</postCode>
									<settlement>Halifax</settlement>
									<region>NS</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Stan</forename>
								<surname>Matwin</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Dalhousie University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>B3H 4R2</postCode>
									<settlement>Halifax</settlement>
									<region>NS</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Big Data Analytics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>B3H 4R2</postCode>
									<settlement>Halifax</settlement>
									<region>NS</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Polish Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Warsaw</settlement>
									<country key="PL">Poland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Marina</forename>
								<surname>Sokolova</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Big Data Analytics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>B3H 4R2</postCode>
									<settlement>Halifax</settlement>
									<region>NS</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Medicine and Faculty of Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Ottawa</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>K1H 8M5</postCode>
									<settlement>Ottawa</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Robert</forename>
								<forename type="middle">G</forename>
								<surname>Beiko</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Dalhousie University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>B3H 4R2</postCode>
									<settlement>Halifax</settlement>
									<region>NS</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining simDEF: definition-based semantic similarity measure of gene ontology terms for functional similarity analysis of genes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv755</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on 7 September 2015; revised on 16 December 2015; accepted on 21 December 2015</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Measures of protein functional similarity are essential tools for function prediction, evaluation of protein–protein interactions (PPIs) and other applications. Several existing methods perform comparisons between proteins based on the semantic similarity of their GO terms; however , these measures are highly sensitive to modifications in the topological structure of GO, tend to be focused on specific analytical tasks and concentrate on the GO terms themselves rather than considering their textual definitions. Results: We introduce simDEF, an efficient method for measuring semantic similarity of GO terms using their GO definitions, which is based on the Gloss Vector measure commonly used in natural language processing. The simDEF approach builds optimized definition vectors for all relevant GO terms, and expresses the similarity of a pair of proteins as the cosine of the angle between their definition vectors. Relative to existing similarity measures, when validated on a yeast reference database, simDEF improves correlation with sequence homology by up to 50%, shows a correlation improvement &gt;4% with gene expression in the biological process hierarchy of GO and increases PPI predictability by &gt; 2.5% in F1 score for molecular function hierarchy. Availability and implementation: Datasets, results and source code are available at https://cbcl.ics.uci.edu/public_data/DAN
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Gene Ontology (GO) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ashburner et al., 2000</ref>) describes the attributes of genes and gene products using a structured vocabulary. Many biomedical databases, such as UniProt (<ref type="bibr">The UniProt Consortium, 2008</ref>) and SwissProt (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Boeckmann et al., 2003</ref>), are annotated by GO terms to communicate semantic meanings of biomedical entities. Computing functional similarity of biomedical entities has been applied to problems such as prediction of protein–protein interaction (PPI) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pu et al., 2015</ref>), gene expression studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ovaska, 2015</ref>) and homology analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Piovesan et al., 2015</ref>). Also, in the context of text mining various studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Jin and Lu, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Jin et al., 2011</ref>) have aimed to enhance the literature-based GO annotation of gene products. There are two main computational models available to measure similarity of terms. Ontology-based models take advantage of lexical structures in their estimation of term similarity. Edge-based ontology measures like Wu (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Wu and Palmer, 1994</ref>) and RSS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Wu et al., 2006</ref>) consider the number of edges along the paths that link two GO terms. Node-based measures (which we designate as<ref type="bibr">, 2010</ref>), GraSM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Couto et al., 2011</ref>) and AIC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Song et al., 2014</ref>) compare the properties of the terms augmented with the properties of their ancestors or descendants. IC vectors (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Pesaranghader and Muthaiyah, 2013</ref>) represent IC values in distributed forms in the computation of semantic similarity. Hybrid measures such as those of<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wang et al. (2007)</ref>, Liu et al. (2009) and HRSS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wu et al., 2013</ref>) combine node-based and edge-based measures. While these measures first compute semantic similarity of two gene products and then aggregate the results as a single functional similarity value, group-wise measures such as simUI (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Falcon and Gentleman, 2007</ref>), simGIC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Pesquita et al., 2007</ref>) and SORA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Teng et al., 2013</ref>) calculate similarity by measuring two sets of GO terms annotating these genes.<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Huang et al. (2007)</ref>also proposed a similarity measure where gene functional similarity is based on vector representations of their GO terms. Ontology-based measures suffer from three important limitations: first, they depend on the constantly changing topological structure of GO; second, they use incomplete GO annotations to compute statistical information; and third, they offer no guarantee of generalization to multiple biological tasks. Distributional-based approaches derive from Firth's idea (1957) that a term is characterized by the company it keeps in its context. Measures following this notion calculate terms' specifications from relevant text data and represent them in a vector space for subsequent computation of their similarities. The Gloss Vector semantic relatedness measure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Pedersen et al., 2004</ref>) is a distributional-based approach with a wide application in natural language processing. This measure constructs definitions (glosses) of terms from a predefined thesaurus, and estimates semantic relatedness of two terms as the cosine of the angle between those terms' gloss-vectors. Interpolation of content words of a text corpus into the terms' definition was shown to outperform the direct definition comparison. Gloss vectors offer a new opportunity to exploit the information of GO term definitions and to infer gene functional similarity.<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Liu et al. (2012)</ref>successfully applied the Gloss Vector measure to the biomedical domain using MEDLINE as the text corpus and the unified medical language system and WordNet for the construction of extended definitions of medical concepts. The Gloss Vector approach requires a frequency cut-off in selecting the best features describing one term (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Pesaranghader et al., 2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Pesaranghader et al., , 2014a</ref>). We have developed simDEF, an optimized version of the Gloss Vector targeted to analysis of gene functions. Here, by using MEDLINE as the text corpus, we compare the performance of simDEF with other leading approaches, and demonstrate its effectiveness using comparisons based on sequence homology, gene expression and PPI data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Experimental data</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">GO and GO annotations</head><p>GO comprises three GOs which express different biological attributes: biological process (BP) for processes such as metabolism or cell proliferation; cellular component (CC) such as the nucleus or cell membrane; and molecular function (MF) such as catalytic or binding activities. GO is maintained and constantly updated by a group of curators. A GO annotation consists of a GO term associated with a specific reference and an evidence code to indicate how a given annotation is supported. Out of all the evidence codes available, Inferred from Electronic Annotation (IEA) is not assigned by a curator and is thus the least reliable so we treat them separately. GO and the required GO annotations were downloaded from the GO website (http://geneontol ogy.org (November 2, 2015).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">MEDLINE abstracts</head><p>MEDLINE (https://mbr.nlm.nih.gov/Download/) contains over 20 million citations of biomedical articles from 1966 to the present. The database includes journal articles from medicine, pharmacy, dentistry, nursing, healthcare and covers the literature in biology and biochemistry. For this study, we used MEDLINE 2013 as the corpus to build a first-order word–word co-occurrence matrix for the later computation of second-order co-occurrence (SOC) matrices which are used by simDEF.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Validation datasets</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1">Sequence homology</head><p>We used bitscores from the Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Altschul et al., 1997</ref>) to create our sequence homology dataset. In the first step, we performed an all-versus-all comparison of proteins in the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Cherry et al., 1998</ref>) with an expectation-value threshold of 0.1. Although this threshold is liberal, the corresponding bitscores associated with e-values near this threshold will be very low and have a minimal effect on our analysis. Since a bitscore for query and subject proteins is not symmetrical, we calculate log-reciprocal BLAST score (LRBS) and relative reciprocal BLAST score (RRBS) to express the general sequence similarity of protein pairs. For proteins A and B, the LRBS and RRBS are LRBSðA; BÞ ¼ log Bitscore A; B ð ÞþBitscore B; A ð Þ 2 ;</p><formula>(1)</formula><p>RRBSðA; BÞ ¼ Bitscore A; B ð ÞþBitscore B; A ð Þ Bitscore A; A ð ÞþBitscore B; B ð Þ :</p><formula>(2)</formula><p>Finally, after LRBS and RRBS computations, we have a dataset of 20 167 protein pairs from the yeast S.cerevisiae database along with their LRBS and RRBS sequence similarity scores. All proteins in the dataset have their own GO annotations from the CC, BP and MF ontologies without considering IEAs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2">Gene expression</head><p>The gene expression dataset comes from the study by Jain and Bader (2010). In their study, the gene-expression dataset for S.cerevisiae was downloaded from GeneMANIA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Warde-Farley et al., 2010</ref>) and other microarray experiments. The authors prepared test datasets of 5000 S.cerevisiae gene pairs randomly selected from a list of all possible pairs of proteins in their gene expression dataset. This was done independently for CC, BP and MF annotations of gene products. Since in our experiments we mainly consider genes with non-electronic annotations, we used 4800 fitting gene pairs from their study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3">Protein–protein interaction</head><p>For the PPI experiment, we employed subsets of the yeast PPI dataset from<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wu et al. (2013)</ref>. In that study, for each GO, independent gold-standard positive datasets for yeast were built from a core subset of the Database of Interacting Proteins (DIP) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Salwinski et al., 2004</ref>). Negative datasets were independently generated by randomly choosing annotated protein pairs in BP, CC and MF, which are absent from a combined dataset of all possible PPIs. Since for different GOs the numbers of generated PPI pairs are different and more importantly many of them do not have GO annotations after excluding simDEF: definition-based semantic similarity measureIEA, we selected subsets of 3000 positive and 3000 negative PPIs for each ontology from that study to evaluate our measure against other similarity measures in a PPI prediction task.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Methods</head><p>Pointwise Mutual Information (PMI) is a measure of association used in information theory. In computational linguistics, the PMI for two given words indicates the likelihood of finding one word in a text document that includes the other word. PMI is formulated as</p><formula>PMI w 1 ; w 2 ð Þ¼log p w 1 ; w 2 ð Þ p w 1 ð ÞÂp w 2 ð Þ ; (3)</formula><p>where p(w 1 , w 2 ) is the probability that words w 1 and w 2 co-occur in a document, and p(w 1 ) and p(w 2 ) for w 1 and w 2 , respectively, are the marginal probabilities of their occurrence in a document. It is expected that rare words are highly associated with and descriptive of each other, yet due to their sparse nature their bigram frequency (i.e. number of times they have been seen next to each other) is small in the corpus. This is the main drawback of the Gloss Vector measure in selection of the best descriptive features. We use PMI in our proposed measure, simDEF, for statistical elimination of insignificant features (words). simDEF requires procedures for building the co-occurrence matrix from a proper text corpus, constructing extended definitions for GO terms using GO term definitions, and finding words that are appropriate descriptors of that GO term. simDEF comprises six steps (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>) (see Supplementary Material for pseudocode of the steps laid out in simDEF).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Step 1—counting bigrams and building the firstorder co-occurrence matrix</head><p>After discarding punctuation, changing all characters to lowercase, and removing stop words (a pre-defined list of 204 non-informative words like a and the) from the MEDLINE corpus, a list of bigrams and their frequencies for all the content words is constructed. A window size of 2 is used for extraction of bigrams. This window size controls how close two words can appear in bigrams. Stemming was found to reduce accuracy and was not adopted in simDEF. Then, by ignoring the order of occurrence in a bigram, we transform it from a bigram list to a co-occurrence list. Finally, we construct the firstorder co-occurrence matrix, which is symmetric and sparse and represents the contextual information of MEDLINE words. Cell values in the first-order matrix represent how many times the word associated with its row is seen in this corpus alongside the word associated with its column.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Step 2—definition construction</head><p>of GO terms and then building BP, CC, and MF definition matrices all GO terms in BP, CC and MF. Now we see that for each word in the definition of a GO term we have an associated first-order co-occurrence vector calculated in Step 1. After changing all characters to lowercase and removing punctuation and stop words from these extended definitions we store them in different matrices for three different subontologies. In these matrices, the value of a cell represents how many times the word associated with its column appears in the definition of the GO term associated with its row.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Step 3—building SOC matrices</head><p>To build the SOC vector for a GO term we sum the first-order cooccurrence vectors from the words in the constructed definition of that GO term (i.e. compute the centroid), and then normalize the result vector by the number of words in the definition. We do this process separately for each GO. The results are three different matrices for BP, CC and MF; each row again represents a GO term and features are the words. We have three SOC matrices for BP, CC and MF at the end of this step.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Step 4—PMI on SOC matrices (PMI-on-SOC matrices)</head><p>In our similarity measure, PMI-on-SOC matrices replace a conventional approach of low-and high-frequency cut-offs for detection of insignificant features or words in the Gloss Vector measure. We statistically measure the level of association between GO terms and their describing features in the SOC matrices and then apply a cutoff threshold on this level in the next step. Following (3), here, PMI(t i , w j ) measures the level of association between GO term i and feature j to discover how descriptive the word j of that GO term is. PMI is biased toward low-frequency words and consequently tends to favor them by assigning them a higher degree of importance (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Pesaranghader et al., 2013</ref>); in order to resolve this weakness, we employ the add-one technique. Before applying PMI on a matrix, all the elements of the matrix are incremented by 1 unit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Step 5—removing insignificant features from the PMI-on-SOC vectors</head><p>Defining a PMI threshold allows us to skip those words which provide low information for GO terms in their constructed PMI-onSOC vectors. By using the available dataset in an iterative way, we gradually increase the threshold of PMI cut-off from zero and then evaluate the results generated by simDEF. Depending on the biomedical task, for a chosen cut-off threshold, criteria such as Pearson's correlation or AUC (see Section 4.3) can be used for the performance evaluation of the estimated similarity results. In general, as cut-off thresholds increase we tend to get better results until a point where performance starts to drop rapidly. Therefore, by recording this curve for different performance results and cut-off points we try to find the optimal cut-off point in order to keep only those informative features describing one GO term. Also, to avoid this interval being sensitive to the choice of dataset, we use 5-fold cross validation to predict the extent to which the threshold will generalize to an independent dataset. This cut-off selection is done separately for the three constructed PMI-on-SOC matrices of the BP, CC and MF ontologies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">Step 6—calculating semantic similarity</head><p>In this final step, the semantic similarity among GO terms is estimated. The cosine of the angle between optimized PMI-on-SOC vectors of two GO terms will indicate the degree of similarity for those terms. For the final usage of the measure, the last produced matrix is loaded into memory and used for measuring similarity between GO terms. In these matrices, each row stores the calculated optimized definition vector of its associated GO term. As, in most cases, gene products are annotated with more than one GO term in the same ontology hierarchy (BP, CC or MF), there are several methods to measure the functional similarity of gene products based on the semantic similarity of these GO terms. MAX and AVE define functional similarity between gene products as the maximum or average semantic similarity values, respectively, over the GO terms annotating the genes. MAX has been shown to be more useful for a PPI task (<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Wu et al., 2006</ref>). If T A and T B are the sets of GO terms which annotate proteins A and B, respectively, the MAX for their functional similarity measurement is achieved by sim MAX A; B ð Þ¼ MAX t1eTA;t2eTB simðt 1 ; t 2 Þ ð Þ :</p><formula>(4)</formula><p>The best-match average (BMA) method is found to be the best for evaluation of semantic similarity measures and the correlation of its results with sequence homology and gene expression data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Pesquita et al., 2008</ref>). BMA for two gene products A and B with n and m GO annotations is given by sim BMA ðA;</p><formula>BÞ ¼ 1 2 1 n X t1eTA MAX t1;t2eTB simðt 1 ; t 2 Þ ð Þ þ 1 m X t2eTB MAX t1eTA;t2 simðt 1 ; t 2 Þ ð Þ 0 @ 1 A :</formula><formula>(5)</formula><p>Consider that in these formulae T A of different ontologies would be different (likewise for T B ). Therefore, we will achieve three different protein functional similarity values for three different gene ontologies. MAX and BMA measure similarity between two gene products by combining semantic similarities between their terms. Semantic similarity estimation was used to evaluate the Resnik, Lin, Jiang, GraSM, Wang, AIC and simDEF measures (see Supplementary ma terial for definitions and formulas). In contrast, groupwise measures like simGIC and simUI are functional similarity measures by nature and do not rely on combining similarities between individual terms to assess gene product similarity, but calculate it directly by their annotation sets. By employing GO annotations for the previous measures and MEDLINE for the simDEF as the needed corpora, we implemented these measures as appropriate, and reported results alongside the best cut-off point for feature removal in each task.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Correlation with sequence similarity</head><p>Several authors have compared the performance of different semantic similarity measures by testing how well these measures correlate with sequence similarity. Various studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Lord et al., 2003</ref>) showed that the more similar two sequences are the more similar their ontological annotations will be. To evaluate the semantic similarity measures, we used two distinct sequence similarity measures: LRBS and RRBS with the formulae of (1) and (2). LRBS is similar to the sequence similarity measure used previously by Lord, but compensates for the fact that BLAST scores are not symmetric. RRBS, suggested by Joshi and Xu (2007), is another indicator of functional similarity acting like the sequence identity percentage by taking amino acid substitutions into account.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 3</ref>shows the degree of correlation between LRBS and the functional similarity estimations calculated by semantic measures of 20 167 protein pairs (without IEAs included).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>simDEF: definition-based semantic similarity measure</head><p>In all cases, whether we use MAX or BMA, simDEF correlates with sequence similarity better than the other IC-based measures. The high correlation between simDEF and LRBS in the MF ontology is notable as it is more than the twice of the second best measure's result (Jiang). Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>shows the exact numerical results of this experiment (with and without IEAs). The other metric used for sequence similarity measurement is RRBS which is not directly affected by sequence length (unlike LRBS). We assessed whether the dependency on sequence length affects the outcome of the evaluation.<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>shows the degree of correlation between the similarity estimations calculated by semantic measures and RRBS. RRBS, like LRBS, shows the highest degree of correlation with simDEF among the similarity measures. In general, measures of functional similarity correlate more with LRBS sequence similarity than RRBS. We also observe among ICbased measures tested here that no single measure is superior to all others in the BP, CC and MF ontologies, which suggests task-dependency of these measures. AIC, the latest variant of IC-based measures, does not offer any improvement over the earlier measures. The Wang topological measure of similarity works only slightly better than the IC-based measures in the RRBS sequence similarity comparison of BP. The correlation results for LRBS and RRBS also demonstrate that BMA is the appropriate metric for functional similarity measurement of proteins from BP and CC points of view when we use IC-based measures while for simDEF in CC it is reverse. The difference between results generated by BMA and MAX for simDEF is typically small, whereas other pairwise semantic similarity measures tend to show larger discrepancies. Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table S2</ref>shows the exact results of this experiment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Correlation with gene expression</head><p>Correlation with gene expression is another desirable criterion (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Pesaranghader et al., 2014b</ref>). Since genes involved in the same process tend to exhibit similar expression patterns, we could expect good semantic similarity estimations calculated on the BP ontology to be correlated with the expression similarity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Yang et al., 2012</ref>). For our experiments, the evaluation is done against the available standard reference of 4800 gene expression values. Here, we report Pearson's correlation between gene expression data and the results from simGIC, simUI and BMA of pairwise measures. We focus on the BMA criterion as it always gave higher correlations. Pearson's correlation between gene expression and semantic measures for CC, BP and MF ontologies with and without IEAs considered are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. The highest correlations in all cases are seen with the CC ontology, followed by BP and MF. Although the difference in correlation coefficients is not as striking as in the homology example, simDEF outperforms the next best method, GraSM, by 4% on the BP ontology and 1–2% on the CC ontology. GraSM has the best correlation for MF, 1–2% better than simDEF, which was also outperformed by the Resnik. Correlation coefficients were generally higher for datasets with IEAs, suggesting that electronic annotations have some value when investigating gene-expression profiles.<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Wang et al. (2004) and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Sevilla et al. (2005)</ref>showed that the correlation between gene expression and semantic similarity was negligible when semantic similarity values were low, but the two measures were highly related when semantic similarity was high.<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Xu et al. (2008)</ref>further showed a linear relationship for gene pairs with high levels of expression correlation. We examined this trend by comparing Resnik against simDEF for variable numbers of the highest correlated genes. For this purpose, after sorting gene expression data from the highest to the lowest values, we measured correlation of these data with Resnik and simDEF as we go from the top correlated expressions to the bottom.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 4</ref>demonstrates the trend of change for this test. Considering other studies' findings and our result demonstrated in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 4</ref>, we see that by being more focused on high-correlated gene expression pairs the overal correlation between functional similarity and gene expression increase only when we take the BP ontology into account. For CC and MF the reverse is true. The other important point learned for BP is that by employing simDEF as semantic measure, when we ignore electronic annotation we get better correlation with highly-correlated gene expression data while this is not true for Resnik. Moreover, we observe that for BP and CC simDEF works better than Resnik no matter which subset we consider. Nevertheless, this issue does not hold for MF and we only get better results from simDEF when we focus on higher correlated genes in terms of their expression.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Comparison with PPIs</head><p>Semantic similarity can also be used as an indicator for the plausibility of putative PPIs, as proteins that interact in the cell in vivo are expected to participate in similar cellular locations and BPs. Like other studies (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Jain and Bader, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wu et al., 2013</ref>), we formulated this as a classification problem and checked how well the different semantic similarity measures perform for predicting true PPIs. For this purpose, the MAX and BMA results are directly interpreted as the classification probability of 'Interaction' and 'Not Interaction'. The higher this value is, the higher the probability of interaction will be. We applied this approach to a dataset of 6000 PPI pairs for each GO while half of the data have positive labels (due to experimentally confirmed PPIs) and the other half have negative labels.In our evaluation, the results of prediction were investigated by receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves, with area under the curve (AUC) as the main accuracy criterion. Here, we report only MAX since, as we expected from the previous studies, for all the cases MAX predicted better results compared with BMA.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>shows the values of AUC for different semantic measures, including a hybrid measure that uses the average of the simDEF and Resnik values as the probability of interaction. As in the gene expression case, we found that including IEA records from GO improved the accuracy (in this case, the AUC). simDEF gave the highest accuracy when the BP and MF ontologies were used, while Resnik and GraSM performed best for CC. The hybrid classifier's AUC results are represented in the last row of<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. This result shows that simDEF is useful on all three ontologies, whether alone or as a complement to the Resnik measure. We believe different approaches of simDEF and IC-based semantic measures in similarity estimation is the main reason for this improvement. With consideration of IEA, the ROC for CC ontology shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref>represents that the combination of Resnik and simDEF benefits from the results of simDEF and Resnik both. ROC is not always the only best approach to evaluate a classifier's performance in a PPI task (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Jain and Bader, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wu et al., 2013</ref>). Therefore, in our second experiment, by keeping the feature cut-off point of simDEF as before, considering Resnik as the baseline measure, and including IEA in the evaluation, we calculated different F1-scores for different classification cut-off points in the simDEF, Resnik and hybrid measures. Then, we compared the calculated mean and maximum F1-score values. While the mean and maximum F1-scores can be indicators of one classifier's performance in the detection of positive interactions (similar to AUC), maximum F1-score also helps in selection of the best classification cut-off point of a classifier having its ROC curve. The mean and maximum F1-score results are shown in<ref type="figure">Table 3</ref>. The simDEF prediction of PPIs based on the F1-score is always better than the results achieved by Resnik. Even though Resnik gave the best AUC for the CC ontology, the simDEF mean F1-score isThe mean and maximum F1 scores are shown for all three GOs. simDEF: definition-based semantic similarity measureconsiderably higher than that of Resnik, while the maximum scores differ by &lt; 1%. For the other two ontologies the improved mean of the F1-scores in the simDEF measure against Resnik is notable. For MF the difference between max F1-score in the hybrid measure is &gt;2.5% compared with Resnik's F1-score itself. We also see this improvement in the result is due more to simDEF than to the Resnik measure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Discussion</head><p>Our approach to similarity estimation based on shared context makes intuitive sense, as concepts which share closely related attributes in their representation should exhibit high levels of similarity. We have shown that implementing these ideas via the Gloss Vector representation yields improved effectiveness across the majority of ontologies and problem types. For the yeast database, simDEF increases the correlation of semantic similarity with sequence homology by 50%, yields an increase of &gt; 4% in correlation with gene expression on the BP ontology, and improves the PPI prediction F1score by &gt;2.5% on the MF ontology. A key advantage of simDEF in comparison with IC-based measures is its reduced dependency on annotation data, and the GO structure. New GO terms typically do not have rich annotation information, which can influence the IC calculation of all GO terms as they depend on the root frequency which itself depends on all GO term frequencies. In contrast, simDEF needs to access only the direct parents and children of one GO term to expand that GO term's definition. In future work, simDEF can be evaluated against Enzyme Commission (EC) and protein family (Pfam) similarities. Gene clustering and orthologous protein distinguishing tasks present yet another opportunity for simDEF performance evaluation. simDEF needs to be tested on the other species than S.cerevisiae as well. Moreover, other statistical measures of association, such as Chisquare and log-lokelihood, can be examined in replacement of PMI for further improvement of simDEF. More in-depth studies can also find out if using larger window sizes of bigrams or even tri-grams in the word extraction of MEDLINE abstracts would improve the achieved results. Also, current advancement in deep neural networks for the low-dimensional yet more accurate representation of GO terms leaves room for further investigation of semantic similarity measures in the distributional model.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Pearson's correlation between semantic measures and LRBS (IEAÀ)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Relationship of gene expression correlation and semantic similarity in three GO ontologies. X ¼ 500 means that only the 500 most highly correlated gene pairs were considered when generating the correlation scores</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. ROC evaluation of the simDEF, Resnik and the hybrid measure of them by MAX for the PPI task at different classification cut-offs based on the yeast dataset using CC ontology (IEAþ)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 1380 Bioinformatics, 32(9), 2016, 1380–1387 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv755 Advance Access Publication Date: 26 December 2015 Original Paper information-content-based), such as Resnik (1995), Jiang (Jiang and Conrath, 1997), Lin (1998), Schlicker et al. (2006), TCSS (Jain and Bader</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2. AUC of the semantic similarity measures for three GOs using MAX in the PPI task on the yeast dataset (IEAþ and IEAÀ)</figDesc><table>Semantic measure Including IEA 
Excluding IEA 

BP 
CC 
MF 
BP 
CC 
MF 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 3.</figDesc><table>F1-score of the simDEF, Resnik and the hybrid measure by 
MAX for the PPI task (IEAþ) 

Semantic measure Mean of F1-score 
Max of F1-score 

BP 
CC 
MF 
BP 
CC 
MF 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">In this step, we construct an extended definition for every term in GO. From the theoretical perspective, definition extension of parent GO terms (i.e. broader concepts) with their children&apos;s definitions (i.e. narrower and more specific definitions) adds more specific information. Although child GO terms may contain contradictory information, this information may nonetheless provide essential context when calculating functional similarity with other genes (which may in turn be augmented with conflicting information). From the practical perspective, we examined all the combinations of definition extension considering GO relationships such as is_a, has_part, part_of, regulates, siblings and synonyms. What is represented in Figure 2 yielded the best results in our experiments conducted in this study. Improvement in the results using relationships such as part_of and regulates indicates that besides the similarity, simDEF accounts for relatedness as well. See Supplementary material for more in-depth explanation of why definition extension can be beneficial. Each GO term has an identifier, a representative name, a GO definition, a namespace defining the sub-ontology of the GO term and other information such as its relationship to the other GO terms. For example, GO:0001104 has the representative name &apos;RNA polymerase II transcription cofactor activity&apos; and belongs to the MF hierarchy. This GO term has the definition &apos;Interacting selectively and non-covalently with an RNA polymerase II (RNAP II) regulatory transcription factor and also with the RNAP II basal transcription machinery in order to modulate transcription. Cofactors generally do not bind DNA, but rather mediate PPIs between regulatory transcription factors and the basal RNAP II transcription machinery.&apos; In order to make this definition even richer we concatenate definitions of its direct parents (i.e. GO:0003712 or &apos;transcription cofactor activity&apos; and GO:0001076 or &apos;RNA polymerase II transcription factor binding transcription factor activity&apos;) and direct children (i.e. GO:0001105 or &apos;RNA polymerase II transcription co-activator activity&apos; and GO:0001106 or &apos;RNA polymerase II transcription co-repressor activity&apos;) to its definition. We also add this GO term&apos;s representative name to this extended definition considering this name as part of its own definition. This process is done for Fig. 1. Computation of the simDEF semantic similarity measure Fig. 2. Pearson&apos;s correlation between semantic measures and RRBS (IEAÀ)</note>

			<note place="foot">A.Pesaranghader et al. at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors acknowledge the support of the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada for this research.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Altschul</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3389" to="3402" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene Ontology: tool for the unification of biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashburner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The SWISS-PROT protein knowledgebase and its supplement TrEMBL in 2003</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Boeckmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="370" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SGD: Saccharomyces genome database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Cherry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disjunctive shared information between ontology concepts: application to Gene Ontology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Couto</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biomed. Semant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using GOstats to test gene lists for GO term association</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Falcon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Gentleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Synopsis of Linguistic Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Firth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1930" />
			<publisher>The Philological Society</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1952" to="59" />
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">David gene functional classification tool: a novel biological module centric algorithm to functionally analyze large gene list</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">183</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An improved method for scoring protein-protein interactions using semantic similarity within the gene ontology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Jain</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Bader</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">562</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Semantic similarity based on corpus statistics and lexical taxonomy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Jiang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Conrath</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>ArXiv Prepr</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">9709008</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying informative subsets of the Gene Ontology with information bottleneck methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Jin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Lu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2445" to="2451" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping annotations with textual evidence using an scLDA model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Jin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">AMIA Annual Symposium Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Medical Informatics Association</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page">834</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative assessment of relationship between sequence similarity and function similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Joshi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Xu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">222</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An information-theoretic definition of similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="296" to="304" />
			<pubPlace>Madison, Wisconsin, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An weighted ontology-based semantic similarity algorithm for web service</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Expert Syst. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12480" to="12490" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semantic relatedness study using second order co-occurrence vectors computed from biomedical corpora, UMLS and WordNet</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2nd ACM SIGHIT International Health Informatics Symposium (ACM)</title>
		<meeting>the 2nd ACM SIGHIT International Health Informatics Symposium (ACM)<address><addrLine>Miami, FL, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="372" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating semantic similarity measures across the Gene Ontology: the relationship between sequence and annotation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Lord</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1275" to="1283" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using Semantic Similarities and csbl. go for Analyzing Microarray Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Ovaska</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WordNet:: similarity: measuring the relatedness of concepts</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Pedersen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Demonstration Papers at Hlt-Naacl</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston, Massachusetts, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="41" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Definition-based information content vectors for semantic similarity measurement</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Pesaranghader</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Muthaiyah</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Soft Computing Applications and Intelligent Systems</title>
		<editor>Noah,S.A. et al.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="268" to="282" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving gloss vector semantic relatedness measure by integrating pointwise mutual information: optimizing secondorder co-occurrence vectors computed from biomedical corpus and UMLS</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Pesaranghader</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE International Conference on Informatics and Creative Multimedia (ICICM) 2013</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="201" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Word sense disambiguation for biomedical text mining using definition-based semantic relatedness and similarity measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Pesaranghader</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Biosci. Biochem. Bioinforma</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="280" to="283" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Gene functional similarity analysis by definition-based semantic similarity measurement of GO terms Advances in Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Pesaranghader</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Sokolova,M. and van Beek,P.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="214" />
			<pubPlace>Dordrecht</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating GO-based semantic similarity measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Pesquita</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 10th Annual Bio-Ontologies Meeting</title>
		<meeting>the 10th Annual Bio-Ontologies Meeting<address><addrLine>Vienna, Austria</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page">38</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metrics for GO based protein semantic similarity: a systematic evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Pesquita</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">INGA: protein function prediction combining interaction networks, domain assignments and sequence similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Piovesan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracting high confidence protein interactions from affinity purification data: at the crossroads</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Pu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Using information content to evaluate semantic similarity in a taxonomy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Resnik</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>ArXiv Prepr. Cmp-Lg9511007</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The database of interacting proteins: 2004 update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Salwinski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new measure for functional similarity of gene products based on Gene Ontology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Schlicker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">302</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation between gene expression and GO semantic similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Sevilla</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEEACM Trans. Comput. Biol. Bioinforma</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="330" to="338" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measure the semantic similarity of go terms using aggregate information content</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Song</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE ACM Trans. Comput. Biol. Bioinforma, TCBB</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="468" to="476" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring gene functional similarity based on groupwise comparison of GO terms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Teng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1424" to="1432" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The universal protein resource (UniProt)</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The UniProt Consortium Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression correlation and gene ontology-based similarity: an assessment of quantitative relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Proceedings of the 2004 IEEE Symposium on Computational Intelligence in Bioinformatics and Computational Biology</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>La Jolla, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="31" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new method to measure the semantic similarity of GO terms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Z</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1274" to="1281" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The GeneMANIA prediction server: biological network integration for gene prioritization and predicting gene function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Warde-Farley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="214" to="220" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of yeast protein–protein interaction network: insights from the Gene Ontology and annotations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2137" to="2150" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving the measurement of semantic similarity between gene ontology terms and gene products: insights from an edge-and IC-based hybrid method</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">66745</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Verbs semantics and lexical selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Palmer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 32nd Annual Meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics</title>
		<meeting>the 32nd Annual Meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics<address><addrLine>Stroudsburg, PA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="138" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of GO-based functional similarity measures using S. cerevisiae protein interaction and expression profile data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Xu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">472</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving GO semantic similarity measures by exploring the ontology beneath the terms and modelling uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1383" to="1389" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">simDEF: definition-based semantic similarity measure</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>