
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:51+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">SiTaR: a novel tool for transcription factor binding site prediction</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="1920">. 20 2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eugen</forename>
								<surname>Fazius</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Research Group Systems Biology/Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Leibniz Institute for Natural Product Research and Infection Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hans Knöll Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07745</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Vladimir</forename>
								<surname>Shelest</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Research Group Systems Biology/Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Leibniz Institute for Natural Product Research and Infection Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hans Knöll Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07745</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ekaterina</forename>
								<surname>Shelest</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Research Group Systems Biology/Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Leibniz Institute for Natural Product Research and Infection Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hans Knöll Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07745</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">SiTaR: a novel tool for transcription factor binding site prediction</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2806" to="2811"/>
							<date type="published" when="1920">. 20 2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr492</idno>
					<note type="submission">Sequence analysis Advance Access publication September 4, 2011 Received on April 19, 2011; revised on August 16, 2011; accepted on August 19, 2011</note>
					<note>[11:08 20/9/2011 Bioinformatics-btr492.tex] Page: 2806 2806–2811 Associate Editor: Martin Bishop Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Prediction of transcription factor binding sites (TFBSs) is crucial for promoter modeling and network inference. Quality of the predictions is spoiled by numerous false positives, which persist as the main problem for all presently available TFBS search methods. Results: We suggest a novel approach, which is alternative to widely used position weight matrices (PWMs) and Hidden Markov Models. Each motif of the input set is used as a search template to scan a query sequence. Found motifs are assigned scores depending on the non-randomness of the motif&apos;s occurrence, the number of matching searching motifs and the number of mismatches. The non-randomness is estimated by comparison of observed numbers of matching motifs with those predicted to occur by chance. The latter can be calculated given the base compositions of the motif and the query sequence. The method does not require preliminary alignment of the input motifs, hence avoiding uncertainties introduced by the alignment procedure. In comparison with PWM-based tools, our method demonstrates higher precision by the same sensitivity and specificity. It also tends to outperform methods combining pattern and PWM search. Most important, it allows reducing the number of false positive predictions significantly. Availability: The method is implemented in a tool called SiTaR (Site Tracking and Recognition) and is available at http://sbi.hki</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Despite the large number of available methods and tools for transcription factor binding sites (TFBSs) prediction, the problem of the high number of false positive (FP) predictions is not solved so far. The attempts to predict putative binding sites using the information about known TFBSs have a long history, with the main stream of PWM-based methods and deviations to applications of other sequence-based methods, such as Hidden Markov Models (HMMs) (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Frith et al., 2002</ref>), or less widely known approaches like, for example, intuitionistic fuzzy sets (IFS) theory (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Garcia-Alcalde et al., 2010</ref>). Further refinement of predictions can be done by including additional information, such as genetic and epigenetic factors in the query region, e.g. clade-specific evolutionary parameters, presence of nearby coding regions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Fu et al., 2009</ref>) or phylogenetic relationships (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Berezikov et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Hestand et al., 2008</ref>) or/and genome-wide expression data (e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Siewert and Kechris, 2009</ref>). These ways are promising and have their field of application, and they also have a serious drawback: this additional information must be available, which is far from being always the case. To find an optimal balance between high specialization provided by pattern-based methods and high sensitivity of the PWMs, several attempts have been made to combine these two approaches. These attempts were implemented in such tools as AliBaba2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Grabe, 2002</ref>) and P-Match (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chekmenev et al., 2005</ref>). AliBaba2 method is based on the examination of a TFBS context by application of an extension of the Berg and von Hippel model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Berg and von Hippel, 1987</ref>). It includes a step of aligning of known TFBSs with a query sequence with subsequent construction of a PWM matching each found motif. The P-Match algorithm uses individual TFBSs along with the corresponding PWMs. It searches for DNA subsequences matching one of the TFBSs from the set and calculates the matching score using the weight matrix. Both approaches, although they still include the obligatory step of the PWM construction, are a significant step forward in comparison with 'pure' PWM-based methods. Being methodologically interesting and promising, these tools are, unfortunately, hardly of use in practice: AliBaba2 is not maintained since 2002, and both tools are dependent on available PWM libraries, which are outdated in their public versions. At the end of the day, PWMs remain the state of the art method. Consequently, the great majority of available tools are PWM based (see, for example,<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bryne et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Cartharius et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Kel et al., 2003</ref>) and differ mostly in the ways of calculating the cut-offs. Introduction of e-values, P-values and background modeling [e.g. in Matrix-scan of RSAT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Turatsinze et al., 2008)]</ref>allow to reduce the number of FP to some extent. Other tools tend to use more mathematically sophisticated methods, such as variable order Bayesian trees and variable order Markov models [e.g. VOMBAT tool (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Grau et al., 2006</ref>)] without breakthrough results. We think, however, that the problem of motif prediction should not be approached by generalizations. We decided to develop a straightforward method based on direct comparison of input (searching) set motifs with the query sequence (see the Section 2). We exploit the idea of non-randomness of biologically meaningful sequence motifs, which can be detected by comparison of observed motifs' occurrences with those predicted to happen by chance. This simple mathematical approach provides high sensitivity and specificity of the method, allowing significant reduction of the FP predictions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SiTaR</head><p>We compared our method, implemented in a tool called SiTaR (Site Tracking and Recognition), with P-Match (http://biobaseinternational.com/,<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chekmenev et al., 2005</ref>) and a state of the art PWM-based tool Jaspar (http://jaspar.genereg.net/,<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bryne et al., 2008</ref>). SiTaR shows better performance false discovery rate (FDR) and F-measure, which is the weighted harmonic mean of precision and recall (see more details in Section 3.2). In six independent cross-validation experiments for arbitrarily taken (TFs), we show that our method is not inclined to overfitting and can predict new motifs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">SiTaR method</head><p>The method is based on the idea that we can calculate the number of motifs with given base composition and given number of mismatches in a random sequence (also with the given nucleotide composition). These predicted numbers can then be compared with the real occurrences of motifs in a query sequence. Let the length of the random sequence be L, the length of the motif be l, the fractions of each nucleotide i in the motif being f i and in the random sequence F i. It is easy to show (see Supplementary Material) that the number of motifs µ with 0 mismatches can be calculated as:</p><formula>M µ,0 = L −l +1 4 i=1 F lf i i ,</formula><formula>(1)</formula><p>With 1 mismatch:</p><formula>M µ,1 = l ·M µ,0 4 i=1 f i 1−F i F i ,</formula><formula>(2)</formula><p>and so on, see Supplementary Material for more details. We can compare these numbers with the real motif occurrences. To count the real motif occurrences, the query sequence is scanned for motifs with a sliding window (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>, Step 1). Each motif of the input TFBS set [searching motif (SM)] is used as a search template with different number of mismatches (normally not more than one-third of the motif length; in reality it is up to four mismatches). To calculate scores for the found motifs (FM), we first assign weights to all SMs. The weight for a searching motif µ with the number of mismatches x we define as:</p><formula>W µ,x = M count µ,x −M pred µ,x M pred µ,x ,</formula><formula>(3)</formula><formula>where M count µ,x and M pred µ,x</formula><p>are measured and predicted occurrences, accordingly. The weight is, in fact, the overrepresentation of the counted motifs with the given number of mismatches over the calculated number of such motifs occurring by chance. After the weights are assigned to each SM, the score for a found motif A is calculated as</p><formula>S A = max µ (W µ,x(µ) )αβ, (4) where max µ (W µ,x(µ)</formula><p>) is the maximal weight for all searching motifs, α is the portion of the SM set that have matched A with positive weight and β is the maximal match (i.e. the maximal portion of A symbols that are identical to SM symbols).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Filtering procedure</head><p>After the search is run (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>, Step 1) and the predictions for the putative motifs and their scores are made (<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>, Steps 2–5), the list of the predicted motifs should be filtered to obtain the optimal results.To select the best hits, we provide scores for each found motif. Those with obviously low scores are filtered out automatically, but in many cases the decision about what to consider 'good' and 'poor' results depends on specific circumstances of a search, in particular on the reliability of the input TFBS set. For this occasion, we provide an opportunity to adjust the filtering threshold according to the desired number of true positive (TP) hits (estimated by the reidentification of true TFBSs inserted in random sequences, see Section 2.4) and acceptable number of FPs (estimated by the run on 'empty' random sequences). By default, the threshold is set to 100% of the TP with 1 allowed mismatch per site and the number of FP corresponding to this threshold is shown in the output. If these numbers are not satisfactory, the user can adjust them by:</p><p>(i) selecting other number of mismatches; and (ii) selecting the optimal score. The search result is accompanied by a plot showing the dependency of true and FPs on the score value. The user-friendly design allows to 'move' the score threshold in the plot showing how it influences the both (TP and FP) parameters and to select the optimal combination.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Align or not align?</head><p>Principally, SiTaR does not require aligned sequences or even sequences of the same length. However, sometimes we encounter unreasonably long (up to 50 bp) TFBSs reported in literature and, consequently, in databases.<ref type="bibr">[</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.Fazius et al.</head><p>should be aligned with the other TFBSs of the set. If all TFBSs of the set are too long, we would recommend to reidentify the 'real' TFBSs within these sequences by looking for a common motif of 6–12 bp [using programs like MEME (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bailey and Elkan, 1994</ref>) or Gibbs Sampler (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Thompson et al., 2003)]</ref>. If the binding sites of the input set are well defined and have comparable length (allowing the same number of mismatches), they can be submitted to the program without further treatment. We want to emphasize that it is not recommendable to look for motifs &lt;6 bp in any case, because the probability of occurrence of such motifs by chance is too high. This is true for any kind of application independently of the searching method: SiTaR, PWMs or another.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Defining true and FPs</head><p>TFBS sets from Jaspar were used as the TP (input) sets in all experiments. In the test run on random sequences (Section 3.2.1), the motifs of the TP (input) set were hidden in a 10 kb random sequence and then reidentified. The results have been cleaned from redundancies (i.e. predictions of motifs in the same location. Location is considered the same if the predicted motifs overlap in more than half of the length). The ranked (from the highest to the lowest score) list of results was cut on the level corresponding to the desired number of TP (by default, 100%). All the predictions made besides hidden sites were considered as FPs. SiTaR: the search was made with 0 mismatches, the threshold being adjusted if 100% of the TP (or the genuine TFBS, in the case of the test run on promoters, Section 3.2.2) has not been reidentified after the first run. Jaspar: the search was made with a low threshold, which was then adjusted to get 100% of the TPs. P-Match: P-Match uses the TRANSFAC matrices, which differ from those in Jaspar. To run P-Match on the exactly same sets of sequences as in the other considered tools, we created PWMs from the Jaspar TFBSs for each considered TF using Create Matrix option of the Professional version of Match TM. The profiles in P-Match were applied with the lowest possible threshold (minFN), and then adjusted to get 100% of the TPs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Validation of the method</head><p>To demonstrate that our models are not overfitted and can indeed predict new motifs, we conducted cross-validation experiments. For each of the selected TFs, the initial set of TFBSs was arbitrarily divided into two halves, one serving as a training set, the other being 'hidden' in a random sequence. The whole procedure was repeated 100 times. The idea was to check whether the approach allows to reidentify those genuine motifs, which were not used for the training. We repeated the experiment for five arbitrarily chosen TFs from TRANSFAC database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Matys et al., 2003</ref>) and one 'reallife' example taken from a paper reporting binding sites for Rlm1 TF (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Jung and Levin, 1999</ref>) (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). The average sensitivity and specificity by reidentification of the 'new' motifs are both 99.9%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Comparison with other methods</head><p>We compared our method with Jaspar database searching tool (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bryne et al., 2008</ref>) and with P-Match (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chekmenev et al., 2005</ref>). Jaspar was selected as the most prominent PWM-based tool and P-Match is the representative of 'mixed' approaches, utilizing PWM information along with the alignments of individual TFBSs. The comparison was run for 22 TFs (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>), which were selected according to the following requirements: (i) the TF should be represented by a PWM in Jaspar; (ii) binding sites should have reasonable length (6–15 bp);and (iii) the number of sequences in the set should be not too small (&gt;20). The sites used for the PWM construction were extracted from Jaspar and considered as the TP set.and F 0,5measure: F β = (1+β 2 )·precision·recall / (β 2 ·precision+recall ); in this case, β is taken equal to 0.5 to give more weight to precision than to recall. Average characteristics of each tool by 100% recall are shown in<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>(see also Supplementary Material for more details). The specificity of SiTaR, P-Match and Jaspar are equally high for all tools and although there is a tendency of SiTaR and P-Match to outperform Jaspar, the difference is not significant. There is also no difference in the performance of SiTaR and P-Match in FDR and F-measure. However, these characteristics significantly differ for SiTaR and Jaspar, SiTaR showing apparently better results than Jaspar.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Test run on random sequences with hidden true sites</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Test run on promoter sequences</head><p>To demonstrate the performance of our tool on real biological sequences, we ran reprediction of known (experimentally proven) TFBSs in promoters where they belong. Information about genuine binding sites of the considered TFs was extracted from TRANSFAC Professional (version 2001.1). The sites were selected according to the following requirements: (i) there should be solid evidence of DNA binding; (ii) coordinates of the TFBS should be provided; and (iii) the corresponding promoter sequence should be available in TRANSFAC. In such way, we collected 44 genuine binding sites for 16 TFs in 38 promoters. The promoter sequences were cut to 2000 bp upstream transcription start sites (according to TRANSFAC). The search was made with the same input TFBS sets as in the previous experiment. The searching parameters were adjusted in such way that we could detect the real TFBSs. All predictions with the scores lower than the score of the genuine site were filtered out. The true TFBSs were successfully reidentified by SiTaR and Jaspar in all considered promoters (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>). P-Match, however, could not find the sites in nine promoters probably due to too high pre-defined cut-offs, which are not adjustable in the professional version of the tool (these cases are marked as 'not found', NF, in the<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>). In approximately 25% of promoters (9 of 38), the performance of the three tools was similarly successful: the number of predictionsbesides the known true sites was 0 or 1 (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>: R28506, R00114, R01457, R03585, R00244, R23825, R29148, R02909, R03963, R00441). However, promoter sequences are hard to interpret in terms of FP predictions, because we practically never can be completely sure in non-functionality of a predicted binding site. This kind of negative evidence is not published, and actually not investigated. On the other hand, our observations made for real TFBSs in mammalian promoters (based on the data from TRANSFAC) suggest that the Page: 2810 2806–2811</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.Fazius et al.</head><p>number of occurrences of binding sites for the same TF in one promoter is rarely &gt;10. Taking this into account, we can assume that all predictions that are &lt;10 per promoter are equally good and can be considered not as false, but as potentially functional TFBSs. Under this assumption, we consider additional predictions as potentially true in 10 of 38 promoters (∼25%) (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>: R14636, R16113, R05060, R24474, R04344, R12441, R22697, R25977, R25317, R20171, R23225, R09707). In seven promoters, SiTaR is superior to P-Match, but the results of SiTaR and Jaspar do not differ (R05061, R29890, R08566, R25062, R20786, R19784, R00036). Only in one case of 38 considered SiTaR was outperformed by P-Match (Elk1 in TNFalpha promoter: one of the three known sites had a low score, hence the number of additional predictions grew to 26 opposed by 17 in P-Match, the number of Jaspar predictions being 43; we must admit, however, that the performance of all tools was not optimal in this promoter). SiTar was not outperformed by Jaspar in any of the considered promoters. Finally, in nine cases (23%) (R00270, R05040, R24127, R29073, R08567, R16582, R00142, R29834, R13028, R13029), SiTaR outperforms the both competitors. All in all, SiTaR performed equally or better in 37 promoters of 38 considered.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>SiTaR is a method for nucleotide composition-based detection of non-random matching motifs applied to prediction of TFBSs or other types of motifs. One of the evident advantages of the method is that it does not require equal length of the searching motifs, nor their alignment, nor a construction of a PWM nor any other modeling prior to the search. Any of those steps (aligning, trimming to equal length, etc.) leads to the loss of information (as any generalization) and hence introduces some degree of uncertainty in the final result. Thus, avoiding these steps we preserve as much information as there was in the initial set of TFBS sequences. It is notable that the demand for a high quality of the initial (searching) set of TFBS sequences is equally strong for any approach: ours or PWM based. The other, quite important, consequence of the lack of the abovementioned steps is saving of time and efforts. To use SiTaR, one needs to have just a set of known TFBS sequences; this can come directly from a publication or a database. To use any PWM-based tool, one needs to have the PWM. It either can be found in a matrix database, such as TRANSFAC or Jaspar, or has to be made de novo (from that set of known sequences, which we directly use in SiTaR). To do that, one has to (i) align the sequences; (ii) find a tool for PWM construction; and (iii) apply it. Of note, Jaspar and other prominent PWM-based tools like Matrix-scan or the public version of P-Match do not allow to construct own matrices. This means that even when SiTaR demonstrates equal performance with a PWM-based tool, this result is achieved by lower expenses. The experiment with reidentification of the TP set with three different methods showed general superiority of the tools that use aligning of individual motifs (SiTaR and P-Match). This conforms to the thesis that PWMs are too generalized. P-Match tries to overcome the PWM generalization by including the step of aligning of individual motifs of a PWM with subsets of the query sequence and applying the PWM characteristics when calculating the scores. This attempt significantly improves the prediction in terms of the number of FPs. However, P-Match remains dependent on PWMs, with all consequences discussed in the previous paragraphs. In SiTaR, we omit the generalization step completely. The positive feature of PWMs is that they reflect conservation of particular nucleotides within the motif. This kind of information is not directly considered by our method, since we allow mismatches in any position of the motif. However, the theoretically allowed mismatches in the conserved positions are in practice corrected by matching of the 'correct' (true) motifs and accumulation of the correct matches. So the conservation of a certain base is in fact taken into account in an indirect way. To reinforce this effect, we put special emphasis on the multiple matching of the motifs when calculating the score. On the other hand, one should not underestimate the fact that TFBS sets can be very divergent, and some single true sites may strongly differ from the rest of the set (in fact, they can be completely unalignable). In a PWM (and, hence, in P-Match), such sites are in a way suppressed, so that their content is not reflected neither by the consensus sequence nor by the weights assigned to each position. On the opposite, our approach allows each motif to play its role independently of the rest of the set. So finally SiTaR is balancing between multiple and individual matching, allowing each of them to be equally successful if the found motif is recognized as non-random. In terms of accuracy of predictions, by 100% of sensitivity SiTaR is superior to Jaspar when reidentifying TFBSs in random sequences (<ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>, Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). The results of P-Match and SiTaR do not significantly differ, although also here there is a slight tendency of SiTaR to have lower FDR and higher F 0.5-measure (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). Ideally, all sites presented in databases like TRANSFAC should be genuine, but we cannot exclude the possibility that one or two of them are actually false, simply because of the FP rate of the wet-lab experiments. For this reason, it not always makes sense to insist on the recovering of the whole TP set; in fact, in some TFBS sets we can observe just one sequence obviously not belonging to the rest of the set, 'spoiling' the whole picture. Taking into account such chances, we also considered reidentification of 90% of the TP. For this level of sensitivity, the difference in the performance of all considered tools is not anymore significant; however, the tendency of SiTaR to outperform Jaspar and P-Match remains the same (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). In promoter sequences, the performance of SiTaR is comparable with that of Jaspar in 27 of 38 promoters (∼70%); in the rest 30%, however, SiTaR predicts less additional (potentially FP) sites. Since we do not know the real number of TP TFBSs in genuine promoters, we cannot estimate such characteristics as FDR, but we can judge about the sensitivity of the methods. In the considered examples, we can see that the sensitivity of Jaspar and SiTaR is equally high (100% of the real TFBSs are redetected), whereas the sensitivity of P-Match remains quastionable (we will return to this point in a few lines). Our demands to the interpretation of the predictions in promoters can be formulated as following:</p><p>(i) the true TFBS has to be recovered; (ii) there should not be too many TP sites (we allowed up to 10 additional TFBSs considering them as potentially TP; an excess over 10 was considered as potential FPs). Both criteria are met by SiTaR with success. It reidentifies all true TFBSs (of note, for this analysis we tried to select those true TFBSs that have not SiTaR</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>been used</head><p>in the SM set); the number of potential FP predictions made by SiTaR is in average lower than that predicted by P-Match and Jaspar. The other advantage of our tool is the possibility to interactively adjust the filtering threshold. The importance of this procedure is illustrated by the problems encountered by P-Match by redetection of TFBSs in real promoters. In SiTaR and Jaspar, the cut-offs are adjustable and this allows to reidentify all true TFBSs. In P-Match, on the opposite, there are only three fixed cut-offs and the lowest of them (MinFN, minimal false negatives) appeared to be still too high for the reidentification of the genuine TFBSs. As a result, the tool fails because of the problem that has nothing to do with the algorithm. Normally, to change the cut-offs one has to return on the input page and change some input parameters. In some tools (like P-Match and Match TM in TRANSFAC), a special procedure of creating a matrix profile is needed. In the others, like Jaspar, it is not clear what the score means, so the procedure of the threshold selection is 'blind'. Having had a severe experience with other tools, we endeavored to make the procedure of the threshold adjustment clear and simple. The user can watch simultaneously: the selected number of mismatches; the current score; the corresponding numbers of FP and TP. The interactive plot allows to see what will be the values of TP and FP if the score changes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">IMPLEMENTATION AND AVAILABILITY</head><p>The SiTaR tool is implemented in PHP. It is freely available at http://sbi.hki-jena.de/sitar/index.php.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Main steps of the SiTaR algorithm. Step 1 (Search): each searching motif (SM) is used as a search template with different number of mismatches; Step 2: for each FM, we mark the number of mismatches between it and each searching motif; Step 3: for each SM, we write down the number of its counted (in the Step 2) occurrences with given number of mismatches and the corresponding predicted value of such occurrence by chance. Step 4: the weights for each SM are calculated according to formula (3). Step 5: calculation of the scores [formula (4)]. The ranked list of the scores is filtered according to the user's wishes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>The normal TFBS length is 6–12 bp, in rare cases up to 18 bp. If a TFBS is too long (30–50 bp), it just means that the authors have not well defined the binding sites and reported approximate regions of the TFBS surroundings.] In such cases, to get searching motifs of reasonable length the reported sequences Page: 2808 2806–2811</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Results of the cross-validation tests</figDesc><table>TF name 
No. of TFBSs 
Re-identification 

Sensitivity (%) 
Specificity (%) 

Srf 
45 
100 
99.98 
Mef2a 
58 
99.96 
99.84 
NFYA 
114 
100 
99.99 
Sox9 
76 
99.63 
98.46 
USF1 
30 
100 
99.78 
Rlm1 
50 
99.96 
99.91 
Average 
99.93 
99.66 

Half of the TFBS set was hidden in a 10 000 bp long random sequence, the other half 
was used as training set. The analysis was repeated 100 times. The 're-identification' 
column shows the values of sensitivity and specificity for each TF averaged through 
100 runs. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2.</figDesc><table>FP predictions made by SiTaR, P-Match and Jaspar by 
reidentification of 100% and 90% of TP sites 

TF 
Jaspar ID No. of 
sites 

FP 

100% recall 
90% recall 

SiTaR P-Match Jaspar SiTaR P-Match Jaspar 

ARID3a MA0151.1 27 
9 
13 
13 
7 
13 
8 
Arnt 
MA0004.1 20 12 
18 
59 
3 
18 
59 
Ddit:Cebp MA0019.1 37 
0 
0 
47 
0 
0 
22 
Elf5 
MA0136.1 44 
2 
3 
372 
2 
3 
32 
Elk1 
MA0028.1 29 
0 
2 
256 
0 
2 
123 
Foxf2 
MA0030.1 20 
2 
5 
153 
2 
5 
119 
HNF4a 
MA0114.1 66 
0 
0 
NA 
0 
0 
36 
Mef2a 
MA0052.1 58 
0 
1 
29 
0 
1 
1 
MIZF 
MA0131.1 20 
0 
0 
184 
0 
0 
5 
NFATC MA0152.1 25 13 
20 
83 11 
20 
58 
NFIL3 
MA0025.1 23 
0 
0 
84 
0 
0 
0 
NFkB 
MA0061.1 27 
0 
0 
33 
0 
0 
16 
NFYA 
MA0060.1 114 
0 
0 
69 
0 
0 
3 
NHLH1 MA0048.1 54 
0 
0 
7 
0 
0 
3 
NKx3-2 MA0122.1 24 
2 
15 
335 
2 
9 
170 
Pax2 
MA0067.1 30 
8 
20 
278 
6 
20 
158 
Pbx 
MA0070.1 18 
0 
0 
68 
0 
0 
1 
RORA 
MA0071.1 25 
0 
2 
5 
0 
2 
2 
Sox5 
MA0087.1 22 
7 
12 
66 
7 
12 
16 
Sox9 
MA0079.1 76 
3 
3 
550 
3 
3 
346 
Srf 
MA0083.1 45 
0 
0 
NA 
0 
0 
0 
T 
MA0009.1 20 
0 
0 
4 
0 
0 
0 

NA, not achieved, 100% of TP could not be reidentified. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><figDesc>All motifs of the TP set were hidden in a 10 kb random sequence; any hit different from the hidden motif was considered as a FP prediction, since random sequences are not supposed to contain TPs. We considered the number of the FP predicted by each tool when recovering 100% and 90% of the TP (Table 2). For 100% sensitivity, Page: 2809 2806–2811 SiTaR Fig. 2. Average specificity, FDR and F 0.5-measure of SiTaR, P-Match and Jaspar by 100% recall (see Supplementary Table S1 for more details). the results of SiTaR and P-Match are comparable in two-thirds of cases, in the rest leaving the superiority to SiTaR. In comparison with Jaspar, SiTaR performs inevitably better for all considered TFs. For 90% sensitivity, Jaspar shows improved results, but still the superiority of SiTaR and P-Match is obvious. To be able to quantitatively compare the methods, we calculate specificity [Spc = TN/(FP + TN), where TN stands for true negatives], false discovery rate [FDR = FP/(FP + TP)]</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 3. Results of the reprediction of genuine TFBSs in promoter sequences TF name Gene name Site ID a Coordinates b Additional predicted sites</figDesc><table>SiTaR P-Match Jaspar 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We would like to thank Reinhard Guthke and Daniela Albrecht for critical reading and valuable comments on the article. We thank the first users of SiTaR for their trust, comments and suggestions for the interface design.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict</head><p>of Interest: none declared.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>btr492. .tex]</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2811" to="2806" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fitting a mixture model by expectation maximization to discover motifs in biopolymers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Bailey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Elkan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Second International Conference on Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology</title>
		<meeting>the Second International Conference on Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="36" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring conservation of transcription factor binding sites with CONREAL</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Berezikov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">395</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="448" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selection of DNA binding sites by regulatory proteins. Statistical-mechanical theory and application to operators and promoters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Berg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Von Hippel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="723" to="750" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">JASPAR, the open access database of transcription factorbindng profiles: new content and tools in the 2008 update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Bryne</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="106" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MatInspector and beyond: promoter analysis based on transcription factor binding sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Cartharius</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2933" to="2942" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">P-Match: transcription factor binding site search by combining patterns and weight matrices</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Chekmenev</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="432" to="437" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical significance of clusters of motifs represented by position specific scoring matrices in nucleotide sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Frith</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3214" to="3224" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DISCOVER: a feature-based discriminative method for motif search in complex genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Fu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="329" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An intuitionistic approach to scoring DNA sequences against transcription factor binding site motifs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Garcia-Alcalde</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">551</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AliBaba2: context specific identification of transcription factor binding sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Grabe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In Silico Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">VOMBAT: prediction of transcription factor binding sites using variable order Bayesian trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Grau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="533" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CORE_TF: a user-friendly interface to identify evolutionary conserved transcription factor binding sites in sets of co-regulated genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Hestand</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">495</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide analysis of gene expression regulated by the yeast cell wall integrity signalling pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Jung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Levin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1049" to="1057" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MATCH A tool for searching transcription factor binding sites in DNA sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Kel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3576" to="3579" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TRANSFAC ® transcriptional regulation, from patterns to profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Matys</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="374" to="378" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of motifs based on a repeated-measures model for integrating cross-species sequence and expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Siewert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Kechris</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Appl. Genet. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Article. 36</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gibbs Recursive Sampler: finding transcription factor binding sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Thompson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3580" to="3585" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using RSAT to scan genome sequences for transcription factor binding sites and cis-regulatory modules</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Turatsinze</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1578" to="1588" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>