
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:52+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis SmashCell: a software framework for the analysis of single-cell amplified genome sequences</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eoghan</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Harrington</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Microbiology and Immunology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94305</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Manimozhiyan</forename>
								<surname>Arumugam</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">EMBL</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Meyerhofstrasse 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>69117</postCode>
									<settlement>Heidelberg, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jeroen</forename>
								<surname>Raes</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">EMBL</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Meyerhofstrasse 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>69117</postCode>
									<settlement>Heidelberg, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">VIB -Vrije Universiteit Brussel</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pleinlaan 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>1050</postCode>
									<settlement>Brussels</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Max Delbrück Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D-13092</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Relman</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Microbiology and Immunology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94305</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genome analysis SmashCell: a software framework for the analysis of single-cell amplified genome sequences</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2979" to="2980"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq564</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 14, 2010; revised on September 10, 2010; accepted on September 30, 2010</note>
					<note>[10:57 17/11/2010 Bioinformatics-btq564.tex] Page: 2979 2979–2980 Associate Editor: Dmitrij Frishman Contact: eoghanh@stanford.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Recent advances in single-cell manipulation technology, whole genome amplification and high-throughput sequencing have now made it possible to sequence the genome of an individual cell. The bioinformatic analysis of these genomes, however, is far more complicated than the analysis of those generated using traditional, culture-based methods. In order to simplify this analysis, we have developed SmashCell (Simple Metagenomics Analysis SHell-for sequences from single Cells). It is designed to automate the main steps in microbial genome analysis—assembly, gene prediction, functional annotation—in a way that allows parameter and algorithm exploration at each step in the process. It also manages the data created by these analyses and provides visualization methods for rapid analysis of the results. Availability: The SmashCell source code and a comprehensive manual are available at http://asiago.stanford.edu/SmashCell</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The rapid evolution of DNA sequencing platforms has had a dramatic, beneficial impact on the study of microbial ecology and population genetics. So far, these benefits have mostly come from shotgun community metagenomics that provides a highlevel overview of the taxonomic and functional composition of microbial communities<ref type="bibr">[see Arumugam et al. (2010) for details]</ref>. However, this approach is limited in its ability to yield complete genome sequences as well as the fine-scale genetic variation that defines population substructures within these communities. One possible solution uses a combination of single-cell manipulation technologies, multiple-displacement amplification (MDA) and highthroughput sequencing to generate single-cell amplified genomes (SAGs). This approach has already been used to characterize the genomes of uncultivated microbes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Marcy et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Woyke et al., 2009</ref>) and as the throughput of the associated technologies</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">FEATURES</head><p>SmashCell automates the steps common to most genome analyses— assembly, gene prediction and functional annotation—and addresses some of the challenges posed by SAGs. For instance, it is difficult to isolate a single cell for sequencing without including some environmental DNA, in effect creating a metagenome. As a result, SmashCell includes both sequence similarity and k-mer based tools to identify potential contaminants, the latter being especially useful when the target genome and/or contaminants are not closely related to existing genome sequences (see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1B</ref>for details). Another challenge with SAGs is the orders of magnitude variance in MDA product abundance along the genome, which creates several obstacles to obtaining high-quality annotation. First, it hampers genome assembly, as most algorithms are designed for lower and more evenly distributed read depth. Secondly, it vastly increases the amount of sequencing required to obtain a complete genome sequence. To address the first challenge, SmashCell includes scripts to downsample overrepresented regions of the SAG and to address the second, SmashCell uses the STRING database (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Jensen et al., 2009</ref>) to obtain counts of single-copy orthologous groups (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1C</ref>), which can then be used to estimate genome completeness. In addition to these SAG-specific features, SmashCell contains genomevisualization and other tools (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1D</ref>) that are generally applicable to genomic and metagenomic data. SmashCell uses the same basic data model as SmashCommunity [designed for shotgun community sequencing;<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arumugam et al. (2010)]</ref>. As a result, several of the analyses available in SmashCell can be run on data generated by SmashCommunity and vice versa. Documentation for these and many more features are available on the SmashCell website.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.D.Harrington et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DESIGN AND IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>SmashCell is a framework written in Python that provides a variety of analysis tools that can be used either from the command line or from within other Python scripts. The main function of SmashCell is to automate the common steps in genome analysis in a way that facilitates parameter and algorithm exploration. Using the data model shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1A</ref>, SmashCell manages the files and data associated with each of these steps, reducing redundancy and providing a layer of abstraction that simplifies access to these data. SmashCell also uses generic databases to provide a common format for assembly and gene prediction information, allowing it to work with a variety of third-party assemblers and gene prediction algorithms. In order to facilitate the exploration of genomic data, SmashCell automatically generates many different types of graphs (e.g. see<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1B</ref>–D) and provides wrappers for exploratory statistical techniques.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the US Government 2010. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. (A) The data model used in SmashCell is designed to reduce redundancy and facilitate the comparison of results using different parameters and/or algorithms [MC: metagenome collection, MG: metagenome (equivalent to a SAG), AS: assembly, GP: gene prediction, FUNC: functional annotation]. (B) K-mer frequency statistics supplement sequence similarity information to identify potential contaminants. This shows a self-organizing map (SOM) trained on the tetramer frequencies of an assembly. The left panel shows a series of pie charts highlighting the taxonomic identity (determined by best hit in GenBank, those with no hits are uncoloured) of the contigs assigned to each neuron. The right panel shows the U-matrix of the SOM. (C) The abundance of single-copy COGs can be used to assess genome completeness, the presence of contamination and the quality of the assembly. (D) SmashCell uses different graphs to aid in parameter and algorithm selection. Here the results from two different gene prediction algorithms are presented, along with GC-content, quality scores and read depth.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. increase it should become possible to obtain high-resolution profiles of populations or communities. However, it is more difficult to produce a high-quality assembly and functional annotation from a SAG than from the output of traditional methods due to limitations inherent in sample preparation and sequencing (detailed below). To overcome this requires an iterative, exploratory approach that transforms the traditional linear process of genome assembly, gene prediction and functional annotation into a tree-like structure, each branch defined by a different choice of algorithm or parameters, one of which will be chosen as the final version (Fig. 1A). This approach is not easily achieved using existing tools, which take an assembled genome as their input and do not allow parameterization of subsequent steps (for a comparison with existing tools see Supplementary Table). In order to automate the process and deal with the resulting combinatorial increase in data we have created SmashCell. While developed for use on SAGs many of its analyses are equally applicable to traditional microbial genome sequences and low-complexity metagenomes.</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from [10:57 17/11/2010 Bioinformatics-btq564.tex]</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We would like to thank S. Pamp and P. Blainey for assistance with testing.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SmashCommunity: a metagenomic annotation and analysis tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Arumugam</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2977" to="2978" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">STRING 8–a global view on proteins and their functional interactions in 630 organisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Jensen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="412" to="416" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dissecting biological &quot; dark matter &quot; with single-cell genetic analysis of rare and uncultivated TM7 microbes from the human mouth</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Marcy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11889" to="11894" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assembling the marine metagenome, one cell at a time</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Woyke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>