
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">SNPdryad: predicting deleterious non-synonymous human SNPs using only orthologous protein sequences</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ka-Chun</forename>
								<surname>Wong</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">The Donnelly Centre for Cellular and Biomolecular Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>M5S 3E1</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Zhaolei</forename>
								<surname>Zhang</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">The Donnelly Centre for Cellular and Biomolecular Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>M5S 3E1</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Banting and Best Department of Medical Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>M5S 3E1</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>M5S 1A8</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alfonso</forename>
								<surname>Valencia</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>M5S 3G4</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">SNPdryad: predicting deleterious non-synonymous human SNPs using only orthologous protein sequences</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1112" to="1119"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt769</idno>
					<note type="submission">Sequence analysis Advance Access publication January 2, 2014 Received on August 6, 2013; revised on November 7, 2013; accepted on December 13, 2013</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Contact: Zhaolei.Zhang@utoronto.ca Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: The recent advances in genome sequencing have revealed an abundance of non-synonymous polymorphisms among human individuals; subsequently, it is of immense interest and importance to predict whether such substitutions are functional neutral or have deleterious effects. The accuracy of such prediction algorithms depends on the quality of the multiple-sequence alignment, which is used to infer how an amino acid substitution is tolerated at a given position. Because of the scarcity of orthologous protein sequences in the past, the existing prediction algorithms all include sequences of protein paralogs in the alignment, which can dilute the conservation signal and affect prediction accuracy. However, we believe that, with the sequencing of a large number of mammalian genomes, it is now feasible to include only protein orthologs in the alignment and improve the prediction performance. Results: We have developed a novel prediction algorithm, named SNPdryad, which only includes protein orthologs in building a multiple sequence alignment. Among many other innovations, SNPdryad uses different conservation scoring schemes and uses Random Forest as a classifier. We have tested SNPdryad on several datasets. We found that SNPdryad consistently outperformed other methods in several performance metrics, which is attributed to the exclusion of paralo-gous sequence. We have run SNPdryad on the complete human proteome, generating prediction scores for all the possible amino acid substitutions. Availability and implementation: The algorithm and the prediction results can be accessed from the Web site</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) are single nucleotide variations between different individuals of the same species. They account for the majority of the genetic variations among human individuals, as it is estimated that a single SNP is present in every 2000 nt between any two individuals (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Altshuler et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Stranger et al., 2007</ref>). Depending on how the amino acid is affected by the polymorphism, the SNPs in the protein coding regions can be classified into synonymous SNP (those that do not change amino acid), non-synonymous SNP (nsSNP) (those change the amino acid) and nonsense mutations (where a SNP results in a stop codon). Based on the data from the 1000 Genomes Project, it is estimated that on an average a human individual possesses 10 000–11 000 non-synonymous substitutions compared with the reference human genome sequence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abecasis et al., 2010</ref>). A number of databases had been developed to curate and store these human SNP data, which include dbSNP, OMIM, SNPdbe and dbNSFP (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Amberger et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Liu et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Schaefer et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Sherry et al., 2001</ref>). In addition to SNPs found in the protein coding regions, recent genome-wide association and expression Quantitative Trait Loci (eQTL) studies and the large-scale ENCODE project also revealed many SNPs located outside of the protein coding regions (called regulatory SNPs or rSNPs) that are also implicated in human diseases. However, these rSNPs are not discussed here, as we only focus on the effect of SNPs found in the protein coding regions. Synonymous SNPs are usually assumed to be functional neutral because they do not change the protein sequence, but in rare cases they can affect protein folding, disrupt RNA secondary structure or disrupt miRNA binding sites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Johnson et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kimchi-Sarfaty et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Lin et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Shabalina et al., 2013</ref>). Although many nsSNPs are probably selectively neutral, i.e. having little functional effects, a substantial fraction of these nsSNPs are indeed predicted to be deleterious because they can potentially disrupt functional sites on a protein or affect their correct folding (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Lohmueller et al., 2008</ref>). Many nsSNPs are also linked to human disorders; many of these disease associated SNPs are documented in databases, such as OMIM, pharmGKB and HGMD (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Adzhubei et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Amberger et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Sunyaev et al., 2001</ref>). Because of the potential functional consequences of nsSNPs, several computational methods had been developed to in silico predict whether an nsSNP is deleterious. Some of these methods include SIFT, PolyPhen, PolyPhen2, SNPs3D, SNAP and MutationTaster (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Adzhubei et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bromberg et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Ng and Henikoff, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Schwarz et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Sunyaev et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Yue et al., 2006</ref>). These methods usually work by estimating the likelihood that a mutation (nsSNP) is tolerated based on whether the *To whom correspondence should be addressed. amino acid residue is observed in other evolutionarily related orthologous or paralogous protein sequences or sequence fragments, and whether the mutation is tolerated based on protein structure and the physiochemical properties of the amino acids. The major differences among these methods are how these evolutionary and structural features are extracted, and what algorithm (classifier) is used in combining these features to make a decision. There also exist ensemble methods, such as Condel and Logit, which use Naive Bayes and Logistic Regression, respectively, to combine individual prediction methods (Gonzalez<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Perez and Lopez-Bigas, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Li et al., 2013</ref>). As described above, an accurate and unbiased multiple sequence alignment of a protein of interest with its orthologous and paralogous sequences is essential to derive a conservation profile of the protein, which can be used to estimate how a mutation is tolerated (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hicks et al., 2011</ref>). Ideally, only orthologous sequences should be used in this step because these orthologs are expected to perform similar function in related organisms, and the corresponding amino acid position is expected to have the same evolutionary, biophysical and structural constraint. However, to the best of our knowledge, all the current nsSNP analysis algorithms include paralogous sequences in the multiple sequence alignment (MSA) step, which perhaps was a necessity a few years ago because of the scarcity of the fully sequenced proteome sequences. However, inclusion of paralogous sequences can potentially introduce noises in generating protein sequence conservation profiles because when compared with orthologs, protein paralogs are more likely to diverge in sequence and in cellular functions. On an average, the amino acid sequence identity between paralogous protein pairs is only 30% (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Axelsen et al., 2007</ref>). The recent breakthroughs in sequencing technology have generated fully sequenced genomes and proteomes for a large number of vertebrates, which potentially can eliminate the need for including paralogous protein sequences in building multiple sequence alignment. In this article, we show that, by including only orthologous protein sequences, we achieved better performance in predicting deleterious nsSNPs. Other innovations in our method include the choice of using Random Forest in classification, which had been previously shown to be effective in high-dimension data classification (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Caruana et al., 2008</ref>). We benchmarked our prediction method, termed SNPdryad, against other methods and showed that SNPdryad consistently achieved better sensitivity and specificity on the datasets tested.<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>summarizes the overall design of SNPdryad. The input of SNPdryad is a non-synonymous human SNP and the sequence of the human protein that the SNP is on; the output is the predicted deleterious score for the input nsSNP. The higher the score, the more deleterious the input nsSNP is predicted to be.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Overview of the SNPdryad algorithm</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Collecting orthologous protein sequences</head><p>We ran the Inparanoid program to obtain orthologous protein sequences from other organisms (<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Ostlund et al., 2010</ref>); the human proteins were extracted from Ensembl (GRCh37). To ensure the quality of the final multiple sequence alignment, we limited our ortholog search to only mammalian species<ref type="bibr">[</ref>. Such an approach has been proven to be successful in detecting conserved regulatory elements (<ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Xie et al., 2005</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Generating sequence alignment profile</head><p>We used the MUSCLE software for multiple-sequence alignment, using the default parameter setting (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Edgar, 2004</ref>). Other alignment tools such as MAFFT and Clustal were also tested; MUSCLE was picked because of its alignment accuracy and speed (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Edgar, 2004</ref>). Given a multiple sequence alignment, the next step is to derive a positional-specific conservation profile and use it to estimate the tolerance toward mutations at each position. Two important calibrations are needed at this step: how to weight each input protein sequence, and how to score the amino acid substitutions. Kumar and colleagues previously showed that the choice of sequence-weighting scheme and substitution-scoring scheme are crucial at this step in distinguishing the deleterious nsSNPs from the rest (<ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kumar et al., 2009</ref>); therefore, we explored four different sequence-weighting schemes and two different substitution-scoring schemes in our work (a total of eight distinct ways of measuring conservation scores). All of the eight conservations scores were input into SNPdryad as features and were automatically weighted and selected by Random Forest classifier to achieve the best performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Constructing feature vectors</head><p>2.4.1 Sequence-weighting schemes (i) In the first sequence-weighting scheme, each individual input protein sequence is treated equally and given the same weight. (ii) In the second sequence-weighting scheme, a weight is calculated for each input protein sequence based on its overall sequence similarity to the human protein sequence. In particular, the sum of pair-wise BLOSUM62 alignment score is computed as the weight to quantify the pair-wise sequence similarity. The higher the sequence similarity (sum of BLOSUM62 scores), the higher weight is given to the input sequence. Such a weighting scheme is different from the ones used in PolyPhen2, SIFT and other prediction methods, which in contrast give low weight to the sequence that is highly similar to the human sequence. The rationale in their approaches is that such a low weight can eliminate redundant or highly similar sequences when searching for homologous sequences in a large sequence database. In contrast, SNPdryad does not have such drawbacks because only orthologous protein sequences are allowed in the alignment. SNPdryad can confidently assign a high<ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. Overall design of the SNPdryad algorithm. Given an nsSNP and the human protein, SNPdryad collects the orthologous protein sequences from other mammals and performs a multiple-sequence alignment (MSA). Once aligned, SNPdryad calculates features from the alignment and uses the trained Random Forest classifier to predict and output a deleterious effect score</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.3">Physiochemical properties of amino acids In addition to</head><p>sequence conservation profile, we also included the physiochemical properties of the amino acids as a feature in our classification scheme. The following properties are included: hydropathy index (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kyte and Doolittle, 1982</ref>), polarity (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Cooper and Hausman, 2007</ref>), mass (<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Reichert and Suhnel, 2002</ref>), volume (<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Zamyatnin, 1972</ref>), surface area (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Chothia, 1976</ref>), residue non-polar surface area (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Karplus, 1997</ref>), estimated hydrophobic effects for residue burial and side chain (<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Karplus, 1997</ref>), population percentage of being exposed in solvent, being buried in solvent and being neither exposed nor buried in solvent (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bordo and Argos, 1991</ref>). We note that these features are not independent from each other.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.4">Other features To alleviate the noise and fluctuation</head><p>in the data, the number of protein sequences included in the multiple-sequence alignment and the number of distinct amino acid residues in the nsSNPcontaining column are also used as features in the classifier. The rationale for such treatment is that the conservation scores derived from alignment of higher number of sequences are deemed more reliable than scores derived from fewer sequences. In addition, functional annotation of the region on the protein where the SNP is present is also important. Based on such a rationale, we have included the presence of the annotations from PFAM, SUPERFAMILY and PROSITE as the features for predictions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Hulo et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Punta et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Wilson et al., 2009</ref>). The complete list of features used is listed in Supplementary Table S1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Classification methods</head><p>We evaluated 10 leading classification methods, applied them onto the aforementioned features and benchmarked their performance following a standard 10-fold cross-validation procedure. These methods include Random Forest (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Breiman, 2001</ref>), Naive Bayes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">John and Langley, 1995</ref>), Bayes Network (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Cooper and Herskovits, 1992</ref>), Multilayer Perceptron (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bishop, 1995</ref>), AdaBoost (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Freund and Schapire, 1996</ref>), Support Vector Machine using Polynomial Kernel (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Burges, 1998</ref>), Support Vector Machine using Radial Basis Kernel (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Burges, 1998</ref>) and three k-Nearest Neighbor Classifiers (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Cover and Hart, 1967</ref>). These methods are implemented in software WEKA (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Hall et al., 2009</ref>); their parameter settings are well-tuned and described in the Supplementary Text.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">Datasets</head><p>To ensure a fair comparison, we have downloaded the datasets from the PolyPhen-2 Web site, namely HumDiv and HumVar (version 2.1.0) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Adzhubei et al., 2010</ref>). Both datasets were compiled from UniProtKB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Magrane and Consortium, 2011</ref>). Specifically, HumDiv was compiled using the annotation keywords, which imply causal mutation–phenotype relationships, whereas HumVar was compiled from all the human disease-causing mutations annotated. HumDiv has 7070 neutral nsSNPs and 5322 deleterious nsSNPs, whereas HumVar has 21 142 neutral nsSNPs and 20 989 deleterious nsSNPs. In particular, HumDiv is considered higher in quality than HumVar because the SNPs in HumDiv were selected using a controlled set of keywords.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Classification model selections in SNPdryad</head><p>We trained and tested the aforementioned 10 classification models on HumDiv and HumVar, following the standard 10-fold cross-validation. The results are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>for HumDiv and HumVar. It is clear that, for each classification method and for both HumDiv and HumVar, using only orthologous proteins had a better performance than inclusion of paralogous proteins. Not only did the orthologs-only approach achieve better prediction accuracy and Area Under Receiver Operating Characteristics (ROC) Curve (AUC), but it also had lower level of error. In addition, the Random Forest method had the best performance; this is also consistent with a previous comparison study showing that Random Forest is the best in highdimensions empirically (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Caruana et al., 2008</ref>). The predictive power of the Random Forest classifier lies in its ensemble nature with bagging and random subspace techniques. Instead of relying on a single-decision tree, Random Forest takes into account the votes of multiple decision trees to make the final prediction decision.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Comparisons on the HumDiv and HumVar datasets</head><p>Next, we compared the prediction performance of SNPdryad (using only orthologs and Random Forest classifier) with other commonly used nsSNP analysis methods, MutationTaster, PolyPhen2 and SIFT (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Adzhubei et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Ng and Henikoff, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Schwarz et al., 2010</ref>). Some other prediction methods such as SNPs3D were not included in the comparison because they are no longer actively maintained (<ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Yue et al., 2006</ref>). Ensemble methods such as Condel, which reanalyze results from other methods, are not included in the comparison either. We used the HumDiv and HumVar datasets for the basis of the comparison. PolyPhen2 and other methods also used the same datasets in evaluations. To ensure an objective and unbiased comparison, we downloaded the prediction results from the web servers of PolyPhen2, SIFT and MutationTaster, respectively, in January 2012.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>compares the ROC curves and the Precision-Recall curves for these four methods. It is clear from<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>that SNPdryad outperforms all three other methods on both HumDiv and HumVar datasets, whereas PolyPhen2 has the second best performance. We like to note that PolyPhen2 was fully trained on the same HumDiv and HumVar datasets, whereas the other methods were not; this may complicate the comparison. After comparing the overall prediction accuracy, we next investigated how frequently the methods agreed with each other on whether an nsSNP is considered deleterious. Because these methods use different statistical schemes to denote prediction confidence or degree of harmful effect, it is impossible to select a single statistical threshold (e.g. a single P-value) to apply to all methods and compare the predictions that are above this threshold. To overcome this problem, for each method, we first selected all the nsSNP that are predicted to be deleterious and ranked these nsSNPs according to this specific method's own scoring scheme, from the most deleterious to the least deleterious. We then compared the overlap among the top ranked nsSNPs predicted by each method. The resultant Venn diagrams are shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>. Three observations can be made from these Venn diagrams. (i) At a lower cutoff, the methods have a greater level of overlap in their predictions; however, among the top predicted nsSNPs, the overlapping fraction becomes much smaller. (ii) The nsSNPs that are predicted to be deleterious by more than one method are always more accurate than those predicted by a single method. Notably, such observation is in contrast to a previous study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Li et al., 2012</ref>). A possible explanation is that SNPdryad and PolyPhen2 are trained on the same datasets, boosting their ensemble performance. (iii) SNPdryad predicts more unique deleterious nsSNP that are missed by the others at a higher accuracy. For example, among the top 10% predicted nsSNPs, SNPdryad predicted 260 unique deleterious nsSNPs alone (256 are true positives, accuracy ¼ 98%). We next ranked the nsSNPs from HumDiv by the predicted scores of each of the three methods, and calculated the pair-wise Spearman's rank correlation coefficients. As a comparison, we also calculated the correlations with the annotated deleterious effect provided in the HumDiv dataset (0 denotes neutral and 1 denotes deleterious).<ref type="figure">Table 2</ref>shows that among the four methods, SNPdryad has the highest correlation with Annotation (0.83) than the others, suggesting that SNPdryad has higher accuracy than other methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Exclusion of paralogs contributes to better performance in SNPdryad</head><p>After concluding that SNPdryad is accurate in predicting deleterious nsSNPs, at least on the HumDiv and HumVar datasets, we next investigated whether such a superior performance was the result of either a better classifier (Random Forest) or the factNote: RF, Random Forest; NB, Naive Bayes; BNet, Bayes Network; MLP, MultiLayer Perceptron; AB, AdaBoost; POLY, Support Vector Machine using Polynomial Kernel; RBF, Support Vector Machine using Radial Basis Kernel; kNN, k Nearest Neighbor. The parameter settings can be referred to supplementary data. In each row the classification model that has the best performance is highlighted in bold. that we only included orthologous protein sequences. We compared the AUC values of PolyPhen2 (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2A</ref>and 2B, 0.95 for HumDiv and 0.89 for HumVar) to the AUC values of different classifiers that we tested in SNPdryad (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). It can be seen from<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>that if homologous sequences are used, PolyPhen2 has higher AUC than all the classification models except for Random Forest (0.96). However, the top half of the<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>shows that if only orthologous sequences are used, several other classification methods such as BNet (Bayesian Net), MLP (MultiLayer Perceptron) and AB (AdaBoost) actually have better AUC scores (0.96) than PolyPhen2 (0.95). Such comparisons showed that the decision of including only orthologous protein sequences is the primary reason for the good prediction power of SNPdryad.To further illustrate such an idea, two examples of deleterious nsSNPs are shown in the Supplementary Figures S1–S6, which are correctly predicted by SNPdryad but by neither PolyPhen2 nor SIFT. These cases demonstrate that the quality of the MSA is crucial in accurately predicting deleterious nsSNPs. The first case is a SNP located at the position 1161 of the Complement C3 protein (P01024), which changes a Glutamine residue (Q) to a Lysine residue (K), causing increased susceptibility to hemolytic uremic syndrome atypical type 5 (AHUS5) (UniProt variation ID: VAR_063219). Supplementary Figures S1–S3 compare the MSAs generated by SNPdryad, PolyPhen2 and SIFT, respectively. The substitutions to Lysine (K) or Arginine (R) are found in the alignments generated by both PolyPhen2 (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure S3</ref>) and SIFT (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S2</ref>), misleading these algorithms to predict this particular SNP as a neutral substitution in human. This is likely caused by the inclusion of protein sequences paralogous to the input human protein. In contrast, neither Lysine (K) nor Arginine (R) is found in the orthologous sequence alignment computed by SNPdryad, which accurately predicted this nsSNP as deleterious (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S1</ref>). Supplementary Figures S4–S6 show another example of a mutation at position 104 on human Transthyretin protein (P02766), which changes an Isoleucine (I) to a Serine residue (S) (UniProt ID: VAR_007584). This deleterious mutation has been shown to contribute to transthyretin-related amyloidosis (AMYL-TTR). The sequence alignments generated by both SIFT (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure S5</ref>) and PolyPhen2 (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S6</ref>) include residue Serine at position 104, which likely caused both programs to predict this substitution as a neutral one. SNPdryad accurately predicted this mutation as a deleterious mutation (Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure S4</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Prediction on nsSNPs annotated in SNPdbe</head><p>Next, as an independent benchmark, we used SNPdryad to make predictions on the nsSNPs curated in the SNPdbe database, and compared the results of SNPdryad, PolyPhen2, SIFT and MutationTaster. SNPdbe is a comprehensive database that collects and annotates SNP information from multiple sources, including dbSNP, SwissProt, OMIM and 1000 Genomes (URL: http://www.rostlab.org/services/snpdbe/) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Schaefer et al., 2012</ref>). A small subset of these SNPs has disease association information. Based on the SNPdbe database dump (<ref type="bibr">March 2012</ref>), we have compiled a dataset, which is given in Supplementary Table S3.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>depicts the ROC curves and the PrecisionRecall curves for these four methods. Again, SNPdryad has the best performance among these methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Prediction on nsSNPs annotated in ExoVar</head><p>As another independent benchmark dataset, we have selected the latest ExoVar dataset (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Li et al., 2013</ref>). ExoVar consists of not only the UniProt annotations but also the recent rare nsSNPs in the 1000 Genomes Project. To be consistent with the past study (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Li et al., 2013</ref>), we have removed the variants that are not derived alleles. As shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref>, the performance of SNPdryad is similar to that of Logit and better than all the other methods, including PolyPhen2 and MutationTaster. It is worth noting that both Logit and Condel are ensemble methods, which take input predictions from individual methods and output a weighted average. SNPdryad has the best performance among all the independent methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">Predictions on human proteome</head><p>In this section, we first trained SNPdryad on the HumDiv dataset then ran it on the entire human proteome (Ensembl version GRCh37.64) for all the possible substitutions at all the amino acid positions. Note, in this sense, we are testing the functional effect of amino acid substitutions instead of on nsSNPs. Prediction Score Distribution: Supplementary<ref type="figure">Figure S7</ref>depicts the average prediction scores for all the possible pair-wise substitutions between 20 amino acid residues, averaged over all the possible amino acid positions in the human proteome. The complete predictions can be accessed at our Website: http://snps. ccbr.utoronto.ca:8080/SNPdryad/. In general, not surprisingly, we observe that the predicted deleterious effect of replacing one amino acid by another is consistent with their similarity in physiochemical properties. In particular, most of the nonsynonymous substitutions to Tryptophan (W) are likely to be deleterious and most of the non-synonymous substitutions to Alanine (A) are likely functional neutral. Furthermore, Serine(S) and Threonine (T) are mostly interchangeable to each other based on the prediction scores. In total, we scanned 92 012 human proteins (including protein isoforms) and 36 935 804 amino acid positions; a total of 10 120 155 substitutions ($1.4%) were predicted to be fully deleterious (with the SNPdryad prediction score of 1). Next, we investigated whether such fully deleterious SNPs are enriched or depleted among common human variants. To achieve this, we filtered the nsSNPs annotated in the SNPdbe database, and retained only those common nsSNPs that have major allele frequency 40.05, as estimated by the 1000 Genomes Project. This resulted in 14 733 nsSNPs on 6645 proteins (designated as Query set). Among them, 627 nsSNPs were predicted by SNPdryad to be fully deleterious. As a Background control dataset, we also took the same 6645 human proteins, and simulated all the possible non-synonymous substitutions at all positions under the constraint that their amino acid type changes [e.g. Arginine (R) to<ref type="bibr">Glutamine (Q)</ref>] do exist in the aforementioned 14 733 common variants. The resultant Background had 32 246 488 nsSNPs, among which 2 529 197 nsSNPs were predicted to be fully deleterious by SNPdryad. By computing the hypergeometric cumulative distribution function between the Query set and Background set, we observed significant depletion of fully deleterious nsSNPs among the common nsSNPs (Query Set) with P51:0674 Â 10 À69. Such depletion of highly deleterious SNPs, while fully expected, further demonstrated the value and effectiveness of prediction algorithms such as SNPdryad. PFAM Domain Statistics: We are interested to know where these fully deleterious substitutions are located, especially which PFAM protein domains are enriched of such extremely deleterious substitutions. Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S2</ref>lists the top PFAM domains that contain the highest number of harmful (i.e. fully deleterious) nsSNPs. It shows that the G protein coupled receptor (GPCR) domain (PF00001) contains the highest number of harmful nsSNPs as predicted by SNPdryad. GPCR domains are important domains in cell-surface receptors, which sense molecules outside of cells in many disease-causing signaling pathways. They are also important therapeutic targets, as $40% of all modern drugs target GPCR proteins (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Filmore, 2004</ref>). We also used odds-ratio to ascertain the statistical significance of these enrichments (last column). (Assuming every sequence position in every human protein are equally likely to be hit by a harmful nsSNP, we define the sum of the sequence lengths of the domain hits of a Pfam domain D as l D in a human proteome. We also define the sum of the sequence lengths of all the proteins in the human proteome as l Total. Given a harmful nsSNP, the probability that it is located at the domain D is calculated as lD lTotal. If we have N harmful nsSNPs, the expected number of their hits located at the domain D can be calculated as N Â lD lTotal. Based on such an idea, the expected nsSNP hits are calculated for each domain. The odds-ratio of a domain is then calculated as the number of observed deleterious nsSNPs residing in a domain, divided by the expected number of deleterious nsSNPs in the domain.)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>In this article, we described SNPdryad, a novel computational method that can predict deleterious effect of amino acid substitutions occurred in human proteins. As elaborated in this article, SNPdryad outperforms other leading algorithms in accurately predicting deleterious nsSNPs. We demonstrated that this is primarily because SNPdryad only includes orthologous sequences in building the multiple-sequence alignment, as opposed to other contemporary methods, which include paralogous sequences as well. Such an innovation allows construction of a more accurate protein sequence conservation profile, allowing a more precise estimate on whether a substitution is tolerated at a specific position. This would not have been possible until now, when a large number of mammalian or vertebrate genome sequences have been completely sequenced, thanks to the drastically decreasing cost of genomic sequencing. The next-generation sequencing technology has generated a deluge of genomic sequences and subsequently, a wealth of genetic variation data such as nonsynonymous polymorphisms. We envision that an intelligent algorithm such as SNPdryad can take advantage of this large amount of data and further improve the accuracy of predicting deleterious nsSNPs.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Pongo pygmaeus abelii (PPYG2), Mus musculus (NCBIM37), Macaca mulatta (MMUL_1), Canis familiaris (BROADD2), Equus caballus (EquCab2), Rattus norvegicus (RGSC3.4), Cavia porcellus (cavPor3), Bos taurus (UMD3.1) and Monodelphis domestica (BROADO5)]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Performance comparison of SNPdryad, MutationTaster, PolyPhen2 and SIFT on the HumDiv and HumVar datasets. (a) ROC curves of the three methods on the HumDiv dataset, (b) ROC curves on the HumVar dataset. The vertical axis denotes true positive rate, while the horizontal axis denotes false positive rate. (c) Precision-Recall Characteristics (PRC) curves on the HumDiv dataset, (d) PRC curves on the HumVar dataset. The vertical axis denotes precision, while the horizontal axis denotes recall. Based on the AUC values, we can observe that their performances are different</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Venn diagram showing the overlap between deleterious nsSNPs predicted by SNPdryad, PolyPhen2, SIFT and MutationTaster on the HumDiv dataset on which they all made successful predictions. The red, green, blue and gray ellipses denote the predictions of SNPdryad, PolyPhen2, SIFT and MutationTaster, respectively. The numbers indicate the number of predicted deleterious nsSNP, whereas the bracketed numbers indicate the number of true positive predictions. In HumDiv, 44% of the SNPs were previously annotated as deleterious; therefore, in panel (a) we selected and compared the top 44% of the predictions made by each method. Panel (b) compares the top 10% predictions made by each method</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. Performance comparison of SNPdryad, PolyPhen2, SIFT and MutationTaster on the labeled SNPdbe dataset. (a) ROC curves (b) PRC curves</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig.5.</head><figDesc>Fig. 5. Performance comparison of SNPdryad with other methods on the ExoVar dataset. (a) ROC curves (b) PRC curves. Note that the ensemble and individual methods are denoted in dotted lines and solid lines, respectively. The performance curves of the other methods are adopted from the past literature (Li et al., 2013)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Results of the 10 Classification Models trained and tested on the HumDiv and HumVar dataset using the standard 10-fold cross-validation</figDesc><table>HumDiv dataset 
RF 
NB 
BNet 
MLP 
AB 
POLY 
RBF 
1NN 
3NN 
5NN 

Using the orthologous sequences from Inparanoid 
Accuracy 
0.93 
0.88 
0.90 
0.91 
0.90 
0.91 
0.91 
0.87 
0.87 
0.87 
Kappa statistics 
0.85 
0.76 
0.79 
0.81 
0.80 
0.83 
0.82 
0.73 
0.74 
0.74 
Root mean absolute error 
0.24 
0.34 
0.31 
0.29 
0.27 
0.29 
0.30 
0.36 
0.32 
0.31 
Root relative squared error 
0.48 
0.68 
0.64 
0.58 
0.54 
0.59 
0.60 
0.73 
0.64 
0.63 
AUC 
0.98 
0.94 
0.96 
0.96 
0.96 
0.92 
0.91 
0.87 
0.92 
0.93 

Using the homologous sequences from UniRef100 
Accuracy 
0.89 
0.78 
0.86 
0.87 
0.85 
0.88 
0.87 
0.84 
0.84 
0.84 
Kappa statistics 
0.77 
0.56 
0.71 
0.73 
0.68 
0.75 
0.72 
0.67 
0.67 
0.68 
Root mean absolute error 
0.28 
0.46 
0.37 
0.34 
0.33 
0.35 
0.37 
0.40 
0.35 
0.34 
Root relative squared error 
0.57 
0.93 
0.75 
0.69 
0.67 
0.71 
0.74 
0.81 
0.71 
0.69 
AUC 
0.96 
0.90 
0.93 
0.94 
0.92 
0.87 
0.86 
0.84 
0.90 
0.91 

HumVar dataset 
RF 
NB 
BNet 
MLP 
AB 
POLY 
RBF 
1NN 
3NN 
5NN 

Using the orthologous sequences from Inparanoid 
Accuracy 
0.83 
0.76 
0.80 
0.81 
0.79 
0.82 
0.82 
0.77 
0.79 
0.80 
Kappa statistics 
0.66 
0.53 
0.60 
0.62 
0.58 
0.64 
0.64 
0.54 
0.58 
0.60 
Root mean absolute error 
0.35 
0.48 
0.44 
0.38 
0.39 
0.42 
0.43 
0.48 
0.40 
0.39 
Root relative squared error 
0.70 
0.96 
0.88 
0.75 
0.77 
0.85 
0.85 
0.96 
0.81 
0.77 
AUC 
0.91 
0.87 
0.88 
0.89 
0.86 
0.82 
0.82 
0.78 
0.85 
0.87 

Using the homologous sequences from UniRef100 
Accuracy 
0.81 
0.73 
0.78 
0.80 
0.79 
0.80 
0.80 
0.76 
0.78 
0.78 
Kappa statistics 
0.63 
0.46 
0.55 
0.59 
0.58 
0.61 
0.61 
0.53 
0.55 
0.56 
Root mean absolute error 
0.36 
0.52 
0.46 
0.38 
0.38 
0.44 
0.44 
0.49 
0.41 
0.40 
Root relative squared error 
0.72 
1.04 
0.92 
0.76 
0.76 
0.89 
0.89 
0.97 
0.83 
0.80 
AUC 
0.90 
0.83 
0.86 
0.88 
0.87 
0.80 
0.80 
0.78 
0.84 
0.85 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><figDesc>Table 2.</figDesc><table>Pair-wise Spearman rank correlation coefficients between the 
prediction scores of SNPdryad, PolyPhen2, SIFT, MutationTaster and 
the annotations on the HumDiv dataset. The highest is highlighted in bold 

SNPdryad PolyPhen2 SIFT Mutation 
Taster 

Annotations 

SNPdryad 
1 
0.8145 
0.7084 0.6983 
0.8271 
PolyPhen2 
1 
0.7764 0.7634 
0.8044 
SIFT 
1 
0.6770 
0.7157 
MutationTaster 
1 
0.7167 
Annotations 
1 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">SNPdryad: Predicting deleterious amino acid substitutions at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from weight to a similar orthologous sequence that is believed to be functionally consistent with the human sequence. (iii) In the third weighting scheme, each input sequence is weighted according to their evolutionary distance from human. We first ran the PhyML program on the aligned sequences to build a phylogenetic tree (Guindon et al., 2010); each sequence is then assigned the weight of 1 minus the additive branch length to human sequence. (iv) In the fourth approach, we adopted the same scheme as in the weighting method used in the &apos;evolutionary trace&apos; (Mihalek et al., 2004). This method takes into account the sequence conservation at multiple levels of the phylogenetic tree constructed and assigns weights globally. 2.4.2 Substitution-scoring schemes We tested two substitutionscoring schemes in estimating the conservation level at each amino acid position: information entropy (Shannon Entropy) and simple BLOSUM62 scores. The former is an unbiased measure of amino acid conservation, whereas the latter can take into account the biophysical properties of each amino acid. In the end, by combining four different sequence-weighting schemes and two different substitution-scoring schemes, we calculated eight different conservation scores for each amino acid at each position that has an nsSNP in the human protein sequence. Next, we calculated the differences in conservation score between the reference allele and the variant allele and incorporated it as a feature into the classification model. Overall Conservation Statistics: Besides the conservation score calculated at the nsSNP-containing column in the multiple-sequence alignment, the mean and standard deviation of the entropy of the alignment is also calculated. Z-score can thus be calculated for the nsSNP-containing column.</note>

			<note place="foot">K.-C.Wong and Z.Zhang at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">SNPdryad: Predicting deleterious amino acid substitutions at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A map of human genome variation from populationscale sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Abecasis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">467</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1061" to="1073" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A method and server for predicting damaging missense mutations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Adzhubei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating common and rare genetic variation in diverse human populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Altshuler</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">467</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">McKusick&apos;s online mendelian inheritance in man (OMIM)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Amberger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="793" to="796" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parameters of proteome evolution from histograms of amino-acid sequence identities of paralogous proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Axelsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Direct</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">32</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Neural Networks for Pattern Recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Bishop</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Suggestions for &apos;&apos;safe&apos;&apos; residue substitutions in sitedirected mutagenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Bordo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Argos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">217</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="721" to="729" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Random forests</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Breiman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mach. Learn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SNAP predicts effect of mutations on protein function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Bromberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2397" to="2398" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A tutorial on support vector machines for pattern recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J C</forename>
				<surname>Burges</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Data Min. Knowl. Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="167" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An empirical evaluation of supervised learning in high dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Caruana</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 25th International Conference on Machine Learning, ICML &apos;08</title>
		<meeting>the 25th International Conference on Machine Learning, ICML &apos;08<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="103" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The nature of the accessible and buried surfaces in proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Chothia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="1976" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A bayesian method for the induction of probabilistic networks from data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Cooper</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Herskovits</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mach. Learn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="347" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Cell: A Molecular Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Cooper</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Hausman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<publisher>Sinauer Associates, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Sunderland, MA, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>4th. edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nearest neighbor pattern classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Cover</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Hart</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inf. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="1967" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Edgar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1792" to="1797" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">It&apos;s a GPCR world</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Filmore</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mod. Drug Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experiments with a New Boosting Algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Freund</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Schapire</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Thirteenth International Conference on Machine Learning</title>
		<editor>Lorenza,S.</editor>
		<meeting>the Thirteenth International Conference on Machine Learning</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="148" to="156" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving the assessment of the outcome of nonsynonymous SNVs with a consensus deleteriousness score, Condel</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Gonzalez-Perez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Lopez-Bigas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="440" to="449" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New algorithms and methods to estimate maximumlikelihood phylogenies: assessing the performance of PhyML 3.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Guindon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="321" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The weka data mining software: an update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Hall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIGKDD Explor. Newsl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of missense mutation functionality depends on both the algorithm and sequence alignment employed</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Hicks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mutat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="661" to="668" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The PROSITE database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Hulo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="230" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating continuous distributions in bayesian classifiers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>John</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Langley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Eleventh conference on Uncertainty in artificial intelligence, UAI &apos;95</title>
		<meeting>the Eleventh conference on Uncertainty in artificial intelligence, UAI &apos;95<address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="338" to="345" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA structures affected by single nucleotide polymorphisms in transcribed regions of the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Johnson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">WebmedCentral Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1600</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrophobicity regained</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Karplus</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1302" to="1307" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A &apos;&apos;silent&apos;&apos; polymorphism in the MDR1 gene changes substrate specificity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Kimchi-Sarfaty</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">315</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="525" to="528" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positional conservation and amino acids shape the correct diagnosis and population frequencies of benign and damaging personal amino acid mutations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kumar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1562" to="1569" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple method for displaying the hydropathic character of a protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Kyte</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Doolittle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Locating protein-coding sequences under selection for additional, overlapping functions in 29 mammalian genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F</forename>
				<surname>Lin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1916" to="1928" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comprehensive framework for prioritizing variants in exome sequencing studies of Mendelian diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">X</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">53</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting mendelian disease-causing non-synonymous single nucleotide variants in exome sequencing studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">X</forename>
				<surname>Li</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003143</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2013) dbNSFP v2.0: a database of human non-synonymous SNVs and their functional predictions and annotations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mutat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2393" to="2402" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proportionally more deleterious genetic variation in European than in African populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Lohmueller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">451</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="994" to="997" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UniProt Knowledgebase: a hub of integrated protein data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Magrane</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">U</forename>
				<surname>Consortium</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Database</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A family of evolution-entropy hybrid methods for ranking protein residues by importance</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Mihalek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">336</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1265" to="1282" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SIFT: predicting amino acid changes that affect protein function</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Ng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Henikoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3812" to="3814" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">InParanoid 7: new algorithms and tools for eukaryotic orthology analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Ostlund</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Pfam protein families database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Punta</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The IMB jena image library of biological macromolecules: 2002 update</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Reichert</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Suhnel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="254" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SNPdbe: constructing an nsSNP functional impacts database</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Schaefer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="601" to="602" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MutationTaster evaluates disease-causing potential of sequence alterations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Schwarz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="575" to="576" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sounds of silence: synonymous nucleotides as a key to biological regulation and complexity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Shabalina</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2073" to="2094" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">dbSNP: the NCBI database of genetic variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Sherry</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="308" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relative impact of nucleotide and copy number variation on gene expression phenotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Stranger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">315</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="848" to="853" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of deleterious human alleles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Sunyaev</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mol. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="591" to="597" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SUPERFAMILY–sophisticated comparative genomics, data mining, visualization and phylogeny</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Wilson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="380" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic discovery of regulatory motifs in human promoters and 3 0 UTRs by comparison of several mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Xie</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">434</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="338" to="345" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SNPs3D: candidate gene and SNP selection for association studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Yue</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">166</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein volume in solution</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Zamyatnin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog. Biophys. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="1972" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>