
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:32+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Solubis: optimize your protein</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Greet</forename>
								<surname>De Baets</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cellular and Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">VIB Switch Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Katholieke Universiteit Leuven</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3000</postCode>
									<settlement>Leuven</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Vrije Universiteit Brussel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1050</postCode>
									<settlement>Brussels</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joost</forename>
								<surname>Van Durme</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cellular and Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">VIB Switch Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Katholieke Universiteit Leuven</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3000</postCode>
									<settlement>Leuven</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Vrije Universiteit Brussel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1050</postCode>
									<settlement>Brussels</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rob</forename>
								<surname>Van Der Kant</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cellular and Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">VIB Switch Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Katholieke Universiteit Leuven</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3000</postCode>
									<settlement>Leuven</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Joost</forename>
								<surname>Schymkowitz</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cellular and Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">VIB Switch Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Katholieke Universiteit Leuven</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3000</postCode>
									<settlement>Leuven</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Frederic</forename>
								<surname>Rousseau</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cellular and Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">VIB Switch Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Katholieke Universiteit Leuven</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3000</postCode>
									<settlement>Leuven</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Solubis: optimize your protein</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv162</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on December 16, 2014; revised on February 26, 2015; accepted on March 16, 2015</note>
					<note>Structural bioinformatics *To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. Associate Editor: Anna Tramontano Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Protein aggregation is associated with a number of protein misfolding diseases and is a major concern for therapeutic proteins. Aggregation is caused by the presence of aggregation-prone regions (APRs) in the amino acid sequence of the protein. The lower the aggregation propensity of APRs and the better they are protected by native interactions within the folded structure of the protein, the more aggregation is prevented. Therefore, both the local thermodynamic stability of APRs in the native structure and their intrinsic aggregation propensity are a key parameter that needs to be optimized to prevent protein aggregation. Results: The Solubis method presented here automates the process of carefully selecting point mutations that minimize the intrinsic aggregation propensity while improving local protein stability. Availability and implementation: All information about the Solubis plugin is available at http://solu</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Protein aggregation remains a major bottleneck in the production of many therapeutic proteins. To reduce this aggregation problem, several approaches have been developed such as (i) generation of a fusion protein containing a solubilizing tag (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Park et al., 2008</ref>); (ii) careful formulation of the buffer (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Wang, 1999</ref>) or (iii) increasing the colloidal stability by increasing the net charge (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Kramer et al., 2012</ref>). Nowadays, it is, however, common knowledge that aggregation is mediated by the presence of aggregation-prone regions (APRs) resulting in several computational methods that can predict the aggregation tendency and therefore, the effect of a mutation on protein aggregation (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>). As none of the available methods currently takes into account protein stability, there is a need of integrating these with protein stability predictors (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>). The Solubis method is such an integration approach that selects mutations that reduce the aggregation tendency by combining both TANGO (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Fernandez-Escamilla et al., 2004</ref>) and the empirical forcefield FoldX (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Schymkowitz et al., 2005</ref>). This combination results in a tool to guide the design of aggregation-resistant protein sequences, by identifying mutations that reduce TANGO while respecting the thermodynamic stability. We experimentally validated the approach by improving the solubility and abundance of both protective antigen and alpha-galactosidase (unpublished results). In addition, we analyzed the performance of our method on published variants that increase solubility (Supplementary<ref type="figure">Table S2</ref>). Eighteen of the 24 variants (75%) lower the aggregation tendency (DTANGO &lt; 0), where the other six mutations do not increase he aggregation tendency. In contrast, many of them do not pass our conservative criteria of respecting structural stability (DDG &lt; 1). However, for a large fraction of mutations with a DDG higher than 1, the calculation were based on homology models, which is known to negatively affect the performance of FoldX. Overall, 6 out of the 24 analyzed variants that increase solubility can be identified following the Solubis method presented here butthis number increases to six out of seven if homology models are not included. Therefore, the use of homology models is not recommended to obtain an accurate prediction of the effect on protein stability. For user friendliness, we here present an implementation of Solubis in the YASARA molecular viewer environment (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Krieger et al., 2002</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Implementation and required software</head><p>The Solubis plugin combines two established methods, FoldX and TANGO into YASARA. YASARA (View) can be downloaded freely at http://www.yasara.org. FoldX and TANGO are free for non-commercial purposes and can be downloaded from, respectively, http:// foldx.crg.es and http://tango.crg.es. This plugin is written in python, which needs to be installed on MS Windows (http://www.python. org), and is platform independent. Installing the plugin adds a new dropdown 'Solubis' menu in the main 'Analyze' menu (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">The solubis menu items</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Complete analysis of object</head><p>Complete analysis of object runs the TANGO algorithm and returns the short APRs present in your protein. To have an idea whether your protein contains such a stretch, you can analyze an object of choice. The APRs are colored, if desired according to their aggregating strength, in the same object or in a newly created object. The output of the algorithm is printed to the YASARA console and to a file (see 'Save last calculation').</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Complete analysis of molecule</head><p>This item has the same function as 'Complete analysis of Object' but allows analyzing only certain molecules.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Mutate residue</head><p>Mutate residue mutates one residue to one or more new residues and returns the effect on aggregation tendency. The necessary steps are (i) residue selection to select the residue to mutate; (ii) selection menu to choose the desired replacement residue(s); (iii) set options (temperature, ionic strength and pH) to run the aggregation predictor, default shown; (iv) settings to define an aggregating stretch, default shown and (v) menu to indicate whether your structure contains a gap. This will return a new object for each selected mutation and outputs whether a mutation affects (both increase and decrease) the aggregation tendency. If the effect on protein stability is also required, we advise to use the FoldX plugin (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Van Durme et al., 2011</ref>) or use the menus 'Solubis run on complete molecule' or 'Solubis run in marked region'.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Solubis run on complete molecule</head><p>Solubis run on complete molecule search for a selected number of mutants that minimize the intrinsic aggregation tendency and, if selected, do not destabilize the protein. As minimizing the aggregation tendency is done by introducing so called gatekeepers (P, R, K, D and E) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Rousseau et al., 2006</ref>) into APRs, it is advised to filter out the destabilizing mutations with FoldX. The required steps are (i) select the molecule to mutate; (ii) set options to run the aggregation predictor, default shown; (iii) set thresholds to define an aggregating stretch, default shown (iv) menu to enable the FoldX analysis to calculate the effect on protein stability. As FoldX needs to start from a repaired structure, you need to select 'FoldX RepairPDB' if not the case; (v) options for FoldX specific settings: number of runs, temperature, pH, Ionic strength and Vander Waals penalty, default shown; (vi) menu to select the threshold for aggregation tendency and protein stability, default shown; (vii) box to select how many mutations you want to retrieve and (viii) menu to indicate whether your structure contains a gap. If a mutation minimizes the aggregation tendency with a certain threshold and the DDG is below the selected value (setting point 6), this mutation is considered as a Solubis mutant. Stringent conditions require a more negative DDG (more stabilizing) and more positive aggregation threshold.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Solubis run in marked region</head><p>Solubis run in marked region performs the same calculation as above but on a selected region of the protein. When analyzing a large protein, these calculations can take a considerable amount of time, as multiple APRs are present. To limit the calculation time, this menu allows you to first select a certain region for further investigation. After this step, the same steps are followed as in 'Solubis run on complete molecule'. The marked region has to contain an APR, so it is recommended to first run 'Complete analysis of Object/ Molecule' if unknown.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">Save last calculation</head><p>The user can save all files or just the SUMMARY file. This file contains, dependent on the performed action, the APRs present in a protein, the effect of a mutation on the aggregation tendency or the Solubis mutations. If the user chooses to save all files, this includes the raw output and the used Options file.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Summary</head><p>Solubis is a protein redesign method to abrogate aggregation through disrupting aggregation-nucleating sequences with mutations that maximally reduce their intrinsic aggregation propensity while preserving thermodynamic stability of the functional protein. The graphical interface makes it very straightforward to identify mutants that lead to marked reduction in protein aggregation upon overexpression and will attract non-experienced computer users to perform these complex calculations. However, we want to emphasize that our method does not take into account available information about the active site or post-translational modifications but focus on theSolubis: optimize your proteinstructural integrity. Therefore; users should always control whether the selected mutations do not affect important functional sites.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Solubis interface in YASARA. This menu is part of the Analyze main menu and offers several implemented Solubis commands</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>V C The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com 2580 Bioinformatics, 31(15), 2015, 2580–2582 doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btv162 Advance Access Publication Date: 19 March 2015 Applications Note</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">G.De Baets et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>The Switch Laboratory was supported by grants from VIB, University of Leuven, the Funds for Scientific Research Flanders (FWO), the Flanders Institute for Science and Technology (IWT) and the Federal Office for Scientific Affairs of Belgium (Belspo, IAP network P7/16). R.v.d.K. was supported by Boehringer Ingelheim Pharma GmbH &amp; Co. KG. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of sequence-dependent and mutational effects on the aggregation of peptides and proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Fernandez-Escamilla</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1302" to="1306" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a molecular understanding of protein solubility: increased negative surface charge correlates with increased solubility</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Kramer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1907" to="1915" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increasing the precision of comparative models with YASARA NOVA—a self-parameterizing force field</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Krieger</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="393" to="402" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solubility enhancement of aggregation-prone heterologous proteins by fusion expression using stress-responsive Escherichia coli protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Park</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RpoS. BMC Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How evolutionary pressure against protein aggregation shaped chaperone specificity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Rousseau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">355</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1037" to="1047" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The FoldX web server: an online force field</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Schymkowitz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="382" to="388" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Web. Server issue</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A graphical interface for the FoldX forcefield</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Van Durme</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1711" to="1712" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Instability, stabilization, and formulation of liquid protein pharmaceuticals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Pharm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">185</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>