
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:41+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis SPLATCHE2: a spatially explicit simulation framework for complex demography, genetic admixture and recombination</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Nicolas</forename>
								<surname>Ray</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Environmental Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">EnviroSPACE laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Climate Change and Climate Impacts</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Geneva</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Battelle -Building D, 7 route de Drize</addrLine>
									<postCode>1227</postCode>
									<settlement>Carouge</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mathias</forename>
								<surname>Currat</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Anthropology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Anthropology, Genetics and Peopling History</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Geneva</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1227</postCode>
									<settlement>Geneva</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Matthieu</forename>
								<surname>Foll</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Ecology and Evolution</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Computational and Molecular Population Genetics Lab (CMPG)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Berne</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Baltzerstrasse 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>3012</postCode>
									<settlement>Berne</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1015</postCode>
									<settlement>Lausanne</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Laurent</forename>
								<surname>Excoffier</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Ecology and Evolution</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Computational and Molecular Population Genetics Lab (CMPG)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Berne</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Baltzerstrasse 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>3012</postCode>
									<settlement>Berne</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1015</postCode>
									<settlement>Lausanne</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename>
								<surname>Barrett</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis SPLATCHE2: a spatially explicit simulation framework for complex demography, genetic admixture and recombination</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2993" to="2994"/>
							<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq579</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 19, 2010; revised on September 23, 2010; accepted on October 11, 2010</note>
					<note>[09:52 30/10/2010 Bioinformatics-btq579.tex] Page: 2993 2993–2994 Associate Editor:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>SPLATCHE2 is a program to simulate the demography of populations and the resulting molecular diversity for a wide range of evolutionary scenarios. The spatially explicit simulation framework can account for environmental heterogeneity and fluctuations, and it can manage multiple population sources. A coalescent-based approach is used to generate genetic markers mostly used in population genetics studies (DNA sequences, SNPs, STRs or RFLPs). Various combinations of independent, fully or partially linked genetic markers can be produced under a recombination model based on the ancestral recombination graph. Competition between two populations (or species) can also be simulated with user-defined levels of admixture between the two populations. SPLATCHE2 may be used to generate the expected genetic diversity under complex demographic scenarios and can thus serve to test null hypotheses. For model parameter estimation, SPLATCHE2 can easily be integrated into an Approximate Bayesian Computation (ABC) framework. Availability and implementation: SPLATCHE2 is a C++ program compiled for Windows and Linux platforms. It is freely available at www.splatche.com, together with its related documentation and example data.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>SPLATCHE2 (for SPatiaL And Temporal Coalescences in Heterogeneous Environments, version 2.0) is derived from the program SPLATCHE released in 2004 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Currat et al., 2004</ref>). This coalescent-based program has been developed to model complex and spatially explicit demographic scenarios, such as range expansions, in a heterogeneous and dynamic environment, and to simulate the resulting molecular diversity of sampled individuals at arbitrary locations. It thus makes it possible to realistically model the environment in order to study the impact of ecological factors on the genetic structure of populations. This approach has already proved * To whom correspondence should be addressed. † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. invaluable to study the patterns of genetic variation in spatially explicit contexts (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Foll and Gaggiotti, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Ray et al., 2005</ref>) or the genetic consequences of range expansion (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Currat et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hamilton et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Klopfstein et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ray et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Wegmann et al., 2006</ref>). Many improvements and new functionalities have been added here as compared to the original version of SPLATCHE, allowing the simulation of a much wider range of evolutionary scenarios. Some of these new features have already been used in published studies, such as the simulation of admixture and competition between populations (<ref type="bibr">Excoffier, 2004, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Currat et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Francois et al., 2010</ref>) or the possibility of defining multiple source populations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Ray et al., 2005</ref>). Those extensions have now been incorporated into SPLATCHE2, together with the ability (i) to simulate linked or partially linked loci, (ii) to have multiple coalescent events per generation and (iii) to generate single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNPs). Moreover, SPLATCHE2 is also available as a non-graphical console program that can be used on computer clusters. Here, we briefly describe the main features of SPLATCHE2, noting that a more detailed description can be found in a user manual.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS AND IMPLEMENTATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Demographic simulation</head><p>SPLATCHE2 begins by simulating the demography of one (or two overlapping and interacting) subdivided population(s) made up of haploid individuals. The population demes are arranged on a 2D lattice and each population can expand from one or several sources. Local deme density is logistically regulated, and migration can occur between a deme and its four nearest neighbors. Directional constraints for migration can be defined through a friction parameter. Deme carrying capacity and friction can be set to arbitrary values in every deme and changed at any generation to simulate environmental heterogeneity and its fluctuation over time. Competition between two populations (or species) can also be simulated, potentially leading to the extinction of one of them. An admixture parameter λ may be used to simulate gene flow between the two populations (or species). The intensity of inter-population gene flow can vary between 0 (no admixture) and 1 (full interbreeding).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Coalescent simulation</head><p>The second phase of the simulations uses the demographic history simulated in the previous forward step (population sizes, admixture and migration events) to generate the genetic diversity for a set of samples drawn from thePage: 2994 2993–2994</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>N.Ray et al.</head><p>population. A backward, discrete coalescent model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hudson, 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kingman, 1982</ref>) including recombination based on the ancestral recombination graph (as in the program SIMCOAL2,<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Laval and Excoffier, 2004</ref>) is implemented. Under the coalescent approach, only the genealogy of sampled lineages needs to be reconstructed, which results in an enormous gain in term of computation time. The coalescent tree obtained after such a simulation is then used to generate molecular diversity for the set of samples. Various commonly used genetic markers can be simulated, such as full DNA sequences, SNPs, short tandem repeats (STRs) and restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP). Various combinations of independent, fully or partially linked loci may be simulated. Note that despite simulating haploid genes, diploid individuals can be simulated by combining pairs of alleles or chromosomes under the assumption of Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium. Other coalescent simulation programs can generate genetic data under an island model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Hudson, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Laval and Excoffier, 2004</ref>). Moreover, other forward simulation programs can also generate data under complex demographic models (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Neuenschwander et al., 2008</ref>). To our knowledge, SPLATCHE2 is currently the only coalescent simulation program that can integrate a dynamic and spatially explicit environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Outputs and integration into an approximate Bayesian computation framework</head><p>The main outputs of SPLATCHE2 are a set of ARLEQUIN files (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Excoffier et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Excoffier and Lischer, 2010</ref>) including the resulting genetic diversity of the simulated samples. These files can thus be analyzed by ARLEQUIN to compute a wide array of summary statistics on the data. Moreover, many aspects of the coalescent process may be directly visualized, either as a tree (NEXUS format) or as the geographic locations of coalescent events. When simulating two interbreeding populations, one can output the resulting final levels of genetic introgression between populations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Currat et al., 2008</ref>). In the Windows graphical interface, various aspects of the demography and genetics can also be visualized (e.g. bitmaps of deme densities, migration intensities, movement of genes during the backward simulation). The command-line version of SPLATCHE2 has been developed to facilitate the parallelization of the simulations, such as to allow one to estimate population parameters [e.g. Approximate Bayesian Computation (ABC);<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Beaumont et al., 2002]</ref>. Indeed, SPLATCHE2 can be easily integrated into the ABCtoolbox framework (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Wegmann et al., 2010</ref>) allowing one to get posterior distributions of various demographic and genetic parameters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSION</head><p>SPLATCHE2 can be used to simulate complex and realistic demographic models and to generate the associated molecular diversity of sampled individuals. Alternative population or environmental histories can be modelled and compared through their impacts on resulting genetic diversity. Due to its explicit handling of spatial information and of environmental and temporal heterogeneities, SPLATCHE2 is particularly well suited for studying spatially distributed population samples over relatively short evolutionary time scales (i.e. a few thousand generations).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>[09:52 30/10/2010 Bioinformatics-btq579.tex]</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 31, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We thank Daniel Wegmann, Seraina Klopfstein, Samuel Neuenschwander, Grant Hamilton, Guillaume Laval, Pierre Berthier, Stefano Mona and Anna Sramkova for technical help and useful discussions throughout the development of SPLATCHE2.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximate Bayesian computation in population genetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Beaumont</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">162</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2025" to="2035" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modern humans did not admix with Neanderthals during their range expansion into Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Currat</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Excoffier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">421</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of the Neolithic expansion on European molecular diversity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Currat</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Excoffier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Roy. Soc. Lond B. Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">272</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="679" to="688" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comment on Ongoing adaptive evolution of ASPM, a brain size determinant in Homo sapiens &quot; and &quot; Microcephalin, a gene regulating brain size, continues to evolve adaptively in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Currat</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SPLATCHE: a program to simulate genetic diversity taking into account environmental heterogeneity</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Currat</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ecol. Notes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The hidden side of invasions: massive introgression by local genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Currat</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1908" to="1920" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ARLEQUIN (version 3.0): an integrated software package for population genetics data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Excoffier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evol. Bioinformatics Online</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Arlequin suite ver 3.5: a new series of programs to perform population genetics analyses under Linux and Windows</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Excoffier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E L</forename>
				<surname>Lischer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ecol. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="564" to="567" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying the environmental factors that determine the genetic structure of populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Foll</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Gaggiotti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">174</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="875" to="891" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Principal component analysis under population genetic models of range expansion and admixture</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Francois</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1257" to="1268" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian estimation of recent migration rates after a spatial expansion</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Hamilton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">170</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="417" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Gene Genealogies and the Coalescent Process</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Hudson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generating samples under a Wright-Fisher neutral model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Hudson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="338" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The coalescent</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F C</forename>
				<surname>Kingman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stoch. Proc. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The fate of mutations surfing on the wave of a range expansion</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Klopfstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="482" to="490" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SIMCOAL 2.0: a program to simulate genomic diversity over large recombining regions in a subdivided population with a complex history</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Laval</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Excoffier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1485" to="2487" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">quantiNEMO: an individual-based program to simulate quantitative traits with explicit genetic architecture in a dynamic metapopulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Neuenschwander</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1552" to="1553" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recovering the geographic origin of early modern humans by realistic and spatially explicit simulations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Ray</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1161" to="1167" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intra-deme molecular diversity in spatially expanding populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Ray</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular diversity after a range expansion in heterogeneous environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Wegmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">174</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2009" to="2020" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ABCtoolbox: a versatile toolkit for approximate Bayesian computations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Wegmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">116</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>