
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:46+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">State and parameter estimation of the heat shock response system using Kalman and particle filters</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Xin</forename>
								<surname>Liu</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electronics and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Southampton</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SO17 1BJ</postCode>
									<settlement>Southampton</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mahesan</forename>
								<surname>Niranjan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electronics and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Southampton</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SO17 1BJ</postCode>
									<settlement>Southampton</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">State and parameter estimation of the heat shock response system using Kalman and particle filters</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1501" to="1507"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts161</idno>
					<note type="submission">Systems biology Advance Access publication April 26, 2012 Received on September 26, 2011; revised on February 22, 2012; accepted on April 2, 2012</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Trey Ideker Contact: m.niranjan@southampton.ac.uk Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Traditional models of systems biology describe dynamic biological phenomena as solutions to ordinary differential equations, which, when parameters in them are set to correct values, faithfully mimic observations. Often parameter values are tweaked by hand until desired results are achieved, or computed from biochemical experiments carried out in vitro. Of interest in this article, is the use of probabilistic modelling tools with which parameters and unobserved variables, modelled as hidden states, can be estimated from limited noisy observations of parts of a dynamical system. Results: Here we focus on sequential filtering methods and take a detailed look at the capabilities of three members of this family: (i) extended Kalman filter (EKF), (ii) unscented Kalman filter (UKF) and (iii) the particle filter, in estimating parameters and unobserved states of cellular response to sudden temperature elevation of the bacterium Escherichia coli. While previous literature has studied this system with the EKF, we show that parameter estimation is only possible with this method when the initial guesses are sufficiently close to the true values. The same turns out to be true for the UKF. In this thorough empirical exploration, we show that the non-parametric method of particle filtering is able to reliably estimate parameters and states, converging from initial distributions relatively far away from the underlying true values. Availability and implementation: Software implementation of the three filters on this problem can be freely downloaded from</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>In systems biology, sets of ordinary differential equations (ODEs) are often used to characterize biochemical reactions. The differential equations capture our knowledge of the underlying interactions in a quantitative way and solutions to such systems of equations help explain behaviour at an overall systems level. Much of the work in the area deals with deterministic differential equations, often non-linear (e.g. Hill kinetics). Unknown parameter values in their specification, such as reaction rates, are obtained from biochemical * To whom correspondence should be addressed. experiments conducted in vitro, or are set to specific values by elaborate hand-tuning, so that a set of observations from the system under study are best explained. Sometimes, such parameters may not have direct biological interpretations and are used as approximations (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Lillacci and Khammash, 2010</ref>). The yeast cell cycle model of (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Chen et al., 2000</ref>) is a good example of this. The parameter estimation problem has often been posed as a search and optimization problem in the literature. For example, (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Mendes and Kell, 1998</ref>) have explored a range of optimization methods including steepest descent gradient search techniques and methods suitable for global optimization, such as simulated annealing and genetic programming, in the parameter estimation of metabolic systems. An alternate method using spline approximation of the solution, using linear and non-linear programming is described in a recent paper (<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Zhan and Yeung, 2011</ref>). These authors consider an enzyme kinetic system and a subset of a cell cycle model.<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ashyraliyev et al. (2008)</ref>show how parameters of a developmental gap gene circuit model may be estimated by extensive search methods. Such approaches to model-based explanation of biological phenomena, often do not take into account system and measurement noise in the modelling process. They also do not explicitly seek to infer parameter values or unobserved states from noisy measurements. Techniques using Bayesian inference are alternatives to optimization-based approaches, but having the added motivation of being able to capture uncertainties in parameter and state estimates. Examples of work along these lines include (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Dewar et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Golightly and Wilkinson, 2005</ref>) who consider stochastic systems.<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Barenco et al. (2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">), Jayawardhana et al. (2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">), Lawrence et al. (2006</ref>and Vyshemirsky and<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Girolami (2008)</ref>address ODE-based systems for which parameter estimation is performed by Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods in a probabilistic inference framework. Some authors have recently studied the role of sequential estimation methods for state and parameter estimation from systems biology models, formulated as state-space models. Lillacci and Khammash (2010),<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Nakamura et al. (2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">), Quach et al. (2007</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">), Sun et al. (2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">) and Yang et al. (2007</ref>fall into this category. The first three of these use parametric methods based on Kalman filtering, whereas the latter two use the non-parametric approach of particle filtering. The power of the tools we explore in this article have been demonstrated in other areas of application over many decades. These include the adaptive estimation of neural networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Kadirkamanathan and Niranjan, 1993</ref>), target tracking from bearing-only measurements (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bar-Shalom et al., 2001</ref>), modelling futures contracts in computational finance (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Niranjan, 1997</ref>) and to find global minima of artificial neural networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">de Freitas et al., 2000</ref>). In the context of biology,<ref type="bibr">Dewar et al. (2010), Quach et al.</ref>(2007) and Wilkinson (2009) are examples of using probabilistic dynamical systems models to characterize biological systems and to make parameter estimation and inferences from them. While most literature on the subject focuses on batch-based models, in which parameter estimation and inference are performed on all the available data, our attention is on sequential, or online, methods. The Kalman filter and its variants, and the particle filter (PF) belong to this family. The formulation of jointly estimating state and parameters by an extended state representation we pursue is due to<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Sitz et al. (2002)</ref>, who applied unscented Kalman filter (UKF) to analyze two dynamical systems: the Lotka–Volterra system (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Hofbauer and Sigmund, 1988</ref>) and the Lorenz system (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Colin, 1982</ref>). Unknown parameters are treated as states with their time variation set to zero. To motivate non-parametric particle filtering, with the argument that computation is sufficiently cheap to be able to do this,<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Nakamura et al. (2009)</ref>used an exceedingly large number of Monte Carlo samples to completely cover all the possible states and parameters space for a complex system such as the mammals circadian genetic control model (<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Matsuno et al., 2005</ref>) which has 45 unknown parameters. While this is an ambitious attempt, motivated under the term peta-computing, we do not believe the authors make a persuasive case for flooding the space with particles. Instead, as we find in this work, a modest number of particles, of the order of a few thousands, offer very attractive performance in parameter estimation. Additionally,<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Sun et al. (2008)</ref>applied extended Kalman filter (EKF) to simultaneously estimate the states and parameters of two real datasets [i.e. JAK/STAT signal transduction pathway (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Timmer et al., 2002</ref>) and Ras/Raf/MEK/ERK regulatory pathway (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Kolch, 2000)]</ref>. The remainder of this article is organized as follows. In Section 2, we give the generic formulation of systems biology models cast in state-space form, in Section 3, we describe the three algorithms, in Section 4, we define the heat shock response model we use as our test problem, and in Section 5 we present our results and discuss them. Typical results needed to support our conclusions are presented in the main body of this article, and more detailed results, covering the estimation of various parameter combinations being estimated, are given as online Supplementary Material accompanying this article in the journal's website.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">NON-LINEAR STATE-SPACE MODELS WITH ODES</head><p>Non-linear state-space models of interest here consist of two sets of equations: a set of state equations describing the dynamics of the biological system under study, and a set of output equations that define how observations arise from the state at any time. In the class of systems we consider here, the dynamical system is deterministic, in that there is no process noise, and the observations are assumed to be corrupted by additive noise. Suppose a biological system consists of n state variables, denoted x = (x 1 ... x n ). In every time step, the states of the system are represented by vector x(t), which might consist of concentrations of chemical species of interest, e.g. mRNA, proteins or metabolites. Outputs, related to the state vector x through the function h(·), denoted as y, quantify the observations. Dynamics of the system, characterized by ODEs, are in general written as follow:</p><formula>˙ x(t) = f (x,θ) x(t 0 ) = x 0 ,</formula><formula>(1)</formula><p>where the vector θ =[θ 1 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>.. θ k ]</head><p>T represents the unknown parameters that are going to be estimated. The extended state representation treats the unknown parameters as constants and imposes zero dynamics on them. With this state extension, (<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Sitz et al., 2002</ref>), the system becomes:</p><formula>˙ x = f (x,θ) ˙ θ = 0 x(t 0 ) = x 0 θ(t 0 ) = θ 0 (2)</formula><p>Here, we have a continuous-time underlying dynamical process which is observed at discrete times. Following<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Sitz et al. (2002)</ref>and other authors, the way to solve this problem is to numerically integrate the state dynamics between temporal points at which observations are made, using parameter values estimated in the previous point in time:</p><formula>x t = x t−1 + t t−1 f (x(τ ),θ )dτ (3)</formula><p>By doing so, we are essentially discretizing the continuous-time process. Finally, it is possible to describe the partial observations of the system through the following equation:</p><formula>y t = h(x t )+ω t (4)</formula><p>where ω t represents the white Gaussian noise with covariance matrix R. h(·) is the output function of the system. While the constant unknown parameters ought to have zero dynamics, it often helps to impose a random walk model on them, in order to enable a tracking behaviour which helps convergence from some arbitrary initial guess to their true values. Several authors including (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kitagawa, 1998</ref>) have suggested this. There is extensive discussion in the literature on the ratio between the assumed noise variance of the random walk and the noise variance of the measurements being the determinant of convergence in the Kalman filter setting [e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bar-Shalom et al. (2001)]</ref>.</p><formula>θ t = θ t−1 +ω θ t (5)</formula><p>However, this random walk may sometimes result in divergence and posteriors will far away from the true values. To deal with this, the method proposed in Liu and West (2001) is adopted. The posteriors are guaranteed to converge, if the variance of the random walk model decay with time. Liu and West (2001) intended using kernel smoothing with shrinkage for parameter evolution as follows:</p><formula>θ t = aθ t−1 +(1−a) ¯ θ t−1 +ω θ t a = 3δ −1 2δ (6)</formula><p>δ is a discount factor that lies in<ref type="bibr">[0 1]</ref>, ¯ θ t−1 is mean of the particles in time instance t −1 and ω θ t ∼ N (0,m 2 V t−1 ) is the additive noise to parameter evolution. m 2 = 1−a 2 , V t−1 is the variance matrix of the parameters at time t −1. This is a crucial aspect of implementing such sequential methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">SEQUENTIAL ESTIMATION METHODS</head><p>In the Bayesian framework, we seek the joint posterior distribution of parameters and states, given the measurements, denoted as p(θ ,x t |y t ). the algorithms of interest here recursively estimate this posterior as data arrives one at a time. We first present the three algorithms of the EKF, UKF and PF.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Extended Kalman filter</head><p>The well-known Kalman filter (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Kalman, 1960</ref>) is an optimal state estimator in the case of linear, Gaussian systems. When either of these conditions is violated, the resulting probability density over the unknown states is no longer Gaussian. The EKF approximates the non-linearities by Taylor series expansion about the current operating point and truncates. When the truncation is to first-and second-order terms, closed form update equations are obtainable (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bar-Shalom et al., 2001</ref>). Truncating to the first-order (gradient) term is the most widely used form of EKF, which we pursue here. In order to recursively estimate, we assume the initial condition x + 0 and its error covariance matrix P + 0 are known. The current prior state distribution termed x − t , obtained by integrating the continuoustime state process in the time interval<ref type="bibr">[t −1 t]</ref>with the previous posterior estimate treated as initial condition. The current prior error covariance distribution termed P − t , obtained by integrating a differential Lyapunov equation and initial condition is the posterior error covariance of previous state (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Simon, 2006</ref>). We now define an extended state vector consisting of the states and unknown parameters, following Lillacci and Khammash (2010).</p><formula>s = x θ (7) ˙ s = f ( s)</formula><formula>(8) s − t = f ( s + t−1 ) (9) ˙ P = A t P +PA T t +Q (10)</formula><formula>P − t = ˙ P + t−1 (11)</formula><p>where Q is the covariance matrix of noise in process model and A t is Jacobian matrix of state process f , define as:</p><formula>A t = ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ ∂ f 1 ∂ x 1 ∂ f 1 ∂ x 2 ... ∂ f 1 ∂ xn ∂ f 1 ∂ θ 1 ∂ f 1 ∂ θ 2 ... ∂ f 1 ∂ θ d .. . .. . .. . .. . .. . .. . ∂ fn ∂ x 1 ∂ fn ∂ x 2 ... ∂ fn ∂ xn ∂ fn ∂ θ 1 ∂ fn ∂ θ 2 ... ∂ fn ∂ θ d . ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ (12)</formula><p>The Kalman gain is</p><formula>L t = P − t H T t (H t P − t H T t +R) −1 ,</formula><formula>(13)</formula><p>where R is the covariance matrix of noise in measurement and H t is Jacobian matrix of the measurement model h. The posterior state and covariances are updated as:</p><formula>s + t = s − t +L t (y t −h( s − t )) (14) P + t = (I −L t H t )P − t (I −L t H t ) T +L t RL T t (15)</formula><p>The EKF algorithm is summarized as Algorithm 1:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Unscented Kalman filter</head><p>The UKF carries out a different approximation, in that it consists of a recipe to deterministically define a minimum number of state samples in the prior distribution and propagate them through the dynamical system. These propagated points, referred to as sigma points, are used to re-compute a prior distribution and its covariance (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Julier et al., 1995</ref>) at the next time step. Thus, the UKF also propagates a Gaussian, but the approximation is formulated in a different way and is in fact equivalent to truncating the Taylor expansion of state non-linearity to the second-order term (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Julier et al., 2000</ref>). For more details on UKF implementations, including pseudocode, see<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Julier et al. (1995) and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Quach et al. (2007</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Particle filter</head><p>Sequential Monte Carlo methods, more widely known as PFs, offer a more powerful approach to parameter estimation and inference in dynamical systems (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arulampalam et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">de Freitas et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Doucet et al., 2001</ref>). The family of Monte Carlo algorithms draw samples according to the probability density from which inference is to be made and approximate difficult integrals by sample averages. The core algorithmic step in particle filtering is importance sampling, that of generating identically and independently distributed samples from a proposal density of convenience, with associated weighting of these samples to account for the fact that they were not drawn from the density of interest. In the sequential setting, PF offers recursive ways of updating these weights in addition to propagating them through the dynamical system. A crucial issue in their implementation is the problem of sample degeneracy, that of all samples collapsing into just one position in the state space, and several tricks to circumvent these exist in the literature. A concise summary of these algorithms can be found in the tutorial paper by<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arulampalam et al. (2002)</ref>. A pseudocode description of the PF algorithm is given in Algorithm 2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">THE HEAT SHOCK MODEL</head><p>We consider cellular response to heat shock as a model system to illustrate the relative performance of the three sequential algorithms. El<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Samad et al. (2006)</ref>describe a heat shock response model in the bacterium Escherichia coli, with three differential equations. The model consists of genes encoding molecular chaperones, transcribed in response to a sudden change of environmental temperature, transcription factor σ 32 , which, via binding to RNA polymerase</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>X.Liu and M.Niranjan</head><p>Algorithm 2 Particle filter</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Initialization</head><p>, t = 0 for i = 1,...,N sample s i 0 ∼ p(s 0 ) and set t = 1 end for 2. Importance sampling for i = 1,...,N sample˜ssample˜ sample˜s i t ∼ p(s t |s i t−1 ) and set˜sset˜ set˜s i 0:t = (s i 0:t ,˜ s i t ) end for for i = 1,...,N evaluate the importance weights˜wweights˜ weights˜w i t = p(y t |˜s|˜s i t ) end for Normalize the importance weights 3. Selection step Resample with replacement N particles (s i 0:t ;i = 1,...,N) from the set (˜ s i 0:t ;i = 1,...,N) according to the importance weights Set t → t +1 and go to step 2. enables the transcriptional regulation of heat shock proteins. σ 32 , which is rarely present under normal temperatures in the range (30 @BULLET C–37 @BULLET C), rapidly accumulates at elevated temperatures activating the transcription of heat shock genes, leading to a different equilibrium. The variation in total numbers of the relevant proteins are lumped in the model as two terms whose dynamics is described, along with the numbers of unfolded proteins as follows:</p><formula>˙ D t = K d S t 1+ K s D t 1+K u U f −α d D t ˙ S t = η(t)−α 0 S t −α s K s D t 1+K u U f 1+ K s D t 1+K u U f S t ˙ U f = K(t)[P t −U f ]−[K(t)+K fold ]D t (16)</formula><p>Hereare constants assuming different values at different steady state temperatures. We simulated data from the heat shock model, making use of MATLAB's ODE45 function to integrate the differential equations, generating data over a time length of 200 s, sampled at regular intervals of 0.2 s, giving 1000 sample points for representing the observations. The true values of parameters used are given in Supplementary Table S1. We then applied the three filters to infer the unknown parameter and state. Subsets of the six parameters of the model are to be estimated from noisy subsets of the three states. In the evaluations we considered various combinations of knowns and unknowns (observed and estimated), as described in the following sections. The simplest scenario we considered is one in which two of the three states (D t and U f ) and five of the six parameters were assumed known. This corresponds to a case in of a well understood biological, some aspects of which are experimentally observable, subject to additive measurement noise, whereas others are inaccessible.Implementation details for this scenario, leading to the results in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>are as follows: of the EKF is set to start from the prior state vector s =<ref type="bibr">[0,0,0,0.01]</ref>, the last element is the initialization for parameter estimate. The diagonal elements in covariance matrix for measurement noise R are 0.01 times variance of synthetic state data x. The diagonal elements of initial error covariance matrix P 0 are 25, 25, 25 and 1×10 −2 , respectively. The process noise covariance matrix was set to a small diagonal matrix, 5×10 −6. The UKF is also initialized to start from the prior state vector s =<ref type="bibr">[0,0,0,0.01]</ref>, the last element being the initial guess of the unknown. The diagonal elements in covariance matrix for measurement noise R are 0.25 times variance of synthetic state date x. The first three diagonal elements (means the error covariance for states) of initial error covariance matrix P 0 are the same, leaving as 0.25 times variance of synthetic state data x. The last diagonal element in P 0 is 0.35, meaning this is for the parameter estimate. For the PF, the initial particles for states and parameter are generated from s 0 ∼ N (0,1). The diagonal elements in covariance matrix for measurement noise R were set as 0.001 times the variance of the synthesized time series. With additive Gaussian noise, the importance weight are updated as˜was˜ as˜w</p><formula>i t = p(y t |˜s|˜s i t ) ∝ N (y t −Hs t , σ 2 I)</formula><p>where, for example, H, the observation matrix, whose diagonal elements will take the form<ref type="bibr">[1 0 1]</ref>, if the state S t is unobserved. The discount factor<ref type="bibr">[Equation (6)]</ref>was set to δ = 0.98 and we ran PFs with 50 and 1000 samples. Further, we also investigated a range of operating regimes with data lengths of 80s to 180s in steps of 20s, sampling intervals of 0.1s, 0.25s, 0.5s and 1s, and noise variance multipliers of 0.0001, 0.001, 0.01, 0.05, 0.1 and 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>We carried out a thorough exploration of the capabilities of the three estimation methods on the heat shock system, at various levels of problem complexity, i.e. the numbers of parameters and states assumed unknown. Typical results obtained are described in the following sections, and results of all the combinations we tested are given as Supplementary Material accompanying this article.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>shows convergence of the three models on estimating a single parameter (K s ) from two noisy state observations. In these, we have included a simulation of PF with only 50 samples failing to correctly estimate the parameter. With 1000 samples, PF achieves convergence to the correct estimate. The EKF and UKF also converge to the correct underlying value, as seen in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure  1</ref>, but note that the starting points of these are set to be very close to the true value. When the initial conditions are set to be far away from the true value, however, the EKF and UKF fail to converge whereas the PF is able to find the correct solution. This is shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>where the initial conditions of the EKF and UKF are set to be the closest to the truth among all the particles used as initial samples of the PF. Hence even in the case of a comparison highly favourable to the EKF and UKF, they fail to recover the correct value of the unknown. We have observed similar behaviour for each of the unknown parameters of the heat shock model. Depending on the form of the interactions, some parameters are easier to identify than the others. Should the conditional posterior probabilities over them be unimodal, and close to Gaussian, parametric models (Kalman filters) have a good chance of finding the correct solutions. When the terms appear in complex non-linear settings, posterior probabilities are often multi-modal and nonparametric PFs are necessary. In Supplementary Table S2, we show in which of the cases of estimating a single unknown parameter from one and two noisy observations the PF clearly outperforms the other two. We explore all the possible combinations and find in 20 of the 42 cases, PF has an advantage over EKF and UKF, whereas in the remaining 22 it performs no worse than them. The difficulty of parameter estimation depends on the complexity of the formulation for the hidden state assumed to be unobserved. We also consider the case in which all the parameters are known, and a single state was to be inferred from the other two. Results of this are shown in Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S1</ref>, and show broadly similar results in the rates of convergence. Other variations of estimating one of the six parameters from one and two observed states are shown in Supplementary Figures S3–S8, and the summary in Supplementary Table S2 is obtained by studying these graphs. In all these simulations, similar to the results in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>, we set the initial guess of the unknown parameter at a value not too close to the true value, and gave the Kalman algorithms an unfair advantageby initializing all particles of the PF further away from the initial values to which EKF and UKF were set.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Estimating a single unknown</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Estimating multiple parameters</head><p>We next examined the performances in multiple unknown parameter spaces, progressively making the problem harder. Results of convergence in estimating two parameters simultaneously, with all possible combinations of which parameters were left unknown, are shown in Supplementary Figures S9–S17. We note the general trend of PF outperforming the other two. Naturally, for the initial conditions chosen, there are cases when all three methods fail to estimate the parameters correctly. This is to be expected because the problem has now been made significantly harder than the case of estimating a single parameter. In exploring different operating regimes, we found the influence due to data lengths to be negligible (Supplementary Figs S19–S21). For the EKF and PF, faster sampling was found to be sometimes advantageous (Supplementary Figs S22–S24).<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3C</ref>–E shows the space of initial conditions from which convergence to the true solution of the three algorithms were compared. We find that the PF is more resilient than either EKF or UKF in converging to the true solution. Also see Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure S28</ref>, which shows the convergence regimes for two other sampling intervals. For completeness, we also considered the extreme case of all parameters being unknown. Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S18</ref>shows convergence of the three filters in the case of estimating all six parameters from two noisy observations (D t and U f ). Here, we find that the EKF correctly estimates the parameter α 0 and UKF is able to successfully converge to α 0 and K s , whereas the PF is able to correctly estimate five of the six unknowns. The PF fails only in the case of the parameter K d , which is probably because K d highly influences the temporal evolution of the system via the state S t , which was assumed unknown in this particular simulation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">The sequential approach</head><p>The Kalman and PF algorithms considered in this work are sequential algorithms. Their use should be considered in the context of Bayesian inference methods that operate on batch data [e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Vyshemirsky and Girolami (2008)</ref>;<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Wilkinson, 2009]</ref>, as in an example like the heat shock model, all the data are available. In such cases, sequential models, being one-pass algorithms offer a computational advantage. This is illustrated in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3A</ref>, where we compare a Metropolis–Hastings sampler with PF. At similar levels of performance, we observed clear computational advantages with the sequential approach. The error bars in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3A</ref>are obtained over 20 different runs of the algorithms. An alternate way of parameter estimation of such models, also considered by El<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Samad et al. (2006)</ref>, is via an optimization approach. We compared such an approach with the Bayesian sequential approach, implementing the optimization via MATLAB's fminsearch program. This can be viewed as a maximum likelihood estimation, under assumptions of Gaussian noise. We found that with Gaussian noise, the optimization approach often outperformed the sequential Bayesian methods. However, with nonGaussian noise, the PF gave substantial advantage. We illustrate this in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3B</ref>, where in a two parameter estimation task, theoptimization approach repeatedly failed to find the correct solution, whereas the PF was successful in over half of the trials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>X.Liu and M.Niranjan</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">CONCLUSION</head><p>This work demonstrates the effectiveness of the method of particle filtering in state and parameter estimation of deterministic systems biological models from noisy observations. We have shown this via a comparative study between extended Kalman, unscented Kalman and particle filtering applied to the heat shock response system using single and multiple parameter estimations. While previous authors have argued that the Kalman filter itself is capable of such estimations, our critical appraisal shows that this is only possible when the initial guess of the state and/or state parameters are very close to the true values. Convergence is not achieved when the initial conditions differ significantly from the corresponding true values. The PF, on the other hand, is able to converge to true values even when all the particles are initially set to values far away from the underlying true values, providing a powerful, yet simple to implement, way of tackling difficult inference problems in systems biology. We further showed in this work that when the complexity of the problem is gradually increased (i.e. the number unknown parameters/states to be inferred), the Kalman filter algorithms failed well before the PF did. Even in the extreme case of all parameters being unknown, the PF manages to find correct estimates of five of the six. This suggests that the non-parametric approach of the PF, by virtue of being able to systematically propagate uncertainties while exploring the space over a wide range, is a powerful methodology to tackle such difficult problems. Our current work concentrates on stretching such analyses to more difficult higher dimensional problems such as cell-cycle regulation, circadian rhythm and sino-atrial pace making in heart tissues.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict</head><p>of Interest: none declared.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Calculate the Kalman gain L t according to Eqn. 13 4.Update the state posterior s + t by Eqn. 14 5.Update the covariance posterior P + t according to Eqn. 15 endfor</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Estimations of single unknown parameter (K s ) of the heat shock model using three different recursive filters. Top row: EKF and UKF; Bottom row: PFs with 50 and 1000 samples, respectively. For the EKF and UKF confidence levels from posterior variances are also shown.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Estimations of a single parameter K s from two observed states with different initializations. The boxes show the distribution of samples of the PF at initial, two hundredth and final points in time.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Computation and performance of sequential models: (A) comparison of computational costs between a batch method and PFs in estimating single unknown parameters; (B) performance of a deterministic optimization approach. From various initial conditions, when simultaneously estimating two unknown parameters with mixture Gaussian observation noise, the optimization method fails to converge (true values denoted by '*') whereas the PF was able to find the correct solution in the posterior mean in about half of these (trajectories not shown); and (C–E) a comparison of initial conditions from which convergence is reached for the three different sequential filters.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>, D t represents the number of molecules of chaperones, S t , the number of molecules of σ 32 and U f describes the total number of unfolded proteins. P t and K fold are the total number of proteins in the cell and a coefficient for the folding process, respectively. K(t) and η(t)</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from X.Liu and M.Niranjan</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from Parameter estimation in computational biology</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A tutorial on particle filters for online nonlinear/nonGaussian Bayesian tracking</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Arulampalam</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parameter estimation and determinability analysis applied to Drosophila gap gene circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Ashyraliyev</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">83</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ranked prediction of p53 targets using hidden variable dynamic modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Barenco</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Estimation, Tracking and Navigation: Theory, Algorithms and Software</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Bar-Shalom</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetic analysis of a molecular model of the budding yeast cell cycle</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Chen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="391" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Lorenz Equations: Bifurcations, Chaos and Strange Attractors</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Colin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parameter estimation and inference for stochastic reactiondiffusion systems: application to morphogenesis in D. melanogaster</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Dewar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequential Monte Carlo methods to train neural network models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F G</forename>
				<surname>De Freitas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neural Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="955" to="993" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sequential Monte Carlo Methods in Practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Doucet</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advanced methods and algorithms for biological networks analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>El-Samad</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<meeting>. IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="832" to="853" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Parameter estimation in computational biology</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian inference for stochastic kinetic models using a diffusion approximation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Golightly</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Wilkinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="781" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Theory of Evolution and Dynamical Systems: Mathematical Aspects of Selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Hofbauer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Sigmund</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian inference of the sites of perturbations in metabolic pathways via Markov chain Monte Carlo</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Jayawardhana</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1191" to="1197" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new approach for filtering nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Julier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Am. Contr. Conf., D</title>
		<meeting>. Am. Contr. Conf., D</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1628" to="1632" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new method for nonlinear transformation of means and covariances in filters and estimators</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Julier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="477" to="482" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A function estimation approach to sequential learning with neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Kadirkamanathan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Niranjan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neural Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="954" to="975" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new approach to linear filtering and prediction problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Kalman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans. ASME, J. Basic Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="1960" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A self-organizing state-space model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Kitagawa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1203" to="1215" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meaningful relationships: the regulation of the Ras/Raf/MEK/ERK pathway by protein interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Kolch</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">351</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="305" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modelling transcriptional regulation using Gaussian processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Lawrence</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 19</title>
		<editor>Schölkopf,B. et al.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Vancouver</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>MIT press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page">785</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parameter estimation and model selection in computational biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Lillacci</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Khammash</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="696" to="713" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Combined parameter and state estimation in simulation-based filtering Sequential Monte Carlo Methods in Practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>West</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Doucet,A. et al.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="217" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new regulatory interactions suggested by simulations for circadian genetic control mechanism in mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Matsuno</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bioinform. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="153" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-linear optimization of biochemical pathways: applications to metabolic engineering and parameter estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Mendes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Kell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="869" to="883" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parameter estimation of in silico biological pathways with particle filtering towards a petascale computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Nakamura</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pac. Symp. Biocomput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequential tracking in pricing financial options using model based and neural network approaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Niranjan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems</title>
		<editor>Mozer,M. et al.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="960" to="966" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating parameters and hidden variables in non-linear statespace models based on ODEs for biological networks inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Quach</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3209" to="3216" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Optimal State Estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Simon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of parameters and unobserved components for nonlinear systems from noisy time series</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Sitz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">66</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extended Kalman filter for estimation of parameters in nonlinear state-space models of biochemical networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Sun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3758</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling the nonlinear dynamics of cellular signal transduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Timmer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Bifurcat. Chaos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2069" to="2079" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioBayes: a software package for Bayesian inference in systems biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Vyshemirsky</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Girolami</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1933" to="1934" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stochastic modelling for quantitative description of heterogeneous biological systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Wilkinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vivo intracellular metabolite dynamics estimation by sequential Monte Carlo filter</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Yang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Symposium on Computational Intelligence</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hawaii, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="387" to="394" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parameter estimation in systems biology models using spline approximation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Zhan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Yeung</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>