
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:36+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining SurpriseMe: an integrated tool for network community structure characterization using Surprise maximization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">7 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rodrigo</forename>
								<surname>Aldecoa</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Instituto de Biomedicina de Valencia</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas (IBV-CSIC)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>46010</postCode>
									<region>Valencia</region>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ignacio</forename>
								<surname>Marín</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Instituto de Biomedicina de Valencia</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas (IBV-CSIC)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>46010</postCode>
									<region>Valencia</region>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining SurpriseMe: an integrated tool for network community structure characterization using Surprise maximization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1041" to="1042"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">7 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt741</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 11, 2013; revised on December 11, 2013; accepted on December 16, 2013</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Detecting communities and densely connected groups may contribute to unravel the underlying relationships among the units present in diverse biological networks (e.g. interactomes, coexpression networks, ecological networks). We recently showed that communities can be precisely characterized by maximizing Surprise, a global network parameter. Here, we present SurpriseMe, a tool that integrates the outputs of seven of the best algorithms available to estimate the maximum Surprise value. SurpriseMe also generates distance matrices that allow visualizing the relationships among the solutions generated by the algorithms. We show that the communities present in small-and medium-sized networks, with up to 10 000 nodes, can be easily characterized: on standard PC computers, these analyses take less than an hour. Also, four of the algorithms may rapidly analyze networks with up to 100 000 nodes, given enough memory resources. Because of its performance and simplicity, SurpriseMe is a reference tool for community structure characterization. Availability and implementation: SurpriseMe is implemented in Perl and C/Cþþ. It compiles and runs on any UNIX-based operating system, including Linux and Mac OS/X, using standard libraries. The source code is freely and publicly available under the GPL 3.0 license at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Complex networks are extensively used for representing interactions among elements of a system. This approach is particularly useful in biology; analyzing networks provides relevant information in fields such as genetics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Costanzo et al., 2010</ref>), ecology (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bascompte et al., 2006</ref>), neuroscience (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bullmore and Sporns, 2009</ref>), systems biology (Baraba´si<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Baraba´si and Oltvai, 2004</ref>) or proteomics (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Schwikowski et al., 2000</ref>), among others. An interesting property of these networks is the fact that related units of the network tend to create tightly knit groups, usually known as communities. By unraveling the close relationships among certain units, community structure characterization improves our understanding of the system as a whole. Recently, many strategies have been devised to detect the optimal division of a network into communities. However, none of them alone is able to achieve high-quality solutions in all kinds of networks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Schaub et al., 2012</ref>; Aldecoa and Marı´nMarı´n, 2013a, b). In recent works, we demonstrated that Surprise (S) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Arnau et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Marı´nMarı´n, 2010, 2011</ref>) is an effective measure to evaluate the quality of a partition of a network into communities (Aldecoa and Marı´nMarı´n, 2011, 2013a, b). Given such a partition, S calculates the unlikeliness of finding the observed number of intra-community links in a totally random network, according to a cumulative hypergeometric distribution:</p><formula>S ¼ Àlog X minðM, nÞ j¼p M j F À M n À j F n</formula><p>Here, F is the maximum possible number of links of the network, n is the actual number of links, M is the maximum possible number of intra-community links and p is the actual number of links within communities. In several complex benchmarks, composed of networks with very different structures, it was shown that the partition of maximum S corresponds to the real community structure, with a minimal/null degree of error (<ref type="bibr">Marı´nMarı´n, 2011, 2013a</ref>, b). We also showed that S outperforms modularity (Q;<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Newman and Girvan, 2004</ref>), the most commonly used criterion to define communities, in all benchmarks (<ref type="bibr">Marı´nMarı´n, 2011, 2013a</ref>). Although a simple algorithm to maximize S has not yet been devised, we found that choosing among the output of seven high-quality algorithms, the one that provided the maximum S value solved the structure of all networks tested. These algorithms are called CPM (<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Traag et al., 2011</ref>), Infomap (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Rosvall and Bergstrom, 2008</ref>), RB (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Reichardt and Bornholdt, 2006</ref>), RN (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Ronhovde and Nussinov, 2010</ref>), RNSC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">King et al., 2004</ref>), SCluster (Aldecoa and Marı´nMarı´n, 2010) and UVCluster (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Aldecoa and Marı´nMarı´n, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Arnau et al., 2005</ref>). The particular performances of each algorithm are detailed in Aldecoa and Marı´nMarı´n (2013a, b). Here, we present SurpriseMe, a tool integrating those seven algorithms. SurpriseMe accelerates the research process by simply accepting a network as input, internally running all the algorithms and outputting their solutions and their Surprise values. SurpriseMe also calculates distances among the solutions provided by the algorithms, allowing understanding of how congruent they are (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Aldecoa and Marı´nMarı´n, 2013b</ref>).names of two connected nodes, separated by a tab or space character. From this text file, the software automatically generates the required input formats and runs the algorithms (either all or a subset chosen by the user). Finally, the algorithm that generates the maximum S value is established. For Infomap, RN and RNSC, the unique partitions generated are evaluated, while for RB, CPM, UVCluster and SCluster, which provide several alternative partitions, the ones with the highest S value are considered. SurpriseMe also compares the solutions of each algorithm, using either the Variation of Information (VI) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Meila˘ , 2007</ref>) or the [1 À NMI] value, where NMI stands for Normalized Mutual Information (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Danon et al., 2005</ref>). In both cases, the greater the value, the more two partitions are different (see Aldecoa and Marı´nMarı´n, 2012, 2013a, b). The program also estimates the distances to two additional solutions called One (all units of the network are in one community) and Singles (each node belongs to a different community). The distances to these two solutions provide further clues of the behavior of the algorithms (Aldecoa and Marı´nMarı´n, 2013b). All distances are saved into two distance matrix files (for VI and for 1 À NMI) that can be directly imported into MEGA5 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Tamura et al., 2011</ref>), a popular free software that allows easily visualizing the hierarchical relationships among the different solutions (see Aldecoa and Marı´nMarı´n, 2013b).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">SurpriseMe features</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Performance</head><p>The algorithms involved are substantially complex. With n being the number of nodes and m the number of links, here we provide their computational complexities (time/space): for CPM and RB, O(n log n)/ O(n þ m); for Infomap, O(m)/O(n þ m); for RN, O(m^1.3)/O(n^2); for RNSC, O(n^2)/O(n þ m); for UVCLUSTER, O(n^2 log n)/O(n^2); and for SCLUSTER, O(n log n)/O(n^2). Therefore, the current version of SurpriseMe is most useful for networks of small to medium size, typically up to 10 000 nodes. We found that very small networks [e.g., those in a typical Girvan and Newman's benchmark (2002), with 128 nodes] are analyzed almost instantaneously. We also tested the software in two more complex standard benchmarks. The first had networks with a Relaxed Caveman (RC) configuration (<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Watts, 1999</ref>) with 10% rewiring, meaning that well-defined communities are present (see Aldecoa and Marı´nMarı´n, 2013a). The second was a set of Erdo¨sErdo¨s-Re´nyiRe´nyi (ER) random graphs (Erdo 00 s and Re´nyi<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Re´nyi, 1959</ref>), essentially without community structure. This last benchmark provides an estimate of the maximum time and resources required. In both cases, we found that networks with up to 10 000 nodes are analyzed by the seven algorithms in less than an hour using a conventional desktop PC, consuming less than 1 GB of memory. However, larger networks require more powerful hardware. With all the programs, a RC network of 50 000 nodes requires about 140 h of analysis and 60 GB of memory. In those cases, it may be advisable to switch off the most time-and resource-consuming programs (RN, SCluster and UVCluster), given that the four remnant programs generally provide very good solutions and are complementary (i.e., they work optimally in different network structures; Aldecoa and Marı´nMarı´n 2013a, b). Thus, their combination will still generate either very high or maximum S values. The resources required for a network of 50 000 nodes are then reduced to 40 min and 14 GB of memory (RC structure) or 8 h and 39 GB of memory (ER configuration). For a RC network of 100 000 nodes, we have determined that the four fastest algorithms take 3 h and 30 GB of memory in RC networks and 21 h and 66 GB of memory in ER networks.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>SurpriseMe analyses require as an input a text file indicating the list of links that characterize the network. Each line of the file must contain the *To whom correspondence should be addressed. y Present address: Cooperative Association for Internet Data Analysis, University of California San Diego (CAIDA/UCSD). San Diego, CA. USA.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> SUMMARY Only few researchers have the time and skills to select, download, compile and run multiple community detection algorithms. SurpriseMe allows very simply running a set of state-of-the-art algorithms and determining the one that generates the best Surprise value, i.e. the best partition of the network. It also provides the user with distance matrices (with VI, 1 À NMI values) that help to compare the solutions of the algorithms. Simple to use, it only needs as input a file containing the network to analyze. The well-established power of this type of analysis, together with the simplicity of its use, makes SurpriseMe an excellent tool for characterizing the community structure of complex networks. Funding: Study supported by grant BFU2011-30063 (Spanish government). Conflict of Interest: none declared.</note>

			<note place="foot">R.Aldecoa and I.Marín at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Jerarca: Efficient analysis of complex networks using hierarchical clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Aldecoa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Marı´nmarı´n</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11585</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deciphering network community structure by surprise</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Aldecoa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Marı´nmarı´n</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24195</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Closed benchmarks for network community structure characterization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Aldecoa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Marı´nmarı´n</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E Stat. Nonlin. Soft Matter Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2 2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">26109</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surprise maximization reveals the community structure of complex networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Aldecoa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Marı´nmarı´n</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1060</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the limits of community detection strategies in complex networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Aldecoa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Marı´nmarı´n</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2216</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Iterative cluster analysis of protein interaction data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Arnau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="378" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network biology: understanding the cell&apos;s functional organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Baraba´sibaraba´si</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<forename type="middle">N</forename>
				<surname>Oltvai</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymmetric coevolutionary networks facilitate biodiversity maintenance</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Bascompte</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">312</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="433" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Complex brain networks: graph theoretical analysis of structural and functional systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Bullmore</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Sporns</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genetic landscape of a cell</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Costanzo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">327</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparing community structure identification On random graphs I</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Danon</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stat. Mech. Publ. Math. Debrecen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="297" />
			<date type="published" when="1959" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>P09008. . Erdo 00 s</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Community structure in social and biological networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Girvan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E J</forename>
				<surname>Newman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7821" to="7826" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein complex prediction via cost-based clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>King</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3013" to="3020" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparing clusterings-an information based distance</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Meila˘</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Multivariate Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="873" to="895" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding and evaluating community structure in networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E J</forename>
				<surname>Newman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Girvan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="026113" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical mechanics of community detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Reichardt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Bornholdt</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E Stat. Nonlin. Soft Matter Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Local resolution-limit-free Potts model for community detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Ronhovde</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Z</forename>
				<surname>Nussinov</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E. Stat. Nonlin. Soft Matter Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">46114</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maps of random walks on complex networks reveal community structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Rosvall</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">T</forename>
				<surname>Bergstrom</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<meeting>. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1118" to="1123" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Markov dynamics as a zooming lens for multiscale community detection: non clique-like communities and the field-of-view limit</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Schaub</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A network of protein-protein interactions in yeast</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Schwikowski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1257" to="1261" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Tamura</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2731" to="2739" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Narrow scope for resolution-limit-free community detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Traag</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E. Stat. Nonlin. Soft Matter Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">16114</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Small Worlds: The Dynamics Of Networks Between Order And Randomness</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Watts</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>