
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:44+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology SurreyFBA: a command line tool and graphics user interface for constraint-based modeling of genome-scale metabolic reaction networks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Albert</forename>
								<surname>Gevorgyan</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Health and Medical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Surrey</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>GU2 7XH</postCode>
									<settlement>Guildford</settlement>
									<region>Surrey</region>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">E</forename>
								<surname>Bushell</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Health and Medical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Surrey</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>GU2 7XH</postCode>
									<settlement>Guildford</settlement>
									<region>Surrey</region>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Claudio</forename>
								<surname>Avignone-Rossa</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Health and Medical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Surrey</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>GU2 7XH</postCode>
									<settlement>Guildford</settlement>
									<region>Surrey</region>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andrzej</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Kierzek</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Health and Medical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Surrey</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>GU2 7XH</postCode>
									<settlement>Guildford</settlement>
									<region>Surrey</region>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Olga</forename>
								<surname>Troyanskaya</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Health and Medical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Surrey</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>GU2 7XH</postCode>
									<settlement>Guildford</settlement>
									<region>Surrey</region>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology SurreyFBA: a command line tool and graphics user interface for constraint-based modeling of genome-scale metabolic reaction networks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="434"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq679</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on August 3, 2010; revised on December 2, 2010; accepted on December 3, 2010</note>
					<note>[13:41 5/1/2011 Bioinformatics-btq679.tex] Page: 433 433–434 Associate Editor: Availability: SurreyFBA is distributed under GNU GPL license and available from http://sysbio3.fhms.surrey.ac.uk/SurreyFBA.zip. Contact: a.kierzek@surrey.ac.uk</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Constraint-based modeling of genome-scale metabolic networks has been successfully used in numerous applications such as prediction of gene essentiality and metabolic engineering. We present SurreyFBA, which provides constraint-based simulations and network map visualization in a free, stand-alone software. In addition to basic simulation protocols, the tool also implements the analysis of minimal substrate and product sets, which is useful for metabolic engineering and prediction of nutritional requirements in complex in vivo environments, but not available in other commonly used programs. The SurreyFBA is based on a command line interface to the GLPK solver distributed as binary and source code for the three major operating systems. The command line tool, implemented in C++, is easily executed within scripting languages used in the bioinformatics community and provides efficient implementation of tasks requiring iterative calls to the linear programming solver. SurreyFBA includes JyMet, a graphics user interface allowing spreadsheet-based model presentation, visualization of numerical results on metabolic networks represented in the Petri net convention, as well as in charts and plots.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>An understanding of how cellular phenotypes emerge from interactions between molecular parts, encoded in the genome, requires computer simulation of genome-scale molecular interaction networks. Due to the scarcity of quantitative information, these simulations have been limited to the special case of metabolic networks operating under quasi-steady state, which is modeled by a set of linear relationships between reaction fluxes. The model is explored by employing Linear Programming optimization, where the optimal flux toward any reaction or substance in the model can be determined. This approach is referred to as constraint based (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Price et al., 2004</ref>), because it evaluates metabolic capabilities under the set of constraints representing stoichiometry, maximal capacity and reversibility of the reactions. This information can be obtained for a particular repertoire of enzymatic activities, predicted from * To whom correspondence should be addressed. the genome, which has permitted reconstruction of genome-scale metabolic reaction networks (GSMNs) for major model organisms, pathogens, industrial microorganisms and humans. The review of the numerous applications of GSMNs is beyond the scope of this article. The software presented here stemmed from our work on metabolic engineering (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Khannapho et al., 2008</ref>) and prediction of gene essentiality in pathogens (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Beste et al., 2007</ref>). Constraint-based simulations are implemented in the COBRA toolbox (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alexandrescu et al., 2007</ref>) running under the Matlab environment. The SimPheny software (www.genomatica.com) is a commercial solution with a database backend providing visualization of numerical results on pathway maps. Visualization is also available in the FBA-SimViz (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Grafahrend-Belau et al., 2009</ref>) and MetaFluxNet (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Lee et al., 2003</ref>) programs, although none of them implements iterative simulations such as flux variability analysis (FVA) or reaction essentiality scans. Here we present SurreyFBA, a GNU GPL software for constraintbased simulations of metabolic reaction networks. In addition to the standard methods, available in existing tools, it implements analysis of minimal substrate and product sets. The command line tool is available as a binary and source code for Linux, Windows and MacOS systems and can be used without dependencies on mathematical modeling environments. It can be easily run using common scripting languages, which makes it particularly suitable for the integration with bioinformatics analysis pipelines. We have already implemented JyMet, a Jython graphics user interface, which provides visualization of networks and numerical results, integrated into network diagrams.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">SOFTWARE</head><p>The SurreyFBA is a metabolic modeling interface to the Gnu Linear Programming Kit (www.gnu.org/software/glpk/glpk.html), distributed within the software. The calculations involving linear programming (LP) are implemented in C++ as an object-oriented LP kernel, which is initialized once and used repeatedly in iterative algorithms, while the objective function and the linear constraints are modified. This increases performance in applications such as FVA and essentiality scans involving thousands of LP solutions. An additional gain in performance can be achieved by applying the optional matrix reduction algorithm (M.G. Poolman, unpublished). For example, SurreyFBA is 41% faster than COBRA toolbox on FVA of Saccharomyces cerevisiae iND750 model. In the current distribution, we also provide JyMet—a desktop graphics user interface written in Jython. JyMet presents model structure in aPage: 434 433–434user friendly spreadsheet and provides a menu-based interface to simulation methods (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). A model can be provided either in a tab-delimited format defining reactions only or in a more extended four-level format describing also genes, enzymes and metabolites. JyMet can also import SBML files that conform to the conventions accepted by the COBRA Toolbox. A separate text file may be provided with one or more problem definitions in a simple scripting format, including objective functions, redefined flux bounds, method-specific arguments and additional linear constraints. The results are written in a tabular format. SurreyFBA implements established metabolic modeling methods, such as flux balance analysis, flux variability analysis, robustness analysis, phenotypical phase planes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Price et al., 2004</ref>), elementary mode analysis (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Heinrich and Schuster, 1996</ref>), essentiality scans and prediction of reaction and gene/enzyme knockout results (involving the evaluation of logical rules relating reactions to genes or enzymes). It also provides some structural methods for model validation, such as detection of live reactions, orphan metabolites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Poolman et al., 2006</ref>), unconserved metabolites (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Gevorgyan et al., 2008</ref>) and connected components. Original methods are provided for the calculation of minimal substrate and product sets (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Gevorgyan, 2009</ref>), enabling quick and concise characterization of nutritional requirements and metabolic capabilities of the organisms investigated. A model or results can be visualized in JyMet on network maps using Petri net convention, with automatically generated and manually editable layouts. Dedicated functions are also provided for showing simulation results in charts and plots.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.Gevorgyan et al.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>The free SurreyFBA software provides a command line tool efficiently implementing a large number of constraint-based modeling approaches, including methods that are not available in other tools. It is an ideal choice for users integrating constraintbased simulations with bioinformatics pipelines, and also provides a user-friendly graphical interface independent on commercial mathematical modeling environments.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>[13:41 5/1/2011 Bioinformatics-btq679.tex]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Usage of SurreyFBA illustrated by screenshots of the command line tool and JyMet GUI. The S.cerevisiae iND750 model available in sample directory is used as an example. The model in spreadsheet interface, visualization of the results on pathway map and the plot of FVA results are shown. The bottom panel shows example command line evaluating biomass objective function.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative prediction of cellular metabolism with constraint-based models: the COBRA Toolbox</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Alexandrescu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="727" to="738" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GSMN-TB: a web-based genome scale network model of Mycobacterium tuberculosis metabolism</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J V</forename>
				<surname>Beste</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">89</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Theoretical and computational methods for studying genomescale metabolic networks applied to Streptococcus agalactiae</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Gevorgyan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<publisher>Oxford Brookes University</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of stoichiometric inconsistencies in biomolecular models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Gevorgyan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2245" to="2251" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FBA-SimVis: interactive visualization of constraintbased metabolic models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Grafahrend-Belau</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2755" to="2757" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The regulation of cellular systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Heinrich</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Schuster</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<publisher>Chapman &amp; Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selection of objective function in genome scale flux balance analysis for process feed development in antibiotic production</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Khannapho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metab. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MetaFluxNet: the management of metabolic reaction information and quantitative metabolic flux analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">Y</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2144" to="2146" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-scale models of microbial cells: evaluating the consequences of constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Price</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="886" to="897" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Challenges to be faced in the reconstruction of metabolic networks from public databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Poolman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEE Proc. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="384" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>