
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:39+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression survcomp: an R/Bioconductor package for performance assessment and comparison of survival models</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Markus</forename>
								<forename type="middle">S</forename>
								<surname>Schröder</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biostatistics and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02215</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Aedín</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Culhane</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biostatistics and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02215</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">John</forename>
								<surname>Quackenbush</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biostatistics and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02215</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Benjamin</forename>
								<surname>Haibe-Kains</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biostatistics and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02215</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression survcomp: an R/Bioconductor package for performance assessment and comparison of survival models</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="3206" to="3208"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr511</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on May 20, 2011; revised on August 26, 2011; accepted on September 3, 2011</note>
					<note>[14:49 19/10/2011 Bioinformatics-btr511.tex] Page: 3206 3206–3208 Associate Editor: Janet kelso Supplementary Information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The survcomp package provides functions to assess and statistically compare the performance of survival/risk prediction models. It implements state-of-the-art statistics to (i) measure the performance of risk prediction models; (ii) combine these statistical estimates from multiple datasets using a meta-analytical framework; and (iii) statistically compare the performance of competitive models. Availability: The R/Bioconductor package survcomp is provided open source under the Artistic-2.0 License with a user manual containing installation, operating instructions and use case scenarios on real datasets. survcomp requires R version 2.13.0 or higher.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Building risk prediction or survival models is an important area of research, especially in cancer where gene expression signatures are used to predict risk of metastasis, response to therapy and overall survival. However, assessing the relative performance of such models is complex due to the lack of standards regarding the best criterion to use in survival analysis (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>;<ref type="bibr">HaibeKains et al., 2008</ref>). Although a number of model performance estimators have been described (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cox, 1972;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Graf et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Harrel et al., 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Heagerty et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Royston and Sauerbrei, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Verweij and Houwelingen, 1993</ref>), they are not widely used. This is partly because these are implemented in many different R packages that use heterogeneous interfaces, which makes it difficult for the non-specialist to easily use or compare the performance of these models. Another challenge in assessing performance of expression-based prediction models is a lack of power due to small sample size. Meta-analytical methods could leverage power from the numerous microarray datasets that are now publicly available by summarizing model performance estimated in multiple-independent studies. Moreover, because they enable efficient joint analysis of multiple datasets, such an analytical framework reduces the risk of artifactual discoveries that are due to bias or confounding factors that may be present in one dataset. This is particularly important when comparing competitive risk prediction models; often authors * To whom correspondence should be addressed.claim better performance of a new model without properly assessing whether a model significantly outperforms its competitors. To the best of our knowledge, there is no commercial or open-source tool to enable statistical comparison of risk prediction models in a meta-analytical framework. To address these issues, we developed a new Bioconductor package, survcomp, which implements several performance criteria for risk prediction models (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>), together with metaanalytical methods that enable combination of performance estimations from multiple-independent datasets [fixed-and random-effects models (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cochrane, 1954</ref>); ?combine.est], and statistical comparison of predictions between competitive models (?cindex.comp for the concordance index). The concordance index as described by<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Harrel et al. (1996)</ref>and implemented in survcomp may be sensitive to the study-specific censoring distribution, therefore we are working to implement a modified concordance index by<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Uno et al. (2011)</ref>that avoids this problem and which should be available in the next release of survcomp. Although the performance criteria that are implemented in survcomp are mostly available in other R packages (except the D index which, to the best of our knowledge, is only in survcomp), our package provides a common interface to facilitate easy use of all these estimators. Moreover, with the exception of ipdmeta by<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Broeze et al. (2009)</ref>and survJamda by<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Yasrebi (2011)</ref>, few R packages perform meta-analysis of survival data. survcomp provides a uniform interface to simplify the use of performance assessment and statistical comparison of risk prediction models, and provides new R functions to statistically compare these in. The blue square and horizontal line represent the concordance index and its 95% confidence interval which is clipped at 0.4 and 0.9 (represented by an arrow). The black rhombus is the overall meta-estimate from the combined five datasets. The greater the concordance index, the more prognostic the risk prediction model. The vertical red bar represents the concordance index of random risk predictions. a meta-analytical framework. It is worth noting that the aim of survcomp is to provide efficient computation of several performance estimates (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>) and not to implement a full validation framework. Proper validation using a fully independent test dataset is of utmost importance to avoid overoptimistic results (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Jelizarow et al., 2010</ref>) and frameworks for cross-validation, multiple random splits or a single split into training/validation datasets are implemented in several existing R packages including peperr (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Porzelius et al., 2009</ref>). We illustrate the functionality of survcomp in a case study that investigates prognosis in breast cancer. In most studies, this is a difficult task due to the (generally) small sample size. Yet despite a large number of published studies, data heterogeneity, both in terms of data sources and microarray technologies, have limited the effectiveness of their joint analysis. Here we apply survcomp functions to statistically compare the prognostic value of a widely used clinical model, a single proliferation gene and two published gene signatures. The results suggest that the multi-gene signatures are not always superior to standard clinical models or to a simple single gene model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">CASE STUDY</head><p>The prognostic ability of gene expression of AURKA, a single proliferation-related gene, was compared with the Nottingham Prognostic Index (NPI,<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Galea et al., 1992</ref>) clinical model for prognosis, and to risk prediction scores from two published multigene prognostic signatures; GGI (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Sotiriou et al., 2006</ref>) and GENIUS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Haibe-Kains et al., 2010</ref>). The NPI, GGI and GENIUS risk scores were calculated using the Bioconductor package genefu. Each score was computed in five publicly available datasets described in the Supplementary Material. To compare the prognostic ability of these four different risk prediction models, we estimated the concordance index for each model in each dataset separately and used the function combine.est to compute the corresponding overall meta-estimate using the well-established random-effects model approach (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cochrane, 1954</ref>). As can be seen in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>, although the performance varies between datasets, all models yielded highly significant overall prognostic value (high-risk predictions represent patient with poor survival, concordance index &gt; 0.5, one-sided P &lt;0.001, see Supplementary Material for R code). AURKA, the single proliferation gene, was the worst predictor of survival (concordance index of 0.64), whereas GENIUS, the risk prediction model taking into account the breast cancer molecular subtypes, was the best (concordance index of 0.69). The continuous risk prediction of NPI, the traditional clinical model which combines nodal status, tumor size and histological grade, yielded a relatively high concordance index (concordance index of 0.66). To identify the best risk prediction model(s), we statistically compared their concordance indices using the function cindex.comp.meta (<ref type="figure">Table 2</ref>). Concurring with Haibe<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Kains et al. (2010)</ref>we observed that GENIUS outperforms AURKA, GGI and NPI (uncorrected P &lt; 0.10;<ref type="figure">Table 2</ref>). However, when P-values are corrected for multiple testing (Holm's method), no P-value remains significant suggesting that a larger meta-analysis is required to definitively claim the superiority of one classifier over another. This also suggests that prognostic clinical models such as NPI are still extremely competitive compared with more complex gene signatures. Repeating this analysis using performance criteria in survcomp other than the concordance index, including the D index or hazard ratio (<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>), leads to similar conclusions (examples are provided in the package user manual and documentation).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSION</head><p>The R/Bioconductor package survcomp provides a uniform interface to an extensive set of performance assessment and statistical comparison methods for survival/risk prediction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>It allows scientists</head><p>Page: 3208 3206–3208</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>M.S.Schröder et al.</head><p>to easily implement large comparative studies integrating multiple independent datasets while providing statistical tools to identify the best model(s) as supported by the data under study.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Forestplots representing the prognostic value of (a) NPI, (b) AURKA, (c) GGI and (d) GENIUS estimated by the concordance index in five independent breast cancer datasets [none of these datasets were used to train the classifiers (a)–(c), duplicated patients were removed what results in a combined dataset of 722 patients]. The blue square and horizontal line represent the concordance index and its 95% confidence interval which is clipped at 0.4 and 0.9 (represented by an arrow). The black rhombus is the overall meta-estimate from the combined five datasets. The greater the concordance index, the more prognostic the risk prediction model. The vertical red bar represents the concordance index of random risk predictions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: National Human Genome Research Institute (1P50 HG004233, to M.S.S.); Fulbright Commission for Educational Exchange to (B.H.-K.); US National Institutes of Health (R01 LM010129-01, to B.H.-K. and J.Q.); Claudia Adams Barr Program in Innovative Basic Cancer Research (A.C.C. and J.Q.); Career Development grant (to A.C.C.) from DFCI Breast Cancer SPORE: CA 08939. Conflict of Interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Functions in survcomp to measure the performance of risk prediction models Name Function in survcomp References</figDesc><table>Concordance index 
concordance.index Harrel et al. (1996) 
D index 
D.index 
Royston and 
Sauerbrei (2004) 
Hazard ratio 
hazard.ratio 
Cox (1972) 
Brier score 
sbrier.score2proba Graf et al. (1999) 
Cross-validated 
partial likelihood 

cvpl 
Verweij and 
Houwelingen (1993) 
Time-dependent ROC 
curve 

tdrocc 
Heagerty et al. (2000) 

Kaplan–Meier curve 
km.cox.plot 
Kaplan and Meier 
(1958) 
Forestplot 
forestplot.surv 
Lewis and Clarke 
(2001) 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 2. Statistical performance comparison for the risk prediction models used in our case study</figDesc><table>Models 
NPI 
AURKA 
GGI 
GENIUS 

NPI 
0.25 
0.37 
0.91 
AURKA 
0.75 
0.70 
0.98 
GGI 
0.63 
0.30 
0.97 
GENIUS 
0.09 
0.02 
0.033 

P-values are computed using a one-sided paired Student's t-test to test whether risk 
prediction models in rows are better than the ones in columns. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Individual patient data meta-analysis of diagnostic and prognostic studies in obstetrics, gynaecology and reproductive medicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Broeze</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Med. Res. Methodol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">22</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The combination of estimates from different experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Cochrane</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrixs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="1954" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regression models and life tables</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Cox</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R Stat. Soc. Ser. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="220" />
			<date type="published" when="1972" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Nottingham prognostic index in primary breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Galea</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Breast Cancer Res. Treat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessment and comparison of prognostic classification schemes for survival data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Graf</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2529" to="2545" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparative study of survival models for breast cancer prognostication based on microarray data: does a single gene beat them all?</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Haibe-Kains</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2200" to="2208" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fuzzy gene expression-based computational approach improves breast cancer prognostication</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Haibe-Kains</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tutorial in biostatistics: multivariable prognostic models: issues in developing models, evaluating assumptions and adequacy, and measuring and reducing error</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Harrel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Jr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="361" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time-dependent ROC curves for censored survival data and a diagnostic marker</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Heagerty</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="344" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Over-optimism in bioinformatics: an illustration</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Jelizarow</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonparametric estimation from incomplete observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Kaplan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Meier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Amer. Stat. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="481" />
			<date type="published" when="1958" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Forest plots: trying to see the wood and the trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Lewis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Clarke</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br. Med. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1479" to="1480" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parallelized prediction error estimation for evaluation of highdimensional models</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Porzelius</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="827" to="829" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new measure of prognostic separation in survival data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Royston</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Sauerbrei</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="723" to="748" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression profiling in breast cancer: understanding the molecular basis of histologic grade to improve prognosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Sotiriou</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Natl Cancer Inst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="272" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the C-statistics for evaluating overall adequacy of risk prediction procedures with censored survival data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Uno</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1105" to="1117" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross-validation in survival analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J M</forename>
				<surname>Verweij</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Van Houwelingen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2305" to="2314" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SurvJamda: an R package to predict patients&apos; survival and risk assessment using joint analysis of microarray gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Yasrebi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1168" to="1169" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>