
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:30+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">SYNCSA—R tool for analysis of metacommunities based on functional traits and phylogeny of the community components</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012">. 15 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Vanderlei</forename>
								<forename type="middle">J</forename>
								<surname>Debastiani</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>vanderleidebastiani@yahoo.com.br</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Programa de Pós-Graduação em Ecologia</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91501-970</postCode>
									<settlement>Porto Alegre</settlement>
									<region>RS</region>
									<country key="BR">Brazil</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Valério</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Pillar</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Programa de Pós-Graduação em Ecologia</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91501-970</postCode>
									<settlement>Porto Alegre</settlement>
									<region>RS</region>
									<country key="BR">Brazil</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">SYNCSA—R tool for analysis of metacommunities based on functional traits and phylogeny of the community components</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2067" to="2068"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012">. 15 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts325</idno>
					<note type="submission">Phylogenetics Advance Access publication June 4, 2012 Received on March 5, 2012; revised on May 29, 2012; accepted on May 30, 2012</note>
					<note>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [10:02 5/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts325.tex] Page: 2067 2067–2068 Associate Editor: David Posada Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>SYNCSA is an R package for the analysis of metacommunities based on functional traits and phylogeny of the community components. It offers tools to calculate several matrix correlations that express trait-convergence assembly patterns, trait-divergence assembly patterns and phylogenetic signal in functional traits at the species pool level and at the metacommunity level. Availability and implementation: SYNCSA is a package for the R environment, under a GPL-2 open-source license and freely available on CRAN official web server for R (http://cran.r-project.org).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Comprehending how biological communities are structured in both time and space is a major challenge for ecologists. It is well known that communities are not random samples from the species pool. Niche theory predicts that in order to persist in a local community, each species has to have a particular set of traits that allow it to overcome environmental filtering and to coexist with other species (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Keddy and Weiher, 1999</ref>). Nonetheless, considering species traits in community ecology studies may be complicated as traits are not independent among species (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Felsenstein, 1985</ref>). In the last decades, functional traits and phylogeny information have been incorporated in ecological models in order to determine the factors responsible for creating and maintaining community structure (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cavender-Bares et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Fine and Kembel, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kembel and Hubbell, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Webb et al., 2002</ref>). Currently, information about traits and phylogeny are available for several groups of organisms (see APG, 2009;<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bininda-Emonds et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Jones et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kattge et al., 2011</ref>). Furthermore, recent developments made possible novel perspectives in functional and phylogenetic analyses of ecological data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Pillar and Duarte, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Pillar et al., 2009</ref>). SYNCSA is an R package (R Development Core Team, http:// www.r-project.org/) released under open-source license, and freely available from CRAN (http://cran.r-project.org), that implements the methods described in Pillar and Duarte (2010) and<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Pillar et al. (2009)</ref>for the comparison of ecological communities based on functional traits and the phylogeny of the community * To whom correspondence should be addressed. components, the detection of phylogenetic signal at the species pool and metacommunity levels and the testing of phylogenetic niche conservatism. SYNCSA allows the identification of optimal trait subsets expressing trait-convergence assembly patterns or traitdivergence assembly patterns in metacommunities. The functions are based on the abovementioned methods and are complementary to other functions available in R for the analysis of communities, which take into account traits and phylogenetic information. SYNCSA for R implements the same methods available in recent versions of SYNCSA application written in C++ (http://ecoqua.ecologia.ufrgs. br/ecoqua/SYNCSA), which was developed by V. Pillar and evolved from methods described in Pillar and Orlóci (1993).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">DESCRIPTION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data manipulation</head><p>SYNCSA uses the same data manipulation as conventionally used in R. Four basic input data matrices (matrix notation follows<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Pillar and Duarte, 2010</ref>) may be entered in order to run all SYNCSA analyses, but at least two matrices are necessary: the community matrix and a matrix with either traits or phylogenetic information. Data matrices should be organized as follows:</p><p>(i) community matrix, arranged with species as columns and sampling units as rows, which may contain either species presences/absences or abundances (matrix</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Fuzzy types, scaling-up and assembly patterns</head><p>SYNCSA offers 10 functions that can be used for data manipulation (organization and transformations), scaling-up of trait and phylogenetic data to the metacommunity level and matrix correlation. The scaling-up allows data exploration and hypothesis testing about trait-convergence and trait-divergence assembly patterns, phylogenetic signal and their relations to environmental</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V.J.Debastiani and V.D.Pillar</head><p>variation (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Pillar and Duarte, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Pillar et al., 2009</ref>). For revealing trait-convergence assembly patterns, community weighted means of each trait will be computed by matrix multiplication (T = WB). A significant matrix correlation ρ(TE) between community resemblances based on traits (D T ) and on environmental variables (D E ) is evidence of trait-convergence assembly pattern at the metacommunity level. For revealing trait-divergence assembly patterns, an essential step for the scaling-up is the weighting of species presences or abundances by the species trait similarities. Analogously, the same approach is used for the phylogenetic data, in which case the weighting is based on species phylogenetic similarities. Each element in the resulting weighted matrix (X for traits and P for phylogeny) will indicate the probability that a given species will occur in a community based on its trait or phylogenetic similarity to the species that were found in the same community, and thus the matrix will convey to the community level the whole trait or phylogenetic information captured by the species similarity matrix. The matrix correlation ρ(XE) measures the strength of the association between variation in community composition weighted by the species traits and variation in community environmental variables (D E ). The partial matrix correlation ρ(XE.T), which removes the effect of trait-convergence in T, will indicate whether a trait-divergence assembly pattern is related to the environmental variation. Furthermore, matrix correlation ρ(PE) measures the strength of the association between community distances based on their phylogenetic structure (D P ) and environmental distances (D E ). Moreover, matrices X and P may be submitted to ordination techniques, as performed by Duarte (2011), enhancing our capability to explore patterns and test hypotheses at the metacommunity level.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Phylogenetic signal</head><p>SYNCSA allows the detection of phylogenetic signal at two levels: at the species pool and at the metacommunity. A phylogenetic signal at the species pool level is expected when the variation in species traits is strongly correlated with their evolutionary history and it is measured by the matrix correlation ρ(BF) between species resemblances based on their traits (D B ) and on their phylogeny (D F ). Phylogenetic signal at the metacommunity level is expected when communities are more similar to their phylogenetic structure, and also more similar to their average trait values which is measured by the matrix correlation ρ(PT). Phylogenetic niche conservatism can be tested using path analysis as proposed by Pillar and Duarte (2010).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Searching for optimal traits</head><p>SYNCSA offers functions for searching for an optimal trait subset unraveling trait-convergence and trait-divergence assembly patterns related to one or more environmental variables. The function optimal examines all possible combinations of traits in subsets with one to a maximum specified number of traits. The output will indicate which trait subset maximizes the specified matrix correlation.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>W). (ii) Trait matrix, with traits as columns and species as rows, which should contain a set of functional traits describing the species (matrix B). Both binary and/or quantitative traits may be included. (iii) The species phylogenetic pairwise dissimilarities (matrix D F ), such as the ones obtained in the software Mesquite (W.P. Maddison and D.R. Maddison, http://mesquiteproject.org) or the R package Ape (Paradis, 2004). (iv) The environmental data of interest, which may be one or more community drivers or ecosystem effects (matrix E), with variables in columns and communities in rows. When labels for both row and columns are available for all matrices, the function organize.syncsa will rearrange all matrices to be in the same order.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Copyedited by: SK MANUSCRIPT CATEGORY: APPLICATIONS NOTE [10:02 5/7/2012 Bioinformatics-bts325.tex] Page: 2068 2067–2068</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> CONCLUSION The methods implemented in the SYNCSA package for R enable the analysis of ecological data in a novel metacommunity perspective. In this way, ecologists may assess the linkages between functional and phylogenetic structure of communities, their responses to environmental drivers and their effects on ecosystem processes. Furthermore, functional and phylogenetic mechanisms explaining both β and α niche differentiation may be empirically examined. The metacommunity approach is complementary to the analysis of trait and phylogenetic patterns within communities, widely available in the R package. Moreover, by having in R methods that were originally available only in the SYNCSA application, users will have more flexibility for modifying the methods to suit their own purposes and for developing new ways to analyze ecological data.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An update of the angiosperm phylogeny group classification for the orders and families of flowering plants: APG III</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Apg</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bot. J. Linn. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">161</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The delayed rise of present-day mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R P</forename>
				<surname>Bininda-Emonds</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">446</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="507" to="512" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The merging of community ecology and phylogenetic biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Cavender-Bares</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="693" to="715" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic habitat filtering influences forest nucleation in grasslands</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Duarte</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oikos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="208" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenies and the comparative method</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Felsenstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Nat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic community structure and phylogenetic turnover across space and edaphic gradients in western Amazonian tree communities</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V A</forename>
				<surname>Fine</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Kembel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="552" to="565" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PanTHERIA: a species-level database of life history, ecology, and geography of extant and recently extinct mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="2648" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Try—a global database of plant traits</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Kattge</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Glob. Change Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2905" to="2935" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction: the scope and goals of research on assembly rules Ecological Assembly Rules: Perspectives, Advances, Retreats</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Keddy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Weiher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Weiher, E. and Keddy, P.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="20" />
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, UK</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The phylogenetic structure of a neotropical forest tree community</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Kembel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Hubbell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">APE: analyses of phylogenetics and evolution in R language</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Paradis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framework for metacommunity analysis of phylogenetic structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Pillar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Duarte</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="587" to="596" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Character-based Community Analysis: The Theory and an Application Program</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Pillar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Orlóci</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<publisher>SPB Academic Publishing, The Hague</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discriminating trait-convergence and trait-divergence assembly patterns in ecological community gradients</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Pillar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Veg. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="334" to="348" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenies and community ecology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Webb</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Ecol. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="475" to="505" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>