
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:40+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology SYSBIONS: nested sampling for systems biology</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rob</forename>
								<surname>Johnson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Integrative Systems Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Paul</forename>
								<surname>Kirk</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Integrative Systems Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">P H</forename>
								<surname>Stumpf</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Integrative Systems Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Janet</forename>
								<surname>Kelso</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Integrative Systems Biology and Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Life Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology SYSBIONS: nested sampling for systems biology</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="604" to="605"/>
							<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu675</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 9, 2014; revised on July 30, 2014; accepted on October 13, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Model selection is a fundamental part of the scientific process in systems biology. Given a set of competing hypotheses, we routinely wish to choose the one that best explains the observed data. In the Bayesian framework, models are compared via Bayes factors (the ratio of evidences), where a model&apos;s evidence is the support given to the model by the data. A parallel interest is inferring the distribution of the parameters that define a model. Nested sampling is a method for the computation of a model&apos;s evidence and the generation of samples from the posterior parameter distribution. Results: We present a C-based, GPU-accelerated implementation of nested sampling that is designed for biological applications. The algorithm follows a standard routine with optional extensions and additional features. We provide a number of methods for sampling from the prior subject to a likelihood constraint. Availability and implementation: The software SYSBIONS is available from http://www.theosysbio.bio.ic.ac.uk/resources/sysbions/</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Given a set of models proposed to explain some observation, we seek to rank them according to the extent to which they are supported by some data. Likelihood-based approaches find the point at which the likelihood function is maximized, and compare models based on these maxima (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Burnham and Anderson, 2002</ref>). Bayesian approaches for model selection rest on Bayes factors: the ratio of evidences of competing models. A number of methods exist to estimate the evidence (<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kirk et al., 2013</ref>), a metric of the support afforded to a model by some data. Nested sampling is a Bayesian method for evidence estimation and parameter inference for systems where a likelihood function can be defined (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Skilling, 2006</ref>). As the algorithm progresses, it generates samples from the posterior parameter distribution directly. We present a C-based nested sampling tool for computational biologists. The user supplies a likelihood function, some experimental data and the prior parameter distribution. The program returns a value for the evidence alongside samples from the posterior parameter distribution. There exists a Fortran-based nested sampling package, MultiNest (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Feroz et al., 2009</ref>), used in the astrophysics community. Our work is aimed specifically at the biological community and includes an SBML (Systems Biology Markup Language,<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Rodriguez et al., 2007</ref>) parser so that models can be specified according to current standards. The recent growing use of nested sampling in systems biology invites the release of a tool implementing the method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Aitken and Akman, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Burkoff et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Dybowski et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Kirk et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Pullen and Morris, 2014</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">APPROACH</head><p>The evidence is defined as Z= R Â 'ðÞðÞ d, where is the parameter set (and Â the parameter space), ' the likelihood function and the prior. The change in notation ðÞ d=dXðÞ, where XðÞ is the cumulative density function, allows the integral to be written Z= R 1 0 'ðÞ dXðÞ. This can be approximated as a sum, Z % P N i=1 ' i W i , where N points are sampled and W i is the proportion of prior mass represented by point i, calculated as the difference between the volume enclosed by the contour of constant likelihood through ' i and that through ' iÀ1. Nested sampling is a method for generating the sequence of points f' i ; W i g. For a thorough presentation of nested sampling, we refer the reader to the work of Skilling (2006) and Sivia and Skilling (2006). For our purposes, we follow the general algorithm: 1. Initialise Z = 0 2. Generate N points from ðÞ</p><formula>3. for i=1 : M a. Find Ã with lowest likelihood, ' Ã b. Calculate W i =exp À iÀ1 N À Á À exp À i N À Á c. Set Z=Z+' Ã W i d. Resample Ã $ðÞj 'ðÞ4' Ã 4. end for 5. Set Z=Z+ X N j=1 ' j exp À M N À Á =N</formula><p>Our program is written primarily in C with additional capability for GPU acceleration. Other features include an SBML parser for automated generation of likelihood functions (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Liepe et al., 2010</ref>) and plotting tools. For the task of sampling from the prior subject to a likelihood constraint (step 3d), we provide three methods. The accuracy of the approximation in step 3b depends on the population of N points (live points) being truly distributed as the prior within the given likelihood constraint (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Skilling, 2006</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">METHODS</head><p>Our nested sampling package is a command-line tool for Linux and MacOSX platforms. Pre-requisites are listed in the accompanying *To whom correspondence should be addressed. yThe authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. manual. The user supplies a likelihood function, either by editing a template file or using an SBML file. An executable is then made that receives input from the command line. When the program is run, live points are generated and their likelihoods evaluated according to the function supplied by the user. On completion, it returns the calculated evidence with standard deviation, samples from the posterior, trajectories generated by points from the posterior and files from which the algorithm can be restarted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Algorithm options</head><p>Options available to the user are listed in<ref type="figure">Table 1</ref>. The only required input is the parameter set (all other variables have default values). Parameters may be constant or inferred subject to a uniform prior distribution, for which lower and upper bounds must be supplied. The algorithm can be terminated either by specifying the number of iterations, or by monitoring the rate at which the evidence accumulates: the loop terminates at iter</p><formula>ation m if ' m W m = P m i=1 ' i W i 5tol.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Sampling methods</head><p>We include three sampling methods for step 3d of the algorithm: rejection, for perfectly sampling from the prior, and random walk (following<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Sivia and Skilling, 2006</ref>) and ellipsoidal (following<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Feroz et al., 2009</ref>) for refined sampling with reduced computational cost. Rejection: The rejection method samples from the prior as initially defined, accepting the point if its likelihood value is within the constraint and rejecting otherwise. This method remains true to the requirement that samples are taken from the prior subject to the likelihood constraint, but its efficiency is poor: as the lowest likelihood increases, the acceptance rate becomes prohibitively small. Random walk: The random-walk method duplicates a point randomly chosen from the current live-point population and walks it 20 steps, accepting the new point at each step if its likelihood is within the constraint. The steps are scaled according to the covariance among the present population, and scaled further to converge to an acceptance rate of 0.5 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Sivia and Skilling, 2006</ref>). Ellipsoidal: The ellipsoidal method (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Mukherjee et al., 2006</ref>) creates an ellipsoid surrounding the current population of live points, expanded by some user-supplied factor. The new point is sampled from within the ellipsoid. This increases the acceptance rate but risks excluding areas of prior mass that lie inside the current likelihood constraint.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Output</head><p>A summary file of input and output information is created, documenting the number of live points, number of iterations, tolerance, sampling method and parameter ranges, followed by the evidence with standard deviation, the prior-to-posterior information gain and the means of all parameters and their standard deviations. Posterior distributions of the parameters can be plotted individually as histograms and in pair-wise scatter plots using the data stored in the posterior file. Finally, a file of trajectories is created that can be compared against the input data. Restart files are created, documenting input parameters that must persist upon restart (such as the number of live points) and listing all points, live and discarded. These files can be used to restart the program from where it completed. It is also possible to specify the path to where the restart files are written.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">SUMMARY</head><p>We present SYSBIONS, a computational tool for model selection and parameter inference using nested sampling. Using a data-based likelihood function, our package calculates the evidence of a model and the corresponding posterior parameter distribution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>605</head><p>Nested sampling for systems biology</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Input options</figDesc><table>Variable 
Tag 
Input 
Default 

Number of live points nLive 
**integer 
1000 
Number of iterations maxIter 
**integer 
on, 10 000 
Tolerance 
tol 
decimal 
off, 0.001 
*Parameters 
constant 
**value 
none 
uniform 
** bounds 
none 
Sampling method 
rejection 
none 
off 
rw 
none 
off 
ellipsoid 
expansion factor on, 2 
Restart from file 
Restart 
file paths 
_restart_points.txt, 
_restart_input.txt 
Write restart 
write_restart file path root 
_restart 
Points to leap 
nLeap 
**integer 
1 
Adaptive leaping 
adaptive 
none 
off 
CUDA 
cuda 
**nLeap, 
off, none, 
**max. threads 
none 

*required; **required if tag given. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head><p>We gratefully acknowledge the help and support of the Theoretical Systems Biology Group at Imperial College London. Funding: This work was supported through a BBSRC PhD studentship to R.J. and an HFSP grant<ref type="bibr">[RGP0061/2011]</ref>to P.K. and M.P.H.S. Conflict of interest: none declared.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nested sampling for parameter inference in systems biology: application to an exemplar circadian model</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Aitken</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Akman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">72</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the energy landscapes of protein folding simulations with Bayesian computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Burkoff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="878" to="886" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Model Selection and Multimodel Inference: A Practical Information-Theoretic Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Burnham</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Anderson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nested sampling for Bayesian model comparison in the context of Salmonella disease dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Dybowski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">82317</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MultiNest: an efficient and robust Bayesian inference tool for cosmology and particle physics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Feroz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">398</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1601" to="1614" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model selection in systems and synthetic biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Kirk</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Biotech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ABC-SysBio—approximate Bayesian computation in Python with GPU support</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Liepe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1797" to="1799" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A nested sampling algorithm for cosmological model selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Mukherjee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">638</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian model comparison and parameter inference in systems biology using nested sampling</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Pullen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Morris</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">88419</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SBMLeditor: effective creation of models in the Systems Biology Markup Language (SBML)</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Rodriguez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Data Analysis: A Bayesian Tutorial</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Sivia</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Skilling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nested sampling for general Bayesian computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Skilling</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bayesian Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="833" to="860" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>