
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:51+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies The Amordad database engine for metagenomics</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">20 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ehsan</forename>
								<surname>Behnam</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Molecular and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Southern California</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Andrew</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Smith</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Molecular and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Southern California</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Janet</forename>
								<surname>Kelso</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Molecular and Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Southern California</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies The Amordad database engine for metagenomics</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2949" to="2955"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">20 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu405</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on February 21, 2014; revised on June 21, 2014; accepted on June 23, 2014</note>
					<note>BIOINFORMATICS ORIGINAL PAPER Associate Editor: Contact: andrewds@usc.edu Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Several technical challenges in metagenomic data analysis , including assembling metagenomic sequence data or identifying operational taxonomic units, are both significant and well known. These forms of analysis are increasingly cited as conceptually flawed, given the extreme variation within traditionally defined species and rampant horizontal gene transfer. Furthermore, computational requirements of such analysis have hindered content-based organization of metagenomic data at large scale. Results: In this article, we introduce the Amordad database engine for alignment-free, content-based indexing of metagenomic datasets. Amordad places the metagenome comparison problem in a geometric context, and uses an indexing strategy that combines random hashing with a regular nearest neighbor graph. This framework allows refinement of the database over time by continual application of random hash functions, with the effect of each hash function encoded in the nearest neighbor graph. This eliminates the need to explicitly maintain the hash functions in order for query efficiency to benefit from the accumulated randomness. Results on real and simulated data show that Amordad can support logarithmic query time for identifying similar metagenomes even as the database size reaches into the millions. Availability and implementation: Source code, licensed under the GNU general public license (version 3) is freely available for download from http://smithlabresearch.org/amordad</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Metagenomicshasrevolutionizedourknowledgeofmicrobialcommunities. Such studies have uncovered intercommunity rules governingthebehaviorofthemicrobialnetworksandvariousaspectsof their symbiotic or parasitic lives within their host ecosystems (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Daniel, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Qin et al., 2010</ref>). With technological advancements on the horizon, whole-metagenome shotgun (WMS) sequencing has increasingly become popular. The results of many WMS projects ranging from direct study of simple biofilms in specific niches (<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Tyson et al., 2004</ref>) to complicated microbial consortia like human gut microbiota (<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Qin et al., 2012</ref>) are now publicly accessible. The first phase of the human microbiome project (<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Turnbaugh et al., 2007</ref>) provided an unprecedented opportunity to explore our 'other genome' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Le Chatelier et al., 2013</ref>). However, making sense of these data has proven tremendously challenging. These challenges stem from both the extreme size and number of possible metagenomes, which may be regarded as continuous mixtures of species whose boundaries can be poorly defined. Popular existing frameworks such as MG-RAST (<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Meyer et al., 2008</ref>) and MEGAN (<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Huson et al., 2011</ref>) rely heavily on alignment-based algorithms to analyze metagenomic data. Assembly of raw reads into longer contigs, binning of sequencing reads and homology searching to characterize the predicted operational taxonomic units (OTUs) are among tasks that require sequence alignment in such frameworks (<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wooley et al., 2010</ref>). The computational requirements of these tasks, however, have reduced their usefulness in large-scale projects. Alignment-free approaches have been successfully applied to overcome the scalability problems associated with alignment and assembly (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Chan and Ragan, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Grabherr et al., 2011</ref>). A large class of alignment-free algorithms rely on the the frequency of oligonucleotides of fixed length k, called k-mers, to represent biological sequences (<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Song et al., 2014</ref>). In metagenomics, several k-merbased algorithms have been proposed mostly targeting the phylogenetic characterization of the metagenomes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">McHardy et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Nalbantoglu et al., 2011</ref>). The idea is to estimate the abundance level of different bacterial families in a metagenome by assigning accurate phylogenetic labels to its reads or contigs. We introduce Amordad, a content-based database engine for metagenomics designed to support rapid indexing and retrieval even as data volumes reach massive scales. In the most basic form, the user makes a query by providing a metagenomic sample sequence and asks for the most similar metagenomes in the database. Similarity between two metagenomes is computed, and query responses are ranked according to similarity with the query. We describe a procedure for assigning an empirical significance score to query responses in this context, which provides additional insight about retrieved metagenomes. Proximity scores also allow, for a given query, efficient identification of the full set of metagenomes sharing some threshold similarity with the query. Amordad does not attempt any sequence alignment or assembly, and is agnostic of OTUs, focusing on the raw metagenome itself as the fundamental data element. Indexing is based on feature vectors, specifically k-mer sequences. In the next section, we describe the combination of random hashing and regular nearest neighbor graph strategies, which enable low complexity queries, both in terms of time and memory usage. Together, these dual index structures allow the database to reorganize itself continually as new data is added, an essential property that is difficult to achieve in highdimensional geometric databases. We demonstrate the efficiency of Amordad in handling up to millions of metagenomes. *To whom correspondence should be addressed</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head><p>We first describe a geometric representation we use for raw metagenomic sequencing data. Then we introduce the two indexing strategies: a randomized hashing strategy based on locality-sensitive hashing<ref type="bibr">[LSH;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Gionis et al. (1999)]</ref>and the regular nearest neighbor graph. Finally, we show how these two indexing strategies are integrated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Geometric interpretation of metagenomes</head><p>A metagenome is the set of genomes for a population of organisms existing in some defined space at a defined time. This is commonly a complex mixture of microorganisms interacting to form a microbial community with behaviors related to the relative frequencies of different microbes in the community. Our window into this population is by sampling parts of these genomes via sequencing. Following a WMS experiment, the totality of information resides in the unprocessed sequenced reads from a given sample (e.g. in FASTQ files). Our goal is to extract information from these data, but to avoid any kind of sequence alignment, assembly (<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Luo et al., 2012</ref>) or assignment of OTUs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Porter and Beiko, 2013</ref>). We instead use representations from alignment-free sequence comparison (<ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Vinga and Almeida, 2003</ref>). Specifically, the set of sequenced reads is transformed into a k-mer count vector. This is a d=4 k-dimensional vector, where coordinate i gives the frequency of occurrence in the metagenome for the ith k-mer. The assumption underlying the use of alignment-free methods in metagenomics is that each microorganism contributes a distinct fingerprint when represented by a k-mer count vector, while similar microbial sequences should give vectors that are closer in this d-dimensional space. This also depends on the measure used for comparing these k-mer count vectors. Assume metagenome M, represented as a set of reads, contains N possible k-mers, which includes all sliding windows of length k in all sequenced reads. We centralize the count of each k-mer to reduce the effect of background noise, as suggested in<ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kantorovitz et al. (2007)</ref>. If each read were a random sequence, letting p a denote the probability of drawing letter a 2 A when generating M, then for any z=z 1 z 2. .. z k 2 A k ,</p><formula>p z = Y k j=1 p zj ;</formula><p>so Np z is approximately the expected number of occurrences of z in M. The centralized k-mer count vector is as follows:</p><formula>MðzÞ=X z À Np z ;</formula><p>where X z is the total number of occurrences of z in M. This simple representation accomplishes the transformation from the set of reads into a vector in d=4 k dimensional space. We treat these vectors as points and hereafter, when we refer to a metagenome, we assume it is represented as a point in this space. In addition to expressing biologically meaningful relationships, appropriate distance measures provide a statistically meaningful foundation for alignment-free sequence comparison. Metric distances are especially appealing, as they allow algorithms to take advantage of the triangle inequality and infer some distance relationships implicitly. Here, we use the angle between two metagenomes as our distance measure. Dot products are computed as usual, the norm of point x is jjxjj= ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi x Á x p , and the angle between points x and y is xy =arccos x Á y=ðjjxjjjjyjjÞ.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Indexing metagenomic points with LSH for angles</head><p>LSH is among the best known indexing methods for high-dimensional data (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Gionis et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Lv et al., 2007</ref>), and provides a framework for understanding and analyzing a large class of randomized dimensionreduction techniques. Intuitively, a family of hash functions is 'locality sensitive' if any of its members hashes closer points to the same bucket with higher probability. We use an LSH family for which the measure of proximity is the angle between points. Suppose u 2 R d is a random unit vector. For any x 2 R d define h u ðxÞ= 1 ifx Á u ! 0; 0 otherwise:</p><formula>( ð1Þ</formula><p>Then, for any two points x and y, it is straightforward to show that</p><p>Pr ðh u ðxÞ=h u ðyÞÞ=1 À xy =; ð2Þ where 0 xy. Let U=fu 1 ;. .. ; u r g be a set of random vectors with norm one and define the hash function as follows:</p><p>processing queries to expand the search region. Specifically, for a set of n metagenomic points in the database, we construct a directed graph in which each metagenome is a node, and each node has exactly m outgoing edges pointing to its m nearest neighbors under the assumed distance measure. This type of graph is called an m-regular nearest neighbor graph, abbreviated as m-NNG (Samet, 2006, sec. 4.5.6). Supplementary<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure S1</ref>provides a schematic depicting how this graph is used to expand the query region. Nearest neighbor graphs have found various applications in different areas including shape recognition (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Beis and Lowe, 1997</ref>) and computational geometry (<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Miller et al., 1997</ref>), and efficient algorithms have been proposed to construct them (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Dong et al., 2011</ref>). To understand how we efficiently construct the m-NNG, recall that LSH provides a probabilistic measure of the relative locality of the points. When two points reside in a common hash bucket it is more likely that they should be connected in the m-NNG. This observation suggests an approximate algorithm to construct the m-NNG: Given a point x, (i) for each hash table T i , examine all points y in the same bucket as x, (ii) keep only the m closest points to x and (iii) connect the corresponding nodes in the m-NNG. As the information from LSH is probabilistic, the probability of misidentifying an edge never reaches zero. However, the theory of LSH guarantees that this 'approximate' graph converges to the actual m-NNG, as we increase the number of hash functions/tables used in this process. In supplementary material, we present results about the rate of convergence of the m-NNG. There is a major problem with this process as just described: the graph encodes no more information than already exists in the hash tables, which are also used in the query process. This redundancy, however, allows us to 'retire' hash functions, replacing them with new ones. This continually refreshes the randomness in Amordad, while retaining the useful information from retired hash tables, as it is encoded in the m-NNG. In Amordad, as each hash table is generated, it is placed in a queue (i.e. first-in, first-out or FIFO) of size L. At the same time, the oldest hash table in the queue is removed; we elaborate this after defining basic insertion and deletion operations for Amordad. The nature of any useful large-scale metagenomic database is dynamic: users must be able to add points over time and possibly also remove them. These basic operations are handled as follows:</p><p>insert(x) computes H Ui ðxÞ for 1 i L and modifies i-th hash table by adding x to buckets corresponding to each H Ui ðxÞ. Then a new vertex is added to the graph and associated with x. delete(x) computes bucket numbers H Ui ðxÞ, for 1 i L, and removes x from the appropriate buckets in all hash tables in queue. Removal of x from the graph follows a lazy deletion strategy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Jannink, 1995</ref>). This lazy deletion is essential to the efficiency of maintaining the graph because, although each node has a fixed out-degree, the in-degree is not constrained. Nodes have a reference count for in-degree. Upon deletion nodes are marked, and although never again reported in response to a query, each subsequent encounter during query or insertion operations removes an incoming edge and decrements the count; the node itself is deleted when the count reaches zero. The insertion and deletion operations are both efficient: the complexity of each operation is dominated by evaluation of L hash functions. Once the graph has converged, for each point, its m out-going edges indicate its m nearest neighbors. A problem arises because the insertion and deletion operations eliminate this property. A newly inserted point might be among the m nearest neighbors of any existing point, but to check this requires processing each metagenome in the database. Similarly, when a metagenome is deleted, some metagenomes will effectively have out-degree of m – 1. The solution is continually applying maintenance operations, which one may imagine as occurring according to a regular schedule, such as once per day. The maintenance consists of l iterations of the following: A random hash function is generated and used to create a new hashT 1 is examined to update edges in the nearest neighbor graph. T L+1 is added to the queue, and T 1 is removed. At any time during this process, queries have access to L hash tables, and T 1 is not discarded until the edges indicated by bucket co-occupancy in T 1 have been added to the graph. The schematic representing this process is depicted in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. In our current implementation, we set L = 200 and l = 50. Amordad queries, or similarity searches, occur in two steps:</p><p>(1) For query point y and 1 i L, compute H Ui ðyÞ and check the distance between y and all other points hashing to same bucket number H Ui ðyÞ in T i .</p><p>(2) For any x in bucket H Ui ðyÞ, evaluate the m neighbors of x in the graph, and check their distance to y. This procedure is summarized in Algorithm 1, where N ðxÞ refers to the set of neighbor points of x in the graph, and the function max_element(R) gives the furthest point in set R to the query point. In Supplementary Material, we give a heuristic model to express the influence of the nearest neighbor graph on query accuracies using a formula similar to those commonly used in the context of LSH alone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Algorithm 1 Similarity search in Amordad</head><p>Input: Set S of points, L hash tables, an m-NNG, query y and parameter t Output: Set R containing t nearest neighbors of y in S 1: R 1; max 1 2: for i 1 to L do 3: compute H Ui ðyÞ 4: for all x 2 H Ui ðyÞ do 5: for all x 0 2 N ðxÞ [ fxg do 6: if x 0 y 5 max then 7:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>We have two objectives in studying the performance of Amordad: (i) investigating its potential for identifying</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Dataset and implementation details</head><p>We obtained WMS data from the European Nucleotide Archive (ENA) (<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Leinonen et al., 2011</ref>), including $3.5TB of compressed FASTQ files from 133 projects (08/15/13). We extracted 5-mers from each sample and obtained 5073 real metagenomic count vectors in d=1024-dimensional space. We augmented this set with an additional 10 6 randomly generated metagenomes to increase the scale of our evaluations. Each simulated metagenome contained N=10 7 i.i.d. reads of length 100. On initiation of the query, the graph and the queue are read into memory (these could be memory residents on a dedicated server). Because of space constraints, we do not load all count vectors but instead an index of their location on disk. For comparison purposes in evaluating accuracy, we implemented the brute-force (quadratic time) nearest neighbor graph construction and the linear time scan for exact results from queries. The implementation of the database engine and associated utilities was done in C++ and with the assistance of the Boost Graph Library (http://www.boost.org/libs/graph). Our Amordad implementation includes multi-threaded query processing. However, all evaluations described here were done using a single core of a 2.4 GHz Xeon CPU and 16GB of memory. Building Amordad is a multi-stage process, involving the construction of hash tables and the nearest neighbor graph. The overall time to build the database with 10 6 count vectors was 44.9 h. We also investigated the memory requirement for building the database. Initial construction of the nearest neighbor graph required the largest memory among all of the programs included in Amordad software package. When examining L = 200 hash tables to construct a 20-NNG representing 10 6 metagenomes, the peak memory was 10.4GB.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Assigning significance to query responses</head><p>Assigning significance to query results is essential, but there should be no expectation that actual distances between metagenomes (for any reasonable representation) follow a simple statistical distribution. To gain insight into how these distances can be interpreted in the context of Amordad queries, we examined the distribution of distances for relatively small sample of available metagenomes.<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>shows the empirical distribution of distances between the 5073 metagenomes from the 133 projects. Denoting F as the cumulative function of this distribution, for any query point y with response x, we defined Fð xy Þ as the significance score of the query answer. This score shows the relative ranking of the distance between x and y among all of the distance measurements. If Fð xy Þ is large, the relatedness between x and y might be questionable. In fact, if x and y are two unrelated metagenomes, the centralization of count vectors and the linearity of expectations assert that Eð xy Þ==2. This important observation suggests that any meaningful xy must belong to the tail of the empirical distribution.</p><p>We decided to define the maximum proximity radius as the maximum distance between the query point and the retrieved data point such that the response is assumed relevant to the query. We denote the maximum proximity radius by 0, and for a query y, we filter out any response x if xy 4 0. In our evaluations, a liberal threshold is F À1 ð0:2Þ, which results in 0 =0:987 radians or 0 % 57 . A more conservative cut-off is F À1 ð0:1Þ which is equivalent to 0 =0:752 radians or approximately 43 . The conservative and liberal cutoff thresholds are respectively selected as the first and second deciles of the empirical cumulative distribution of distances within the database.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Evaluation of the graph effect on the query space requirement</head><p>We can view the m-NNG as having two effects: increasing accuracy when using a fixed number of hash tables or reducing the number of hash tables required to achieve a particular accuracy. We conducted a series of experiments to compare the performance of the various instances of Amordad with the basic LSH algorithm when they are both using the same sets of hash tables. For LSH alone, we exclude the graph. The evaluation metric used here is average recall on a set of queries. Given a query y, denoting the t nearest neighbors as N t ðyÞ, if R(y) is the set of points reported by the algorithm, then recallðyÞ=jN t ðyÞ \ RðyÞj=jN t ðyÞj:</p><p>The detailed experimental set up is as follows: We randomly selected 10 of 133 projects and regarded their 94 samples as the query set. Different instances of Amordad were then constructed considering all other samples as database points and m-NNG for m 2 f1; 10; 20g. Next, using 1 L 200 hash tables, we compared the average recall value of different instances of Amordad with the basic LSH algorithm. For simplicity, we only considered the first nearest neighbor (i.e. t = 1), and performed experiments separately for both the conservative and liberal-maximum proximity radius. If the distance between any query point and its nearest neighbor exceeded the maximum proximity radius in an experiment, it was discarded from the query set. As hash functions are randomly generated, we repeated each experiment<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>, for a fixed accuracy, Amordad requires considerably fewer hash tables than LSH. When the graph is constructed for m = 10 or m = 20, Amordad already exhibited no query errors in any experiment. However, LSH is not able to reach perfect recall even when L = 200 hash tables are used under the liberal-maximum proximity radius.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Measuring query time in a large-scale database</head><p>We conducted a set of experiments to investigate the scalability of the Amordad engine. Similar to the previous experiment, we randomly selected 10 projects and used their metagenomes (183) for queries. All n d = 4890 remaining metagenomic points were used, along with n s simulated points, to construct the different instances of the database. We set the value of n s such that n s + n d =2 i for i increasing from 16 to 20. Then, we created an instance of the database with n points as follows. We set the number of hash functions to r=log n. We used the conservative threshold 0 =0:752 to determine the number of hash tables required by the LSH to bound the probability of missing a nearest neighbor below =0:05. Finally, we constructed the graph with 10 outgoing edge from each node. To evaluate the relation between the query time and the number of points in the database, we calculated the average wall-time and number of angle computations required for responding to all queries. As shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>, the query time grows almost linearly with log n. This establishes the scalability of Amordad, validating its ability to efficiently process queries in large database instances. In each experiment conducted here, the query accuracy was 100%, again demonstrating the effect of the graph to drive the probability of query error to virtually zero.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Relationships captured in the nearest neighbor graph</head><p>Our original purpose for including the m-NNG in the design of Amordad was to eliminate the space that would otherwise be required to explicitly use enough hash tables to ensure the desired accuracy. But it can also be leveraged as a persistent and adaptive knowledge base that links close points and therefore permits the detection of biologically similar metagenomes. We expectrequired distance computations per query as a function of (log) database size many edges in the graph will link between biological replicates, the precise definition of which might depend on the goals of the project. For example, a cohort representing sea water samples taken at slightly different depths, or gut microbiota samples obtained at slightly different times. Recovering biological replicates within a cohort is an easy task under our framework and could be potentially useful. However, we claim our approach can cluster inherently similar metagenomes together even when the methodologies for obtaining, preparing and sequencing samples vary. To demonstrate this type of relationship captured within Amordad, we constructed the least informative graph (i.e. the 1-NNG) using metagenomes from the 133 projects. We identified any edge connecting metagenomes that belong to two distinct projects. Among the 194 such edges, 58 showed the significance score 50.01.<ref type="figure" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>shows the top 10 most similar pairs of samples (projects are listed by accession number from ENA). To avoid redundancy, any pair of projects is reported at most once in the table (Supplemetary Material contains a complete list). In general, we expect the number of applications that can benefit from mining this graph is extremely broad.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A B</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head><p>We presented Amordad, a database engine for whole-metagenome sequencing data. Amordad uses alignment-free principles, representing metagenomes as points in a high-dimensional geometric space. LSH is used to efficiently index the database points. To improve accuracy and efficiency beyond what is practical from LSH alone, Amordad augments this indexing with a regular nearest neighbor graph. The randomness in Amordad is continually refreshed by resampling new random hash functions. Although only a fixed number of hash functions is alive within Amordad at any given time, those that are extinct have contributed to optimizing connectivity in the graph, and thus continue to assist queries even if they are no longer used for hashing. Results from a series of experiments have demonstrated this approach to have a significant effect on query efficiency and accuracy. The ability to cope with the rapid accumulation of data was a central design goal. LSH is a well-known approach to index high-dimensional data, but it is also a randomized method. A major drawback is the number of hash tables one must maintain to provide guarantees on the accuracy of queries, imposing time and space constraints. This is a well-known problem, and solutions have been proposed to overcome this pitfall (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Lv et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Panigrahy, 2006</ref>). These solutions mostly rely on the fact that each hash function (i.e. each bit in our scheme) provides a ranking based on the proximity of points to a certain query. Therefore, even if the closest neighbor is not hashed to the same bucket as the query, it is highly probable that buckets close to the query bucket contain the nearest neighbor. Consequently, one may avoid generating many hash tables at the cost of checking more buckets from each table. This clever strategy has a direct effect on the indexing memory consumption (<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Lv et al., 2007</ref>). However, as the distance between the query and its nearest neighbors increases, there is a rapid growth in the number of buckets that must be checked. This presents a challenge in our applications because of the inherent diversity of microbial communities in many circumstances. In fact, if we view a set of biologically related metagenomes as a cluster in high-dimensional space, the diameter of some complex clusters like human gut microbiota (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arumugam et al., 2011</ref>), might be large enough to make the process of searching close buckets to the query bucket time-consuming. Our approach, augmenting the LSH indexing with a graph structure, avoids having to explicity search additional buckets, and depends on transitivity of relationships encoded in the graph. Intuitively, if the underlying distance measure between metagenomes satisfies the triangle inequality, the graph should guide the search in the most appropriate directions. Additionally, the LSH provides a means of streamlining the database maintenance process. Hash tables are maintained in a fixed size queue that is continually updated, and each new hash table contributes to refining edges in the graph. As a consequence, we are able to keep the graph in a near ideal state without requiring explicit operations to maintain the graph after metagenomes are added to (or removed from) the database. This design decision acknowledges that in the near future large (and distributed) metagenome databases will be updated frequently, and efficiency of queries will be more important to users of Amordad.It is clear that many applications of Amordad will involve maintaining large metagenomic data clusters so that new metagenomes can be understood through their neighborhoods in the graph. From this perspective, the graph becomes the primary structure, and the LSH serves simply to find the right neighborhood without exhaustive search. Finally, we address some limitations of this work. We represent each metagenome by a feature vector that included the frequencies of all k-mers for a fixed k. We did not use feature selection, and were bound to relatively small values of k. Many of the k-mers were almost certainly irrelevant in our experiments on real data. More flexibility could be obtained if a metagenome is represented by a 'bag of features' (<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Salton, 1991</ref>) composed of a variety of words (i.e. subsets of k-mers for varying k). From statistical point of view, this is equivalent to shifting the paradigm from a full Markov chain of order k toward a variable length Markov chain (B € uhlmann and Wyner, 1999). The main challenge is to find a parsimonious algorithm for feature extraction at large scale. More important than irrelevant features, however, are features representing technical artifacts, for example, of the sequencing experiments.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Schematic showing how the basic operations interact with the different components of the database. The continual procedure for updating the graph is also depicted</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig.2.</head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Probability density function of angles resulted from real metagenomes</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.3.</head><figDesc>Fig. 3. Average recall for a query set, showing (A) the conservative and (B) liberal maximum proximity radius</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig.4.</head><figDesc>Fig. 4. (A) Average wall-time and (B) required distance computations per query as a function of (log) database size</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: This work was supported by the National Institute of Health [P50 HG002790]. Conflict of interest: none declared.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>table T L+1 .</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><figDesc>Table 1. Top 10 most similar pairs of metagenomes from different projects, with scope of corresponding projects, distance between metagenomic points (i.e. the angle in degrees) and associated significance scores</figDesc><table>Accession I 
Accession II 
Project scope I 
Project scope II 
Distance 
Relative ranking 

ERP001737 
ERP001736 
Sea water 
Sea water 
4 
0.0016 
ERP001736 
ERP001227 
Sea water 
North sea water 
4.6 
0.0020 
SRP009476 
ERP001736 
Sea water 
Sea water 
5.3 
0.0023 
ERP001068 
SRP013944 
Low and neutral PH soil 
Forest soil 
5.3 
0.0023 
SRP021115 
ERP001736 
Marine matter 
Sea water (different depth) 
5.4 
0.0023 
SRP009476 
SRP021115 
Sea water 
Marine matter 
5.5 
0.0024 
SRP017582 
ERP001568 
Oil sands 
Polluted water 
6.5 
0.0028 
ERP001737 
SRP021115 
Sea water 
Marine matter 
6.6 
0.0029 
SRP016067 
ERP002469 
Gut microbiota a 
Gut microbiota b 
6.8 
0.0030 
SRP019913 
SRP021115 
Red sea water 
Marine matter 
7.3 
0.0033 

a 

From a cohort of normal and atherosclerosis samples. b Metagenomes are sampled from European women with normal, impaired and diabetic glucose control. </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">H U ðxÞ=ðh u1 ðxÞ;. .. ; h ur ðxÞÞ: ð3Þ Equation (2) suggests that under the r-bit binary embedding induced by H U , the &apos;locality&apos; of points is likely to be preserved. In other words, the closer the two points in R d , the more likely are they to share the same mapping in the Hamming space, that is, the codomain of H U. This function, which is locality sensitive when distances are measured as angles for pairs of points, was first introduced in a theoretical work by Goemans and Williamson (1995) before its first use in the context of LSH by Charikar (2002). Subsequently, this function has been applied in different contexts including natural language processing (Ravichandran et al., 2005) and computational biology (Behnam et al., 2013). To achieve our desired accuracy during the query process, we index points in multiple iterations, with each iteration generating a new hash table. Therefore, the first step in our indexing procedure can be summarized as follows: Generate U as a set of r random unit-length vectors in R d [using an established method (Muller, 1959)]. For each metagenomic point x, find H Ui ðxÞ and store the result in a hash table T i. Repeat the above two steps L times, producing the set T =fT 1 ;. .. ; T L g of hash tables. Although LSH provides a simple indexing scheme and guarantees sublinear query complexity under certain conditions (Gionis et al., 1999), its use in large databases has been hindered because a large number of hash tables can be required to overcome its approximate nature, which is critical for applications that must guarantee query accuracy. Our starting point to address this problem in the metagenomics context was to ask how could we keep some of the useful information from each hash table, without explicitly using all the hash tables or explicitly storing them. The solution was to augment the indexing structure of Amordad by incorporating a proximity graph. This graph encodes important distance relationships that have accumulated through the application of many distinct hash functions, allowing all but a small number of hash tables to be discarded. We show how this graph is constructed and later examine its use in the query process. 2.3 Supplemental indexing with a developing nearest neighbor graph The family of hash functions defined in Equation (1) corresponds to hyperplanes in R d , each partition the space of metagenomes. Consider the geometric loci of all points that are hashed to the same bucket as the query point. This &apos;query region&apos; is the intersection of r half-spaces, defined by r hyperplanes, that contain the query point. The query region is likely to contain the actual nearest neighbor point, but even if it does not, it is reasonable to expect that this point remains close to the query region. We grow this region by searching the neighborhood of all points inside it. Amordad encodes spatial information about the proximities of data points using a graph, and employs the graph when</note>

			<note place="foot">E.Behnam and A.D.Smith at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">The Amordad database engine for metagenomics at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enterotypes of the human gut microbiome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Arumugam</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">473</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="180" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A geometric interpretation for local alignment-free sequence comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Behnam</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="471" to="485" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shape indexing using approximate nearest-neighbour search in high-dimensional spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Beis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Lowe</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Puerto Rico</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1000" to="1006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variable length Markov chains</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>B€ Uhlmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Wyner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="480" to="513" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Next-generation phylogenomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">X</forename>
				<surname>Chan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Ragan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Direct</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Similarity estimation techniques from rounding algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Charikar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Thiry-Fourth Annual ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing</title>
		<meeting>the Thiry-Fourth Annual ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing<address><addrLine>Las Vegas, Nevada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="380" to="388" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The metagenomics of soil</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Daniel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="470" to="478" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient k-nearest neighbor graph construction for generic similarity measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Dong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on World Wide Web</title>
		<meeting>the 20th International Conference on World Wide Web<address><addrLine>Hyderabad, India</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="577" to="586" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Similarity search in high dimensions via hashing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Gionis</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In: VLDB</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="518" to="529" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved approximation algorithms for maximum cut and satisfiability problems using semidefinite programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">X</forename>
				<surname>Goemans</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Williamson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1115" to="1145" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Grabherr</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="644" to="652" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrative analysis of environmental sequences using megan4</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Huson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1552" to="1560" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implementing deletion in B+-trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Jannink</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Sigmod Rec</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymptotic behavior of k-word matches between two uniformly distributed sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kantorovitz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Probab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="788" to="805" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Richness of human gut microbiome correlates with metabolic markers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Le</forename>
				<surname>Chatelier</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">500</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="541" to="546" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The european nucleotide archive</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Leinonen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">SOAPdenovo2: an empirically improved memory-efficient short-read de novo assembler</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Luo</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-probe LSH: efficient indexing for high-dimensional similarity search</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Lv</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 33rd international conference on Very large data bases. VLDB Endowment</title>
		<meeting>the 33rd international conference on Very large data bases. VLDB Endowment<address><addrLine>Vienna, Austria</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="950" to="961" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate phylogenetic classification of variable-length DNA fragments</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Mchardy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The metagenomics rast server–a public resource for the automatic phylogenetic and functional analysis of metagenomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Meyer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">386</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Separators for sphere-packings and nearest neighbor graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Miller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A note on a method for generating points uniformly on n-dimensional spheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">E</forename>
				<surname>Muller</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="1959" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RAIphy: phylogenetic classification of metagenomics samples using iterative refinement of relative abundance index profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<forename type="middle">U</forename>
				<surname>Nalbantoglu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entropy based nearest neighbor search in high dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Panigrahy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the seventeenth annual ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithm</title>
		<meeting>the seventeenth annual ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithm<address><addrLine>Philadelphia, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1186" to="1195" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SPANNER: Taxonomic assignment of sequences using pyramid matching of similarity profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Porter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">G</forename>
				<surname>Beiko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1858" to="1864" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A human gut microbial gene catalogue established by metagenomic sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Qin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">464</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A metagenome-wide association study of gut microbiota in type 2 diabetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Qin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">490</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomized algorithms and NLP: using locality sensitive hash function for high speed noun clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Ravichandran</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 43rd Annual Meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics</title>
		<meeting>the 43rd Annual Meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics<address><addrLine>Ann Arbor, MI</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="622" to="629" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developments in automatic text retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Salton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">253</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="974" to="980" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Foundations of Multidimensional and Metric Data Structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Samet</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Burlington, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New developments of alignment-free sequence comparison: measures, statistics and next-generation sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Song</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="343" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human microbiome project</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Turnbaugh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">449</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="804" to="810" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Community structure and metabolism through reconstruction of microbial genomes from the environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Tyson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">428</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free sequence comparison–a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Vinga</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Almeida</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="523" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A primer on metagenomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Wooley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000667</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>