
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:47+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies The GOBLET training portal: a global repository of bioinformatics training materials, courses and trainers</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-09-04">2015 . September 4, 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Manuel</forename>
								<surname>Corpas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">The Genome Analysis Centre</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Rafael</forename>
								<forename type="middle">C</forename>
								<surname>Jimenez</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">ELIXIR</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hinxton</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Erik</forename>
								<surname>Bongcam-Rudloff</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">The Swedish University for Agricultural Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Uppsala</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Aidan</forename>
								<surname>Budd</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">European Molecular Biology Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michelle</forename>
								<forename type="middle">D</forename>
								<surname>Brazas</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Ontario Institute for Cancer Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pedro</forename>
								<forename type="middle">L</forename>
								<surname>Fernandes</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Instituto Gulbenkian de Ci^ encia</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Oeiras</settlement>
									<country key="PT">Portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bruno</forename>
								<surname>Gaeta</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution">The University of New South Wales</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sydney</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Celia</forename>
								<surname>Van Gelder</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Netherlands Bioinformatics Centre</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Radboud Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands</addrLine>
									<settlement>Nijmegen</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Eija</forename>
								<surname>Korpelainen</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="institution">CSC -IT Center for Science Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Espoo</settlement>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Fran</forename>
								<surname>Lewitter</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Whitehead Institute for Biomedical Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">MIT</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Annette</forename>
								<surname>Mcgrath</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff11">
								<orgName type="institution">CSIRO, Bioinformatics Core</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Canberra</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Daniel</forename>
								<surname>Maclean</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff12">
								<orgName type="laboratory">The Sainsbury Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Norwich Research Park</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Patricia</forename>
								<forename type="middle">M</forename>
								<surname>Palagi</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff13">
								<orgName type="institution">SIB Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 Rue Michel Servet, Genè ve</addrLine>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Kristian</forename>
								<surname>Rother</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff14">
								<orgName type="institution">Academis</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Illstrasse 12</addrLine>
									<postCode>12161</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jan</forename>
								<surname>Taylor</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff15">
								<orgName type="department">The Nowgen Centre</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>29 Grafton Street</addrLine>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Allegra</forename>
								<surname>Via</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff16">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sapienza University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Rome</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Mick</forename>
								<surname>Watson</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff17">
								<orgName type="institution">The Roslin Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Maria</forename>
								<forename type="middle">Victoria</forename>
								<surname>Schneider</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">The Genome Analysis Centre</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Teresa</forename>
								<forename type="middle">K</forename>
								<surname>Attwood</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff18">
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Manchester</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Databases and ontologies The GOBLET training portal: a global repository of bioinformatics training materials, courses and trainers</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Advance Access publication</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="140" to="142"/>
							<date type="published" when="2015-09-04">2015 . September 4, 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu601</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on July 8, 2014; revised on August 29, 2014; accepted on August 31, 2014</note>
					<note>Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Rapid technological advances have led to an explosion of biomedical data in recent years. The pace of change has inspired new collaborative approaches for sharing materials and resources to help train life scientists both in the use of cutting-edge bioinformatics tools and databases and in how to analyse and interpret large datasets. A prototype platform for sharing such training resources was recently created by the Bioinformatics Training Network (BTN). Building on this work, we have created a centralized portal for sharing training materials and courses, including a catalogue of trainers and course organizers , and an announcement service for training events. For course organizers, the portal provides opportunities to promote their training events; for trainers, the portal offers an environment for sharing materials , for gaining visibility for their work and promoting their skills; for trainees, it offers a convenient one-stop shop for finding suitable training resources and identifying relevant training events and activities locally and worldwide. Availability and implementation:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1</head><p>The Genome Analysis Centre, Norwich, 2 ELIXIR, Wellcome Trust Genome Campus, Hinxton, UK, 3 The Swedish University for Agricultural Sciences, Uppsala, Sweden, 4 European Molecular Biology Laboratory, Heidelberg, Germany,ABSTRACT Summary: Rapid technological advances have led to an explosion of biomedical data in recent years. The pace of change has inspired new collaborative approaches for sharing materials and resources to help train life scientists both in the use of cutting-edge bioinformatics tools and databases and in how to analyse and interpret large datasets. A prototype platform for sharing such training resources was recently created by the Bioinformatics Training Network (BTN). Building on this work, we have created a centralized portal for sharing training materials and courses, including a catalogue of trainers and course organizers, and an announcement service for training events. For course organizers, the portal provides opportunities to promote their training events; for trainers, the portal offers an environment for sharing materials, for gaining visibility for their work and promoting their skills; for trainees, it offers a convenient one-stop shop for finding suitable training resources and identifying relevant training events and activities locally and worldwide.and/or international networks and societies, research institutes, foundations, academic groups and so on). Materials are available under a CC BY-SA 3.0 licence for download and use, but materials and courses may currently be uploaded only by registered members and/or by GOBLETaffiliated trainers—i.e. upload to the site requires registration with the GOBLET Foundation (this helps to minimize spurious entries and maintain quality standards). Materials may be presentations, tutorials, datasets, case studies, curricula, etc.; courses may be workshops, summer schools or road shows, and may be linked to their respective materials once uploaded to the repository. All contents are tagged: tags allow classification or filtering of entities by keyword, making them easy to find—the main content filters are currently 'audience' and 'topic'.<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>shows a filtered view of courses and materials using audience tag 'beginner bioinformatician'. Audience tags are particularly valuable because they pinpoint the level to which specific materials are geared. In addition to filtering, a star-rating scheme can be used to rank-order search results. The portal also provides a catalogue of trainers, with information describing their fields of expertise, and lists of their training materials and courses. This registry of trainers and their learning resources may prove useful for course or event organizers, wishing to identify trainers with particular skill sets, and for students and learners looking to acquire particular skills or techniques (here, the rating system may help to guide their choice of materials). To date, 83 training materials and courses have been uploaded to the portal, which also contain profile information on 66 registered trainers and course organizers; it currently receives 500+ hits per day. To augment its functionality, the portal is seamlessly integrated with the iAnn platform (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Jimenez et al., 2013</ref>), a distribution system for generic bioinformatics events around the world. Several future enhancements are planned: among these, we are devising an ontology to standardize the portal's content tags. In developing this ontology, we are collaborating with initiatives like ELIXIR-UK to allow course providers to share information in a standard manner, facilitating the distribution of this information through third-party federated resources. Overall, the portal offers an established, supported and sustainable infrastructure for individuals, groups, organizations, projects, etc., that are routinely producing training materials and courses, but have no framework for organizing or storing their content: e.g. the AllBio consortium recently saw the advantage of exploiting the portal, rather than creating yet another training resource that would be unsupported when project funds cease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>The GOBLET training portal is a pioneering global initiative to federate information relevant to bioinformatics, biocomputing, biocuration and computational biology trainers, courses and materials. The contents are free to download, and are catalogued according to topic and audience to enhance their discoverability. The portal is an evolving resource, whose functionality and utility will grow in harmony with the evolving needs of the global life science research communities it serves, and synergistically with bioinformatics training initiatives around the world.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>Availability and implementation: http://mygoblet.org/training-portal Contact: manuel.corpas@tgac.ac.uk Received on July 8, 2014; revised on August 29, 2014; accepted on August 31, 2014</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><figDesc>5 Ontario Institute for Cancer Research, Toronto, Canada, 6 Instituto Gulbenkian de Ci^ encia, Oeiras, Portugal, 7 The University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia, 8 Netherlands Bioinformatics Centre, 9 Department of Bioinformatics, Radboud Medical Center, Nijmegen, The Netherlands, 10 CSC-IT Center for Science Ltd., Espoo, Finland, 11 Whitehead Institute for Biomedical Research, MIT, Cambridge, MA, USA, 12 CSIRO, Bioinformatics Core, Canberra, Australia, 13 The Sainsbury Laboratory, Norwich Research Park, Norwich, UK, 14 SIB Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics, 1 Rue Michel Servet, Genè ve, Switzerland, 15 Academis, Illstrasse 12, 12161 Berlin, Germany, 16 The Nowgen Centre, 29 Grafton Street, Manchester, UK, 17 Department of Physics, Sapienza University, Rome, Italy, 18 The Roslin Institute, Edinburgh, UK and 19 The University of Manchester, Manchester, UK</figDesc><table>Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> INTRODUCTION Technologies underpinning the life sciences are constantly evolving (Abeln et al., 2013) and, at the same time, are spurring development of new methods for data analysis and interpretation (Carvalho and Rustici, 2013; Brazas and Ouellette, 2013; Libeskind-Hadas and Bush, 2013). Researchers—students and professionals alike—therefore constantly need to acquire new skills to keep abreast of the latest developments (Schneider et al., 2010; Via et al., 2011, 2013; Vincent and Page, 2013). Attempting to address this need, the Global Organisation for Bioinformatics Learning, Education and Training (GOBLET) has established a training portal, spanning the fields of bioinformatics, biocuration, biocomputing and computational biology. The portal provides a freely available collection of materials and courses, and a catalogue of trainers, classified by tags. The tags make it easy to find and share materials and to identify trainers with appropriate expertise. The portal inherits much of the functionality of the prototype BTN website (Schneider et al., 2012), extending its features to accommodate the diverse needs of global communities of life scientists: enhancements include (i) the addition of features such as the definition of fields for describing materials, to make them more discoverable, and (ii) the possibility to add course pages, linked to their associated materials, so that the portal is both a repository and a record of what is to be, and what was, taught at a given time, rather than just a bag of disconnected contents. 2 THE TRAINING PORTAL The portal, built using the Drupal content management system, embodies three main entities: members, materials and courses. Members may be individuals representing their own interests, or they may represent particular organizations or groups (national *To whom correspondence should be addressed. y The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors. ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="141"> The GOBLET training portal at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.Corpas et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors gratefully acknowledge the support of GOBLET's member organizations.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bioinformatics and systems biology: bridging the gap between heterogeneous student backgrounds</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Abeln</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="589" to="598" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Navigating the changing learning landscape: perspective from bioinformatics.ca</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Brazas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">F F</forename>
				<surname>Ouellette</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="556" to="562" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The challenges of delivering bioinformatics training in the analysis of high-throughput data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Carvalho</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Rustici</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="538" to="547" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">iAnn: an event sharing platform for the life sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Jimenez</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1919" to="1921" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A first course in computing with applications to biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Libeskind-Hadas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Bush</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="610" to="617" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bioinformatics Training Network (BTN): a community resource for bioinformatics trainers</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Schneider</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="383" to="389" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bioinformatics training: a review of challenges, actions and support requirements</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Schneider</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="544" to="551" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Best practices in bioinformatics training for life scientists</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Via</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="528" to="537" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ten simple rules for developing a short bioinformatics training course</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Via</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002245</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing an online programme in computational biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Vincent</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief. Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="775" to="783" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>