
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:39+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining The FAF-Drugs2 server: a multistep engine to prepare electronic chemical compound collections</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<surname>Lagorce</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">MTi</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Julien</forename>
								<surname>Maupetit</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">MTi</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Ressource Parisienne en Bioinformatique Structurale (RPBS)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Institut National de la Santé et de la Recherche Médicale (INSERM)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">UMR-S 973 – Paris Diderot University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Cedex 13</addrLine>
									<postCode>75205</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Jonathan</forename>
								<surname>Baell</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">The Walter</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3052</postCode>
									<settlement>Parkville</settlement>
									<region>Victoria</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Melbourne</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3010</postCode>
									<settlement>Parkville</settlement>
									<region>Victoria</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Olivier</forename>
								<surname>Sperandio</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">MTi</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pierre</forename>
								<surname>Tufféry</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">MTi</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Ressource Parisienne en Bioinformatique Structurale (RPBS)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Institut National de la Santé et de la Recherche Médicale (INSERM)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">UMR-S 973 – Paris Diderot University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Cedex 13</addrLine>
									<postCode>75205</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Maria</forename>
								<forename type="middle">A</forename>
								<surname>Miteva</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">MTi</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Hervé</forename>
								<surname>Galons</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR8601</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Paris Descartes University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>75006</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Associate Editor: John Quackenbush</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Bruno</forename>
								<forename type="middle">O</forename>
								<surname>Villoutreix</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>bruno.villoutreix@inserm.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">MTi</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Ressource Parisienne en Bioinformatique Structurale (RPBS)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Institut National de la Santé et de la Recherche Médicale (INSERM)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">UMR-S 973 – Paris Diderot University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Cedex 13</addrLine>
									<postCode>75205</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data and text mining The FAF-Drugs2 server: a multistep engine to prepare electronic chemical compound collections</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2018" to="2020"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr333</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on April 6, 2011; revised on May 16, 2011; accepted on May 28, 2011</note>
					<note>[12:50 23/6/2011 Bioinformatics-btr333.tex] Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The FAF-Drugs2 server is a web application that prepares chemical compound libraries prior to virtual screening or that assists hit selection/lead optimization before chemical synthesis or ordering. The FAF-Drugs2 web server is an enhanced version of the FAF-Drugs2 package that now includes Pan Assay Interference Compounds detection. This online toolkit has been designed through a user-centered approach with emphasis on user-friendliness. This is a unique online tool allowing to prepare large compound libraries with in house or user-defined filtering parameters. Availability: The FAF-Drugs2 server is freely available at http://press-sulfenyla
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The most established method for the identification of hit compounds modulating the functions of a target is experimental high-throughput screening (HTS). Alternatively or in parallel, screening can be performed in silico (virtual ligand screening or VLS) in order to prioritize compounds for in vitro screening. The screening process involves measurement/prediction of activities of sometimes millions of chemical compounds in vitro, on cells or in silico. The first two, in particular, are time consuming and costly, and as such, the preparation of the compound collections is critical. Analyses of past failures have led to a much better understanding of crucial properties that distinguish any chemical from an interesting drug-candidate or a relevant chemical probe. Thus, the concept of screening high-quality compound collections in terms of improved ADMET (absorption, distribution, metabolism, excretion, toxicity) properties and containing a reduced number of 'nuisance compounds' is gaining momentum. Hence, we decided to develop a user-friendly online tool dedicated to the preparation of compound collections. In fact, such a service, freely available and able to handle several thousands of compounds with either predefined filtering parameters * To whom correspondence should be addressed. or user-tuned parameters, assisting decision making has not been reported to date. Our online in silico filtering engine is based on a significantly improved version of a previously reported stand-alone package named FAF-Drugs2, standing for Free ADMET FilteringDrugs2 (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Lagorce et al., 2008</ref>), which was successfully employed for preparing compound datasets for different projects as in<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Reynes et al. (2010)</ref>. While many free online services are available to compute molecular properties (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ertl et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Tetko, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Walker et al., 2010</ref>), FAF-Drugs2 is the first free web-based package capable of preparing compound libraries through physicochemical rules, functional groups and Pan Assay Interference Compounds (PAINS) detection (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baell et al., 2010</ref>). In the present application note, we describe the FAF-Drugs2 server highlighting the new functionalities introduced as compared with the original stand-alone package.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">THE FAF-DRUGSSERVER</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Improvements of FAF-Drugs2 in the web server version</head><p>FAF-Drugs2 client version requires as input the compound collection in SD or SMILES file format and two parameter files, one containing among others physicochemical thresholds and another one listing the chemical substructures that have to be investigated. Various output files are generated, e.g. SDF filtered files or a tabulated file reporting all the computed values/descriptors. The main improvements on the server version as compared with the FAF-Drugs2 stand-alone tool include: (i) a step before the filtering process to prepare and clean the electronic input molecular data file, with removal of empty structures, salts, counterions, inorganics, mixtures, duplicates. Further, we apply a standardization procedure on eight common chemical groups using SMARTS search and the ChemAxon Standardizer utility (see Supplementary Material). Yet, in order to compute some descriptors the way they were originally described, a rule-based protonation protocol is internally performed with OpenBabel (O'<ref type="bibr">Boyle et al., 2008</ref>)Finally, an intuitive visualization of the results through any web browser is now implemented. More explanations about our filtering engine protocol are detailed in the Supplementary Material and the online userguide.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Implementation</head><p>The optimized FAF-Drugs2 engine has been embedded in the RPBS' Mobyle Portal (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Neron et al., 2009</ref>). Mobyle's features makes it the perfect solution for online toolkit implementation, because it offers: (i) a centralized workspace for the end-user (bookmarked results and parameters are stored on the server for further uses and backup); (ii) on-the-fly program results pipelining; and (iii) a userfriendly interface and a robust tool to interact with end users and control programs'execution on the server side (storage and resources quota, jobs tracking, etc.). The FAF-Drugs2 web server is organized as a toolkit composed of three services: (i) Bank-Formatter (e.g. converts SMILES input files to SD files format, see Supplementary Material); (ii) Filter-Editor (customizes user-defined filters); and (iii) the FAF-Drugs2 filtering service. The server has been validated and optimized: (i) on 10 000 molecules from the WEHI HTS library (see Supplementary Material); (ii) to be fully functional on popular operating systems and web browsers; and (iii) to run on our 800 nodes cluster (see Supplementary Material).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Interface features</head><p>SD files, as long as they do not exceed 50 000 molecules, can be submitted to the FAF-Drugs2 either by uploading input files on the server or by pasting data in a dedicated window. Instead of using the Filter-Editor service, users can also choose among various physicochemical elsewhere-published pre-tuned filters; among others REOS (<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Walters et al., 2002</ref>) or ZINC (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Irwin et al., 2005</ref>). Furthermore, users can decide to activate the PAINS and functional group substructures detection. When the process is terminated, while filtering result files can be downloaded, various analyses can be done directly in several internet browser windows, like a statistical analysis of the main descriptor distributions (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1a</ref>), a pie chart summarizing the results for the substructures search (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>), a table detailing the results for each compound: the filtering options, the compound's 2D depiction via the ChemAxon molconvert tookit (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1c</ref>), the compound projection (magenta) onto the first plan of the principal component analysis of the orally bioavailable (blue) DrugBank Small molecules (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1d</ref>) and a radar plot depicting some molecular properties important for oral absorption (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1e</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">SUMMARY AND PERSPECTIVES</head><p>The FAF-Drugs2 web server is the first free web-based application devoted to compound library preparation and PAINS detection. The service can also be used to evaluate drug-like properties, the presence of an undesirable substructure and oral absorption of a small set of compounds before synthesis. This service should be of interest to both academic and private research groups.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Various screenshots from Internet browser windows that screenplay the FAF-Drugs2 results. (a) Main PhysChem descriptors analysis of random_bank_5000.sdf library; (b) Pie chart of the most found flaggedrejected chemical moieties in the random_bank_5000.sdf library; summary of the random_bank_5000_1_formatted_standardized_pH.sdf library: (c) compound 2D representation; (d) oral property space; (e) oral absorption estimation.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank INSERM and Paris Diderot University for supports and Dr G. Laconde and Mr. C. Gageat for helpful discussions. We are grateful to Chemaxon for providing a license allowing the use of several utilities included in their package.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict</head><p>of Interest: none declared.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New substructure filters for removal of pan assay interference compounds (PAINS) from screening libraries and for their exclusion in bioassays</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">B</forename>
				<surname>Baell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Holloway</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2719" to="2740" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Designing drugs on the internet? Free web tools and services supporting medicinal chemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Ertl</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Jelfs</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Top. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1491" to="1501" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ZINC–a free database of commercially available compounds for virtual screening</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<forename type="middle">J</forename>
				<surname>Irwin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">K</forename>
				<surname>Shoichet</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FAF-Drugs2: free ADME/tox filtering tool to assist drug discovery and chemical biology projects</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Lagorce</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">396</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mobyle: a new full web bioinformatics framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Neron</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3005" to="3011" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Page</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Lagorce</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pybel: a Python wrapper for the OpenBabel cheminformatics toolkit</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O &apos;</forename>
				<surname>Boyle</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Cent. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Designing focused chemical libraries enriched in protein-protein interaction inhibitors using machine-learning methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Reynes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000695</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The WWW as a tool to obtain molecular parameters</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Tetko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mini. Rev. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="809" to="820" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chembench: a cheminformatics workbench</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Walker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3000" to="3001" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of &apos;drug-likeness&apos;. Adv</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Walters</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">A</forename>
				<surname>Murcko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Drug Deliv. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="271" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>