
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:58+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis XIBD: software for inferring pairwise identity by descent on the X chromosome</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Lyndal</forename>
								<surname>Henden</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Population Health and Immunity Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Walter</addrLine>
									<postCode>3052</postCode>
									<settlement>Parkville</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">David</forename>
								<surname>Wakeham</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Physics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Melanie</forename>
								<surname>Bahlo</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Population Health and Immunity Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Walter</addrLine>
									<postCode>3052</postCode>
									<settlement>Parkville</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mathematics and Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Melbourne</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Melbourne</settlement>
									<region>VIC</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Oliver</forename>
								<surname>Stegle</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Genetics and population analysis XIBD: software for inferring pairwise identity by descent on the X chromosome</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw124</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on October 1, 2015; revised on February 4, 2016; accepted on March 1, 2016</note>
					<note>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Associate Editor: Availability and implementation: XIBD is written in R/Rcpp and executed from shell scripts that are freely available from http://bioinf.wehi.edu.au/software/XIBD along with accompanying reference datasets. Contact: henden.l@wehi.edu.au Supplementary information: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>XIBD performs pairwise relatedness mapping on the X chromosome using dense single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) data from either SNP chips or next generation sequencing data. It correctly accounts for the difference in chromosomal numbers between males and females and estimates global relatedness as well as regions of the genome that are identical by descent (IBD). XIBD also generates novel graphical summaries of all pairwise IBD tracts for a cohort making it very useful for disease locus mapping.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Genomic regions that have been inherited from a common ancestor are said to be identical by descent (IBD). Identification of IBD regions has proven useful in many applications, including discovery and quantification of unknown or misspecified familial relatedness (<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">McPeek and Sun, 2000</ref>) and disease mapping where a region inherited in multiple affected individuals is indicative of a critical region containing disease susceptibility genes (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Albrechtsen et al., 2009</ref>). Several methods have been proposed for inferring IBD, however few allow for analysis of the X chromosome. This is unfortunate as the X chromosome allows for inference of more distant relatedness than autosomes since fewer recombination events occur, resulting in IBD segments that are sustained over longer periods of time. Current IBD analysis of the X chromosome is based on identity by state sharing, which is non-probabilistic and does not necessarily imply IBD (<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Browning and Browning, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Gusev et al., 2009</ref>). Here we present XIBD; the only hidden Markov model (HMM) that infers IBD on the X chromosome in addition to the autosomes, where IBD is detectable between individuals with a recent common ancestor, within 25 generations, rather than more distant relatedness. Many IBD methodologies rely on large cohorts to estimate allele frequency data or to infer linkage disequilibrium structure. XIBD can be applied to as few as two samples with the option to use HapMap allele frequency data for 11 populations. Furthermore, it can be applied to either single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) chip or next generation sequencing (NGS) data (exome or genome wide).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>XIBD implements a first order continuous time HMM to infer IBD between pairs of individuals using unphased genotype data, where time is the genetic map distance in centimorgans (cM). While the model is continuous time, IBD is estimated at the genotyped positions only. The memoryless assumption of a Markov process is unlikely to hold due to recombination, howeverThe hidden states in the Markov model are the number of alleles shared IBD between a pair of individuals, which depend on the genders of the individuals being compared. Assuming the pair are not inbred, if at least one individual is male, then 0 or 1 allele will be shared IBD and the state space is Z ¼ f0; 1g. Alternatively, if both individuals are female then 0, 1 or 2 alleles will be shared IBD with Z ¼ f0; 1; 2g. The initial state probabilities of sharing 0, 1 or 2 alleles IBD are denoted x 0 , x 1 and x 2 respectively, where P 2 i¼0 x i ¼ 1. These probabilities can be calculated using identity coefficients if relationships are known. We use IdCoefs (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abney, 2009</ref>) for autosomes and have implemented the equivalent for the X chromosome. Individuals may be distantly related with unknown relationships, therefore these values must be calculated using an alternative approach. We use the method-of-moments approach described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Purcell et al. (2007)</ref>to estimate these probabilities. The estimated values are used in the analysis as they can be accurately calculated for known and unknown relationships and avoid misspecified pedigrees leading to incorrect global estimates. Since there are two state spaces in the model, we require two transition probability matrices. These can be computed by solving Kolmogorov's forward (or backward) equation given the transition rate matrices (Supplementary information, Eqs. S1 and S2). The transition rate matrices require the number of meiosis m separating the pair of individuals, estimated as in<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Purcell et al. (2007)</ref>, and the recombination rate h estimated by Ott (1999). The genotypic state space for an individual also depends on their gender. Let A and a denote the reference allele and alternative allele respectively. Since male X chromosomes are haploid, they cannot have heterozygous genotype calls. Therefore the male genotypic state space is G ¼ fA; ag while the female genotypic state space is G ¼ fAA; Aa; aag. A pair of genotypes makes up the observation for each marker in the model. Hence, the observation state space differs for each of the three pairwise combinations of genders and this difference leads to three sets of emission probabilities (Supplementary Information,<ref type="figure">Table S1</ref>). The emission probabilities are functions of the individuals' genders, the state space, the observed genotype pair and the population allele frequencies. The population allele frequencies are calculated from either a reference dataset such as HapMap (http://hapmap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/) or the input dataset itself. We include a genotyping error term into our calculation of the emission probabilities as implemented by<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Albrechtsen et al. (2009)</ref>(Supplementary Information, Tables S2 and S3) and accommodate missing data. Dense marker datasets allow for better detection of small IBD tracts and hence more distant relatedness. However, the presence of LD can result in unwanted background sharing. To avoid this, we allow the user to select one of two models to accommodate for LD.<ref type="bibr">et al. (2007)</ref>, model 1 assumes the markers are in linkage equilibrium, which may require thinning of datasets prior to use. However datasets with denser markers in LD can be used at the expense of false IBD segments being reported (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Brown et al., 2012</ref>). 2. Like<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Albrechtsen et al. (2009)</ref>, LD is implicitly accounted for in model 2 using conditional emission probabilities (Supplementary Information, Tables S4–S6). Pairwise LD between markers is calculated using the squared correlation (R 2 ) of reference genotypes using PLINK (<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Purcell et al., 2007</ref>).<ref type="bibr">Consortium, 2003</ref>); allowing the user to choose between the 11 HapMap population. Furthermore, given a homogeneous population, we allow the user to calculate the necessary frequencies from the input dataset itself or to specify their own homogeneous reference dataset of matching population. Global relatedness estimates (x 0 , x 1 , x 2 and m) are reported for each pair of individuals analyzed, as well as inferred IBD tracts from the Viterbi algorithm and posterior probabilities from the forward– backward algorithm (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Rabiner, 1989</ref>). IBD results are reported in spreadsheets. These can be cumbersome to investigate when many shared regions are inferred. However, XIBD also produces novel graphical summaries that allow the user to visualize shared regions in multiple individuals (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1</ref>). Unlike other algorithms, XIBD does not require a large cohort for accurate IBD inference. In<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Shaw et al. (2015)</ref>, XIBD was implemented on a single pair of male individuals with X-linked intellectual disability, to verify that a detected variation was contained within a small shared IBD tract on the X chromosome, thus leading to the conclusion that the variant was causal, rather than a technical artifact. Results from simulation studies can be found in the Supplementary Information, Figures S1 and S2. We note that pseudo-autosomal regions are excluded from analysis. Finally,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Like Purcell</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>McPeek and Sun (2000) have shown it to be a good approximation and like Albrechtsen et al. (2009) and Epstein et al. (2000), we also make this assumption.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Markers in high LD (R 2 &gt; 0:99) and markers with low minor allele frequency (MAF &lt; 0:01) are removed from the analysis. Unlike Purcell et al. (2007) and Albrechtsen et al. (2009), reference datasets are provided with XIBD. These datasets are the combined HapMap Phase II and III genotypes and allele frequencies from build 19 (The International HapMap</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Summary figure produced by XIBD of simulated IBD segments inherited up to 25 generations from the common ancestor. Pair identifiers are given on the y-axis. i.e. 23_1/23_2 are individuals 1 and 2 from generation 23, respectively. The x-axis displays the genetic map position in base-pairs with tick markers indicating the SNP positions. The ideogram for the X chromosome is below. Blue rectangles are regions where pairs share one allele IBD while yellow rectangles represent two alleles shared IBD</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">V C The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</note>

			<note place="foot">at University of California, Los Angeles on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A graphical algorithm for fast computation of identity coefficients and generalized kinship coefficients</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Abney</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1561" to="1563" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relatedness mapping and tracts of relatedness for genome-wide data in the presence of linkage disequilibrium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Albrechtsen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genet. Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inferring coancestry in population samples in the presence of linkage disequilibrium</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">D</forename>
				<surname>Brown</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">190</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1447" to="1460" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving the accuracy and efficiency of identity-by-descent detection in population data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<forename type="middle">L</forename>
				<surname>Browning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Browning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">459471</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="0194" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved inference of relationship for pairs of individuals</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Epstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1219" to="1231" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole population, genome-wide mapping of hidden relatedness</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Gusev</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">318326</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical test for detection of misspecified relationships by use of genome-screen data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">S</forename>
				<surname>Mcpeek</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Sun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1076" to="1094" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction and basic genetic principles. Analysis of Human Genetic Linkage</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Ott</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd. edn. Baltimore</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PLINK: A tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Purcell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="559" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A tutorial on hidden Markov models and selected applications in speech recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<forename type="middle">R</forename>
				<surname>Rabiner</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<meeting>. IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="286" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identical by descent L1CAM mutation in two apparently unrelated families with intellectual disability without L1 syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Shaw</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Med. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="368" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The International HapMap Consortium The International HapMap Project</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">426</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="789" to="796" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>