
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/joey/Project/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-10T23:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology XiP: a computational environment to create, extend and share workflows</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Masao</forename>
								<surname>Nagasaki</surname>
							</persName>
							<email>nagasaki@megabank.tohoku.ac.jp</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Integrative Genomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Tohoku Medical Megabank Organization</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Tohoku University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Japan</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">André</forename>
								<surname>Fujita</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Mathematics and Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Sã o Paulo</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="BR">Brazil</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Yayoi</forename>
								<surname>Sekiya</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Human Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Medical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Ayumu</forename>
								<surname>Saito</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Human Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Medical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Emi</forename>
								<surname>Ikeda</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Human Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Medical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Chen</forename>
								<surname>Li</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Human Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Medical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Satoru</forename>
								<surname>Miyano</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Human Genome Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Medical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systems biology XiP: a computational environment to create, extend and share workflows</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="139"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts630</idno>
					<note>Associate Editor: Martin Bishop Availability: XiP is open source, freely available under the Lesser General Public License (LGPL) and can be downloaded from http:// xip.hgc.jp. Contact:</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>XiP (eXtensible integrative Pipeline) is a flexible, editable and modular environment with a user-friendly interface that does not require previous advanced programming skills to run, construct and edit workflows. XiP allows the construction of workflows by linking components written in both R and Java, the analysis of high-throughput data in grid engine systems and also the development of customized pipelines that can be encapsulated in a package and distributed. XiP already comes with several ready-to-use pipeline flows for the most common genomic and transcriptomic analysis and 300 computational components.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Large-scale sequencing and microarray technologies are high-throughput methodologies that generate huge genomic and transcriptomic data that must be processed in a multi-step fashion. Usually, it is carried out by several distinct programs that are interconnected in a specific order, forming a workflow process, namely pipeline (<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Durham et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Fujita et al., 2007</ref>). For example, a simple workflow to investigate genes potentially related to cancer might begin with microarray image analysis, normalization, statistical tests to identify differentially expressed genes between the normal and the tumor tissues followed by a multiple test P-value correction.<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Shah et al. (2004)</ref>have described that pipelines must satisfy at least three characteristics: (i) flexibility: a software can be used to analyze different data sets that may require different analysis tools; (ii) integrability: a system should provide the framework to facilitate data integration of analysis results from different tools; and (iii) extensibility: a system needs to allow for the inclusion of new tools in a modular fashion. In addition to these characteristics that are actually necessary to a pipeline, we believe that the portability with grid engines and the interoperability with pre-existing systems are also important in this new era of generation of high-throughput data. The portability with grid engines makes possible to run heavy routines in supercomputers (hundreds of cores) in an easy manner while the interoperability allows the use of workflows constructed under different platforms. To facilitate the construction of workflows, we present XiP (eXtensible integrative Pipeline), a free [under the Lesser General Public License (LGPL)] and easy-to-use environment designed to integrate the state-of-the-art computational methods and to satisfy researchers' need in multi-collaborative projects. carried out in different laboratories to guarantee both reproducibility and quality. The construction of a computational pipeline under the XiP platform does not require advanced computer-programming skills. At<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1a</ref>, there is a list of components and a tool to search for a specific algorithm. To build a workflow, the user clicks on the component of interest and drags and drops on the canvas (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>). The order of analysis in the pipeline is set according to the order of the components defined by the arrows of the workflow (<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1b</ref>). The tail of the arrow represents from which component the data comes, and the head points to the next analysis step. In other words, the direction of the arrows indicates the data flow. The parameters of each component can be easily set up by using the graphical interface illustrated on<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1c</ref>, and the results are visualized in separate windows as shown in<ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1d</ref>. XiP satisfies the three essential characteristics for a pipeline platform and also the fourth (portability to grid engines) and fifth (interoperability) described in Section 1 as follows:</p><p>(1) Flexibility: The specific requirements of a research project make it difficult to use a pipeline designed for a particular data set for analysis of another data set. As a result, two different pipelines must be constructed, both sharing several common components. However, notice that it is not necessary to reconstruct the entire pipeline, but only the different parts. As the pipelines constructed by XiP are modular, i.e. the pipelines are composed of an ordered sequence of components, one must replace only the different components to adapt the pipeline to a new data set.</p><p>(2) Integrability: Components written in both R and Java programming languages run on XiP. Internally, XiP translates the R data structures into Java structures, thus allowing the connection of packages available at the R webpage (http://www.r-project.org) and the BioJava project (<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Holland et al., 2008</ref>).</p><p>(3) Extensibility: R and Java functions developed by different groups can automatically be translated to a XiP component and included in the platform. Therefore, XiP can be customized and extended with several components depending on the user's necessities.</p><p>(4) Portability to grid engine: The analysis of large amounts of data generated by the new technological approaches in molecular biology requires high-performance computational resources. The XiP platform allows the construction of pipelines that use grid engines to parallelize computational jobs. To run a parallel job, the user must set up a cluster (server) with several cores and log in to this remote server. The integration with grid engines makes XiP suitable for individual researchers with modest data sizes as well as for big collaborative projects with large amounts of data.</p><p>(5) Interoperability: Owing to several different pipeline platforms available in the literature such as Pegasus (<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Deelman et al., 2004</ref>), Kepler (<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Altintas et al., 2004</ref>) and Galaxy (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Goecks et al., 2010</ref>), each one with unique advantages, it would be interesting whether one platform could integrate components developed in different environments. XiP satisfies the interoperability by converting the components developed in the Galaxy platform (<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Goecks et al., 2010</ref>) to an XiP component. Interoperability with other systems is under development. Once a pipeline is constructed, it can be distributed in both a XiP XML format and a jar file. The XiP XML is a markup language that stores the pipeline structure, i.e. the information about how the components are interconnected. The jar format is a closed stand-alone package that runs in a computational<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Koh et al., 2010</ref>) and the CSO validator (<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Jeong et al., 2011</ref>). Other examples can be found at the XiP webpage. Summing up, the main advantages of XiP are (i) it satisfies all the five characteristics for a pipeline platform; (ii) components developed in the Galaxy platform can be converted to XiP components; and (iii) stand-alone packages created under XiP can be run outside the XiP environment. The entire code is open and we encourage researchers to contribute with novel functionalities for the XiP platform.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head><p>The super-computing resource was provided by Human Genome Center, Institute of Medical Science, University of Tokyo.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.1.</head><figDesc>Fig. 1. Screenshot of a XiP graphical interface and a regulatory network estimation pipeline. (a) The list of components; (b) the pipeline schema; (c) the parameters for each component of the pipeline; (d) the output, i.e. the estimated regulatory network</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Funding: This work was supported by a grant of the Genome Network Project from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology, Japan. A.F. was partially supported by CNPq and FAPESP, Brazil. Conflict of Interest: none declared</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> IMPLEMENTATION XiP was entirely developed in Java and runs at the client&apos;s machine via the Java Web Start technology. In other words, XiP runs in the majority of operating systems, requiring only a pre-installation of the Java Runtime Environment (JRE version 1.6) at the client&apos;s machine. If JRE is not installed, the installation package asks for the permission to install JRE. Although XiP was originally designed to run via the Web, it can also be installed in local machines. XiP already comes with 300 components, where each component represents one computational algorithm (e.g. Support Vector Machine, k-means, t-test, etc). XiP also recognizes components written in R (R Development Core Team, 2011), one of the most popular statistical programming languages in Bioinformatics. For data input, XiP accepts any Java and R basic data structures, Cell System Markup Language (CSML) (Nagasaki et al., 2010), Cell System Ontology (CSO) (Jeong et al., 2007), Cell System Markup Language Data Base (CSMLDB) and CSODB formats. The complete list of components that comes with XiP (300 components), tutorials, documentation and some example pipelines are available at the XiP project webpage (http://xip.hgc.jp). 3 RESULTS AND DISCUSSIONS With the advances in the generation of high-throughput data and the development of large-scale projects, which involve dozens of labs around the world, computational pipelines become crucial and indispensable, especially when the same protocol must be *To whom correspondence should be addressed. ß The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot">M.Nagasaki et al. at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>

			<note place="foot" n="139"> eXtensible integrative pipeline at :: on August 30, 2016 http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kepler: an extensible system for design and execution of scientific workflows</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Altintas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 16th International Conference on Scientific and Statistical Database Management</title>
		<meeting>the 16th International Conference on Scientific and Statistical Database Management</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="424" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pegasus: mapping scientific workflows onto the grid</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Deelman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lect. Notes Comput. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3165</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EGene: a configurable pipeline generation system for automated sequence analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">M</forename>
				<surname>Durham</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2812" to="2823" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GEDI: a user-friendly toolbox for analysis of large-scale gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Fujita</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">457</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Galaxy: a comprehensive approach for supporting accessible, reproducible, and transparent computational research in the life sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Goecks</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">86</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cell system ontology: representation for modeling, visualizing and simulating biological pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Jeong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In Silico Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="623" to="638" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CSO validator: improving manual curation workflow for biological pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Jeong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2471" to="2472" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cell Illustrator 4.0: a computational platform for systems biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Nagasaki</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In Silico Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioJava: an open-source framework for bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C G</forename>
				<surname>Holland</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2096" to="2097" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DA 1.0: a parameter estimation of biological pathways using data assimilation approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">H</forename>
				<surname>Koh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1794" to="1796" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">R: a language and environment for statistical computingR Foundation for Statistical Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Development</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Core</forename>
				<surname>Team</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<pubPlace>Vienna, Austria</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct   xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pegasys: software for executing and integrating analyses of biological sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Shah</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">40</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>